<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>08</num>
  <heading>Conduct of Public Meetings</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Frequency.</heading>
    <text>Public meetings of the Commission may be held where and when the Commission directs for any authorized purpose, provided, however, that at least six meetings are held per year.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Attendance.</heading>
    <text>A quorum need not be present in order for the Commission to hold a public meeting. If, however, less than a quorum is present at any public meeting, matters submitted for a vote shall be deferred.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Presiding Officer.</heading>
    <text>The Chairman, or in his absence, the Vice-Chairman of the Commission or a designee shall preside at public meetings which may be called to order when the above presiding officer or his designee is in attendance. The Commission shall transact routine business and shall sit for the consideration of any and all matters which may properly be brought before it at the meeting.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Agenda.</heading>
    <text>The Executive Director of the Commission in consultation with the Chairman shall be responsible for developing the agenda for each public meeting.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Records.</heading>
    <text>Minutes of the meeting shall be taken by the Commission and made available for public inspection at the offices of the Commission, during ordinary business hours.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Voting.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each Commission member, except the Chairman, shall be entitled to one vote on each matter submitted to a vote at the meeting.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Voting shall be in person or by proxy.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Chairman shall vote only to break a tie or cast a fourth concurring vote.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>During the time between public meetings, each Commission member shall be entitled to one vote on each matter submitted to vote.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Adjournment.</heading>
    <text>A public meeting may be adjourned by a majority of those Commission members present in person.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health-General Article, §19-206, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1977-05-11">Effective date: May 11, 1977 (4:10 Md. R. 767)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
