<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>10</num>
  <heading>Rate Application and Approval Procedures</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>"Burden of proof" means the burden of persuasion by the preponderance of the evidence.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>"Commission" means the Health Services Cost Review Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>"Executive Director" means the Executive Director of the Commission, or in his absence, the Commission staff member designated to act in his stead.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>"Opinion" means a written statement setting forth the reasons and grounds why the writer of the statement believes that certain actions should be taken or decisions or recommendations made.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>"Order Nisi" means an order of the Commission that certain actions shall be taken or that certain matters are approved as of a future date, thereby permitting parties affected by the Order Nisi to make any objections they may have known to the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Partial Rate Application.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Partial rate application" means a request by a hospital for the amendment or establishment of a single approved rate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Partial rate application" includes, but is not limited to, those requests enumerated in <cite path="|10|37|10|.03|B.|(4)">Regulation .03B(4) of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>"Publish" means the insertion of a public notice concerning proposed actions, including but not limited to public hearings, in a newspaper or newspapers in general circulation in the community in which the hospital affected is located, and, if the public notice relates to a public hearing, in the Maryland Register at least 15 days before the date of the public hearing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>"Rate application" and "application" mean a hospital application for rate approval, to be submitted as specified in these regulations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>"Recommendation" means a written statement from the Commission's staff to the Commission, advocating a resolution of issues or approval, disapproval, or modification of certain hospital rates and procedures for evaluating the rates.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>"Regression analysis" means a statistical technique used to measure and control for the effect of selected independent variables (for example, percentage of Medicaid revenue) on one dependent variable (for example, bad debts).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>"Uncompensated care" means care provided for which compensation is not received (that is, any combination of bad debts and charity care), and as more fully described in the Commission's Accounting and Budget Manual for Fiscal and Operating Management which is incorporated by reference at <cite path="10.37.01.02">COMAR 10.37.01.02</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>"Value of the substantial, available, and affordable coverage (SAAC) differential" means the difference between the amount paid out by SAAC-approved nonprofit health service plans, health insurers, and health maintenance organizations on behalf of SAAC enrollees to hospitals, and what they would have paid to hospitals absent the differential.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01-1</num>
    <heading>Incorporation by Reference.</heading>
    <text>The Alternative Rate Setting Method (ARM) Manual (1998) is hereby incorporated by reference.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Rate Review System.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The rate review system, otherwise known as the Accounting and Budget Manual for Fiscal and Operating Management, shall consist of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The rate review forms; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Instructions for completion of the forms.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The rate review system is incorporated by reference in <cite path="10.37.01.02">COMAR 10.37.01.02</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A hospital's rate review system and a schedule of published rates shall be filed by the last day of the third month after the close of the hospital's fiscal year.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|37|10|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Regular Rate Applications.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A hospital may not file a full rate application with the Commission until the Commission staff is able to determine through analysis that the data used to evaluate a full rate application has not been substantially affected by the COVID pandemic. During this interim period, a hospital may seek a rate adjustment under any other administrative remedy available to it under existing Commission law, regulation, or policy. In no event shall this moratorium continue in effect beyond June 30, 2023. Once the moratorium is lifted, a hospital may file a regular rate application at any time if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The rates being requested are not the subject of a hospital-instituted case pending before the Commission; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The subject hospital has not obtained permanent rates through the issuance of a Commission rate order within the previous 365 days.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Full Rate Application.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Full rate application" means a regular rate application which requests the amendment of more than one previously approved rate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In order for a full rate application to be docketed, it shall comply with a template for such applications as prescribed by the Commission staff and shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Enumerate the services for which new rates are being requested, listing present and proposed rates;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Be accompanied by appropriate supporting documents, including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The Annual Report of Revenues, Expenses, and Volumes projected and explained (e.g., how much of the requested increase relates to inflation, volumes, and other factors) for the period for which the hospital requests new rates;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Any audited financial statements over the most recent 5 years not yet filed with the Commission, plus the most recent unaudited financial statements for the current period, which are available at the time of the filing of the full rate application;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>An Excel file listing and summarizing balance sheets, statements of operations and changes in net assets, and statements of cash flow for the last 5 years per the audited financial statements along with a narrative explaining any major changes;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>An Excel file listing the information contained within the Annual Report RE schedules for the last 5 years breaking out regulated and unregulated revenues and expenses by category and in total;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>A detailed history of HSCRC-approved revenue and actual revenue for the hospital for the last 2 calendar years;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>A detailed history for the most recent 4 Rate Years of HSCRC-approved GBR revenue and actual revenue and volumes, in addition to any approved and actual revenue and volumes available at the date of the filing of the full rate application. The history of approved and actual revenue changes should detail the basis of the changes in approved and actual revenue including allowed inflation and all other factors;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>An identification of related organizations (i.e., an organization related to the hospital through some type of control or ownership), including subsidiaries of the hospital as well as hospitals that are part of the same hospital system as the applicant hospital. For applicant hospitals that are part of a system, the hospital may be required to submit financial and other information related to the system hospitals, including any system transactions among the system hospitals, which may affect the financial condition of the applicant hospital;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>A listing of any services provided by related organizations including the amount charged to the applicant hospital for the services;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ix)</num>
            <text>A listing of any transfers of funds to or from a related organization including an explanation of such transfers;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(x)</num>
            <text>Copies of the two most recent Medicare Cost Reports, including any home office cost report files — the Interns and Resident Information System report (IRIS) files, and the wage and occupational mix files, along with any adjustments and corrections;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xi)</num>
            <text>Reconciliations of inpatient and outpatient volumes and revenue submitted in the HSCRC abstract data to the departmental revenue and statistics submitted monthly for the last 3 years;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xii)</num>
            <text>In Excel, listing of Outpatient drugs accounting for at least 80 percent of the Hospital’s total outpatient drug expenses, with applicable HCPCS codes for last 3 years, including frequency of charges, amount of charges and units billed, Average Sales Price at the end of each year and applicable 340B discounts and an estimate of billed charges for unlisted drugs;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xiii)</num>
            <text>For profits or losses associated with the support of physician practices, the applicant hospital may be required to provide a detailed accounting of those profits or losses over time. Additional information regarding compensation, subsidies and other forms of financial support provided to physicians may be required following staff’s initial review to the extent that these profits or losses have a material impact on the financial condition of the applicant hospital;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xiv)</num>
            <text>A supporting document, in Excel, that compares the requested departmental rates of the applicant hospital to that hospital’s current departmental rates. The supporting document should also compare these current and requested departmental rates to those of other HSCRC-regulated hospitals located in the Primary Service Area (PSA) of the applicant hospital. If no other regulated hospitals are located in the applicant hospital’s PSA, then the comparison should be made to Statewide median departmental rates; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xv)</num>
            <text>An accounting of the amounts reported by the applicant hospital to the HSCRC regarding its uses of population health infrastructure money included in rates;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Include a description of the rate adjustments that are being requested in the full rate application;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Include specific detail and substantiation of any circumstances the applicant hospital cites as unique to its facility, which would require revenue in excess of the amount currently provided in its approved regulated revenue;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Describe in detail what the applicant hospital has specifically done consistent with the All-Payer Model to reduce or eliminate unnecessary or potentially avoidable utilization. For purposes of this regulation, unnecessary or potentially avoidable utilization means the utilization of health care items and services, including care furnished to treat complications during a hospital admission, that may be avoided through improved efficiency, care coordination, or effective community-based care, or that is not medically necessary or evidence-based care. The Staff may request additional information as needed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Provide estimates for the next 5 years of reductions in utilization that will be accomplished through care redesign initiatives;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Provide a history of denials for the most recent 3 years, including any year-to-date figures; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Any additional information the Staff may request that bears directly on the hospital’s request for rate relief and its financial condition.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The provisions of <cite path="10|37|10|.03|B.|(2)">§B(2) of this regulation</cite> may be waived by staff if the application applies only to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A request filed for a change in the applicant hospital’s uncompensated care allowance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A request for rates to cover government-mandated or similar action affecting more than one previously approved rate for which the staff believes the provisions of <cite path="10|37|10|.03|B.|(2)">§B(2) of this regulation</cite> are not necessary; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A request for rates associated with a Certificate of Need-approved capital project, which request may be considered to be a “partial rate application” by staff.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Uncompensated Care Policy.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Commission's rate-setting methodology shall include in the rates of each hospital a provision for a reasonable level of uncompensated care provided at the hospital. The Commission may use a regression analysis or other statistical method to establish the reasonable level of uncompensated care.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In establishing a reasonable level of uncompensated care in a full rate review, the Commission shall consider for each hospital the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Amount of uncompensated care actually incurred;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Predicted amount of uncompensated care; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The hospital's requested amount.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A hospital may request a change in its approved provision of uncompensated care to the predicted amount by means of a partial rate application provided the request is revenue neutral.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03-1</num>
    <heading>Partial Rate Application.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The provisions of <cite path="|10|37|10|.03|B.|(2)">Regulation .03B(2) of this chapter</cite> may be waived by staff in the review of a partial rate application.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A hospital may file a partial rate application with the Commission at any time, consistent with the provisions of <cite path="|10|37|10|.03|A.">Regulation .03A of this chapter</cite>. A partial rate application is not a contested case under the provisions of the Administrative Procedure Act.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Commission shall act on a docketed partial rate application within the time frames established for a full rate application that does not involve a public hearing, consistent with Commission law and regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A hospital that has been denied its request for a partial rate change may file a full rate application with the Commission in accordance with Commission law and regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Commission Review of Established Rates.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Commission may order a review of a hospital's established rates at any time, as it deems necessary and proper.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This order, provided it orders the review of any rate or charge, may constitute a Commission-initiated rate proceeding.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In reviewing a hospital’s established rates during a Commission-initiated rate proceeding or while reviewing a hospital’s full rate application, the Commission shall consider the hospital’s performance since the implementation of the All-Payer Model Agreement with the federal government, which took place in February 2014.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04-1</num>
    <heading>Rate Efficiency Methodology.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In evaluating the reasonableness of a hospital's permanent rate structure, the Commission shall use an Inter-hospital Cost Comparison (ICC) methodology, which compares the costs of the hospital to those costs, including adjustments for reasonableness and efficiency, of its peer hospitals, with appropriate adjustments to reflect changes in the hospital’s volume since the beginning of the new All-Payer Model Agreement and the inception of the hospital’s revenue agreement, as the foundation of its review of the full rate application. The staff shall make modifications to the ICC which are needed to properly reflect any additional factors that are relevant to the determination of a reasonable cost level that should be reflected in the hospital’s approved regulated revenue. The ICC analysis does not constitute a strict, unalterable or absolute methodology. It shall be modified as needed to give proper attention to the particular circumstances of the hospital, and the staff shall give due consideration to information provided by the hospital in determining the appropriate rate levels and rate structure for the hospital. The ICC shall take into account, in the establishment of appropriate rate levels, those factors for which the hospital will not be held accountable such as special grants from the Commission, assessments, uncompensated care levels, and characteristics of the population in the hospital’s primary service area.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Factors considered in the ICC methodology may evolve during the course of full rate reviews. The Commission shall take into account the specific circumstances of the applicant hospital, and staff shall make the key contents, analytic steps, and findings of such reviews available to all hospitals and the public.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>When reviewing a full rate application filed by a hospital that is owned or controlled by a hospital system that also owns other hospitals located in Maryland, the Commission may take into account the financial situation of the other hospitals in the system including their profitability and any shifts of services, volume, revenues or assets between the hospital and the other hospitals or related organizations of the system.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The final rates that are approved by the Commission for a nonprofit hospital’s permanent rate structure shall allow the hospital to charge reasonable rates that will permit it to provide, on a solvent basis, effective and efficient service that is in the public interest.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The final rates that are approved by the Commission for a proprietary profit-making hospital’s permanent rate structure shall allow the hospital to charge reasonable rates that will permit it to provide effective and efficient service that is in the public interest and include enough allowance for and provide a fair return to the owner of the hospital.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Commission shall set rates for the applicant hospital consistent with the All-Payer Model approved by the federal Center for Medicare and Medicaid Innovation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04-2</num>
    <heading>Global Budget Revenue Methodology.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Global Budget Revenue (GBR) methodology implemented by the Commission effective January 1, 2014, establishes reasonable revenue levels for Maryland's general acute hospitals, which will enable them to improve quality and efficiency on a solvent basis within the constraints imposed by the All-Payer Model.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In setting reasonable revenue levels, the Commission shall take into account a number of factors. These may include, but are not limited to the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The casemix severity and reasonable utilization of the hospital’s patients;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The historical charges of the hospital;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The statutory requirement regarding the reasonable relationship between costs and charges;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The hospital’s payer mix;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The reasonable uncompensated care requirements of the hospital;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The reasonable Graduate Medical Education (GME) costs of the hospital as determined by the Commission;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Appropriate adjustments, if any, associated with exceptional or outlier cases as defined by the Commission;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Wage levels at the hospital and at other hospitals in the geographic area of the hospital and elsewhere in Maryland;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Adjustments for quality improvement and value-based payment programs applicable to the hospital;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Reasonable infrastructure funding for care management and care coordination for hospital patients;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>The annual update factor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>The proportion of unnecessary care, including Potentially Avoidable Utilization (PAU) at the hospital; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>The performance of the State as a whole under the All-Payer Model.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The GBR shall be implemented through a written agreement entered into by the Commission and each individual general acute hospital. This agreement and any addenda thereto, which shall be annual and renewed automatically, shall set forth all relevant provisions governing the GBR including, but not limited to, performance corridors; interim rate adjustments; the exclusion or special treatment of certain cases; the treatment of volume changes, including those involving residents of Maryland and other patients; the penalties associated with failure to comply with the terms of the GBR agreement; interim revenue limits; care redesign requirements; and other changes to the agreement that may be needed from time to time. A hospital that enters into a GBR agreement shall submit a signed copy of the agreement to the Commission’s offices within 60 days after it is initially approved by the Commission. A hospital that is party to the addendum shall submit a signed copy of the addendum to the Commission’s offices within 60 days from the issuance of the addendum. Failure to submit the signed GBR agreement or the signed addendum in a timely manner, absent an extension granted by staff, may subject the hospital to penalties under <cite path="10.37.01.03|R.">COMAR 10.37.01.03R</cite>. Thereafter, on an annual basis, the hospital shall receive an updated rate order. A hospital that disagrees with a proposed GBR may file a full rate application with the Commission in accordance with <cite path="|10|37|10|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|37|10|.04-3">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04-3</num>
    <heading>Global Budget Revenue Mechanism.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>For purposes of this regulation, the following definitions apply:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Annual update factor” means the amount by which total State hospital revenue may increase in a rate year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Demographic adjustment” means the percentage increase in allowed revenue related to changes in population and the age/sex mix of the population residing in the hospital’s primary service area, net of any reductions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Factor cost inflation” means increases in the costs of goods, services, wages, and salaries experienced by the hospitals as calculated by the Commission for the most recent period for which data are available preceding the year for which the Commission calculates case target updates.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Hospital update” means the amount by which an individual hospital’s approved GBR revenue changes in a particular rate year (i.e., July 1—June 30).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Market shift adjustment” means the rate adjustment applied by the Commission, which increases or decreases the approved GBR revenue of a hospital to reflect changes in volume at the hospital for which there was a corresponding change in volume at another Maryland hospital or other provider.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Annual Update Factor.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>On or before July 1 of each year, the Commission shall establish an annual update factor for the purpose of adjusting the GBR revenue of each individual hospital. The annual update factor shall be designed to reflect projected factor cost inflation, an allowance for certain volume adjustments, productivity adjustments, the revenue constraints included in the All-Payer Model Agreement and other relevant factors, demographic adjustments, market shift adjustments, and other appropriate adjustments.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If after approving an update factor for a given year, a hospital or hospitals collectively exceed their approved revenue, the annual update factor may be reduced in future years to recoup the excess revenue growth. Similarly, if a Maryland hospital or hospitals collectively fall below their approved revenue for a given year, the annual update factor may be adjusted accordingly in future years.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If Maryland hospitals accrue a national growth reduction for 2 consecutive years, in the following year the annual update factor shall be reduced by the first of the 2-year national growth reduction. Except as provided in <cite path="10|37|10|.04-3|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>, the annual update may not be less than 1 percent.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The technical provisions of the methodology used to convert the annual update factor into the hospital update for the next rate year shall be fully described and publicly disseminated on or before July 1 of each year, allowing sufficient time for comment and implementation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Corrective Action. If, at any time, the Commission estimates that the financial constraints or other terms imposed by the All-Payer Model Agreement are at risk of being violated (based on modelling using the CMS actuary’s most recent projections and Health Services Cost Review Commission analysis of Medicare payments data), the Commission may take immediate and appropriate corrective action as it deems necessary and proper to meet the Medicare savings requirements and limits on growth in Medicare payments and prevent any further deterioration in compliance with the Model Agreement. The Commission shall provide sufficient notice and opportunity for comment before taking corrective action. This comment opportunity does not constitute a contested case within the meaning of the Administrative Procedure Act.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The provisions of this regulation apply to all Maryland's general acute care hospitals from July 1, 2014, and thereafter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Compliance and Penalties. GBR compliance shall be monitored during the agreement period. Penalties shall be assessed prospectively at the beginning of the next period. Penalties shall be based on the corridors specified in the GBR Agreement.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Application for Temporary Change in Rates.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Commission may issue a general notice setting forth circumstances under which a hospital may obtain a temporary change in rates. The rates, if approved or modified, shall be effective before the rate review procedure set forth in these regulations, but not before the date of application.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A hospital may apply at any time for a temporary change in rates provided that one of the following conditions is satisfied:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A decline in the hospital's experienced or projected net revenues, due to factors beyond the hospital's control, requiring funds beyond those normally available;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An increase in the hospital's experienced or projected expenses, due to factors beyond the hospital's control, requiring funds beyond those normally available; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A hospital's expenses from regulated services exceed its revenues from regulated services, or the hospital's financial integrity is otherwise jeopardized (for example, for breaching its bond covenants).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Commission and its staff shall review the application and consult with the hospital as to the necessity for the temporary change in rates and the amount of the change required. Designated interested parties shall have 6 working days from the filing of the application to submit comments to the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Within 12 working days from the filing of the application, the Commission shall issue its order:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Denying the temporary change in rates and stating the grounds therefor; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Granting a temporary change in rates, stating:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The amount of the temporarily changed rates, which may or may not be the same as the rates set forth in the hospital's application;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The necessity for the temporary change in rates;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>That a regular rate review proceeding on the proposed rates will be conducted by the Commission as soon as practicable;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The availability of copies of the order at the offices of the Commissioner; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The availability of the record of the temporary rate application for inspection at the Commission's office during ordinary business hours.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Commission order denying or granting the temporary change in rates shall be published and copies forwarded to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The hospital;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Designated interested parties; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Persons writing to the Commission requesting a copy of the order.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>In conducting an expedited review to establish a temporary rate for both inpatient and outpatient services, the Commission shall consider the hospital’s financial condition in addition to its relative efficiency and effectiveness in its performance under the Total Cost of Care Model. A temporary rate approved by the Commission may not result in regulated revenue exceeding regulated expenses in the most recently completed fiscal year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A temporary change in rates is subject to the Commission's final rate order in the regular rate review proceeding, which may be effective as of the date of the temporary rate order.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Application for Alternative Method of Rate Determination.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>At any time on or after July 1, 1974, a hospital may file a written application with the Commission requesting an alternative method for submitting or reviewing any or all of its rates and charges, specifying the reasons for and details of the alternative methods.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If warranted by the circumstances set forth in the application, the Executive Director may grant a temporary approval of an alternative method of rate determination.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The procedure for submitting and reviewing an application under an alternative method of rate determination shall follow as closely as possible the procedure for a regular rate application, except that the time periods and limitations set forth in these regulations do not apply to an application for an alternative method of rate determination.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>At anytime after the approval of an alternative method of rate review by the Executive Director, the Commission may initiate further proceedings to determine the hospital's continuing qualification for the alternative method of rate determination.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>ARM System.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Commission may implement a system providing for alternative rate setting methods (ARM) which would permit hospitals to accept financial risk for the provision of hospital services under certain conditions and circumstances.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The implementation of an ARM system shall be consistent with the principles of equity and access embodied in the Commission's all-payer rate setting system.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The ARM Manual shall set forth the process and requirements associated with the ARM system.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Required Reports under ARM System.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A hospital granted approval for an alternative method of charging under this regulation is required to file quarterly reports and annual reports, to include but not be limited to those listed below in this section, in order to determine that the hospital continues to qualify for the alternative method of rate determination.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Quarterly Reports. The following reports shall be completed in the form prescribed by the Commission and submitted to the Commission within 30 days after the end of each hospital's calendar quarter:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Statistical Data Summary—Each Capitation or Risk-Sharing Contract;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Statistical Data Summary—Each Fixed-Price Contract;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Statistical Data Summary—Other;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Revenue Summary—Each Capitation or Risk-Sharing Contract;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Revenue Summary—Each Fixed-Price Contract; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Revenue Summary—Other.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Annual Reports. The following annual reports shall be completed in the form prescribed by the Commission and submitted to the Commission within 90 days after the end of the appropriate fiscal year:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Statement of Revenue and Expense—Each Capitation or Risk-Sharing Contract;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Statement of Revenue and Expense—Each Fixed-Price Contract;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Statement of Revenue and Expense—Other;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Audited Statement of Revenue and Expense—Contracting Entity; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Audited Balance Sheet—Contracting Entity.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Filing of Reports/Extension.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A hospital required to file the reports in this section may request a reasonable extension of time for filing, if the extension request is:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Made in writing to the attention of the Executive Director;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Supported by sufficient justification; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Made at a reasonable time before the due date of a required report.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Executive Director shall respond promptly in writing to the requesting hospital upon receipt of the request by either approving or disapproving the request.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Extensions will be granted only for valid reasons.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Any required report submitted by a hospital that is substantially incomplete or inaccurate shall be considered untimely filed.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Time for Filing. An application for an alternative rate application shall be filed at least 30 days before the proposed effective date of the alternative rate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Penalties.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Commission may impose penalties of up to $1,000 per day for failing to file reports as required under this section.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Commission may refuse to grant a rate increase to a hospital that does not file a report as required under this section.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A fine assessed for failure to file an alternative rate application on a timely basis shall begin as of the date the application should have been filed.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Funding for Health Information Technology.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Commission may adjust a hospital's rates for health information technology (HIT) projects in conjunction with action taken by the Maryland Health Care Commission (MHCC) under <cite path="|10.25.13">COMAR 10.25.13</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Upon receipt of a recommendation for funding from the MHCC, the Commission's staff shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Review the information presented;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Consult with appropriate parties; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Recommend to the Commission approval, denial, or modification of the MHCC recommendation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>In deciding the course of action to follow on an MHCC HIT project recommendation, the Commission and its staff shall consider, among other things, the following criteria:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The basis for the MHCC recommendation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The applicant's statement of the purpose, mission, vision, goals, and measurable objectives of the project;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The planned approach, including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>An explanation of how the project's goals and objectives will be met;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The technical strategy of the project;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>What activities will be used;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>What personnel will be needed; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>How that personnel will be utilized;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>How the project will be evaluated, as well as specific measurement strategies;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>A timeline that includes the start and end dates of the project and a schedule of activities;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The credentials of the entity and participating individuals, including information that demonstrates their background and ability to carry out the project successfully;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>The potential of the project to enhance the value of health care in Maryland, such as improving health care outcomes and reducing health care costs;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Information that demonstrates why the project is needed; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>A budget that details cost projections for the project that is specific, reasonable, realistic, accurate, and flexible.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Decision.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Based on its consideration of the above-stated criteria and staff's recommendation, the Commission shall decide on the nature, extent, terms, and conditions of any rate adjustment approved.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The decision of the Commission on an MHCC recommendation for HIT funding is final.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A request for funding under this section is not a contested case under the Administrative Procedure Act.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Rate Applications by New Hospitals or Existing Hospitals with Expanded Facilities or New Revenue Centers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>At least 60 days before the operational opening of a new hospital, a revenue center, or a new service within a hospital whose projected annual operating cost exceeds $100,000, the hospital shall file a rate application for the requested rates. This application shall be supported by financial data presented in the format of the Commission's rate review system.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If an existing hospital expends its operations so that the number of in-patient beds is increased by 20 percent or more, and if a rate application is filed pertaining to the expended facilities and providing for an occupancy rate for the expanded facilities of the hospital at an amount below the target occupancy established by the Commission, the Commission may require the filing of additional information projecting the hospital's expanded facilities' activity levels for the first 5 years of their operation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|37|10|.07-1">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07-1</num>
    <heading>Outpatient Services — At the Hospital Determination.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definitions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In this regulation, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Terms Defined.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“At the hospital” means a service provided in a building on the campus of a hospital in which hospital services are provided.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Health care provider” means an individual who is licensed, certified, or otherwise authorized by law to provide health care services under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>“Telehealth services” means the delivery of health care services provided through the use of interactive audio, video, or other telecommunications or electronic technology by a health care provider at a hospital to a patient at a location other than at the hospital, or to a patient at the hospital where the provider is at a location other than the hospital, which enables the patient to interact with the health care provider at the time the health care services are provided.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A service at the hospital is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Presumed to be an outpatient service; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Subject to rate regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In accordance with Health-General Article, §19-201, Annotated Code of Maryland, the Commission’s rate-setting jurisdiction extends to outpatient services provided at the hospital. Outpatient services associated with the federal 340B Program under the federal Public Health Service Act provided in a department of a regulated hospital that, on or before June 1, 2015, is under a merged asset hospital system, and which are physically located at another regulated hospital under the same merged asset hospital system, shall be subject to the rate-setting jurisdiction of the Commission. The Commission may begin setting rates for these services in anticipation of the hospital’s obtaining provider-based status for purposes of the 340B Program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A hospital that desires an exception to the presumption stated under <cite path="10|37|10|.07-1|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> must receive a determination under the provisions of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Commission Approval.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A hospital may not charge a Commission-approved rate for an outpatient service without prior Commission or Commission staff approval.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A hospital may not open a new outpatient service, relocate an existing outpatient service, or convert an existing outpatient service from regulated or unregulated status without a prior determination from the Commission’s staff as to whether the service is being provided at the hospital. A request for determination shall be made in writing at least 60 days before the contemplated action.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Upon request for an exception under <cite path="10|37|10|.07-1|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>, the Commission's staff shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Review the information presented;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Consult with appropriate parties;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Visit the site of the service as it considers necessary; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Notify the hospital of its determination as soon as practicable.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>In deciding whether an outpatient service is at the hospital, the Commission staff may consider, among other things, the following criteria:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Location of the entrances;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Location and signage of parking;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Location and language of signage at entrances, within buildings, on the campus, and in parking areas effectively alerting the public that a given building or service is either at the hospital or not at the hospital;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Location of registration, changing, and waiting areas;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Whether billing reflects clearly that the service is rate regulated or not rate regulated;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Whether any physical connection from an unregulated facility to the hospital, such as tunnels, hallways, covered walkways, elevators, or connecting bridges, will be restricted to hospital staff and physician use in order to ensure that patients and visitors do not have access to the unregulated facility from the hospital;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Whether there is any duplication of an unregulated service within the hospital in order to avoid inappropriate patient steering;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Whether there is any inappropriate mixing of regulated and unregulated services in the same building, which would tend to have the effect of confusing patients about the regulated or nonregulated status of a given service being provided; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Whether any Medicare Part B physician's service being provided in an unregulated building also includes components of a Medicare Part A hospital service that would be reasonably expected by a patient to fall under Commission rate-setting jurisdiction.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Based on consideration of the criteria stated in <cite path="10|37|10|.07-1|G.">§G of this regulation</cite>, the Commission's staff shall make its determination on the request made under <cite path="10|37|10|.07-1|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>A hospital that fails to obtain or violates a staff determination on the hospital status of a given service may be subject to fines for inaccurate reporting under <cite path="10.37.01.03|R.">COMAR 10.37.01.03R</cite> and paybacks for inappropriate charges made during the time a staff determination on an outpatient service was not obtained or adhered to.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>A request for a determination under this regulation is not a contested case under the Administrative Procedure Act.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>A hospital may not bill a separate hospital facility fee when a health care provider who provided telehealth services is authorized to bill independently for the professional services rendered.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>The delivery of telehealth services as described in <cite path="10|37|10|.07-1|A.|(2)">§A(2) of this regulation</cite> constitutes outpatient services provided at the hospital.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|37|10|.07-2">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07-2</num>
    <heading>Outpatient Services — Freestanding Medical Facility.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definition. In this regulation, “freestanding medical facility” means a freestanding medical facility licensed under Health-General Article, Title 19, Subtitle 3A, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The following outpatient services provided at a freestanding medical facility are considered hospital services under Health-General Article, §19-201, Annotated Code of Maryland:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Emergency Services;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Observation Services; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Associated Ancillary Services, such as laboratory, radiology, imaging, EKG, and Medical/Surgical Supplies and Drugs.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In accordance with Health-General Article, §19-201, Annotated Code of Maryland, the Commission’s rate-setting jurisdiction extends to those outpatient services provided at a freestanding medical facility, as designated by the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A freestanding medical facility or a proposed freestanding medical facility that desires to provide a service not designated in <cite path="10|37|10|.07-2|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> (an undesignated service) must receive a determination under the provisions of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Commission Approval.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A freestanding medical facility may not charge a Commission-approved rate for an undesignated service without prior Commission staff approval.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A freestanding medical facility may not open a new outpatient service, relocate an existing outpatient service, or convert an existing outpatient service from regulated or unregulated status without a prior determination from the Commission’s staff as to whether the service constitutes a hospital service subject to Commission rate regulation. A request for determination shall be made in writing at least 60 days before the contemplated action.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Upon request for a determination, the Commission’s staff shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Review the information presented;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Consult with appropriate parties;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Visit the site of the service as it considers necessary; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Notify the freestanding medical facility of its determination as soon as practicable.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>In deciding whether the service constitutes a hospital service subject to Commission rate regulation, Commission staff shall consider, among other things, the following criteria:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Cost of the service;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In consultation with Maryland Health Care Commission (MHCC) staff, access to and need for the service in the community;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Feasibility of providing the outpatient service in the community on an unregulated basis; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Impact of the service on the All-Payer Model including, but not limited to, the Total Cost of Care limitations as prescribed in the All-Payer Model Agreement with the Center for Medicare and Medicaid Innovation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Based on the consideration of the criteria stated in <cite path="10|37|10|.07-2|G.">§G of this regulation</cite>, the Commission staff shall make its determination on the request made under <cite path="10|37|10|.07-2|E.">§E of this regulation</cite> within a reasonable period of time, taking into account, among other things, whether either a Certificate of Need application to establish a freestanding medical facility or a request for exemption from Certificate of Need to convert a licensed general hospital to a freestanding medical facility is pending before the MHCC and, if so, the time frame for staff to comment to MHCC on the financial feasibility of the proposed project.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>A freestanding medical facility that fails to obtain, or violates, a staff determination on the regulated status of a given service may be subject to fines for inaccurate reporting under <cite path="10.37.01.03|R.">COMAR 10.37.01.03R</cite> and paybacks for inappropriate charges made during the time a staff determination on an outpatient service was not obtained or adhered to.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Content.</heading>
    <text>Each rate application shall include a list of services for which new rates are being requested, a list of the present and requested rates, and shall be based on the currently filed or required rate review system.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Method of Filing.</heading>
    <text>The application may be filed by private messenger at the Offices of the Commission, or may be filed by registered mail, return receipt requested, at the following address:</text>
    <text>Health Services Cost Review Commission</text>
    <text>4160 Patterson Avenue</text>
    <text>Baltimore, Maryland 21215</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Docketing and Receipt.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Docketing.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>When a valid rate application is received, as per the above regulations, it shall be entered on the Commission docket and a file opened.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Each rate application shall be given an annual docket number and a consecutive page number in the docket.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Each rate application shall be given a consecutive file number.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A regular rate application file number shall be noted "R".</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The file number of an order authorizing Commission investigation and review of established rates shall be noted "C".</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A temporary rate application file number shall be noted "I".</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>An alternative method of rate determination application file number shall be noted "A".</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>A rate application file number by a new hospital or a hospital with expanded facilities or new revenue centers shall be noted "N".</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>The date of receipt of the rate application shall be noted on the docket and on the file.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Upon request of the hospital, the Commission shall give the hospital a receipt for the rate application filing, showing the docket, page, and file numbers, and the date of receiving the rate application.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The hospital shall file an original and three copies of each rate application and its supporting documents, if any. The Commission may prescribe the format to be used in the submission of rate applications and their supporting documents. In addition, the hospital shall file with each rate application a certificate of service indicating that the application and supporting documents have been mailed or served upon all designated parties to that proceeding and upon the Commission at its offices.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Recommendations of the Commission's Staff to the Commission, Options for Commission Review.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A rate application review shall be completed and the recommendation given to the Commission as soon as possible.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The recommendation shall include a specification of those areas of costs which the staff believes should be reviewed. When practicable, the recommendation shall also include the amounts challenged by the staff.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Any of four actions may be recommended to the Commission. If two or more actions are recommended, the issues and rates to be evaluated in each action shall be set forth clearly. These four actions are as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Commission should hold a public hearing on rates;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Commission should grant tentative approval or modify all or some of the rates and publish notice of an order nisi;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Commission should hold a general hearing on rates;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Commission should deny the application in which case it shall state the grounds for the denial.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A copy of the recommendation shall be placed in the file and a copy shall be forwarded to each Commission member, the hospital, and each interested party.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Commission may not call for the effective date of an Order Nisi or call for a public hearing for 30 days after the Commission acts on the staff's recommendation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Before a staff recommendation or public hearing, the staff may hold conferences with hospital representatives and interested parties in an attempt to clarify or resolve potential issues.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The Commission may prescribe a process for its consideration of a full rate application, which allows for written submissions in support of an application in lieu of an evidentiary hearing. A hospital that chooses this process for a Commission decision on its full rate application shall be afforded the right to submit to the Commission rebuttal information following any written response to the full rate application filed by Commission staff or designated interested parties. A hospital that chooses this written submission process waives its right to an evidentiary hearing. A hospital that chooses this written submission process does not waive its right to judicial review of a final Commission decision under the Administrative Procedure Act. As an additional alternative to an evidentiary hearing, a hospital may choose to enter into a binding arbitration process as prescribed by the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Preliminary Commission Order.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Commission shall consider the staff recommendation and, within 20 days of the date of the recommendation, issue its preliminary order adopting or modifying the recommendation, or referring the recommendations back to the staff for further review and subsequent recommendations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Order Nisi.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If the Commission issues a preliminary order granting tentative approval of any rates, it shall publish notice of the order nisi and the rates.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In addition, the Commission shall forward copies of the order nisi and the rates to the hospital and interested parties.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The order nisi shall state:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The name and address of the hospital; the names of the designated interested parties; the docket, page, and file numbers of the rate application proceeding and the date the application was filed with the Commission.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An enumeration of services and the proposed representative rates to be charged:</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>That the Commission has approved the rates as of a date to be specified, with a provision that the order may be suspended if reasonable cause is shown within 15 days of the date of the Order Nisi.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>That objections to the tentatively approved rates shall be submitted (in person or by mail) to the Commission in writing; that designated interested parties shall submit copies of their objections, identifying the proceeding and Order Nisi to which objections are made to the hospital, and nine copies to the Commission office; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>That the file, which may contain supporting documents from the hospital, the Commission staff recommendation, the Accounting and Reporting reports and the Rate Review System of the hospital, is available at the Commission offices during regular business hours for public inspection.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the Commission issues an order for a public hearing, it shall forward copies of the order and public notice of the hearing to the hospital and the designated interested parties and shall publish a public notice of the hearing. The notice shall state:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The name and address of the hospital: the names of the designated interested parties; the docket, page, and file numbers of the rate application proceeding; the date the application was filed with the Commission; and the time, date, and place of the hearing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A description of the issues to be presented at the public hearing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>That any person interested in the matter may attend the public hearing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>That all persons wishing to present relevant testimony or a statement at the public hearing shall forward copies to the hospital, each designated interested party, and nine copies to the Commission office; that the hospital and members of the public shall forward their testimony at least 8 days before the hearing; that the designated interested parties shall forward their testimony at any time before the close of the first session.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Written testimony will not be considered unless the person submitting the testimony makes himself available for cross-examination unless stipulated to the contrary.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If the Commission issues an order for a general hearing by the Commission, it shall forward copies of the order and public notice of the hearing to the hospital and the designated interested parties and publish a public notice of the hearing.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Public Hearing Before the Commission.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Testimony shall be in writing and may not be delivered orally, except as set forth in Regulation .14K, of this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Presenting Direct Testimony.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Any person who wishes to present direct testimony at the public hearing shall forward copies to the hospital and to every designated interested party, and shall file nine copies at the Commission's office.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the public hearing is the result of a hospital rate application pursuant to Regulation .03, of this chapter, the applicant shall file its testimony at least 20 days before the date of the hearing. The staff of the Commission and members of the public shall file their testimony at least 10 days before the date of the hearing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the public hearing is the result of a Commission-initiated review of the rates of a hospital pursuant to Regulation .04, of this chapter, the Commission staff shall file its testimony at least 20 days before the date of the hearing. The hospital and members of the public shall file their testimony at least 10 days before the date of the hearing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The designated interested parties shall file their testimony before the close of the first hearing session.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The written direct testimony shall set forth the conclusions of the person submitting it and the arguments and facts supporting these conclusions. This testimony shall specifically pertain to the issues set forth in the public notice.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Written direct testimony shall be verified either by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Appearing before an officer or other person authorized to administer an oath; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Signing the documents containing the statements required to be under oath and including the following representation: I do solemnly declare and affirm under the penalties of perjury that the facts set forth in the foregoing testimony are true and correct to the best of my knowledge, information and belief.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Copies of written direct testimony shall be forwarded by the person submitting them to the hospital and the designated interested parties.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>All written direct testimony shall pertain solely to the proposed rates and be relevant to that subject. The presiding officer shall separate irrelevant material from the remainder of the record and keep that material apart. Parts of the body of the written direct testimony judged irrelevant by the presiding officer shall be so marked and may not be considered by the Commission in its deliberations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Persons submitting written testimony shall make themselves available for cross-examination and may give redirect and rebuttal testimony, orally or in writing, as directed or permitted by the presiding officer.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>All testimony at public hearings shall be filed in a timely manner. Requests for hearing postponements shall be made at a reasonable time before the hearing. These requests will only be granted for valid reasons, at the discretion of the Commission. If a hospital requests a postponement of an initial hearing session after the staff has already submitted its testimony, the Commission may require the hospital to file its testimony within the time frame of the original hearing date.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Conduct of Public Hearing.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Chairman of the Commission shall preside at the public hearing, which may be called to order when the presiding officer is in attendance. If the Chairman is absent or has been disqualified, the Vice-chairman or another commissioner shall preside.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Commission may direct that a hearing officer preside at the public hearing. In this case, the hearing officer may exercise all powers given to a presiding commissioner in these regulations during all sessions of the public hearing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>At the discretion of the Commission, the specific duties of the hearing officer may include the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Making all rulings as to evidence, testimony, and official notice;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Setting the order for the examination and cross-examination of witnesses;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Administering oaths and affirmations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Preparing both written and oral summaries of cases heard;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Preparing a recommendation for the Commission consisting of a written report with findings of fact and conclusions of law.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The presiding officer may adjourn a hearing to a specified time, date, and place.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>All public hearings shall be recorded and testimony shall be under oath. A transcript of the record of the hearing shall be placed in the file of the proceeding. If the hospital or any other party desires a copy of the transcript, that party shall make arrangements with the stenographer.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>All direct testimony shall be submitted in writing and in an issue-by-issue format. The hearing shall begin with the examination of the representative of the hospital and any witnesses which the hospital may desire to have testify in its behalf. Whenever practicable, the testimony of witnesses shall proceed on an issue-by-issue basis.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The Commission's staff member assigned to the proceeding shall be the next witness to be examined on the issue in question. In a Commission initiated review, the staff member assigned to the proceeding shall be examined before the hospital witness.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Representatives of the other interested parties who have submitted written testimony shall be examined in the order set by the presiding officer.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>The Commission may examine witnesses at any time during the course of the proceeding. Commission staff and representatives of the hospital and interested parties may also examine witnesses.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>All testimony and examination shall be relevant to the subject of the proposed rates. Redundant and irrelevant testimony and examination shall be prohibited or stricken by the presiding officer. In addition, all interested parties may move the Commission to strike redundant and irrelevant testimony.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>At the presiding officer's discretion, he may allow direct oral testimony if a person attending the hearing demonstrates good cause for not submitting the testimony in written form before the hearing. Witnesses giving direct oral testimony shall be subject to cross-examination in the same manner as other witnesses. Anyone denied an opportunity to testify may appeal in writing to the full Commission within 7 days from this denial.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>To preserve his rights on appeal or otherwise, it is not necessary for a party objecting to a Commission ruling or decision to state the grounds of his objection, unless specifically requested to do so by a member of the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>At the Commission's reasonable discretion, it may permit the filing of post hearing briefs by the hospital, the Commission staff member or any interested party. Those parties submitting briefs shall file copies within a reasonable time designated by the presiding officer to the hospital, the designated interested parties, the Commission office and to each Commission member.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>A Commission member shall remove himself from participation in a public hearing as a Commission member if he decides that a conflict of interest may appear to prejudice his evaluation of the issues considered at the public hearing. Challenges to a Commission member's participation in a public hearing as a Commission member shall be considered by the Commission, the decision made by a majority vote, excluding the member objected to. Challenges shall be made by motion, at least 7 days before the public hearing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>Except as otherwise provided, all decisions required during the conduct of the public hearing shall be made by the presiding officer.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Decision and Opinions of the Commission.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The decision and the opinions of the Commission shall be based solely on the testimony, examination, and evidence presented at the public hearing, on the briefs filed, if any, on the evidence incorporated into the record of the proceeding by reference, on information and data in the record of the proceeding, and on matters as to which the Commission has taken official notice, which matters shall be made known to the parties to the proceedings.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The deliberations of the Commission may be held in private executive session.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The decision shall be made by a majority of the Commission members attending all sessions of the public hearing, or having read the record of hearings they did not attend.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The decision shall be in writing and shall be based on a written majority or unanimous opinion stating the reasons and grounds for the Commission's decision. If a majority of Commissioners who are to render the final decision have not heard the evidence, the decision, if adverse to a party to the proceeding other than the Commission itself, may not be made until a proposal for decision, including findings of fact and conclusions of law, has been served upon the parties, and an opportunity has been afforded to each party adversely affected to file exceptions and present argument to a majority of the Commissioners who are to render the decision, who shall personally consider the whole record or those portions of it as may be cited by the parties.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>At the discretion of a Commission member (or members) who agrees with the decision reached by the majority of the Commission, but who does not agree with the majority opinion, or any part of it, the Commission member (or members) may file a written concurring opinion.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A commission member (or members) who does not agree with the decision or any part of it reached by the majority of the Commission may, at his discretion, file a written dissenting opinion.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The Commission's decision and the opinion (or opinions) shall be filed promptly and the Commission's staff then shall forward copies of the Commission's decision and the opinion (or opinions) to the hospital, to the designated interested parties, and to those parties who submitted written direct testimony before the public hearing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The Commission shall then publish:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An order approving, modifying, or disapproving the rates under review in the proceeding:</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A notice that copies of the Commission's decision and the opinion (or opinions) may be obtained by written request to the Commission offices; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A notice that the record of the complete proceeding is open for public inspection at the Commission offices during regular business hours.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>General Hearing Before the Commission.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>To obtain general information from the region and community in which a hospital is located, the Commission, at its discretion, may hold a general hearing during the course of any rate proceeding.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A general hearing shall be supplementary to other methods of rate review and may not replace them.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A general hearing shall be held in the region in which the hospital whose rates are being reviewed is located.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The public notice of a general hearing may state:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The name and address of the hospital, the designated interested parties, the docket, page, and file numbers of the application, and the time, date, and place of the hearing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A description of the issues to be considered at the general hearing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>That any party interested in the matter may attend and present written or oral statements concerning the announced issues; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>That presentations may be limited as to time and that the number of spokespersons representing any group or organization may be limited.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The general hearing shall be conducted by a hearing officer, any member of the Commission, a senior member of the Commission staff or its legal counsel.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Persons attending the general hearing may present written or oral statements concerning the issues and rates set forth in the notice, which statements need not be verified. The presiding officer, within his discretion, may limit the number of spokespersons representing a group or organization and may limit the time allowed for oral statements.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The conduct of the general hearing shall be recorded and the transcript shall be placed in the file of the proceedings. Any person may purchase a transcript of the hearing from the stenographer.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The presiding officer may ask questions of the spokespersons. Within the discretion of the presiding officer, examination or questions of the spokespersons by other persons may be permitted.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>A transcript of the oral statements and copies of the written statements shall be placed in the Commission's file of the particular rate review proceeding.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.17</num>
    <heading>Forms.</heading>
    <text>The following forms are illustrative of pleadings and papers commonly used by parties in rate review proceedings and should be used wherever possible and, if necessary, adapted to the facts in the proceeding and the needs of the party using the forms:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Rate Application.</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">IN RE THE <br/>APPLICATION <br/>OF<br/>____________ <br/><br/>[ ] (Hospitals)</td>
              <td/>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">BEFORE THE <br/>MARYLAND HEALTH SERVICES <br/>COST REVIEW COMMISSION DOCKET: ______________________ <br/>PAGE: _____________________________________________________ <br/>PROCEEDING NO.: __________________________________________</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Public Notice of Rate Proceeding.</text>
      <text class="center">HEALTH SERVICES</text>
      <text class="center">COST REVIEW COMMISSION</text>
      <text class="center">PUBLIC NOTICE</text>
      <text class="center">RATE PROCEEDING OF</text>
      <text class="center">(specify type of application)</text>
      <text class="center">____________________________________</text>
      <text class="center">(name of hospital)</text>
      <text class="center">(reference to proceeding)</text>
      <text>PUBLIC NOTICE is hereby given that (specify type of application) has been filed (by-concerning) (name of hospital) before the Health Services Cost Review Commission in regard to the following rates or rate components:</text>
      <text>(Specify services and old and new rates or rate components.)</text>
      <text>Further notice shall be given when or if a public or general hearing is held.</text>
      <text>The file of this application is available for public inspection at the offices of the Commission, 4160 Patterson Avenue, Baltimore, Maryland 21215, during regular business hours.</text>
      <text class="center">HEALTH SERVICES</text>
      <text class="center">COST REVIEW COMMISSION</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Notice of Public Hearing.</text>
      <text class="center">PUBLIC NOTICE OF PUBLIC HEARING</text>
      <text class="center">HEALTH SERVICES</text>
      <text class="center">COST REVIEW COMMISSION</text>
      <text class="center">RATE PROCEEDING OF</text>
      <text class="center">(specify type of application)</text>
      <text class="center">____________________________________</text>
      <text class="center">(name of hospital)</text>
      <text class="center">(reference to proceeding)</text>
      <text>Pursuant to regulations of the Commission, the public notice is hereby published of a public hearing before (the Commission) at (location), at (time) A.M. or P.M., on (date), to consider the following issue and/or rates of (name of hospital):</text>
      <text>(Set forth issues and/or rates.)</text>
      <text>The designated interested parties participating in this proceeding are:</text>
      <text>Provider Reimbursement Department of Blue Cross of Maryland, Inc.</text>
      <text>Medical Care Programs Administration of the Maryland Department of Health (Medicaid).</text>
      <text>Division of Provider Reimbursement and Accounting Policy, Bureau of Health Insurance, Social Security Administration, Department of Health, Education and Welfare of the United States (Medicare).</text>
      <text>(List other designated interested parties, if any, for the hospital in question.)</text>
      <text>Any person interested in this proceeding may attend the hearing.</text>
      <text>All persons wishing to present relevant testimony or a statement at this public hearing shall forward copies to the hospital, each designated interested party and nine copies to the Commission office. The hospital and members of the public shall forward their testimony at least 8 days before the hearing. The designated interested parties shall forward their testimony at any time before the close of the first session. The Office of the Commission is as follows:</text>
      <text class="center">Health Services Cost Review Commission</text>
      <text class="center">4160 Patterson Avenue</text>
      <text class="center">Baltimore, Maryland 21215</text>
      <text>Address of designated interested parties may be obtained at the Commission's office at 410-764-2605.</text>
      <text>All testimony and statements shall identify the proceeding to which they pertain, setting forth the name of the hospital and the docket, file and proceeding number, and must be signed by the person submitting the testimony or statement or by a representative of a group submitting testimony or a statement.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Notice of General Hearing:</text>
      <text class="center">HEALTH SERVICES COST REVIEW COMMISSION</text>
      <text class="center">PUBLIC NOTICE OF GENERAL HEARING</text>
      <text class="center">CONCERNING</text>
      <text class="center">RATE PROCEEDING OF</text>
      <text class="center">(specify type of application)</text>
      <text class="center">____________________________________</text>
      <text class="center">(name of hospital)</text>
      <text class="center">(reference to proceeding)</text>
      <text>Pursuant to rules of procedure of the Commission, public notice is hereby given of a general hearing in the above proceeding at (location), at (time) A.M., or P.M., on (date) concerning the following rates or rate components of (hospital):</text>
      <text>(Specify services and old and new rates or rate components.)</text>
      <text>Any person, group or organization interested in this matter may attend this hearing and present written or oral statements concerning the above rates or rate components.</text>
      <text>Presentations may be limited as to time and the number of spokespersons representing any group or organization may be limited.</text>
      <text>The file in the above proceeding is available at the offices of the Commission, 4160 Patterson Avenue, Baltimore, Maryland 21215.</text>
      <text class="center">HEALTH SERVICES</text>
      <text class="center">COST REVIEW COMMISSION</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Notice of Orders Nisi.</text>
      <text class="center">PUBLIC NOTICE</text>
      <text class="center">AS TO ORDERS NISI</text>
      <text class="center">HEALTH SERVICES</text>
      <text class="center">COST REVIEW COMMISSION</text>
      <text>Pursuant to regulations of the Commission, public notice is hereby given of the following Order Nisi of the Commission: (Order Nisi is to be set forth in full, including tentatively approved rates and issues.)</text>
      <text>Motions raising objections to the above tentatively approved rates and/or issues shall be submitted (in person or by mail) to the hospital and nine copies to the Commission office in legibly written or typed copies, within the above deadline, _________________, 20__, identifying the proceeding and Order Nisi to which objections are made.</text>
      <text>A copy of the Commission's decision and opinions, if any, may be obtained by written request to the Commission office as follows:</text>
      <text class="center">Health Services Cost Review Commission</text>
      <text class="center">4160 Patterson Avenue</text>
      <text class="center">Baltimore, Maryland 21215</text>
      <text>Addresses of designated interested parties may be obtained at the Commission's offices at 410-764-2605.</text>
      <text>The record of the complete proceeding in which the above Order Nisi was passed is open for public inspection at the above Commission offices during regular business hours.</text>
      <text class="center">HEALTH SERVICES</text>
      <text class="center">COST REVIEW COMMISSION</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Order Nisi.</text>
      <text class="center">ORDER NISI</text>
      <text>Upon (open public hearing) (recommendation of Commission staff, etc.), it is this _____ day of _____________________, 20__, by the Maryland Health Services Cost Review Commission,</text>
      <text><strong>ORDERED</strong>, that (the following rate of ________________________ hospital be and they hereby are approved), whatever actions are to occur or whatever issues are to be resolved, etc.), as of the ____ day of ____________ 20__, unless reasonable cause to the contrary is shown on or before the ____ day of __________, 20__.</text>
      <text class="center">MARYLAND HEALTH SERVICES</text>
      <text class="center">COST REVIEW COMMISSION</text>
      <text>A majority of the Commission members have concurred in the above Order.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Orders.</text>
      <text class="center">ORDER</text>
      <text>Upon (consideration of Motion to _________________________) (recommendation of Commission's staff, (consideration of etc.), it is, this ____ day of ___________, 20__, by the Maryland Health Services Cost Review Commission,</text>
      <text><strong>ORDERED</strong>, that (requested action) be and it hereby is (approved, disapproved, etc.)</text>
      <text class="center">MARYLAND HEALTH SERVICES</text>
      <text class="center">COST REVIEW COMMISSION</text>
      <text>A majority of the Commission members have concurred in the above Order.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Motions.</text>
      <text class="center">MOTION</text>
      <text>(Name of movant) hereby moves that the Health Services Cost Review Commission (described action to be taken or question to be answered) and as reasons therefore states:</text>
      <text>(Set for the reasons, authorities, citations, etc.)</text>
      <text>_______________________(date)_____________________________________________________(signature of movant)</text>
      <text>(Type name, title, if any, and address and telephone number of movant)</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Service.</text>
      <text class="center">CERTIFICATE OF SERVICE</text>
      <text>I HEREBY CERTIFY THAT on this ____ day of ___________,20__, I (mailed or caused to be mailed) (served or caused to be served) a copy of the above describe pleading) upon (state name and address of a party (parties) or attorney (attorneys) upon whom a copy of the pleading was served)</text>
      <text>Date: __________________, 20__</text>
    </para>
    <aftertext>________________________________________________________________________________________________________</aftertext>
    <aftertext>(Signature of party filing pleading)</aftertext>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Subpoena Duces Tecum for Rate Review.</text>
      <text class="center">WRIT OF SUBPOENA DUCES TECUM</text>
      <text>TO: (name and address of person subpoenaed)</text>
      <text>You are hereby summoned to appear in person at the Commission's offices, 4160 Patterson Avenue, Baltimore, Maryland 21215 on (date) at (time) to give testimony under oath concerning the above proceeding.</text>
      <text>You are also commanded then and there to produce the following documents and records:</text>
      <text>(description of documents and records)</text>
    </para>
    <aftertext>__________ (date) ________________________________________________________________________________________</aftertext>
    <aftertext>Health Services Cost Review Commission</aftertext>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Summons for Rate Review.</text>
      <text class="center">WRIT OF SUMMONS</text>
      <text>TO: (Name and address of person summoned)</text>
      <text>You are hereby summoned to appear in person at the Commission's offices, 4160 Patterson Avenue, Baltimore, Maryland 21215 on (date) at (time) to give testimony under oath concerning the above proceeding.</text>
    </para>
    <aftertext>__________ (date) ________________________________________________________________________________________</aftertext>
    <aftertext>Health Services Cost Review Commission</aftertext>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Summons for Hearing.</text>
      <text class="center">WRIT OF SUMMONS</text>
      <text>TO: (Name and address of person summoned)</text>
      <text>You are hereby summoned to appear in person at a public hearing before (the Commission), at (location) on (date) at (time) to testify under oath thereat.</text>
    </para>
    <aftertext>__________ (date) ________________________________________________________________________________</aftertext>
    <aftertext>Health Services Cost Review Commission</aftertext>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>Subpoena Duces Tecum for Hearing.</text>
      <text class="center">WRIT OF SUBPOENA DUCES TECUM</text>
      <text>TO: (name and address of person subpoenaed)</text>
      <text>You are hereby summoned to appear in person at a public hearing before (the Commission), in the above proceeding at (location) on (date) at (time) to testify under oath thereat.</text>
      <text>You are also commanded then and there to produce the following documents and records:</text>
      <text>(description of documents and records)</text>
    </para>
    <aftertext>__________ (date) ________________________________________________________________________________________</aftertext>
    <aftertext>Health Services Cost Review Commission</aftertext>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.18</num>
    <heading>Format.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>All pleadings, motions, and other papers filed in a Commission proceeding shall be typed or legibly written on sheets of bond paper not more than 11 inches long or 8-1/2 inches wide, and each paper shall have a left margin of at least 1 inch and a top margin of at least 1-1/2 inches.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>All pleadings, motions, and other papers, excluding exhibits appended to the pleadings, shall contain a heading at the top of the first page and, excluding appended exhibits and written direct testimony for a public hearing, a certificate of service at the bottom of the last page.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.19</num>
    <heading>Filing of a Rate Application.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A rate application filed by private messenger at the offices of the Commission shall be deemed to be filed on the date the application is received during normal working hours in the Commission's office.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A rate application sent by registered mail shall be deemed to be filed 3 days after the application is placed in the U.S. Postal Service, these days to exclude Saturdays, Sundays, and holidays on which mail is not delivered to the Commission. The rate application's file date shall be entered on the docket of the proceeding.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.20</num>
    <heading>Service.</heading>
    <text>An original and three copies of all other pleadings, documents, testimony, or motions to be considered by the Commission shall be filed at the office of the Commission during regular business hours. All pleadings, documents, testimony, or motions shall contain a certificate of service indicating that the pleading, document, testimony, or motion has been mailed or served upon all designated parties to that proceeding and upon the Commission at its offices.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.21</num>
    <heading>Computations of Time Periods and Extensions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In computing any period of time prescribed by these regulations, by order of the Commission or by any applicable statute, the day of the action or default initiating the designated period of time not be included. The last day of the period so computed is to be included unless it is a day on which the office of the Commission is closed, in which event the period runs until the end of the next day on which the office of the Commission is open. When the period of time allowed is more than 5 days, intermediate Saturdays, Sundays, and legal holidays shall be considered in the same manner as other days, but if the period of time allowed is 5 days or less, intermediate Saturdays, Sundays, and legal holidays may be not counted in computing the period of time.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>At the discretion of the Executive Director or his designee and, upon reasonable cause being shown by the submitting party, a period of time to submit a document or perform any other act permitted or prescribed by these regulations may be extended for a reasonable period of time.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.22</num>
    <heading>Motions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Motions shall be in writing, except when made at a hearing or conference and shall state concisely the question which the Commission is called upon to determine, or the action the movant desires the Commission to take. It shall state all reasons, authorities, and citations in the body of the motion or in a supporting memorandum. A certificate of service, setting forth all parties upon whom a copy of the motion was served, shall be attached to the motion.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The following actions shall be taken by motion:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Objections to actions of the Commission, or the Commission's staff; motions for clarification or reconsideration may not stay the orders of the Commission;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Demands for actions which the movant desires the Commission, or the Commission's staff to take;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Showing reasonable cause why an Order Nisi should not become effective;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Presenting a proper and justifiable question to the Commission;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Objections to the introduction of statements or other evidence by another party during a proceeding;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Challenges to members of the Commission;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Proposals for stipulations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Answers to prior motions; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>All other actions which might be initiated properly or undertaken by a party to a proceeding and which are not otherwise provided for in these regulations.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The motion shall be filed with the Commission and a copy shall be served on each affected party.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A motion need not be verified unless it is based upon facts not apparent from the record or documents filed in the proceeding.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Any affected party may answer an initial motion.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The method of considering the motion, whether by executive communication, private hearing, or public hearing shall be determined by the chairman of the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The Commission shall decide upon the question presented or action demanded in the motion in an equitable manner and as soon as practicable.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Except when a motion is made at a conference or a hearing, the order granting or denying the motion shall be in writing and shall be entered on the record of the proceeding and copies of the order shall be served upon the moving party and all affected parties.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>The decision expressed in the order shall be decided pursuant to these regulations, if provision is made. If no provision is made, the motion shall be decided by a majority of the Commission. However, motions made in the course of a private conference or at a public hearing shall be decided by the presiding officer or a majority of the Commission attending the session of the conference or hearing at which the motion was made, as provided elsewhere in these regulations. Motions made in the course of a general hearing shall be decided by the hearing officer.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.23</num>
    <heading>Subpoenas.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>At any time, the Commission may issue subpoenas directing a designated person to do the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Appear to testify at a hearing or private pre-hearing conference conducted by the Commission:</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Appear at a specified time and date at the Commission offices or any designated place within the State, and, under oath or otherwise, give testimony and answer questions of the Commission or its authorized representatives; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Produce documents, reports, or records of a particular activity for a specific period of time if he has custody of or access to the documents, reports, or records; the records may be in any reasonable form; the production shall be made at a specified time, date, and place.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A subpoena shall be in whatever form is prescribed by the Commission and shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The name, title, if any, and address of the person upon whom it is to be served and the address at which it is to be served;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The name(s), title(s), or position(s) of the witness(es) who shall appear and the time, date and place of their appearance.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A reasonable specification of the documents, reports and/or records, if any, to be produced at the designated time, date and place.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Subpoenas shall be served at least 7 days before any public hearing or private or pre-hearing conference or executive session of the Commission at which the witness or witnesses are directed to appear, and shall be served at least 3 days before a private appointment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Subpoenas shall be served in person by a person designated by the executive director or, at his discretion, by registered or certified mail, return receipt requested. A signed return of the service or the return receipt shall be entered in the file and noted on the docket of the proceeding.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A witness or a party with whom he is associated or affiliated may move to quash or modify the subpoena directed to him at any time before the date set for his appearance by filing with the Commission a motion to quash or modify the subpoena as provided in that section which pertains to motions in general.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Failure to appear or to produce documents in accordance with a subpoena shall subject the witness or the party with which he is affiliated or associated to a finding of contempt by the Commission and other penalties provided by law or these regulations.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.24</num>
    <heading>Effective Dates and Suspensions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The effective date of rates applied for in a rate application shall be 30 days from the date of the filing of the rate application with the Commission and shall be specified in the rate application.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Commission's staff may recommend the suspension of the effective date of the rates under review.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>At any time during a rate review, the Commission may order a suspension of the effective date of the rates under review, within the time specifications of Health-General Article, §19-219, Annotated Code of Maryland, and shall state the grounds for its action.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.25</num>
    <heading>Evidence, Testimony, and Official Notice.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The presiding officer at a public hearing or general hearing shall make all rulings as to evidence, testimony, and official notice and he may call on the legal counsel of the Commission for guidance in his rulings.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>All evidence and testimony shall be relevant and pertain solely to the issues being considered in a particular proceeding.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Redundant evidence or testimony may not be permitted at public or general hearings or in the records of proceedings.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Non-expert opinion testimony may be considered at a hearing and documentary opinion evidence may be entered in the record of a proceeding if the testimony or evidence is based on facts and matters admissible into evidence and the facts and matters are within the personal knowledge of the submitter of the document.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Qualification as an expert shall be within the discretion of the presiding officer of the public or general hearing at which the proposed expert may proffer testimony or evidence or, if evidence is proffered at a time other than at a public hearing, within the discretion of the chairman of the Commission considering the proceeding. The expert qualification need not be based upon academic degrees or learning; reasonably extensive practical experience with the subject may be sufficient for an expert qualification.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Subject to the provisions of these regulations, legal rules of evidence shall be followed as far as practicable at public and general hearings.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Reliable and probative documents previously filed with or compiled by the Commission or its staff or consultants that are relevant to issues being considered by the Commission may be incorporated by reference into the record of a proceeding by the Commission or, by leave of the presiding officer, by a party to the proceeding.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>In the course of a proceeding, the Commission may take official notice of facts and matters in the same manner as the courts of the State take judicial notice of facts and matters and, additionally, may take notice, without meeting formal evidentiary rules, of general, technical, or scientific facts within the specialized knowledge of a member of the Commission. However, any party to the proceeding is entitled, on timely request, to an opportunity to show that the Commission should not take official notice of specific facts and matters or that the fact or matter to be officially noticed is inapplicable to the proceeding or is incorrect or misunderstood by the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>In reviewing a hospital's rate structure, the Commission may consider or take official notice of any public document, including, but not limited to, any filing made with the Maryland Health Resources Planning Commission relative to a Certificate of Need application including all projections of volumes, revenues, rates, and feasibility studies, as well as any public document concerning the financing of a project approved pursuant to a Certificate of Need.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|37|10|.26">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.26</num>
    <heading>Patient Rights and Obligations; Hospital Credit and Collection and Financial Assistance Policies.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Hospital Information Sheet.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each hospital shall develop an information sheet that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Describes the hospital's financial assistance policy;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Describes a patient's rights and obligations with regard to hospital billing and collection under the law;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Provides contact information for the individual or office at the hospital that is available to assist the patient, the patient's family, or the patient's authorized representative in order to understand:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The patient's hospital bill;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The patient’s rights and obligations with regard to the hospital bill, including the patient’s rights and obligations with regard to reduced-cost, medically necessary care due to a financial hardship;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>How to apply for free and reduced-cost care; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>How to apply for the Maryland Medical Assistance Program and any other programs that may help pay the bill;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Provides contact information for the Maryland Medical Assistance Program;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Includes a statement that physician charges, to both hospital inpatients and outpatients, are generally not included in the hospital bill and are billed separately;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Informs patients that the hospital is permitted to bill outpatients a fee, commonly referred to as a “facility fee”, for their use of hospital facilities, clinics, supplies and equipment, and nonphysician services, including but not limited to the services of nonphysician clinicians, in addition to physician fees billed for professional services provided in the hospital;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Informs patients of their right to request and receive a written estimate of the total charges for the hospital nonemergency services, procedures, and supplies that reasonably are expected to be provided and billed for by the hospital;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Informs a patient or a patient’s authorized representative of the right to file a complaint with the Commission or jointly with the Health Education and Advocacy Unit of the Maryland Attorney General’s Office against a hospital for an alleged violation of Health-General Article, §§19-214.1 and 19-214.2, Annotated Code of Maryland, which relate to financial assistance and debt collection; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Provides the patient with the contact information for filing the complaint.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The information sheet shall be in:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Simplified language in at least 10-point type; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The patient’s preferred language or, if no preferred language is specified, each language spoken by a limited English proficient population that constitutes 5 percent of the overall population within the city or county in which the hospital is located as measured by the most recent census.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The information sheet shall be provided to the patient, the patient’s family, or the patient’s authorized representative:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Before the patient receives scheduled medical services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Before discharge;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>With the hospital bill;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>On request; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>In each written communication to the patient regarding collection of the hospital bill.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The hospital bill shall include a reference to the information sheet.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Commission shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Establish uniform requirements for the information sheet; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Review each hospital's implementation of and compliance with the requirements of this section.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>A-1.</num>
      <text>Hospital Credit and Collection Policies.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each hospital shall submit to the Commission, at times prescribed by the Commission, the hospital's policy on the collection of debts owed by patients.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The policy shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Prohibit the charging of interest on bills incurred by self-pay patients before a court judgment is obtained;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Describe in detail the consideration by the hospital of patient income, assets, and other criteria;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Describe the hospital's procedures for collecting any debt;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Describe the circumstances in which the hospital will seek a judgment against a patient;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Provide for a refund of amounts collected from a patient or the guarantor of a patient who was later found to be eligible for free care on the date of service, in accordance §A-1(3) of this regulation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>If the hospital, has obtained a judgment against or reported adverse information to a consumer reporting agency about a patient who later was found to be eligible for free care on the date of the service for which the judgment was awarded or the adverse information was reported, require the hospital to seek to vacated the judgment or strike the adverse information;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Provide a mechanism for a patient to file with the hospital a complaint against the hospital or an outside collection agency used by the hospital regarding the handling of the patient’s bill;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Provide detailed procedures for the following actions:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>When a patient debt may be reported to a credit reporting agency;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>When legal action may commence regarding a patient debt;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>When garnishments may be applied to a patient’s or patient guarantor’s income; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>When a lien on a patient’s or patient guarantor’s personal residence or motor vehicle may be placed.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Beginning October 1, 2010, as provided by Health-General Article, §19-214.2(c):</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A hospital shall provide for a refund of amounts exceeding $25 collected from a patient or the guarantor of a patient who, within a 2-year period after the date of service, was found to be eligible for free care on the date of service;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A hospital may reduce the 2-year period under §A-1(3)(a) of this regulation to no less than 30 days after the date the hospital requests information from a patient, or the guarantor of a patient, to determine the patient’s eligibility for free care at the time of service, if the hospital documents the lack of cooperation of the patient or the guarantor of a patient in providing the required information; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If a patient is enrolled in a means-tested government health care plan that requires the patient to pay out-of-pocket for hospital service, a hospital shall have a refund policy that complies with the terms of the patient’s plan.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>For at least 120 days after issuing an initial patient bill, a hospital may not report adverse information about a patient to a consumer reporting agency or commence civil action against a patient for nonpayment unless the hospital documents the lack of cooperation of the patient or the guarantor of the patient in providing information needed to determine the patient’s obligation with regard to the hospital bill.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A hospital shall report the fulfillment of a patient’s payment obligation within 60 days after the obligation is fulfilled to any consumer reporting agency to which the hospital had reported adverse information about the patient.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A hospital may not force the sale or foreclosure of a patient’s primary residence to collect a debt owed on a hospital bill. If a hospital holds a lien on a patient’s primary residence, the hospital may maintain its position as a secured creditor with respect to other creditors to whom the patient may owe a debt.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>If a hospital delegates collection activity to an outside collection agency, the hospital shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Specify the collection activity to be performed by the outside collection agency through an explicit authorization or contract;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Specify procedures the outside collection agency must follow if a patient appears to qualify for financial assistance; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Require the outside collection agency to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>In accordance with the hospital’s policy, provide a mechanism for a patient to file with the hospital a complaint against the hospital or the outside collection agency regarding the handing of patient’s bill; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>If a patient files a complaint with the collection agency, forward the complaint to the hospital.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The Board of Directors of each hospital shall review and approve the financial assistance and debt collection policies of the hospital every 2 years. A hospital may not alter its financial assistance or debt collection policies without approval by the Board of Directors.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>The Commission shall review each hospital's implementation of and compliance with the hospital's policy and the requirements of §A-1(2) of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>A-2.</num>
      <text>Hospital Financial Assistance Responsibilities.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Definitions.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In this regulation, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Terms Defined.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>“Financial hardship” means medical debt, incurred by a family over a 12-month period that exceeds 25 percent of family income.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>“Medical debt” means out-of-pocket expenses, excluding copayments, coinsurance, and deductibles, for medical costs billed by a hospital.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Financial Assistance Policy.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>On or before June 1, 2009, each hospital and, on or before October 1, 2010, each chronic care hospital under the jurisdiction of the Commission shall develop a written financial assistance policy for providing free and reduced-cost care to low-income patients who lack health care coverage or to patients whose health insurance does not pay the full cost of the hospital bill. A hospital shall provide notice of the hospital’s financial assistance policy to the patient, the patient’s family, or the patient’s authorized representative before discharging the patient and in each communication to the patient regarding collection of the hospital bill. The financial assistance policy shall provide at a minimum:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Free medically necessary care to patients with family income at or below 200 percent of the federal poverty level;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Reduced-cost, medically necessary care to low-income patients with family income between 200 and 300 percent of the federal poverty level, in accordance with the mission and service area of the hospital;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A maximum patient payment for reduced-cost care not to exceed the charges minus the hospital mark-up;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>A payment plan available to patients irrespective of their insurance status with family income between 200 and 500 percent of the federal poverty level who request assistance; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>A mechanism for a patient, irrespective of that patient’s insurance status, to request the hospital to reconsider the denial of free or reduced care, including the address, phone number, facsimile number, email address, mailing address, and website of the Health Education and Advocacy Unit, which can assist the patient or patient’s authorized representative in filing and mediating a reconsideration request.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A hospital whose financial assistance policy as of May 8, 2009, provides for free or reduced-cost medical care to a patient at an income threshold higher than those set forth above may not reduce that income threshold.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Presumptive Eligibility for Free Care. Unless otherwise eligible for Medicaid or CHIP, patients who are beneficiaries/recipients of the following means-tested social services programs are deemed eligible for free care, provided that the patient submits proof of enrollment within 30 days unless the patient or the patient’s representative requests an additional 30 days:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Households with children in the free or reduced lunch program;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Supplemental Nutritional Assistance Program (SNAP);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Low-income-household energy assistance program;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Primary Adult Care Program (PAC), until such time as inpatient benefits are added to the PAC benefit package;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Women, Infants and Children (WIC); or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Other means-tested social services programs deemed eligible for hospital free care policies by the Maryland Department of Health and the HSCRC, consistent with HSCRC regulation <cite path="10.37.10.26">COMAR 10.37.10.26</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A hospital that believes that an increase to the income thresholds as set forth above may result in undue financial hardship to it may file a written request with the Commission that it be exempted from the increased threshold. In evaluating the hospital’s request for exemption, the Commission shall consider the hospital’s:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Patient mix;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Financial condition;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Level of bad debt experienced;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Amount of charity care provided; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Other relevant factors.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Based on staff’s evaluation of the written request for an exemption, the Executive Director shall respond in writing within a reasonable period of time approving or disapproving the hospital’s exemption request.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>A hospital denied an exemption request shall be afforded an opportunity to address the Commission at a public meeting on its request. Based on arguments made at the public meeting, the Commission may approve, disapprove, or modify the Executive Director’s decision on the exemption request.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Each hospital shall submit to the Commission within 60 days after the end of each hospital’s fiscal year:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The hospital’s financial assistance policy developed under this section; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An annual report on the hospital’s financial assistance policy that includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The total number of patients who completed or partially completed an application for financial assistance during the prior year;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The total number of inpatients and outpatients who received free care during the immediately preceding year and reduced-cost care for the prior year;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The total number of patients who received financial assistance during the immediately preceding year, by race or ethnicity and gender;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>The total number of patients who were denied financial assistance during the immediately preceding year, by race or ethnicity and gender;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>The total cost of hospital services provided to patients who received free care; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>The total  cost of hospital services provided to patients who received reduced-cost care that was covered by the hospital as financial assistance or that the hospital charged to the patient.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Financial Hardship Policy.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Subject to §A-2(3)(b) and (c) of this regulation, the financial assistance policy required under this regulation shall provide reduced-cost, medically necessary care to patients with family income below 500 percent of the federal poverty level who have a financial hardship.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A hospital may seek and the Commission may approve a family income threshold that is different than the family income threshold under §A-2(C)(1) of this regulation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>In evaluating a hospital’s request to establish a different family income threshold, the Commission shall take into account:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The median family income in the hospital’s service area;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The patient mix of the hospital;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The financial condition of the hospital;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>The level of bad debt experienced by the hospital;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>The amount of the charity care provided by the hospital; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Other relevant factors.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>If a patient has received reduced-cost, medically necessary care due to a financial hardship, the patient or any immediate family member of the patient living in the same household:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Shall remain eligible for reduced-cost, medically necessary care when seeking subsequent care at the same hospital during the 12-month period beginning on the date on which the reduced-cost, medically necessary care was initially received; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>To avoid an unnecessary duplication of the hospital’s determination of eligibility for free and reduced-cost care, shall inform the hospital of the patient’s or family member’s eligibility for the reduced-cost, medically necessary care.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If a patient is eligible for reduced-cost medical care under a hospital’s financial assistance policy or financial hardship policy, the hospital shall apply the reduction in charges that is most favorable to the patient.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A notice shall be posted in conspicuous places throughout the hospital including the billing office informing patients of their right to apply for financial assistance and who to contact at the hospital for additional information.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The notice required under §A-2(6) of this regulation shall be in:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Simplified language in at least 10-point type; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The patient’s preferred language or, if no preferred language is specified, each language spoken by a limited English proficient population that constitutes 5 percent of the overall population within the city or county in which the hospital is located as measured by the most recent census.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Each hospital shall use a Uniform Financial Assistance Application in the manner prescribed by the Commission in order to determine eligibility for free and reduced-cost care.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Each hospital shall establish a mechanism to provide the Uniform Financial Assistance Application to patients regardless of their insurance status. A hospital may require from patients or their guardians only those documents required to validate the information provided on the application.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Asset Test Requirements. A hospital may, in its discretion, consider household monetary assets in determining eligibility for financial assistance in addition to the income-based criteria, or it may choose to use only income-based criteria. If a hospital chooses to utilize an asset test, the following types of monetary assets, which are those assets that are convertible to cash, shall be excluded:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>At a minimum, the first $10,000 of monetary assets;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A “safe harbor” equity of $150,000 in a primary residence;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Retirement assets to which the Internal Revenue Service has granted preferential tax treatment as a retirement account, including, but not limited to, deferred-compensation plans qualified under the Internal Revenue Code or nonqualified deferred-compensation plans;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>One motor vehicle used for the transportation needs of the patient or any family member of the patient;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Any resources excluded in determining financial eligibility under the Medical Assistance Program under the Social Security Act; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Prepaid higher education funds in a Maryland 529 Program account.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Monetary assets excluded from the determination of eligibility for free and reduced-cost care under these provisions shall be adjusted annually for inflation in accordance with the Consumer Price Index.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>In determining the family income of a patient, a hospital shall apply a definition of household size that consists of the patient and, at a minimum, the following individuals:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A spouse, regardless of whether the patient and spouse expect to file a joint federal or State tax return;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Biological children, adopted children, or stepchildren; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Anyone for whom the patient claims a personal exemption in a federal or State tax return.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>For a patient who is a child, the household size shall consist of the child and the following individuals:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Biological parents, adoptive parents, stepparents, or guardians;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Biological siblings, adopted siblings, or stepsiblings; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Anyone for whom the patient’s parents or guardians claim a personal exemption in a federal or State tax return.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>A-3.</num>
      <text>Patient Complaints. The Commission shall post a process on its website for a patient or a patient’s authorized representative to file with the Commission a complaint against a hospital for an alleged violation of Health-General Article, §19–214.1 or 19–214.2, Annotated Code of Maryland. The process established shall include the option for a patient or a patient’s authorized representative to file the complaint jointly with the Commission and the Health Education and Advocacy Unit. The process shall conform to the requirements of Health-General Article, §19-214.3, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Working Capital Differentials — Payment of Charges.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A third-party payer may obtain a discount in rates established by the Commission if it provides current financing monies in accordance with the following terms.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A third-party payer that provides current financing equal to the average amount of outstanding charges for bills from the end of each regular billing period and for discharged patients shall be entitled to a 2-percent discount. For purposes of this regulation, a regular billing period shall be based on a 30-day billing cycle. The current financing provided in here corresponds to a third party's paying on discharge.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A third-party payer that provides current financing equal to the average amount of outstanding charges for discharged patients plus the average daily charges times the average length of stay, shall be entitled to a 2.25-percent discount. The current financing provided in here corresponds to a third party's paying on admission.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Outstanding charges shall be calculated by an amount equal to the hospital’s current average daily payment by the payer, multiplied by the hospital’s and third party payer’s processing and payment time. The precise calculation shall be made in accordance with the guidelines specified by Commission staff.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Upon request from an applicant, the Commission may approve an alternative method of calculating current financing monies.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The third-party payer shall adjust the current financing advance to reflect Commission rate orders and changes in volume associated with the particular payer and hospital. This adjustment shall be made within 45 days of a rate order or at such other time as circumstances warrant. In the absence of a rate order, the adjustment shall be made at least annually.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The third-party payer shall promptly provide the Commission with a verified record of the detailed calculation of the current financing and of each recalculated balance as adjustments are made. The detailed calculations shall become a part of the public record. The Commission may, at any time, evaluate the amount of current financing monies provided to a hospital to assure that it meets the discount of requirements specified in <cite path="10|37|10|.26|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite>. If the Commission finds that the amount of current financing is inconsistent with the requirements of §B(1), the Commission may, at its sole discretion, require an adjustment to the working capital advance or to the discount.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A payer or self-paying patient, who does not provide current financing under §B(1)(a)—(e) of this regulation, shall receive a 2-percent discount if payment is made at the earlier of the end of each regular billing period or upon discharge from the hospital. Payment within 30 days of the earlier of the end of each regular billing period or discharge entitles a payer or self-pay patient to a 1-percent discount. For those payers not subject to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-1005">Insurance Article, §15-1005, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, after 60 days from the date of the earlier of the end of each regular billing period or discharge, interest or late payment charges may accrue on any unpaid charges at a simple rate of 1 percent per month. The interest or late payment charges may be added to the charge on the 61st day after the date of the earlier of the end of each regular billing period or discharge and every 30 days after that.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Hospital Billing Responsibilities.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A patient shall be given a bill for services at the earlier of the end of each regular billing period or upon discharge or dismissal (when dismissal for outpatients is analogous to discharge for inpatients).</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>This bill shall cover substantially all care rendered and should, except for some last day ancillary services and excepting arithmetic errors, represent the full charge for the patient's care. In addition, a notice shall be posted prominently at the billing office of the hospital clearly notifying all patients of the availability of the discounts mentioned above.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The bill and the notice shall state that the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Charge is due within 60 days of discharge or dismissal;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Patient shall receive a 2-percent discount by paying upon discharge or a 1-percent discount by paying within 30 days; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Payers not subject to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-1005">Insurance Article, §15-1005, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, may be subject to interest or late payment charges at a rate of 1 percent per month beginning on the 61st day after the date of the earlier of the end of each regular billing period or discharge and every 30 days after that.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Hospital Written Estimate.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>On request of a patient made before or during treatment, a hospital shall provide to the patient a written estimate of the total charges for the hospital services, procedures, and supplies that reasonably are expected to be provided and billed to the patient by the hospital.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The written estimate shall state clearly that it is only an estimate and actual charges could vary.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A hospital may restrict the availability of a written estimate to normal business office hours.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The provisions set forth in §B(5)(a)—(c) of this regulation do not apply to emergency services.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>GME Discounts. In those instances where a teaching hospital is reimbursed separately for the costs associated with the provision of graduate medical education (GME), the Commission shall calculate the percentage of the hospital's rates that these GME payments represent and provide notice of the amounts that may be credited toward the payment for services rendered. At all times, total payment received by the teaching hospital shall be in accordance with Commission-approved rates.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.26-1</num>
    <heading>Maryland Health Insurance Plan (MHIP) Assessment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Commission shall determine and assess those funds necessary to operate and administer the MHIP. The Commission shall adjust hospital rates to implement the revenue neutral assessment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Commission shall assess each hospital up to 1 percent of its net patient revenue to operate and administer the MHIP. There shall be no MHIP assessment for Fiscal Year 2016.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Beginning on September 5, 2003, each hospital whose rates have been approved by the Commission shall remit monthly, by the 5th of each month, 1/12 of its total share of the annual funding assessment determined by the Commission to be owed by the hospital to the Maryland Health Insurance Plan Fund as established under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin">Insurance Article, Title 14, Subtitle 5, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A hospital that fails to remit its funding assessment due in a timely manner may be subject to an annualized interest charge of 3 percentage points above the most recent average prime rate of interest, as published in the "Money Rates" section of The Wall Street Journal, on the unpaid balance. In addition, the Commission may impose penalties of up to 5 percent of the amount of any underpayment made by the hospital.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.26-2</num>
    <heading>Assessment for Savings in Averted Uncompensated Care.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Beginning July 1, 2008, the Commission shall assess annually a uniform, broad-based, and reasonable amount in hospital rates to reflect the aggregate reduction in hospital uncompensated care resulting from the expansion of health care coverage under Ch. 7, Acts of 2007 Special Session.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Given the prospective nature of the rate system, the Commission shall ensure that the assessment amount does not exceed the savings projected in averted hospital uncompensated care from the health care coverage expansion. The Commission shall notify hospitals annually of the amount to be assessed by July 1 of each year, to be effective July 1.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Beginning September 2008, on or before the 5th business day of each month, each hospital assessed in accordance with Health-General Article §19-214, Annotated Code of Maryland, and the provisions of this regulation shall make payment into the Health Care Coverage Fund established under Health-General Article, §15-701, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A hospital that fails to remit its monthly funding assessment in a timely manner may be subject to an annualized interest charge of 3 percent the most recent average prime rate of interest, as published in the "Money Rates" section of the Wall Street Journal, on the unpaid balance. In addition, the Commission may impose penalties of up to 5 percent of the amount of any underpayment made by the hospital.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.27</num>
    <heading>Designated Interested Parties.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Designated interested parties for a specific rate review proceeding may include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Those community oriented groups which the Commission determines have a significant interest in the hospital and its rate application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Those third-party payors or their representatives who have been designated by the Commission as interested parties for this proceeding;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The hospital whose rates are being reviewed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Maryland Health and Higher Educational Facilities Authority for rate review proceedings concerning hospitals with capital financing through the Authority.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Group Hospitalization, Incorporated, for rate review proceedings concerning hospitals with which it has contractual relations; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Legal Aid Bureau of Baltimore City.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Designated interested parties for all rate applications are:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provider Reimbursement Department of Blue Cross of Maryland, Inc.;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Medical Care Programs Administration of the Maryland Department of Health (Medicaid);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Division of Provider Reimbursement and Accounting Policy, Bureau of Health Insurance, Social Security Administration, Department of Health, Education and Welfare of the United States (Medicare); and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Health Insurance Association of America.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.28</num>
    <heading>Right to Counsel.</heading>
    <text>A hospital or any other party in a rate review proceeding may be represented by legal counsel at any or all times during the proceeding, but there is no requirement that parties have legal counsel.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.29</num>
    <heading>Challenges.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Any party to a proceeding may challenge the ability of any member of the Commission to consider the rates or issues in that proceeding. Excepting private conferences, this challenge shall be made during the proceeding before its first hearing. Challenges may not be permitted after the first hearing, except in extraordinary circumstances.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A challenge shall be verified in writing, specifying the member of the Commission and shall set forth all its reasons. The challenge shall be filed with the Commission and entered upon the record of the proceeding.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A copy of the challenge shall be forwarded to the challenged member immediately after it is filed, and he may make whatever response he deems proper and necessary.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The challenge shall be denied or allowed by a majority of the Commission, excluding the challenged member. The order based on the decision shall be filed with the Commission, entered in the record of the proceeding and served on the challenged member and the challenging party.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If a challenge to a Commission member is allowed, he immediately shall cease all participation in the proceeding in question as a Commission member.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The allowance of a challenge to a member of the Commission may not, in itself, disqualify him from serving as a Commission member in other matters and proceedings.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.30</num>
    <heading>Consolidation.</heading>
    <text>When two or more rate proceedings involve common questions of fact, the Commission, upon a majority vote of its members, may order that the common questions of fact be decided in a consolidated proceeding.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.31</num>
    <heading>Burden of Proof.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In proceedings initiated by a regular, temporary, or new hospital rate application, the burden of proof of the reasonableness, equity, and lack of undue discrimination of the proposed rates shall rest with the hospital.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In proceedings initiated by an application for an alternative method of rate determination, the burden of proof of the applicability of the alternative method of rate review to the hospital shall rest with the hospital.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In proceedings initiated by an order for Commission review of established rates, the burden of proof of the reasonableness, equity, and lack of undue discrimination of the established rates under review shall rest with the hospital.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.32</num>
    <heading>Severability.</heading>
    <text>If any section or provision of these regulations is declared unconstitutional or void by any court of competent jurisdiction, or its applicability to any person or circumstances is held invalid, the constitutionality or validity of the remainder of the regulations and the applicability to other persons and circumstances are not affected, and to this end, the sections and provisions of these regulations are declared to be severable.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.33</num>
    <heading>Petition for Promulgation, Amendment, or Repeal of Regulation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Any interested party may file with the Commission a petition for the promulgation, amendment, or repeal of a regulation designed to implement, interpret, or prescribe law, policy, organization, procedure, or practice requirements of the Commission. The petition shall set forth:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The interest of the petitioner and the nature of the relief desired;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Any facts, views, arguments, and data deemed relevant by the petitioner;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Verification under oath by the party or by a duly authorized officer or agent of the party, whose address and title shall be stated.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the petition is for the promulgation of a regulation, a copy of the proposed regulation shall be attached.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the petition is for the amendment of a regulation, a copy of the amended regulation shall be attached with new matters underlined and matters to be deleted bracketed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>In addition to and accompanying the original of the petition filed with the Commission, there shall be 12 copies for use of the Commission and other interested parties.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Commission shall consider the petition as well as all comments relating to it by interested parties. Within 30 days from the filing of the petition, the Commission shall render a decision:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Denying the petition and stating the reasons therefor; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Submitting the proposed action to the Maryland Register for notice to, and comments by, all interested parties.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.34</num>
    <heading>Petition for Declaratory Ruling.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An interested person may file with the Commission a petition for a declaratory ruling with respect to the manner in which the Commission would apply a statute that the Commission enforces, a regulation of the Commission, or an order of the Commission, to a person or property on the facts set forth in the petition.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The petition for a declaratory ruling shall be filed in writing and shall contain a statement describing in detail the interest of the petitioner in making the request, the issues involved, a statement of the facts, a listing of documents or statements, or both, to be considered, and a sworn statement by the petitioner that the facts contained there are true to the best of the person's knowledge and belief.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Sixty days from the receipt of the petition the Commission shall inform the petitioner whether the petition will be granted. If the petition is not granted the Commission shall inform the petitioner in writing of the reasons for the denial. If the petition is granted, the Commission shall inform the petitioner when to expect the declaratory ruling.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.35</num>
    <heading>Consideration and Disposition.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Consideration.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The petition shall be granted whenever the Commission deems issuing a declaratory ruling advisable under the circumstances.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In rendering its declaratory ruling, the Commission:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Shall consider all the materials submitted with the petition; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>May, in its discretion:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Consult individuals or materials outside the corners of the petition; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Require argument of the question or permit the introduction of evidence.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Disposition.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A declaratory ruling issued shall be in writing, stating the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Issue;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Conclusion;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Facts upon which the conclusion was based; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Sources relied upon.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A declaratory relief issued by the Commission shall plainly state on its face that it is a declaratory ruling pursuant to this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A written answer from the Commission to an inquiry may not be construed as a declaratory ruling unless made in conformity with these regulations.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Publication and Inspection. The Commission:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall keep a record of each declaratory ruling issued and index all declaratory rulings issued by reference to statute or statutes or regulation or regulations involved.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>May publish a declaratory ruling of general interest subject to the mandates of the Public Information Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-601">State Government Article, §10-601 </cite>et seq., Annotated Code of Maryland, and allow inspection of the declaratory rulings subject to the Public Information Act.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Denial of a Petition for Declaratory Ruling. A petition may be denied if the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Request contains incomplete information upon which to base an informed declaratory ruling;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Commission concludes that a declaratory ruling cannot reasonably be given on the matter;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Matter is adequately covered by a prior regulation, declaratory ruling, decision, or legal opinion; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Commission concludes that a declaratory ruling would not be in the public interest.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.36</num>
    <heading>Effect and Appeal.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Effect.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A declaratory ruling shall be binding upon the Commission and the petitioner on the statement of facts covered in the declaratory ruling and set forth in the petition.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>After notice and an opportunity to reply, a declaratory ruling may be reconsidered, amended, altered, or revoked by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Appeal. A declaratory ruling is subject to review as provided in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-305">State Government Article, §10-305, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health-General Article, §§15-601 et seq. and 19-201, 19-207, 19-210—19-214, 19-214.1, 19-214.2, 19-214.3, 19-216—19-220, and 19-222;<br/>Insurance Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|14-501">14-501</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|14-502">14-502</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|14-504">14-504</cite>; State Government Article, §10-304(b); Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1974-11-07">Effective date: November 7, 1974 (1:4 Md. R. 177)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1975-08-20"><cite path="|10|37|10|.16">Regulation .16</cite> amended effective August 20, 1975 (2:18 Md. R. 1234)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1975-12-10"><cite path="|10|37|10|.10">Regulation .10</cite>0 adopted effective December 10, 1975 (2:28 Md. R. 1680)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1976-10-27" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective October 27, 1976 (3:22 Md. R. 1250)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-11-08"><cite path="|10|37|10|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective November 8, 2004 (31:22 Md. R. 1595)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-01-08"><cite path="|10|37|10|.01|I.">Regulation .01I</cite>, J adopted effective January 8, 1990 (16:26 Md. R. 2794)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-05-12"><cite path="|10|37|10|.01|K.">Regulation .01K</cite> adopted effective May 12, 2003 (30:9 Md. R. 615)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-10-05"><cite path="|10|37|10|.01-1">Regulation .01-1</cite> adopted effective October 5, 1998 (25:20 Md. R. 1531)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1987-12-14"><cite path="|10|37|10|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective December 14, 1987 (14:25 Md. R. 2660)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-06-15"><cite path="|10|37|10|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective June 15, 1998 (25:14 Md. R. 1127); emergency status expired December 15, 1998</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-01-15"><cite path="|10|37|10|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective August 5, 2002 (29:15 Md. R. 1142); January 15, 2018 (45:1 Md. R. 14)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-07-01"><cite path="|10|37|10|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 1, 2000 (27:17 Md. R. 1616); emergency status extended at 27:26 Md. R. 2356; emergency status extended at 28:7 Md. R. 687; emergency status expired July 1, 2001</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-12-13"><cite path="|10|37|10|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite> amended effective November 7, 2005 (32:22 Md. R. 1756); October 8, 2007 (34:20 Md. R. 1740); April 11, 2016 (43:7 Md. R. 450); January 16, 2017 (44:1 Md. R. 12); December 13, 2021 (48:25 Md. R. 1080)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-11-03"><cite path="|10|37|10|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective November 3, 2022 (49:25 Md. R. 1048); emergency provision expired May 1, 2023</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-05-01"><cite path="|10|37|10|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite> amended effective May 1, 2023 (50:8 Md. R. 338)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-03-15"><cite path="|10|37|10|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite> amended effective September 1, 2003 (30:17 Md. R. 1203); March 15, 2004 (31:5 Md. R. 449)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1984-11-19"><cite path="|10|37|10|.03|C.">Regulation .03C</cite> adopted effective November 19, 1984 (11:23 Md. R. 1993)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1988-10-03"><cite path="|10|37|10|.03|C.">Regulation .03C</cite> amended effective October 3, 1988 (15:20 Md. R. 2334)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-01-08"><cite path="|10|37|10|.03|D.">Regulation .03D</cite> adopted effective January 8, 1990 (16:26 Md. R. 2794)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-08-05"><cite path="|10|37|10|.03|D.">Regulation .03D</cite> recodified as .03C effective August 5, 2002 (29:15 Md. R. 1142)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-05-10"><cite path="|10|37|10|.03|D.">Regulation .03D</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective January 1, 2004 (31:4 Md. R. 313); adopted permanently effective May 10, 2004 (31:9 Md. R. 713)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-10-05"><cite path="|10|37|10|.03|D.">Regulation .03D</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 1, 2009 (36:15 Md. R. 1163); amended permanently effective October 5, 2009 (36:20 Md. R. 1529)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-11-08"><cite path="|10|37|10|.03-1">Regulation .03-1</cite> adopted effective November 8, 2004 (31:22 Md. R. 1595)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-01-15"><cite path="|10|37|10|.03-1A">Regulation .03-1A</cite> amended effective January 15, 2018 (45:1 Md. R. 14)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-04-11"><cite path="|10|37|10|.03-1B">Regulation .03-1B</cite> amended effective May 8, 2006 (33:9 Md. R. 796); April 11, 2016 (43:7 Md. R. 450)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1979-06-15"><cite path="|10|37|10|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective June 15, 1979 (6:12 Md. R. 1050)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-05-01"><cite path="|10|37|10|.04|C.">Regulation .04C</cite> adopted effective May 1, 2023 (50:8 Md. R. 338)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-02-08"><cite path="|10|37|10|.04-1">Regulation .04-1</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective October 8, 1998 (25:22 Md. R. 1650); adopted permanently effective February 8, 1999 (26:3 Md. R. 175)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-09-03"><cite path="|10|37|10|.04-1">Regulation .04-1</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective May 21, 2001 (28:13 Md. R. 1214); amended permanently effective September 3, 2001 (28:17 Md. R. 1557)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-01-15"><cite path="|10|37|10|.04-1">Regulation .04-1</cite> amended effective January 15, 2018 (45:1 Md. R. 14)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-11-13"><cite path="|10|37|10|.04-2">Regulation .04-2</cite> adopted effective November 13, 2000 (27:22 Md. R. 2060)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-01-15"><cite path="|10|37|10|.04-2">Regulation .04-2</cite> amended effective April 30, 2001 (28:8 Md. R. 760); January 15, 2018 (45:1 Md. R. 14)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-01-12"><cite path="|10|37|10|.04-2A">Regulation .04-2A</cite>, C amended effective January 12, 2009 (36:1 Md. R. 22)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-10-09"><cite path="|10|37|10|.04-2C">Regulation .04-2C</cite> amended effective October 9, 2006 (33:20 Md. R. 1617)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-11-13"><cite path="|10|37|10|.04-3">Regulation .04-3</cite> adopted effective November 13, 2000 (27:22 Md. R. 2060)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-01-15"><cite path="|10|37|10|.04-3">Regulation .04-3</cite> amended effective April 30, 2001 (28:8 Md. R. 760); January 15, 2018 (45:1 Md. R. 14)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-11-13"><cite path="|10|37|10|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 1, 2000 (27:17 Md. R. 1617); amended permanently effective November 13, 2000 (27:22 Md. R. 2060)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-09-03"><cite path="|10|37|10|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective September 3, 2001 (28:17 Md. R. 1557)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-11-03"><cite path="|10|37|10|.05|F.">Regulation .05F</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective November 3, 2022 (49:25 Md. R. 1048); emergency provision expired May 1, 2023</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-05-01"><cite path="|10|37|10|.05|F.">Regulation .05F</cite> amended effective May 1, 2023 (50:8 Md. R. 338)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-08-28"><cite path="|10|37|10|.06|E.">Regulation .06E</cite> adopted effective August 28, 1995 (22:17 Md. R. 1318)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-02-09"><cite path="|10|37|10|.06|E.">Regulation .06E</cite> amended effective September 9, 1996 (23:18 Md. R. 1317); November 4, 1996 (23:22 Md. R. 1497); February 9, 1998 (25:3 Md. R. 146)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-10-05"><cite path="|10|37|10|.06|E.">Regulation .06E</cite> recodified to .06F and new .06E adopted effective October 5, 1998 (25:20 Md. R. 1531)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-03-04"><cite path="|10|37|10|.06|F.">Regulation .06F</cite> amended effective March 4, 2013 (40:4 Md. R. 346)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-10-09"><cite path="|10|37|10|.06|G.">Regulation .06G</cite> adopted effective October 9, 2006 (33:20 Md. R. 1617)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1977-08-31"><cite path="|10|37|10|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective August 31, 1977 (4:18 Md. R. 1398)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-09-10"><cite path="|10|37|10|.07-1">Regulation .07-1</cite> adopted effective September 10, 2007 (34:18 Md. R. 1580)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-12-13"><cite path="|10|37|10|.07-1A">Regulation .07-1A</cite> amended effective December 13, 2021 (48:25 Md. R. 1080)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-05-09"><cite path="|10|37|10|.07-1C">Regulation .07-1C</cite> amended effective December 21, 2015 (42:25 Md. R. 1544); May 9, 2016 (43:9 Md. R. 530)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-05-14"><cite path="|10|37|10|.07-1E">Regulation .07-1E</cite> amended effective May 14, 2012 (39:9 Md. R. 612)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-12-13"><cite path="|10|37|10|.07-1K">Regulation .07-1K</cite>, L adopted effective December 13, 2021 (48:25 Md. R. 1080)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-01-16"><cite path="|10|37|10|.07-2">Regulation .07-2</cite> adopted effective January 16, 2017 (44:1 Md. R. 12)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-12-21"><cite path="|10|37|10|.10|C.">Regulation .10C</cite> amended effective April 9, 1984 (11:7 Md. R. 626); March 8, 1999 (26:5 Md. R. 391); December 21, 2015 (42:25 Md. R. 1544)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1981-05-29">Regulations .11C and .12B amended effective May 29, 1981 (8:11 Md. R. 975)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-01-15"><cite path="|10|37|10|.11|G.">Regulation .11G</cite> adopted effective January 15, 2018 (45:1 Md. R. 14)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1980-09-19"><cite path="|10|37|10|.13|B.">Regulation .13B</cite> amended effective September 19, 1980 (7:19 Md. R. 1806)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1978-07-28"><cite path="|10|37|10|.13|H.">Regulation .13H</cite> adopted effective July 28, 1978 (5:15 Md. R. 1190) (originally codified as Regulation .12G)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-12-12"><cite path="|10|37|10|.14|I.">Regulation .14I</cite> amended effective December 12, 2002 (29:24 Md. R. 1919)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-03-08"><cite path="|10|37|10|.20">Regulation .20</cite> amended effective April 9, 1984 (11:7 Md. R. 626); March 8, 1999 (26:5 Md. R. 391)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1977-05-11"><cite path="|10|37|10|.23">Regulation .23</cite> amended effective May 11, 1977 (4:10 Md. R. 767)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1983-05-09"><cite path="|10|37|10|.25|I.">Regulation .25I</cite> adopted effective May 9, 1983 (10:9 Md. R. 791)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-10-05"><cite path="|10|37|10|.26">Regulation .26</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective June 19, 2009 (36:15 Md. R. 1163); amended permanently effective October 5, 2009 (36:20 Md. R. 1530)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-11-15"><cite path="|10|37|10|.26">Regulation .26</cite> amended effective November 15, 2010 (37:23 Md. R. 1611)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-08-01"><cite path="|10|37|10|.26|A.">Regulation .26A</cite> amended effective July 1, 1988 (15:13 Md. R. 1555); April 3, 1989 (16:6 Md. R. 728); November 26, 1990 (17:23 Md. R. 2732); March 30, 1992 (19:6 Md. R. 674); June 7, 1993 (20:11 Md. R. 913); July 5, 1993 (20:13 Md. R. 1049); August 1, 1994 (21:15 Md. R. 1306)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1996-06-01"><cite path="|10|37|10|.26|A.">Regulation .26A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective June 1, 1996 (23:13 Md. R. 938); emergency status expired November 13, 1996</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1996-12-30"><cite path="|10|37|10|.26|A.">Regulation .26A</cite> amended December 30, 1996 (23:26 Md. R. 1860)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-10-31"><cite path="|10|37|10|.26|A.">Regulation .26A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective November 24, 1997 (24:26 Md. R. 1752); emergency status extended to August 31, 1998 (25:12 Md. R. 943); emergency status extended to October 31, 1998 (25:18 Md. R. 1431)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-10-05"><cite path="|10|37|10|.26|A.">Regulation .26A</cite> amended October 5, 1998 (25:20 Md. R. 1531)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-06-28"><cite path="|10|37|10|.26|A.">Regulation .26A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective February 25, 1999 (26:6 Md. R. 480); amended permanently effective June 28, 1999 (26:13 Md. R. 1020)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-11-13"><cite path="|10|37|10|.26|A.">Regulation .26A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective June 26, 2000 (27:15 Md. R. 1397); amended permanently effective November 13, 2000 (27:22 Md. R. 2060)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-04-30"><cite path="|10|37|10|.26|A.">Regulation .26A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective December 6, 2000 (28:3 Md. R. 203); amended permanently effective April 30, 2001 (28:8 Md. R. 760)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-05-13"><cite path="|10|37|10|.26|A.">Regulation .26A</cite> amended effective October 29, 2001 (28:21 Md. R. 1856); May 13, 2002 (29:9 Md. R. 745)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-09-01"><cite path="|10|37|10|.26|A.">Regulation .26A</cite> repealed effective September 1, 2003 (30:17 Md. R. 1203)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-04-05"><cite path="|10|37|10|.26|A.">Regulation .26A</cite> amended effective November 15, 2010 (37:23 Md. R. 1611); August 6, 2012 (39:15 Md. R. 963); May 6, 2019 (46:9 Md. R. 445); April 5, 2021 (48:7 Md. R. 259)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-04-05"><cite path="|10|37|10|.26|A.">Regulation .26A</cite>-2 amended effective December 10, 2012 (39:24 Md. R. 1577); April 5, 2021 (48:7 Md. R. 259)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-04-05"><cite path="|10|37|10|.26|A.">Regulation .26A</cite>-3 adopted effective April 5, 2021 (48:7 Md. R. 259)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-08-04"><cite path="|10|37|10|.26|B.">Regulation .26B</cite> amended effective October 3, 1988 (15:20 Md. R. 2334); May 29, 1989 (16:10 Md. R. 1109); May 14, 1990 (17:9 Md. R. 1092); August 1, 1994 (21:15 Md. R. 1306); March 11, 1996 (23:5 Md. R. 380); September 30, 2002 (29:19 Md. R. 1524); April 10, 2006 (33:7 Md. R. 673); April 5, 2010 (37:7 Md. R. 572); August 4, 2014 (41:15 Md. R. 891)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-09-07"><cite path="|10|37|10|.26|C.">Regulation .26C</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective April 7, 1998 (25:9 Md. R. 677); emergency status expired July 22, 1998; adopted permanently effective September 7, 1998 (25:18 Md. R. 1435)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-05-12"><cite path="|10|37|10|.26-1">Regulation .26-1</cite> adopted effective May 12, 2003 (30:9 Md. R. 615)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-10-06"><cite path="|10|37|10|.26-1">Regulation .26-1</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective June 12, 2008 (35:14 Md. R. 1244); amended permanently effective October 6, 2008 (35:20 Md. R. 1775)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-08-01"><cite path="|10|37|10|.26-1B">Regulation .26-1B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective March 21, 2014 (41:8 Md. R. 468); emergency status extended to August 1, 2014 (41:15 Md. R. 888); amended permanently effective July 7, 2014 (41:13 Md. R. 753)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-11-09"><cite path="|10|37|10|.26-1">Regulation .26-1</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 1, 2015 (42:16 Md. R. 1053); amended permanently effective November 9, 2015 (42:22 Md. R. 1378)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-03-09"><cite path="|10|37|10|.26-2">Regulation .26-2</cite> adopted effective March 9, 2009 (36:5 Md. R. 423)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-02-18"><cite path="|10|37|10|.27|A.">Regulation .27A</cite> amended effective February 18, 2002 (29:3 Md. R. 221)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1987-08-01"><cite path="|10|37|10|.34">Regulation .34</cite> adopted effective August 1, 1987 (14:15 Md. R. 1660)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1987-08-01"><cite path="|10|37|10|.35">Regulation .35</cite> adopted effective August 1, 1987 (14:15 Md. R. 1660)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1987-08-01"><cite path="|10|37|10|.36">Regulation .36</cite> adopted effective August 1, 1987 (14:15 Md. R. 1660)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
