<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>Permits for Oversize and Overweight Vehicles</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Administration" means the State Highway Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Axle weight" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr">Transportation Article, Title 24, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Excessive size" means an overall dimension of 16 feet or more in height, 16 feet or more in width, or 100 feet or more in length.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Excessive weight" means a gross vehicle weight exceeding 60 tons (120,000 pounds).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Oversize" means dimensions of length, width, or height that exceed the limits allowed by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr">Transportation Article, Title 24, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Overweight" means weights that exceed the limits allowed by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr">Transportation Article, Title 24, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6-1)</num>
        <text>"Permittee" means the person or entity to whom a permit is issued by the Unit and includes the person who is operating a vehicle under authority of that permit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Special mobile equipment" means a vehicle that is not used primarily for highway transportation of people or property and is operated or moved on a highway only as an incident to its nonhighway use.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Special vehicle" means a vehicle of special design which cannot comply with Maryland size or weight limits or qualify as special mobile equipment. The special vehicle may carry equipment for its designed purpose.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Unit" means the Hauling Permits Unit of the Motor Carrier Division, Office of Traffic and Safety, State Highway Administration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01-1</num>
    <heading>Unit Authority.</heading>
    <text>The Unit has the authority to issue permits for oversize and overweight vehicles.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Permits Available.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>There are seven types of permits which may allow oversize or overweight vehicles to move on State highways.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A person may move special mobile equipment or a vehicle where the load or vehicle or both are oversize or overweight on State highways, under one of the following types of permits:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Blanket hauling permit;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Book permit (issued in books of ten);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Containerized cargo permit;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Special hauling permit;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Special vehicle permit;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Exceptional hauling permit; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Heavy Weight Port Corridor permit.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A person may move a special vehicle under a special vehicle permit only.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|04|01|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Blanket Hauling Permit.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as provided for in <cite path="11|04|01|.03|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>, a blanket hauling permit may not be issued or used when a load can be dismantled or disassembled in such a way that moves can be made within the size and weight limits imposed by the laws of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A permit issued under this regulation for a vehicle which exceeds 27,000 pounds per axle but is less than or equal to 30,000 pounds per axle shall comply with <cite path="11.04.02.01">COMAR 11.04.02.01</cite>-1E.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Size.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A blanket hauling permit may be issued for a single oversize vehicle with overall dimensions which may not exceed 75 feet in length, 12 feet in width, or 14 feet in height.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The oversize vehicle shall be either:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Special mobile equipment as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|11-159">Transportation Article, §11-159, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A vehicle properly registered and carrying an oversize load or traveling empty to or from carrying an oversize load.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Weight of Special Mobile Equipment.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A blanket hauling permit may be issued for a single overweight vehicle which is special mobile equipment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The overweight special mobile equipment may not exceed:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A gross vehicle weight of 45 tons (90,000 pounds) including all tolerances; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A single axle weight of 27,000 pounds.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Repealed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Repealed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To obtain a blanket hauling permit, the applicant shall submit an originally signed completed application on a form and in a manner prescribed by the Unit to the Hauling Permits Unit, Motor Carrier Division, Office of Traffic and Safety, State Highway Administration, 7491 Connelly Drive, Hanover, Maryland 21076.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The application shall include the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Name of the applicant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Address and telephone number of the applicant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Name of a contact person;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Name of the applicant's insurance company;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Make, year, model, license tag number, and state of issuance of the license tag;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Manufacturer's gross vehicle weight rating of the vehicle; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Requested starting date of the permit.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>In addition to other information required by <cite path="11|04|01|.03|G.|(2)">§G(2) of this regulation</cite>, applications for self-propelled special mobile equipment shall include a serial number, identification number, or other similar information specifically identifying the unit of special mobile equipment for which the permit is requested.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Except for permits issued under §§E and F of this regulation, the Unit may issue a blanket hauling permit that is valid for 30 days or for 1 year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Unit shall complete all blanks on the face of a blanket hauling permit before issuing the permit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The permittee or user of a blanket hauling permit shall carry the original (not a copy) of the permit on the vehicle for which it was issued when moving the vehicle on a highway in the State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>A person may move a vehicle for which a blanket hauling permit has been issued on any highway under the jurisdiction of the Administration, during the period for which the permit is effective, without reporting any move to the Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The person may not move a vehicle across a bridge when the gross vehicle weight or axle weight exceeds posted bridge limitations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>A permittee shall comply with all restrictions attached to the permit as well as any hauling permit restrictions posted on the Motor Carrier Division and Chart websites found at www.marylandroads.com. It is the responsibility of the permittee to review these websites for current hauling permit restrictions prior to any move being made under the authority of the permit.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Book Permits.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Unit may issue books of permits. Each book contains ten single trip book permits.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A permit issued under this regulation for a vehicle which exceeds 27,000 pounds per axle but is less than or equal to 30,000 pounds per axle shall comply with <cite path="11.04.02.01">COMAR 11.04.02.01</cite>-1E.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>One book permit shall be used for each movement of a qualified vehicle between the points and over the route designated on the permit. It also authorizes the return of an empty oversize vehicle to its starting place if the empty vehicle does not exceed the weight limits imposed by the laws of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Qualifications.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A vehicle and its load or special mobile equipment may not exceed:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A gross vehicle weight of 45 tons (90,000 pounds);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Overall dimensions of 85 feet in length, 13 feet in width, or 15 feet in height; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A single axle weight of 27,000 pounds.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A vehicle traveling under a book permit shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Properly registered in Maryland; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Special mobile equipment displaying a special mobile equipment plate issued by the Motor Vehicle Administration of Maryland.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Before any movement may be made under any book permit, the permittee shall complete each of the following steps:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Advise the Unit of the date on which the permittee or another user authorized by the permittee proposes to move the vehicle and the specific route the permittee or the other user proposes to take;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Obtain approval of the date and route and a route verification number from the Unit; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Enter the period of validity of the permit, the approved route, and the route verification number on the original and permittee's copy of the permit.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The permittee or other user of a book permit shall carry the original (not a copy) of the permit on the vehicle. The permittee shall keep a copy of the book permit among his records until every permit in the book has been used.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Unit may not issue additional books of permits to a permittee if the records of the Unit show that the permittee has outstanding and unused more than two books of permits.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A book of permits is valid for 2 years from its date of issuance.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A permittee shall comply with all restrictions attached to the permit as well as any hauling permit restrictions posted on the Motor Carrier Division and Chart websites found at www.marylandroads.com. It is the responsibility of the Permittee to review these websites for current hauling permit restrictions prior to any move being made under the authority of the permit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A permittee shall notify the appropriate Maryland Transportation Authority facility at least 1 hour before using the facility.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Containerized Cargo Permit.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A containerized cargo permit allows for the movement of an indivisible load of containerized cargo and is only valid for movement to or egress from the Port of Baltimore. Special hauling permits are available for movement to or egress from other international ports.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Determination of an Indivisible Load. A truck tractor-semitrailer combination of vehicles carrying manifested international freight as the only load of the vehicle in a sealed, seagoing container on a semitrailer is deemed to be carrying an indivisible load if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The vehicle does not exceed the following maximum axle and gross vehicle weight limits:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>22,400 pounds on a single axle;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>44,000 pounds on two consecutive axles at least 4 feet apart; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>90,000 pounds gross vehicle weight;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The maximum allowable gross vehicle weight on a 20-foot container is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>80,000 pounds if loaded on a 20-foot intermodal chassis; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>90,000 pounds if loaded on a 40-foot intermodal chassis; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The maximum allowable gross vehicle weight on a 40-foot container is 90,000 pounds.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Containerized cargo permits are valid for 1 year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A permittee shall comply with all restrictions attached to the permit as well as any hauling permit restrictions posted on the Motor Carrier Division and Chart websites found at www.marylandroads.com. It is the responsibility of the Permittee to review these websites for current hauling permit restrictions prior to any move being made under the authority of the permit.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Special Hauling Permit.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Authority to Issue. The Unit may issue a special hauling permit for a single movement of special mobile equipment or a vehicle where the load or vehicle or both are oversize or overweight.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A permit issued under this regulation for a vehicle which exceeds 27,000 pounds per axle but is less than or equal to 30,000 pounds per axle shall comply with <cite path="11.04.02.01">COMAR 11.04.02.01</cite>-1E.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Application.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To obtain a special hauling permit, the applicant shall submit an originally signed written application, facsimile, or electronic copy of the application on a form and in a manner prescribed by the Unit when the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Gross vehicle weight exceeds 40 tons (80,000) pounds); or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Overall dimensions exceed 85 feet in length, 15 feet 6 inches in height, or 13 feet 11 inches in width.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The applicant shall also comply with the specific conditions under <cite path="11.04.03.02">COMAR 11.04.03.02</cite> to obtain a special hauling permit for moves which involve excessive weight or excessive size as defined in <cite path="11.04.03.01">COMAR 11.04.03.01</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Unit may otherwise accept an application by telephone.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A special hauling permit authorizes the permit vehicle to make a single one-way trip between the points and over the route designated on the permit. It also authorizes the return of an empty oversize vehicle to its starting place if the empty vehicle does not exceed the weight limits imposed by the Maryland Vehicle Law.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Carrying Permit or Substitute on Vehicle.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Multiple Page Permit.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Unit shall label each page of a multiple page permit to show the page number and total number of pages.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The original or clearly legible approved substitute of a multiple page permit shall be carried in the permit vehicle.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A telegram or computer generated copy is an approved substitute for a multiple page permit if the format in which the permit information appears has been approved by the Unit.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Single Page Permit.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The permittee of a special hauling permit shall carry the original of the permit or clearly legible approved substitute in the permit vehicle.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A facsimile copy of a special hauling permit is an approved substitute if all of the information on the permit is legible.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A telegram or computer generated copy is an approved substitute for a permit if the format in which the permit information appears has been approved by the Unit.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Extension of Time for Move.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If the move for which a special hauling permit is issued will be delayed to a time beyond the original expiration date of the permit, the permit may be extended once for a period of 5 consecutive days, not including Sundays or holidays when no move is allowed, upon payment of the prescribed fee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The permittee shall request the extension before the original permit period expires.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The 5-day extension period shall begin immediately upon expiration of the original permit period.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>If, after issuance, a special hauling permit is not used in the designated period or extension period, it is no longer valid. The Unit may not routinely cancel and issue a credit for the permit. The Unit shall consider requests for cancellation of the permit only in instances when extreme weather conditions prevent moves in Maryland, or when extraordinary circumstances exist preventing the move (e.g. emergency highway closure for repairs or extended crash investigation, police escort diverted—move canceled, etc.) as approved by the Chief, Motor Carrier Division.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>A Permittee shall comply with all restrictions attached to the permit as well as any hauling permit restrictions posted on the Motor Carrier Division and Chart websites found at www.marylandroads.com. It is the responsibility of the Permittee to review these websites for current hauling permit restrictions prior to any move being made under the authority of the permit.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Special Vehicle Permit.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Controlled Movement.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In exceptional cases, the Unit may issue a special vehicle permit for the controlled movement of a special vehicle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A special vehicle permit authorizes the vehicle to make a single one-way trip between the points of origin and destination specified, and only over those routes designated on the permit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Special vehicle permits may not allow the regular or continuous movement of a special vehicle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A permit issued under this regulation for a vehicle which exceeds 27,000 pounds per axle but is less than or equal to 30,000 pounds per axle shall comply with <cite path="11.04.02.01">COMAR 11.04.02.01</cite>-1E.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A special vehicle shall display a valid registration plate issued by its state of origin. If the special vehicle is of a type not subject to registration, the special vehicle shall be identified by its vehicle identification number (V.I.N) or other unique number, as approved by the Unit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>To obtain a special vehicle permit, the applicant shall submit the originally signed written application, facsimile, or electronic copy of the application on a form and in the manner prescribed by the Unit with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A complete description of the vehicle;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An explanation of the purpose for traveling highways in the State; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any other information considered necessary by the Unit.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Procedures and limitations for special vehicle permits, unless otherwise noted, will follow the procedures and limitations established for special hauling permits under <cite path="|11.04.01">COMAR 11.04.01</cite>—11.04.04.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|04|01|.08">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Fees.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Blanket Hauling Permits. The fees for blanket hauling permits are:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>30-day blanket permit — $50;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Annual blanket permit — $500.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Book Permits.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The fee for a book of ten single trip book permits is $300.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a book permit is unused and has not been completed or detached from the book, the permittee may return the book before its expiration date with the original and permittee's copies of the permit to the Unit, and the Unit may give a refund or credit, except when <cite path="11|04|01|.08|B.|(3)">§B(3) of this regulation</cite> applies.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the Unit has approved the use of a book permit for a move over a designated route, the move shall be considered completed and the Unit may not make changes on or give a refund or credit for the single trip permit.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Special Hauling Permits. The fees for special hauling permits and special vehicle permits are as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The base fees for oversize and overweight are:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Thirty dollars for the first 40 tons or less of gross weight; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Five dollars for each additional ton or part of a ton in excess of 40 tons.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>There are additional fees associated with permits for excessive size and excessive weight as described in §§D—I of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The fee for extension of a special hauling permit or special vehicle permit is $5.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Engineering Structural Review.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For each application submitted for gross weights exceeding 60 tons, there is a fee for engineering structural review as provided in this section.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For an engineering structural review, the number of analyzed and reviewed structures to be crossed, as determined by the Administration's bridge engineers, shall be multiplied by $8.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>For an engineering structural review requiring escort by the Administration's bridge engineers, the number of analyzed and reviewed structures to be crossed shall be multiplied by $20 for the initial move. For additional moves that follow the same route and are identical in vehicle load that are requested on the original application, the escort fee shall be $12 for each analyzed and reviewed structure crossed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A permit is not valid for more than 6 months from the date of the engineering structural review on which it is issued.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>For repeat moves that are identical as to vehicle, load, and route and that are requested on the original application, the engineering review may be valid for up to 6 months from the engineering structural review on which it is issued, without the need for additional engineering structural reviews or assessments of fees, if, within that 6-month period, there is no change in:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The condition of any structure on the approved route; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Vehicle, load, or route from the specifications which are designated on the original application.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Change in Structure Condition. If a change in the condition of any structure on the approved route occurs during that 6-month period, a new engineering structural review shall be performed on the structure or structures which have so changed, and the Unit shall assess the per bridge fee as set forth in §D(2) or (3) of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Change in Vehicle, Load, or Route.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If a change in the vehicle, load, or route specified on the original application occurs during that 6-month period, the permittee shall submit a new application, and a new engineering structural review shall be performed, for which the Unit shall assess the applicable fee.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A new application is considered an original application and, if it covers repeat moves, may be valid for up to 6 months from the date of the engineering structural review on which it is issued, subject to the provisions of <cite path="11|04|01|.08|D.|(5)">§D(5) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An Administration district engineer may require a special permit move to be monitored by Administration personnel to promote compliance with permit provisions, to observe and report damage to State highways, and to summon assistance if necessary. The daily fee for monitoring by Administration personnel is $200.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Except for permits requiring unique or unusual considerations as may be determined by the Maryland State Police, the fee for a single escort by off-duty Maryland State Police officers is based upon the reasonable expenses incurred, as established by a schedule maintained by the Unit. These expenses include, but are not limited to, the maintenance and use of Maryland State Police vehicles and the overtime rate of Maryland State Police personnel.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The fees for an engineering structural review, monitoring by Administration personnel, and escorting by police will be added to the permit fee at the time of issuance. Regardless of whether a permit is actually issued, the fee for engineering review will be assessed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The Unit may assess and collect, on behalf of the Maryland Transportation Authority, fees imposed by the Authority for permit moves on or across property owned by the Authority.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H-1.</num>
      <text>The Unit may assess and collect, on behalf of the City of Baltimore, fees imposed by the City for permit moves on or across roadways under the jurisdiction of the City in relation to the issuance of a joint permit to accommodate moves associated with the Port of Baltimore.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H-2.</num>
      <text>Refunds or Credits.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Unit may issue an appropriate refund or credit if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An Administration district engineer withdraws a monitoring requirement;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The police escort, upon determining that the permit move can proceed with reasonable safety, responds to an activity that takes priority over the escort;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A charge added to the permit for a district engineer escort, police escort, or other related service was not performed; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A charge was found to be in error as determined by the Chief, Motor Carrier Division.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Refunds or credits made to a permittee's account shall be deducted from any fund transfer the Unit makes to an allied agency that was the subject of the refund or credit for a service not provided or charge made in error.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any fee or charge that is contested shall be in writing and submitted within 30 days of issuance of the permit by the Unit. The Chief, Motor Carrier Division will review the contested fee or charge and render a decision within 30 calendar days following receipt of the complaint. The decision of the Chief, Motor Carrier Division is final.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Refunds for exceptional hauling permits are strictly prohibited.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>There will be no permit fee charged to Maryland State agencies and local government jurisdictions, or to federal agencies. However, fees will be charged for engineering reviews and monitoring.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Additional fees may be assessed by other jurisdictions affected by the permitted routes.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Time of Payment.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The permittee or applicant shall pay the total of all fees for any permit at the time of issuance by certified check, money order, or approved credit card unless a satisfactory credit bond or escrow account is on file with the Unit. The Unit may not accept cash.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the permittee or applicant has filed a credit bond with the Unit guaranteeing timely payment of all fees incurred, and if the Unit has approved the credit bond as to form, security, and amount, the Unit may bill the permittee or applicant for the permits issued during 1 or more preceding months. Escrow accounts are not guaranteed by an independent insurer and shall be valid only for the amount currently available in that account.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Denial of Permit.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Unit may not issue a permit or authorize use of a book permit, if it determines that the proposed movement would constitute an unreasonable hazard to other highway traffic or be unreasonably detrimental to highway surfaces or structures.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Unit may not issue a blanket hauling permit or a special hauling permit, or authorize use of a book permit, if the vehicle and its load can be dismantled or disassembled or hauled in such a way that moves can be made within the size and weight limits imposed by the laws of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Unit may not issue a special hauling permit for the movement of any overweight vehicle unless the vehicle:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Has five axles or more and is registered for at least the maximum gross weight in its State of registration; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is special mobile equipment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Unit may not authorize the use of a book permit for movement of any overweight vehicle unless the vehicle:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Has five axles or more and is registered in Maryland for the maximum allowable gross weight; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is registered as special mobile equipment in Maryland and displays special mobile equipment plates issued by the Motor Vehicle Administration of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Unit may not issue a special vehicle permit when the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Special vehicle reasonably can be disassembled to comply with the size and weight limits of Maryland law; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Permit movement would constitute the regular and continuous movement of a special vehicle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Unit may not issue an exceptional hauling permit unless the vehicle:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is a combination of vehicles that has six or more axles; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Has a minimum front to rear centerline axle spacing of not less than 50 feet.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Suspension and Revocation of Hauling Permits.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If a permittee has violated the regulations under <cite path="|11.04.01">COMAR 11.04.01</cite>—11.04.04, or the terms of any permit issued to the permittee, two times within any 6-month period, the Unit may suspend for 30 days the use of any hauling permit requested by or issued to the permittee and outstanding.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If a permittee has violated the regulations under <cite path="|11.04.01">COMAR 11.04.01</cite>—11.04.04, or the terms of any permit issued to the permittee, three times within any 12-month period, the Unit may suspend for up to 90 days the use of any hauling permit requested by or issued to the permittee and outstanding.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If a permittee has violated the regulations under <cite path="|11.04.01">COMAR 11.04.01</cite>—11.04.04, or the terms of any permit issued to the permittee, more than three times within any 12-month period, the Unit may suspend for up to 120 days the use of a special hauling permit, and may revoke permanently any blanket hauling permit or any book permit issued to the permittee and outstanding.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A permittee, whose blanket hauling permit or book permit has been suspended or revoked, may apply for a special hauling permit. The Unit will consider the request, but the determination on whether to issue a permit will be based on a case by case basis.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D-1.</num>
      <text>If a permittee violates the weight restrictions of an exceptional hauling permit that exceeds 5,000 pounds and the permit is confiscated, on notification of the confiscation, the Unit shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Review the circumstances of the confiscation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Verify that a weight violation did occur; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Revoke the permit if the weight violation exceeds the allowable permit weight by more than 5,000 pounds.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Unit determines initially all violations of the regulations under <cite path="|11.04.01">COMAR 11.04.01</cite>—11.04.04 or the terms of any permit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the Unit determines that there has been a violation, it shall notify the permittee by certified mail of the specific violations, the period of suspension or revocation, and the opportunity for appeal and to be heard.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The permittee has 7 business days from receipt of the written notice of violation to file a written appeal to the Director, Office of Traffic and Safety, State Highway Administration. Only a written appeal filed within the timeframe specified will be accepted.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If an appeal is filed, the Director, Office of Traffic and Safety, shall review the entire record relating to any violation charged. If the appellant specifically requests a hearing, the Director, Office of Traffic and Safety, shall grant a hearing. If the appellant fails to appear at the hearing, the Director, Office of Traffic and Safety, may proceed by a review of the record.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>After reviewing the record and any evidence submitted at any hearing, the Director, Office of Traffic and Safety, shall affirm, amend, or reverse the findings of the Unit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The decision of the Director, Office of Traffic and Safety, is the final decision of the State Highway Administration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>False Statement in Permit Application.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If an application for a permit for movement of an oversize or overweight vehicle contains a false statement of a material fact, the Unit may deny that permit and any future permits to the permittee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If the Unit determines that an application contains a false statement of a material fact, the Unit shall notify the permittee by certified mail of its determination, the status of suspension from future permits, the duration of that suspension as provided in <cite path="11.04.01.10">COMAR 11.04.01.10</cite>, and the opportunity for appeal and to be heard.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The permittee has 7 business days from receipt of the written notice of violation to file a written appeal to the Director, Office of Traffic and Safety, State Highway Administration. Only a written appeal filed within the time frame specified will be accepted.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If an appeal is filed, the Director, Office of Traffic and Safety, shall review the entire record relating to any violation charged. If the appellant specifically requests a hearing, the Director, Office of Traffic and Safety, shall grant a hearing. If the appellant fails to appear at the hearing, the Director, Office of Traffic and Safety, may proceed by a review of the record.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>After reviewing the record and any evidence submitted at any hearing, the Director, Office of Traffic and Safety, shall affirm, amend, or reverse the decision of the Unit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The decision of the Director, Office of Traffic and Safety, is the final decision of the State Highway Administration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Exceptional Hauling Permits.</heading>
    <text>The State Highway Administration may issue an exceptional hauling permit in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|24-113">Transportation Article, §24-113</cite>.2, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Heavy Weight Port Corridor Permits.</heading>
    <text>The State Highway Administration may issue a Heavy Weight Port Corridor permit in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|24-113">Transportation Article, §24-113</cite>.3, Annotated Code of Maryland, and <cite path="|11.04.17">COMAR 11.04.17</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|2-103">2-103</cite>(b), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|4-204">4-204</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|4-205">4-205</cite>(f), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|8-204">8-204</cite>(b)—(d) and(i), 24-109, 24-112, 24-113, 24-113.2, and 24-113.3, <br/>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1975-05-20">Effective date: May 20, 1975 (2:10 Md. R. 752)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1977-07-20">Chapter revised effective July 20, 1977 (4:15 Md. R. 1146)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|11.04.04">COMAR 11.04.04</cite> to <cite path="|11.04.01">11.04.01</cite></annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1984-08-01" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective August 1, 1984 (11:15 Md. R. 1331)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-06-11"><cite path="|11|04|01|.03|D.">Regulation .03D</cite> amended effective June 11, 1990 (17:11 Md. R. 1343)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-10-12"><cite path="|11|04|01|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective May 1, 1992 (19:10 Md. R. 928); amended permanently effective October 12, 1992 (19:20 Md. R. 1816)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-08-14"><cite path="|11|04|01|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective August 14, 1995 (22:16 Md. R. 1221)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-04-17">Regulations .03 and .07 amended as an emergency provision effective April 17, 1995 (22:9 Md. R. 642)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1996-03-25"><cite path="|11|04|01|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective March 25, 1996 (23:6 Md. R. 477)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-08-14"><cite path="|11|04|01|.07|A.">Regulation .07A</cite> amended effective August 14, 1995 (22:16 Md. R. 1221)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1984-09-24">Regulations .05A and .08B amended as an emergency provision effective July 5, 1984 (11:15 Md. R. 1328); adopted permanently effective September 24, 1984 (11:19 Md. R. 1666)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-02-01" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective February 1, 1998 (25:2 Md. R. 76)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-05-31"><cite path="|11|04|01|.03|E.">Regulation .03E</cite> amended effective May 31, 1999 (26:11 Md. R. 856)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-12-22" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective December 22, 2003 (30:25 Md. R. 1849)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-03-22" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective March 22, 2010 (37:6 Md. R. 478)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-04-20"><cite path="|11|04|01|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective October 25, 2019 (46:24 Md. R. 1100); amended permanently effective April 20, 2020 (47:8 Md. R. 435)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-04-20"><cite path="|11|04|01|.13">Regulation .13</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective October 25, 2019 (46:24 Md. R. 1100); adopted permanently effective April 20, 2020 (47:8 Md. R. 435)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
