<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>General Conditions for Movement of Oversize and Overweight Vehicles</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Administration" means the State Highway Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(1-1)</num>
        <text>“Authority” means the Maryland Transportation Authority.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(1-2)</num>
        <text>“Authority highway” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|21-1401">Transportation Article, §21-1401, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Certified weights" means vehicle or axle weights that have been weighted on scales approved or accepted by the Commercial Vehicle Enforcement Division of the Department of State Police.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Construction Equipment.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Construction equipment" means equipment used to build, repair, replace, or maintain structures, transportation facilities, or infrastructure.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Construction equipment" includes, but is not limited to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Demolition;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Excavation;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Grading;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Digging;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Stockpiling;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Erection; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Placement of materials or supplies.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Heavy Machinery.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Heavy machinery" means large stationery machinery transported on tractor-trailer combination vehicles.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Heavy machinery" includes, but is not limited to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Armored tanks;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Transformers;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Vessel tanks;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Girders;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Compressors; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Rotors.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Irreducible" means a vehicle configuration exceeding applicable size or weight limits which, if separated into smaller loads, would:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Compromise the intended use of the vehicle, for example, make it unable to perform the function for which it was intended;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Destroy the value of the load or vehicle, for example, make it unusable for its intended purpose; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Require more than 8 manhours to dismantle, using appropriate equipment.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Oversize" means dimensions of length, width, or height that exceed the limits allowed by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr">Transportation Article, Title 24, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Overweight" means weights that exceed the limits allowed by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr">Transportation Article, Title 24, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Self-propelled vehicle" means a single unit vehicle containing the means for its own propulsion within itself.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Spacing" means the distance measured lengthwise and horizontally between axle center lines or the center lines of exterior axles within a group.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Special mobile equipment" means a vehicle that is not used primarily for highway transportation of people or property and is operated or moved on a highway only as an incident to its nonhighway use.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Unit" means the Hauling Permits Unit of the Motor Carrier Division, Office of Traffic and Safety, within the State Highway Administration, and is the Unit that issues permits for oversize and overweight vehicles.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|04|02|.01-1">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01-1</num>
    <heading>Miscellaneous Conditions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The conditions set forth in §§B—K of this regulation apply to each permit for an oversize or overweight vehicle.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Compliance.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>While making a move under the authority of any permit, the permittee or user shall comply with the vehicle laws of Maryland (except those general size and weight limits from which the permit authorizes departure), the regulations under <cite path="|11.04.01">COMAR 11.04.01</cite>—11.04.04, conditions, both general and specific, attached to the permit, and all updates posted on the Motor Carrier Division and CHART websites found at www.marylandroads.com.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Notwithstanding any other provision of COMAR and absent an emergency declaration by the Governor, the Director, Office of Traffic and Safety may request and the Administrator may grant, reasonable exceptions of limited scope and duration to these conditions and any other requirements considered appropriate for reasons of public safety including, but not limited to, disaster relief outside the State and emergency response throughout the State.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Failure to Comply.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Failure to comply with weight or dimension limits, or with other provisions (including restrictions, conditions, and notes) stated specifically in a permit or updates posted on the Motor Carrier Division and CHART websites found at www.marylandroads.com, renders the permit subject to immediate revocation and confiscation by any officer or authorized civilian employee of the Maryland State Police, any officer of the Maryland Transportation Authority Police, or any other police officer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a permit is revoked for failure to comply with weight or size limitations, the permittee or user of the permitted vehicle shall be cited for the weight in excess of the permitted weight and for size in excess of the permitted size.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2-1)</num>
        <text>If the weight violation exceeds the allowable permit weight by more than 5,000 pounds, the permitted vehicle shall be subject to all weight limitations and tolerances otherwise specified by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr">Transportation Article, Title 24, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2-2)</num>
        <text>A weight violation of an exceptional hauling permit, voids the permit and the permitted vehicle shall be subject to all weight limitations and tolerances otherwise specified by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr">Transportation Article, Title 24, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A permitted vehicle may not go off the route specified on the permit by more than 1 mile to rest or to secure food, fuel, or repairs. Failure to comply subjects the permitted vehicle to all weight limitations and tolerances otherwise specified by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr">Transportation Article, Title 24, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If a permittee or user is cited only for permit violations, the citing officer or authorized civilian employee of the Maryland State Police, an officer of the Maryland Transportation Authority Police, or other police officer may confiscate the permit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If a permit is revoked or confiscated, the permittee shall apply for a new permit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>If a permit is revoked for failure to comply, the permittee shall obtain a new permit before moving the vehicle on any highway in the State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>An officer or authorized civilian employee of the Maryland State Police, an officer of the Maryland Transportation Authority Police, or another police officer who confiscates a permit shall immediately notify the Unit and return the confiscated permit to the Unit after it has been used as evidence in any law enforcement proceedings brought against the permittee or user.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The permit carried in a vehicle is open for inspection by, and the permittee or user shall exhibit it upon request to, any State, county, municipal, or other public official, including any officer or civilian employee of the Maryland State Police, any employee of the Maryland Transportation Authority, and any employee of the Administration, or to any person involved in an accident with that vehicle.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The permittee shall reduce each vehicle and load which together are overweight of as much excess weight as possible and each vehicle and load which together are oversized as much as possible, unless the vehicle or load is irreducible.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The applicant for an irreducible load permit has the burden of proof as to the number of hours required to dismantle the load. Irreducible is defined in <cite path="|11|04|02|.01|B.|(5)">Regulation .01B(5) of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The Unit may issue a permit without an engineering structural review to a vehicle which weighs more than 80,000 pounds, but which does not exceed 120,000 pounds.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The Unit may require an applicant to provide certified weight measurements.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>The permit does not authorize, and the permittee may not carry, a load which exceeds the tire manufacturer's weight rating.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Combination Vehicles.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Size.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Width of Load. Vehicles with buckets, blades, scoops, or other attachments over 12 feet wide measured perpendicular to the vehicle's longitudinal center line shall have the buckets, blades, scoops, or other attachments removed and transported on another vehicle.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Height of Load. A pole vehicle escort shall accompany vehicles and loads exceeding a height of 14 feet 6 inches.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Weight.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Heavy Machinery. A permittee of a vehicle with a load of heavy machinery shall comply with the requirements of <cite path="11|04|02|.01-1|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Unit may not issue a permit authorizing a permittee to carry more than 27,000 pounds on any one axle of the permit vehicle except under the specific exceptions set forth in <cite path="11|04|02|.01-1|J.|(3)">§J(3) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>An overweight combination vehicle using a semitrailer and manufactured and purchased after October 31, 1997, shall comply with the 27,000 pound per axle maximum load limit.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Unit may issue a permit to a vehicle or a vehicle and load weighing more than 150,000 pounds only after a valid engineering structural review.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The Unit may issue a permit without an engineering structural review to a vehicle which weighs more than 120,000 pounds, but which does not exceed 150,000 pounds, if the Unit determines that the vehicle will travel only on roadways for which a review is not required and the applicant has reduced the vehicle load or increased the number of axles on the vehicle tractor or semitrailer, or on both, to bring the vehicle within the following per-axle weight limits and axle spacing requirements:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Steering axle—20,000 pounds;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Single axle (axle spacing over 8 feet)—27,000 pounds;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Two (tandem) axles (axle spacing 4—8 feet)—26,000 pounds per axle;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Three (tri) axles (axle spacing 8—16 feet)—21,000 pounds per axle;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Four or more axles (minimum axle spacing 4 feet)—18,000 pounds per axle;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Minimum inner bridge axle spacing is 30 feet.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Exceptions.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An overweight combination vehicle using a semitrailer and registered, manufactured, or in the inventory of a licensed dealer on or before October 31, 1997, and sold before June 30, 1998, shall comply with the 27,000 pounds per axle maximum load limit after June 30, 2012.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An existing overweight combination vehicle using a semitrailer may continue to be operated with axle loads not exceeding 30,000 pounds until October 31, 2012, if it complies with the permit regulations in effect on January 1, 1997, and, if the gross vehicle weight exceeds 110,000 pounds (55 tons), pays the fees set forth in <cite path="|11.04.01">COMAR 11.04.01</cite> for any required engineering structural reviews.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Load Reduction—Construction Equipment.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A weight of a permitted vehicle of up to and including 27,000 pounds per axle shall be considered as irreducible if the vehicle is in compliance with the requirements of <cite path="11|04|02|.01-1|J.">§J of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A weight of a permitted vehicle over 27,000 pounds and up to 30,000 pounds per axle shall be considered as irreducible if the vehicle is in compliance with the requirements of <cite path="11|04|02|.01-1|J.|(1)">§J(1) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Maximum Axle Weight.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A vehicle that has reduced the load as much as possible and that has added as many axles as possible, but still is not able to achieve the 27,000 pound maximum axle weight limit, may still qualify for a permit.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>After the permittee demonstrates that axle weights have been reduced as much as possible, the Administration's Office of Bridge Development shall perform a bridge review and analysis on an individual basis.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A combination vehicle seeking this maximum axle weight exception shall have a minimum of 15 axles on the entire combination vehicle, and any axle weighing more than 27,000 pounds shall have a minimum of eight tires and be at least 10 feet wide.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>An axle on a combination vehicle may not weigh more than 36,000 pounds.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Self-Propelled Vehicles.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Size.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Width of Load. Vehicles with buckets, blades, scoops, or other attachments over 12 feet wide measured perpendicular to the vehicle's longitudinal center line shall have the buckets, blades, scoops, or other attachments removed and transported on another vehicle.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Height of Load. A pole vehicle escort shall accompany vehicles and loads exceeding a height of 14 feet 6 inches.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Weight.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Unit may not issue a permit authorizing a permittee to carry more than 27,000 pounds on any one axle of the permit vehicle except under the specific exceptions set forth in <cite path="11|04|02|.01-1|K.|(3)">§K(3) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A self-propelled truck crane manufactured and purchased after October 31, 1997, shall comply with the 27,000 pound per axle maximum load limit.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A self-propelled vehicle with a gross vehicle weight of 120,000 pounds or less which meets the requirements of this chapter and <cite path="|11.04.01">COMAR 11.04.01</cite>, <cite path="|11.04.03">11.04.03</cite>, and <cite path="|11.04.04">11.04.04</cite> may obtain a permit from the Unit without an engineering structural review by the Administration's Office of Bridge Development.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Unit may issue a permit for a self-propelled crane (hydraulic or lattice boom) with a gross vehicle weight in excess of 120,000 pounds without requiring a bridge review for each move after the Administration's Office of Bridge Development performs an initial special bridge analysis and, as necessary or prudent, subsequent special bridge analyses for each self-propelled truck crane configuration if the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Maryland State Police Commercial Vehicle Enforcement Section has certified the axle weight and axle spacings of the applicant's vehicle before the application is submitted for a bridge analysis; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Crane configuration has a maximum axle weight of 27,000 pounds, and a minimum of five axles.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The Unit shall keep a file of approved self-propelled crane configurations and any restrictions for them.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Exceptions—Self-Propelled Truck Cranes (Hydraulic and Lattice Boom).</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A self-propelled truck crane owned, manufactured, or in the inventory of a licensed dealer on or before October 31, 1997, and sold before October 31, 1998, shall comply with the 27,000 pounds per axle maximum load limit after October 31, 2012.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>To bring this vehicle into compliance with the 27,000 pound per axle maximum load limit, the use of boom dollies, the addition of booster axles, or other comparable measures are allowed.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A self-propelled truck crane may continue to be operated with axle loads not exceeding 30,000 pounds until October 31, 2012, if it complies with the permit regulations in effect on January 1, 1997, and, if the gross vehicle weight exceeds 110,000 pounds (55 tons), pays the fees set forth in <cite path="|11.04.01">COMAR 11.04.01</cite> for any required engineering structural reviews.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Load Reduction.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A weight of a permitted vehicle of up to and including 27,000 pounds per axle shall be considered as irreducible.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A permittee of a vehicle with a weight over 27,000 pounds and up to 30,000 pounds per axle shall remove counterweights as necessary.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Maximum Axle Weight.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A vehicle that has reduced the load as much as possible and that has added as many axles as possible, but still is not able to achieve the 27,000 pound maximum axle weight limit, may still qualify for a permit.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>After the permittee demonstrates that axle weights have been reduced as much as possible, the Administration's Office of Bridge Development shall perform a bridge review and analysis on an individual basis.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A self-propelled vehicle seeking this maximum axle weight exception shall have a minimum of seven axles.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>An axle on a self-propelled vehicle may not weigh more than 32,000 pounds.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Costs and Damages for Which Permittee is Responsible.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The permittee is responsible for payment of each of the following items:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All damage that the vehicle causes, either directly or indirectly, to any road surface, bridge, or other structure, whether maintained by the Administration or by another;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The cost of all telegrams, express mail deliveries, or telephone calls made in connection with the permit;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any additional expense incurred by the Administration in connection with the permit or the move authorized by the permit.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration may repair or correct any damage caused to facilities maintained by it and collect the cost of those repairs or corrections from the permittee. The Administration may agree to allow the permittee to perform the necessary repairs or corrections at the permittee's own expense. Any work performed by the permittee or its agent shall comply with all applicable standards and be satisfactory to the Administration. If the Administration finds the permittee's repairs or corrections unsatisfactory, the Administration may complete the repairs and collect the cost to complete the repairs from the permittee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The permittee shall be responsible for any injury to persons or damage to public or private property caused directly or indirectly by the transportation of vehicles and loads under permit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The permittee shall hold the State, its agents, and employees harmless from all suits, claims, damages, or proceedings of any kind, arising as a direct or indirect result of the transportation of vehicles and loads under permit, including the use of any permit vehicle waiting areas provided by the State.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Safety.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>When moving an oversize or overweight vehicle under the authority of a permit, the permittee or user shall ensure the safety and rights of the public.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Before crossing narrow bridges or traveling on narrow roads with equipment or a load extending over the center line of the road, the permittee or user shall make arrangements in advance, so that adequate flagpersons, escorts, or police are present to warn and direct approaching traffic.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Escort. The Unit, the Maryland State Police, or the Maryland Transportation Authority Police may require the permittee to provide one or more escort vehicles to accompany the oversize or overweight vehicle during its move.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Wide Load or Oversize Load Signs. If the vehicle, together with any load, exceeds 9 feet in width, the permittee shall display wide load or oversize load signs that conform to the specifications under <cite path="11.04.04.01">COMAR 11.04.04.01</cite>, on the front and rear of the vehicle.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A permit vehicle shall maintain a 1/2 mile distance from another permit vehicle traveling in the same direction. Each permit vehicle with escort shall maintain a 1-mile distance from another escorted permit vehicle traveling in the same direction.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Turn signal flashing warning lamps may be used by the operator of a permit vehicle when the vehicle is traveling 20 miles per hour less than the posted speed limit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>To the greatest extent possible, permittees and users shall limit travel to the shortest practical route using interstate and State routes to reduce travel on secondary and local highways. In the case of exceptional hauling permits, permittees shall limit travel to State routes.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Notwithstanding any other provisions of <cite path="|11.04.01">COMAR 11.04.01</cite>—11.04.04, the Administration may include any conditions in a permit that are necessary to protect State highways and bridges or to maintain safety.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Road and Weather Conditions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The use of a permit is subject to favorable road and weather conditions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Travel is not allowed:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>On any highway when visibility is limited by atmospheric conditions or travel is made hazardous by weather or other conditions;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>When the surface of the highway is made hazardous by rain, sleet, snow, or ice, or movement is made hazardous by fog, flood, or wind.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If a permitted vehicle is moving when inclement weather occurs, the driver shall proceed to a safe place off the roadway and park the vehicle until the weather clears.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>During inclement weather, police officers may require that the permitted vehicle be parked off the roadway until conditions warrant safe travel.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Warning Flags.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>During daylight hours, permitted vehicles shall display warning flags which are:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Red fluorescent or orange fluorescent;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>At least 18 inches square; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Securely fastened by at least one corner or securely mounted on a staff.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Two warning flags placed at the widest extremities of the vehicle or load shall be displayed by permitted vehicles or loads which exceed legal width.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Warning flags shall be displayed on permitted vehicles or loads which exceed legal length or which have a rear-end overhang in excess of the legal limit. A single flag shall be displayed at the extreme rear if the overlength or projecting portion is 2 feet wide or less. Two flags shall be displayed at each side of the extreme rear in order to indicate maximum width if the overlength or projecting portion is wider than 2 feet.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Warning Lights.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Permitted vehicles shall display warning lights if operating at night.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Overwidth Loads.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>For overwidth loads which are uniform in width, amber lights shall be displayed on the forward corners of the load and red lights shall be displayed on the rear corners of the load.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For loads which are overwidth for their entire length with a wider portion near the middle of the load, either amber or red lights shall be displayed at the front and rear corners of the load and amber lights shall be displayed on the sides of the load at the widest point.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>For loads which are not uniform in width with the overwidth portion of the load at the extreme rear of the load, red lights shall be displayed on the side of the load at its widest point.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>For loads which are not uniform in width with the overwidth portion of the load at the front of the load, amber lights shall be displayed on the side of the load at its widest point.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Overlength Loads. For overlength loads with a rear overhang exceeding 4 feet, two red lights shall be displayed on the end of the overhang portion of the load, along with one red light on each side of the overhanging portion of the load.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Limitations on Authority Conferred by Permit.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The authority conferred by any permit does not include authority to do any of the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Move the oversize or overweight vehicle over any highway, bridge, or other structure under the jurisdiction of any county, municipality, or other entity (other than the Administration), except that a permit authorizes the permittee or user to cross the highway, bridge, or structure, after giving sufficient notice to the responsible authority and making proper arrangements with that authority for the crossing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Move the oversize or overweight vehicle over any railroad or railway track or right-of-way, at grade, except that a permit authorizes the permittee or user to cross the track or right-of-way at an established grade crossing, after giving sufficient notice to the local superintendent of the railroad or railway, or to the duly authorized representative of the superintendent, and making proper arrangements with the superintendent or the superintendent's representative for the crossing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Use or damage any private property;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Disturb any wires, cables, traffic signs and signals, street lights, limbs of trees, signs, or other structures or appurtenances. If a proposed move is expected to disturb any of these structures, the permittee shall obtain permission from the owner of the structure and shall make any arrangements required by the owner to avoid damage to the structure, before the move is begun.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Local road designations may be used in a route description for purposes of continuity to indicate connecting routes of travel. However, nothing contained in a permit shall be construed to confer authority to cross any road, bridge, or other structure that is not under the jurisdiction of the Administration.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Movement on or Across Toll Facilities.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The following restrictions apply to the movement of any oversize or overweight vehicle on or through the following Authority highways:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Baltimore Harbor Tunnel Thruway (I-895);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Thomas J. Hatem Memorial Bridge (Susquehanna River Bridge, U.S. 40);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Harry W. Nice Memorial/Thomas “Mac” Middleton Bridge (Potomac River Bridge, U.S. 301);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>William Preston Lane Jr. Memorial Bridge (Bay Bridge, U.S. 50/301);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Francis Scott Key Bridge (MD 695);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>John F. Kennedy Memorial Highway (I-95);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Fort McHenry Tunnel (I-95);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Intercounty Connector (MD 200); and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Any other Authority highway operated by the Authority on which the permittee may travel.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Any oversize or overweight vehicle and any vehicle and load together exceeding 96 inches (8 feet) in width or 13 feet 6 inches in height is prohibited from entering the Baltimore Harbor Tunnel and its approaches (I-895).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Any oversize vehicle and load together exceeding 14 feet 6 inches in height or 11 feet in width is prohibited from entering the I-95 Fort McHenry Tunnel and its approaches unless, in the case of vehicles and loads exceeding 11 feet in width, special written permission is obtained from the Administrator of the Tunnel.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Unless otherwise approved by the Authority, a permittee or user may move an oversize or overweight vehicle on or across an Authority highway only during daylight hours between 9 a.m. Monday and 12 noon Friday.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>When moving any oversize or overweight vehicle on or across an Authority highway, the permittee or user shall comply with all regulations issued by the Authority to regulate the use of an Authority highway, and with the direction of the Transportation Authority Police, including directions requiring that the vehicle be escorted during its move.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The permittee or user shall notify the Facility Administrator or the Transportation Authority Police assigned to a particular Authority highway, as specified on the permit at least 1 hour before beginning movement of an oversize or overweight vehicle on or across the project. This does not include any permit vehicle waiting area provided by the Authority.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Regardless of any other provision of the regulations under <cite path="11.04.0111.04">COMAR 11.04.0111.04</cite>.04, the movement of any oversize or overweight vehicle on or across an Authority highway may be delayed or prohibited if, in the opinion of the Facility Administrator or the Transportation Authority Police assigned to the project, the movement of the oversize or overweight vehicle would endanger life or property or result in undue interference or interruption of traffic at that project.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|04|02|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Hours for Movement, in General.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The permittee or user may move an oversize or overweight vehicle during any daylight hours from 1/2 hour after sunrise to 1/2 hour before sunset, subject to the following restrictions.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Restrictions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may not move an oversize or overweight vehicle, even during daylight hours, on:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Any Saturday after 12 noon;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Any Sunday;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Those holiday periods included on a list compiled by the Unit for each calendar year, available upon request from the Unit after December 15 of the preceding calendar year.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The permittee or user may move any vehicle and load that together exceed 45 tons gross weight or are 100 feet or more in length or 12 feet or more in width over either of the following facilities from 9 a.m. to 3:30 p.m. only, on those days not specified in <cite path="11|04|02|.06|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite>:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>I-495/I-95 (Capital Beltway);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>I-695/MD 695 (Baltimore Beltway).</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The permittee or user may move any vehicle and load that together are 14 feet or more in width on any highway in the State from 9 a.m. to 3:30 p.m. only, on those days not specified in <cite path="11|04|02|.06|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Notwithstanding §§A and B of this regulation, the permittee or user may move an oversize or overweight vehicle on dates and during hours specifically set forth in the permittee's or user's permit. The Unit may specify additional conditions under which that movement may be made.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Oversize or overweight special mobile equipment that is self-propelled and cannot maintain a speed of at least 40 miles per hour is prohibited from the Capital Beltway (I-95/I-495) and Baltimore Beltway (I-695/MD 695) between the hours of 7 a.m. to 9 a.m. and 4 p.m. to 6 p.m. on those days not specified in <cite path="11|04|02|.06|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|04|02|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Emergency Movement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Emergency Status.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An emergency exists when there is a danger of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Loss of life;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Serious bodily injury;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Fire;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Severe property damage;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Hazardous material leakage; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Major interruption to the flow of traffic on any part of the State highway system.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A potential permittee with an oversize or overweight vehicle, expecting to respond to emergency situations, shall send a written request for emergency response status to the Director, Office of Traffic and Safety.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Notwithstanding any other provision of regulations under this chapter and <cite path="|11.04.01">COMAR 11.04.01</cite>, <cite path="|11.04.03">11.04.03</cite>, and <cite path="|11.04.04">11.04.04</cite>, a person may move rescue, construction, or utility equipment which is oversize or overweight to the scene of an emergency in order to provide or assist in providing relief without having a permit in hand, and at any time, under one of the procedures in <cite path="11|04|02|.07|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If, at the time the owner or operator of the equipment learns of the emergency and decides that a move must be made, and the office of the Unit is open for business, the procedure established below shall be followed:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The owner or operator shall telephone and advise the Unit's headquarters office of the nature of the emergency, the route proposed to be traveled, and the characteristics of the oversize or overweight equipment to be moved;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The move may be made only after the Unit has approved the proposed move, has given a permit number, and has advised the Maryland State Police concerning the proposed move;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Telecommunications Section, Electronic Systems Division, of the Maryland State Police shall send instructions, as necessary, to State Police and other appropriate authorities in areas affected by the move;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Unit shall issue a special hauling permit the same day and shall charge the owner or operator the appropriate fee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If, at the time the owner or operator of the equipment learns of the emergency and decides that a move must be made, and the office of the Unit is not open for business, the following procedure shall be followed:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The owner or operator shall telephone the Statewide Operations Center at 1-800-543-2515, located at the State Highway Administration's Office of Traffic and Safety in Hanover, Maryland;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Statewide Operations Center will upon being notified by a permittee of the need for an emergency move notify an on-call representative for the Unit and will provide the permittee's telephone number directly to the on-call representative who will call the permittee to obtain pertinent information concerning the emergency move relative to the proposed route of travel, and the characteristics of the oversize or overweight equipment to be moved;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The move may be made only after the designated Unit representative has approved the proposed move and has advised the Telecommunications Section, Electronic Systems Division, of the Maryland State Police concerning the proposed move;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Telecommunications Section, Electronic Systems Division, of the Maryland State Police shall send instructions, as necessary, to State Police and other appropriate authorities in areas affected by the move;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The Unit shall issue a special hauling permit the next working day and shall charge the owner or operator the appropriate fee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>After the emergency:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The permittee or user shall obtain a permit for the return move and shall be subject to all normal permit provisions; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Unit may require the permittee to submit on a form and in a manner prescribed by the Unit, a report describing the emergency.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|04|02|.08">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Continuous Travel for Certain Special Mobile Equipment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this regulation:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Continuous travel" means travel allowed 24 hours a day, 7 days a week, subject to the provisions on the permit and any attachments or updates listed on the Motor Carrier Division and CHART websites found at www.marylandroads.com, and subject to all regulations (except hours for movement) under <cite path="|11.04.01">COMAR 11.04.01</cite> —11.04.04.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Qualifying special mobile equipment" means any self-propelled special mobile equipment as defined by Maryland Vehicle Law and reasonably determined by the Maryland State Police to be capable of complying with safety requirements applicable to class E (truck) vehicles.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Subject to the requirements of this regulation, the Unit may issue permits for continuous travel for qualifying special mobile equipment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Notwithstanding any regulation to the contrary, special mobile equipment traveling under a permit allowing continuous travel is required to comply with the motor carrier safety provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|25-111">Transportation Article, §25-111, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, including, but not limited to, compliance with the following requirements:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The special mobile equipment shall be equipped with all safety equipment and devices required by the Transportation Article and regulations promulgated under the Transportation Article for class E (truck) vehicles;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The special mobile equipment is subject to roadside safety inspections by the Maryland State Police or other authorized police officers; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>For safety violations, penalties shall be charged as established for <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|25-111">Transportation Article, §25-111, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>To qualify for continuous travel, the special mobile equipment:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>May not be oversize;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shall be capable of safely maintaining a speed of 45 miles per hour and may not impede the flow of traffic;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>May not exceed a gross vehicle weight of 90,000 pounds (45 tons) including all tolerances;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>May not exceed a single axle weight of 27,000 pounds including all tolerances; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Shall meet the safety equipment requirements in <cite path="11|04|02|.08|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>With the exception of the departure from weight limits provided for in the permit, the user shall comply with all of the vehicle weight laws of Maryland and may not cross over bridges when the vehicle weight exceeds posted bridge limitations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To obtain the permit, the applicant shall submit an originally signed completed application, facsimile, or electronic copy of the application on a form and in the manner prescribed by the Unit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In addition to other information required by the Unit, the application shall include the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Written request for continuous travel;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Serial number, identification number, or other similar information specifically identifying the unit of special mobile equipment for which the continuous travel permit is requested;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Statement certifying that the particular unit of special mobile equipment identified on the application meets the safety equipment requirements described in <cite path="11|04|02|.08|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Statement of understanding that if the special mobile equipment is not in safe operating condition or fails to comply with safety equipment requirements, the permit automatically becomes void and the privilege to move the equipment granted under the conditions of the permit is immediately suspended until reinstated by the Unit.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The permit is valid only for the unit of special mobile equipment for which it was issued and the original (not a copy) of the permit shall be carried in the unit when traveling on a highway in the State.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Penalties.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If the special mobile equipment is found to be in unsafe operating condition or fails to comply with safety equipment requirements, in addition to the penalties provided for under Maryland Motor Vehicle Law, the permit shall be immediately rendered void and suspended until repairs are accomplished.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A police officer may confiscate the permit if a safety violation is sufficient to place the vehicle out of service or for other reasonable cause. The officer shall immediately notify the Unit of the confiscation and return the confiscated permit to the Unit after it has been used as evidence in any law enforcement proceedings.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Unit may not give a credit, refund, or time extension for a period of suspension or confiscation, and the permit is not transferable to another unit of special mobile equipment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|2-103">2-103</cite>(b), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|4-204">4-204</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|4-205">4-205</cite>(f), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|8-204">8-204</cite>(b)—(d) and(i), 24-112, and 24-113, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1975-05-20">Effective date: May 20, 1975 (2:10 Md. R. 752)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1977-07-20">Chapter revised effective July 20, 1977 (4:15 Md. R. 1146)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|11.04.05">COMAR 11.04.05</cite> to <cite path="|11.04.02">11.04.02</cite></annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1984-08-01" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective August 1, 1984 (11:15 Md. R. 1331)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-02-01"><cite path="|11|04|02|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective February 1, 1998 (25:2 Md. R. 76)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-06-24"><cite path="|11|04|02|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective June 24, 2013 (40:12 Md. R. 1042)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-03-22"><cite path="|11|04|02|.01-1">Regulation .01-1</cite> amended effective February 1, 1998 (25:2 Md. R. 76); December 22, 2003 (30:25 Md. R. 1849); March 22, 2010 (37:6 Md. R. 479)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-06-11"><cite path="|11|04|02|.01-1A">Regulation .01-1A</cite> amended effective June 11, 1990 (17:11 Md. R. 1344)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-03-22"><cite path="|11|04|02|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective March 22, 2010 (37:6 Md. R. 479)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-06-11"><cite path="|11|04|02|.02|C.">Regulation .02C</cite>, D amended effective June 11, 1990 (17:11 Md. R. 1344)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-06-11"><cite path="|11|04|02|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite>, G amended, I adopted, effective June 11, 1990 (17:11 Md. R. 1344)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-03-22"><cite path="|11|04|02|.03|G.">Regulation .03G</cite>, H amended effective March 22, 2010 (37:6 Md. R. 479)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1996-03-25"><cite path="|11|04|02|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective March 25, 1996 (23:6 Md. R. 477)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-02-01"><cite path="|11|04|02|.03|C.">Regulation .03C</cite> amended effective February 1, 1998 (25:2 Md. R. 76)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-06-11"><cite path="|11|04|02|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective June 11, 1990 (17:11 Md. R. 1344)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-03-22"><cite path="|11|04|02|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite> amended effective March 22, 2010 (37:6 Md. R. 479)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-12-25"><cite path="|11|04|02|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective May 19, 1986 (13:10 Md. R. 1157); June 11, 1990 (17:11 Md. R. 1344); December 22, 2003 (30:25 Md. R. 1849); March 22, 2010 (37:6 Md. R. 479); June 24, 2013 (40:12 Md. R. 1042); December 25, 2023 (50:25 Md. R. 1088)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-02-01"><cite path="|11|04|02|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective June 11, 1990 (17:11 Md. R. 1344); March 25, 1996 (23:6 Md. R. 477); February 1, 1998 (25:2 Md. R. 76)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-03-22"><cite path="|11|04|02|.06|B.">Regulation .06B</cite> amended effective March 22, 2010 (37:6 Md. R. 479)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-12-22"><cite path="|11|04|02|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective February 1, 1998 (25:2 Md. R. 76); December 22, 2003 (30:25 Md. R. 1849)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-03-22"><cite path="|11|04|02|.07|B.">Regulation .07B</cite> amended effective March 22, 2010 (37:6 Md. R. 479)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-06-11"><cite path="|11|04|02|.08">Regulation .08</cite> adopted effective June 11, 1990 (17:11 Md. R. 1344)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-03-22"><cite path="|11|04|02|.08">Regulation .08</cite> amended effective February 1, 1998 (25:2 Md. R. 76); March 22, 2010 (37:6 Md. R. 479)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-12-22"><cite path="|11|04|02|.08|F.">Regulation .08F</cite>, G amended effective December 22, 2003 (30:25 Md. R. 1849)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
