<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Specific Conditions for Movement of Certain Oversize and Overweight Vehicles</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Administration" means the State Highway Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Excessive size" means an overall dimension of 16 feet or more in height, 16 feet or more in width, or 100 feet or more in length.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Excessive weight" means a gross vehicle weight exceeding 60 tons (120,000 pounds).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3-1)</num>
        <text>"Massive weight" means a gross weight exceeding 250 tons (500,000 pounds).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Unit" means the Hauling Permits Unit of the Motor Carrier Division, Office of Traffic and Safety, within the State Highway Administration, and is the Unit that issues permits for oversize and overweight vehicles.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Vehicles Over 45 Tons, Over 60 Tons (Excessive Weight), Over 250 Tons (Massive Weight), or of Excessive Size.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In addition to the general conditions under <cite path="|11.04.02">COMAR 11.04.02</cite>, specific conditions apply to certain permits as indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Applications.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Excessive Weight. A person applying for a permit to move a vehicle which together with its load exceeds 60 tons, but does not exceed 250 tons, gross weight shall submit an application a minimum of 10 business days in advance of the proposed move to allow the Administration to complete any surveys, studies, or investigations necessary to determine an acceptable route and to determine any special conditions which should be included in the permit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(1-1)</num>
        <text>Massive Weight. A person applying for a permit to move a vehicle which together with its load exceeds 250 tons gross weight shall submit an application a minimum of 30 business days in advance of the proposed move to allow the Administration to complete any surveys, studies, or investigations necessary to determine an acceptable route and to determine any special conditions which should be included in the permit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Excessive Size. For the movement of any vehicle, which together with its load is of excessive size, a person shall submit an application a minimum of 2 working days before the proposed move.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Safety. When the permittee or user moves a vehicle and load together exceeding 45 tons gross weight on any highway in the State, the speed of the overweight vehicle may not exceed 10 miles per hour under the posted speed limit at any time.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Surety Bonds.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Unit may require any applicant for a permit for movement of a vehicle which together with its load is of excessive size, excessive weight, or massive weight to post either or both of the bonds described in §D(2) and (3) of this regulation, before the permit is issued.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Bond to Cover Administration Costs.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Unit may require the posting of a surety bond, satisfactory to the Unit, guaranteeing payment of the costs of any surveys, studies, or investigations which the Administration is required to perform in order to determine an acceptable route and to determine any special conditions for the permit.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Unit shall fix the amount of the bond.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Unit shall review and may disapprove the form of the bond and the security.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Bond or Insurance to Assure Satisfactory Performance of Move.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Unit may require the posting of a surety bond, satisfactory to the Unit, guaranteeing performance of the move in a manner satisfactory to the Administration, and protecting the Administration and the State from any expense caused to them through failure of the permittee or user to comply with all the provisions of the permit or through any negligence of the permittee or user.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Unit shall fix the amount of the bond.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Unit shall review and may disapprove the form of the bond and the security.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The applicant may substitute for the bond required under this subsection a contractual liability clause, satisfactory to the Unit, added to a standard certificate of insurance. The Unit shall fix the amount of the insurance and shall review and may disapprove the form of the clause and the insurer.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|04|03|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Steel-Rimmed Equipment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The special requirements in <cite path="11|04|03|.03|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> apply when any person moves heavy equipment having steel rims (steel wheels or tracks which would make contact with the road surface in the absence of protective devices) under its own power.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Special Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If the gross weight of the equipment is more than 13 tons and less than 20 tons, the permittee shall move it on 2-inch thick timber mats at least 6 inches wider than the treads of the wheels or tracks of the equipment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the gross weight of the equipment is 20 tons or more, the permittee shall move it on timber mats not less than 3 inches thick and at least 12 inches wider than the treads of the wheels or tracks of the equipment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|2-103">2-103</cite>(b), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|4-204">4-204</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|4-205">4-205</cite>(f), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|8-204">8-204</cite>(b)—(d),(i), 24-112, 24-113, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1975-05-20">Effective date: May 20, 1975 (2:10 Md. R. 752)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1977-02-16"><cite path="|11|04|03|.01|G.">Regulation .01G</cite> adopted effective February 16, 1977 (4:4 Md. R. 283)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1977-07-20">Chapter revised effective July 20, 1977 (4:15 Md. R. 1146)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|11.04.06">COMAR 11.04.06</cite> to <cite path="|11.04.03">11.04.03</cite></annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1984-08-01"><cite path="|11|04|03|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective August 1, 1984 (11:15 Md. R. 1331)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1984-08-01"><cite path="|11|04|03|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective August 1, 1984 (11:15 Md. R. 1331)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-10-23" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective October 23, 1995 (22:21 Md. R. 1616)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-02-01"><cite path="|11|04|03|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective February 1, 1998 (25:2 Md. R. 76)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-03-22"><cite path="|11|04|03|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective March 22, 2010 (37:6 Md. R. 479)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-03-22"><cite path="|11|04|03|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective February 1, 1998 (25:2 Md. R. 76); March 22, 2010 (37:6 Md. R. 479)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
