<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>06</num>
  <heading>Residential Entrance Permits</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Procedure for Obtaining Permit.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Work within the State right-of-way may not be undertaken until a permit has been issued by the State Highway Administration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An individual or corporation desiring to construct an entrance to serve a private residence shall make written application, transmitted by methods as determined acceptable by the Administration, in the form prescribed in these regulations, to the appropriate office listed below:</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>County</th>
              <th>Address</th>
              <th>Telephone</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>Allegany</td>
              <td>State Highway Administration<br/>P.O. Box 3347<br/>LaVale, MD 21502</td>
              <td>(301)729-8400</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Anne Arundel</td>
              <td>State Highway Administration<br/>P.O. Box 33<br/>Glen Burnie, MD 21061</td>
              <td>(410)766-3770</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Baltimore</td>
              <td>State Highway Administration<br/>8375 Pulaski Highway<br/>Rosedale, MD 21237</td>
              <td>(410)574-4511</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Calvert</td>
              <td>State Highway Administration<br/>P.O. Box 239<br/>Prince Frederick, MD 20678</td>
              <td>(410)535-1748</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Caroline</td>
              <td>State Highway Administration<br/>P.O. Box 340<br/>Denton, MD 21629</td>
              <td>(410)479-0770</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Carroll</td>
              <td>State Highway Administration<br/>5111 Buckeystown Pike<br/>Frederick, MD 21701</td>
              <td>(301)624-8115</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Cecil</td>
              <td>State Highway Administration<br/>P.O. Box 486<br/>Elkton, MD 21921</td>
              <td>(410)398-1565</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Charles</td>
              <td>State Highway Administration<br/>P.O. Box 610<br/>La Plata, MD 20646</td>
              <td>(301)934-8031</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Dorchester</td>
              <td>State Highway Administration<br/>P.O. Box 261<br/>Cambridge, MD 21613</td>
              <td>(410)228-4977</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Frederick</td>
              <td>State Highway Administration<br/>5111 Buckeystown Pike<br/>Frederick, MD 21701</td>
              <td>(301)624-8115</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Garrett</td>
              <td>State Highway Administration<br/>Route 2, P.O. Box 68<br/>Accident, MD 21520</td>
              <td>(301)895-3234</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Harford</td>
              <td>State Highway Administration<br/>P.O. Box 303 <br/>Churchville, MD 21028</td>
              <td>(410)838-7788</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Howard</td>
              <td>State Highway Administration<br/>5111 Buckeystown Pike<br/>Frederick, MD 21701</td>
              <td>(301)694-8115</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Kent</td>
              <td>State Highway Administration<br/>615 Morgnec Rd.<br/>Chestertown, MD 21620</td>
              <td>(410)810-3300</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Montgomery</td>
              <td>State Highway Administration<br/>9300 Kenilworth Avenue<br/>Greenbelt, MD 20770</td>
              <td>(301)513-7350</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Prince George's</td>
              <td>State Highway Administration<br/>9300 Kenilworth Avenue <br/>Greenbelt, MD 20770</td>
              <td>(301)513-7350</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Queen Anne's</td>
              <td>State Highway Administration<br/>P.O. Box 217 <br/>Centreville, MD 21617</td>
              <td>(410)758-0700</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>St. Mary's</td>
              <td>State Highway Administration<br/>27345 Point Lookout Road <br/>Leonardtown, MD 20650</td>
              <td>(301)475-8035</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Somerset</td>
              <td>State Highway Administration<br/>10980 Market Lane <br/>Princess Anne, MD 21853</td>
              <td>(410)651-1333</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Talbot</td>
              <td>State Highway Administration<br/>Box 745 <br/>Easton, MD 21601</td>
              <td>(410)822-3525</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Washington</td>
              <td>State Highway Administration<br/>18320 Col. Henry K. Douglas Drive<br/>Hagerstown, MD 21740</td>
              <td>(301)791-4790</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Wicomico</td>
              <td>State Highway Administration<br/>660 West Road<br/>Salisbury, MD 21802</td>
              <td>(410)543-6710</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Worcester</td>
              <td>State Highway Administration<br/>P.O. Box 268 <br/>Snow Hill, MD 21863</td>
              <td>(410)632-0511</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B-1.</num>
      <text>Addresses may be posted on the Administration's website.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Application. Applications shall be submitted in duplicate on forms provided by the Administration, or by other methods as determined acceptable by the Administration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Plans. If the entrance is proposed to be built in substantial similarity to typical entrance designs available from the Administration, plans are not required. The number of the appropriate plan should be indicated on the application forms. If plans are required, submit three copies drawn to appropriate scale (recommended scale is 1 inch = 20 feet).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Performance Surety.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To ensure complete and satisfactory compliance with the terms and specifications of the entrance permit, the permittee may be required to submit a performance bond, letter of credit, or certified check in the amount of 150 percent of the cost estimated for the construction for each entrance. The estimate must be acceptable to the Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a surety is submitted, the Administration shall be designated as the obligee, and the permittee as principal.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If a certified check is submitted, the check shall be made payable to the State Highway Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The permittee shall inform the State Highway Administration's resident maintenance engineer when work within the State's right-of-way is completed. Upon formal approval, the performance bond, letter of credit, or posted funds shall be returned to the permittee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Utility Adjustment. The permittee shall relocate or have relocated all utilities which are within the paving and in front of the curbs to be constructed under the permit. The permittee shall obtain, from the appropriate party or agency, all other permits or approvals necessary to conform to the requirements of the permit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Engineering Fee. In connection with the processing of applications, an engineering fee determined by the Administration may be charged for each point of access and offsite improvement beyond the first point of access. No engineering fee may be charged for the first access to a single residential property.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Inspection Cost.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At the discretion of the Administration, a State highway construction inspector may be assigned to inspect the work stipulated in the permit. The cost of the inspection shall be the responsibility of the permittee and shall be submitted before a permit is issued.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the cost of the inspection, including any necessary laboratory work, is expected to exceed $5,000, the cost shall be paid in advance. The cost shall be calculated on the base pay of the assigned employee, plus overhead, and all administrative and general expenses.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Standards and Specifications.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>All work and materials shall conform to Administration construction specifications, standards, and addenda current at the time of the permit grant.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>All work is subject to periodic inspection and final approval by the Administration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The number and location of entrances which may be granted shall be based on usage, interior and exterior traffic patterns, and current design policy of the Administration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Circular drives (ingress and egress point connected by a common driveway) require a minimum frontage of 100 feet.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The minimum width of a residential entrance is 10 feet, and the maximum width is 20 feet, unless otherwise permitted by the district engineer. Any exception shall be made by a permit, signed by the district engineer.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Existing sidewalks, curb, and gutter disturbed by construction shall be replaced in kind to the alignment and grade specified by authorized Administration personnel in a manner acceptable to the Administration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Positive drainage shall be maintained. Minimum pipe size is 18 inches or equivalent elliptical pipe. An end section or end walls, required by the resident maintenance engineer, shall be installed at the ends of the pipe. All pipes shall be State-approved or certified. Drainage pipes shall be located as far as practicable from the edge of a travelled lane to reduce the hazard to traffic. The minimum desirable distance is 30 feet. When pipe headwalls for other physical obstructions are placed within the clear zone, they shall be protected by guardrails or other appropriate barrier system.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Paving.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Area with Existing Sidewalks and Concrete Curb and Gutter. Paving shall consist of 6 inches Portland cement concrete on a suitable subbase.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Area Without Sidewalks and Concrete Curb and Gutter. Paving shall consist of 3-1/2 inches bituminous concrete (2 inch base, 1-1/2 inch surface) on 6 inches crusher run stone or 6 inches selected backfill. Variance to suit the conditions and locale may be made by a permit, signed by the district engineer.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>If the roadway is on an embankment and the roadway is not provided with existing standard traffic barriers along the roadway embankment, the driveway or embankment side slope shall be as flat as possible to reduce the hazard to traffic. The minimum desirable embankment side slope shall be 10:1 within 30 feet of the edge of the travelled lane or to the right-of-way line, whichever is less.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Mailboxes.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Mailboxes erected within the State Highway Administration's right-of-way shall be placed on a break-away type post or support.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The maximum size wooden post shall be 4 × 4 inches. The maximum size pipe type support shall be 2 inches in diameter. Any other type of support, ornamental or otherwise, may not have a structural strength greater than either of the two items listed above.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The property owner shall be directed to remove any mailbox support of a size greater than that listed above, and if not removed by the property owner, it shall be removed by the State Highway Administration's forces.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|2-103">2-103</cite>(b), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|8-202">8-202</cite>(b)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|2">2</cite>)(i), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|8-203">8-203</cite>(a), and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|8-204">8-204</cite>(b), (c),(i), Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1975-05-14">Effective date: May 14, 1975 (2:10 Md. R. 757)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|11.04.09">COMAR 11.04.09</cite> to <cite path="|11.04.06">11.04.06</cite></annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-01-14"><cite path="|11|04|06|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective January 14, 2010 (37:1 Md. R. 15)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-12-18"><cite path="|11|04|06|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective December 18, 1995 (22:25 Md. R. 1963)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-09-03"><cite path="|11|04|06|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite>—E amended effective September 3, 1990 (17:17 Md. R. 2082)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-02-01">Regulations .01G amended effective February 1, 2016 (43:2 Md. R. 128)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-09-03"><cite path="|11|04|06|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective September 3, 1990 (17:17 Md. R. 2082)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-01-14"><cite path="|11|04|06|.02|F.">Regulation .02F</cite> amended effective January 14, 2010 (37:1 Md. R. 15)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-09-03">Regulations .03 and .04 repealed effective September 3, 1990 (17:17 Md. R. 2082)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
