<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>10</num>
  <heading>Specific Information or Business Signs</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Administration" means the State Highway Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Business" means the provider of one of the four services (gas, food, lodging, and camping).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Drive-in” means a food business that provides stalls for which customers in vehicles can park, order, and eat food.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Expressway" means a major highway of two or more traffic lanes in each direction that is designed to eliminate principle traffic hazards and has the following characteristics:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A median divider separating opposing traffic lanes to eliminate head-on collisions and side-swiping;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Grade separation structures to eliminate the conflict of cross streams of traffic at each intersection;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Points of entrance and exit limited to predetermined locations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Vertical curves long enough to provide long sight distances; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Shoulders wide enough to permit vehicles to stop or park out of traffic lanes.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Generic motorist services symbols" means blue signs upon which white symbols are placed to indicate the presence of gas, food, lodging, or camping.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Gore" means the point at which the ramp roadway leaves the mainline roadway.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Logos" means the individual business trademarks.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Mainline" means the through roadway of the highway.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Ramp" means the connecting roadway between the mainline and the intersected road.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Services" means the four basic motorist services of gas, food, lodging, and camping.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>“Stall” means a clearly defined space for parking a vehicle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Applications.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An application is available for business establishments desiring to take part in the specific services signing program from the SHA Office of Traffic and Safety, c/o Logo Coordinator, 7491 Connelley Drive, Hanover, MD 21076, as well as on marylandroads.com.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An annual fee will cover all installation, maintenance, and administrative costs associated with this program, with a revised fee to be established as of July 1st of each year. The revised fee will be effective October 1 with respect to all new participants and renewals after that.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Once the business establishment mails or otherwise delivers the completed application to the office and address noted in the application, the Administration will ascertain whether or not space exists along the highway for the posting of signs and that the business establishment meets the required criteria.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The initial annual fee will be remitted by the business to the Administration upon approval of its application.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The annual fee period will begin on the date of the sign installation, with annual renewals.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>General Requirements for All Signing.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The specific services signing program applies only to expressways along the Maryland State highway system.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Repealed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Logo signs are motorist information signs, therefore, advertising may not be permitted on the logo sign.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Placement and Maintenance of Logo Signs.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The ability to place and maintain logo signing at a particular interchange is dependent upon the space available along the mainline and the space along the ramp to the intersected highway and other safety considerations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>At those locations where insufficient space is available for the use of logo signs, such as in urban and suburban locations, the Administration will place and maintain at its cost the generic motorist services symbols.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Specific services signs may not be considered for placement at those interchanges which do not provide direct re-entry to the mainline.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E-1.</num>
      <text>Number of Logo Signs.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Specific service signing is limited to no more than ten logos per service per direction per interchange.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A specific service sign is limited to six logos.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If there are more than six eligible logos for a service, the Administration may display up to four additional logos if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>On a new service sign the number and placement of signs is consistent with §§M—O of this regulation; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>On an existing service sign, at least two logo spaces remain available after additional logos are displayed.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Business to Provide Logo Sign Plates.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The business establishment will be responsible for providing logo sign plates to the State Highway Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The logo sign plates shall follow State Highway Administration specifications with regard to sign material and fabrication. These specifications will be forwarded to the business upon approval of the application.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Before the manufacture of the logo sign plate, the business shall submit to the Administration a layout plan of their proposed logo for approval.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Alterations may not be allowed to the logo sign once installed. Any subsequent change in the logo design will require Administration approval, and logo plates of the new design shall then be provided to the Administration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>All sign maintenance activities will be performed at the discretion of the Administration. Maintenance will be performed by the Administration or its contractors.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Eligible service establishments may not discriminate on the basis of race, religion, sex, nationality, or creed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Eligible service establishments shall conform with all applicable State and local laws with regard to licensing and operation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Logos will be placed on specific services signs on the basis of those establishments closest to the interchange.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>In those instances in which the maximum capacity of the specific services signs has been reached and an additional qualified business is established closer to the interchange, the following procedure will be effective:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The logo for the newer qualifying business shall be placed on the sign and the existing logo of the establishment farthest from the interchange shall be removed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The removal will occur on the anniversary date and there will be no refund of any fees paid.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Changes in service resulting in non-compliance with the requirements of this program will result in notification that signs shall be removed if the situation is not corrected within 30 days. There shall be no refund of fees under these circumstances.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>Spacing between mainline signs shall be at least 800 feet and spacing between ramp signs shall be at least 100 feet.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>Distance from gore to the first ramp sign shall be at least 100 feet.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>Measurements to services are referenced to the gore, or if more than one, to the first gore.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>P.</num>
      <text>Specific services signs are not advertising signs but are traffic control devices. Local zoning regulations may not apply.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>Q.</num>
      <text>Specific services signs and generic motorist services symbols may be used at the same intersection. However, for any one specific service type, both logos and generic motorist services symbols may not be used.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>R.</num>
      <text>In the event that specific services signs are not sought at a qualifying interchange, the generic motorist services symbols shall be used. Should one or more business at a qualifying interchange opt for a specific services sign, the generic motorist services symbols for that type of service or services shall then be removed. However, the generic motorist services symbols for the other service or services will remain.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>S.</num>
      <text>In deciding the distance and routing to a particular service where two or more interchanges are closely spaced, the interchange best serving the public through better road alignment, higher class highway, and more direct access will be used for the placing of the specific services signing. Along any one highway only one access point shall be signed for any one specific service establishment per direction.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Specific Conditions for Gas Signing.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Signing for gas shall be limited to those business establishments within 1 mile from the gore of the associated off-ramp.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Repealed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The business establishment shall provide vehicle services to include fuel, oil, and water.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The business establishment shall include restroom facilities and public drinking water.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The business establishment shall be in continuous operation 16 or more hours per day and 7 days per week.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The business establishment shall have a telephone available for public use.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|04|10|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Specific Conditions for Food Signing.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Signing for food shall be limited to those business establishments within 3 miles from the gore of the associated off-ramp.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Repealed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The business establishment shall be open for continuous operation serving at least 14 hours a day, at least 6 days a week and be opened not later than 7 a.m., except as noted in §§D and E of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the logo sign has less than the number of permitted logo plates, as described in regulation .03 E-1 of this chapter, a business establishment that is open continuously serving at least 8 hours a day, at least 6 days a week and opening no later than 11 a.m. may be approved for placement under the conditions of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If a business open for continuous operation as described in <cite path="11|04|10|.05|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> applies for space on a full logo sign that has logo plates displayed for businesses approved under <cite path="11|04|10|.05|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>, the business approved under <cite path="11|04|10|.05|D.">§D of this regulation</cite> that is the farthest from the interchange shall be removed as provided in Regulation .03K(1) and (2) of this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The business establishment shall have a telephone available for public use.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Except as provide in <cite path="11|04|10|.05|H.">§H of this regulation</cite>, the business establishment shall have a minimum seating capacity for 20 persons.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Drive-ins shall have a minimum of 10 stalls.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Specific Conditions for Lodging Signing.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Signing for lodging shall be limited to those business establishments within 3 miles from the gore of the associated off-ramp.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Repealed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The business establishment shall have a minimum of ten rooms or units and shall be open the year round.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The business establishment shall have a telephone available for public use.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Specific Conditions for Camping Signing.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Signing for camping shall be limited to those business establishments within 15 miles from the gore of the associated off-ramp.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Repealed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The campground shall have a minimum of ten camping spaces.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The campground shall have adequate parking for each camping space.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The campground shall have sanitary facilities.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The campground shall have drinking water.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The campground access shall be capable of accommodating vehicles and trailers during all weather conditions.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The campground shall have a telephone available for public use.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>The campground may not be closed to public use other than for a single period of up to 120 consecutive days between November 1 and April 1.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|4-205">4-205</cite>(f), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|4-405">4-405</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|8-204">8-204</cite>(b), and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|8-605">8-605</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1984-09-24">Effective date: September 24, 1984 (11:19 Md. R. 1666)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-12-24"><cite path="|11|04|10|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective December 24, 2012 (39:25 Md. R. 1614)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-12-02"><cite path="|11|04|10|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite>-1 adopted effective December 2, 1985 (12:24 Md. R. 2349)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-12-24"><cite path="|11|04|10|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended effective December 2, 1985 (12:24 Md. R. 2349); December 18, 1995 (22:25 Md. R. 1963); December 24, 2012 (39:25 Md. R. 1614)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-12-24"><cite path="|11|04|10|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective December 2, 1985 (12:24 Md. R. 2349); December 24, 2012 (39:25 Md. R. 1614)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-12-24"><cite path="|11|04|10|.04|B.">Regulation .04B</cite> repealed effective December 24, 2012 (39:25 Md. R. 1614)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-12-24"><cite path="|11|04|10|.04|D.">Regulation .04D</cite> amended effective December 24, 2012 (39:25 Md. R. 1614)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-12-02"><cite path="|11|04|10|.04|C.">Regulation .04C</cite> amended effective December 2, 1985 (12:24 Md. R. 2349)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-07-17"><cite path="|11|04|10|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective February 17, 2006 (33:6 Md. R. 576); amended permanently effective July 17, 2006 (33:14 Md. R. 1164)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-12-24"><cite path="|11|04|10|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective December 24, 2012 (39:25 Md. R. 1614)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-07-09"><cite path="|11|04|10|.05|B.">Regulation .05B</cite> amended effective July 9, 1990 (17:13 Md. R. 1611)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-12-02"><cite path="|11|04|10|.05|C.">Regulation .05C</cite> amended effective December 2, 1985 (12:24 Md. R. 2349)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-07-09"><cite path="|11|04|10|.06|B.">Regulation .06B</cite> amended effective July 9, 1990 (17:13 Md. R. 1611)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-12-24"><cite path="|11|04|10|.06|B.">Regulation .06B</cite> repealed effective December 24, 2012 (39:25 Md. R. 1614)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-07-09"><cite path="|11|04|10|.07|B.">Regulation .07B</cite> amended effective July 9, 1990 (17:13 Md. R. 1611)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-12-24"><cite path="|11|04|10|.07|B.">Regulation .07B</cite> repealed effective December 24, 2012 (39:25 Md. R. 1614)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-12-24"><cite path="|11|04|10|.07|E.">Regulation .07E</cite> amended effective December 24, 2012 (39:25 Md. R. 1614)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
