<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>11</num>
  <heading>Overweight Vehicle Permits for Certain Containerized Cargo Hauling</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Administration" means the State Highway Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Containerized cargo" means manifested international freight in a sealed, seagoing container that is heading to or egressing the Port of Baltimore.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Overweight" means weights that exceed the limits allowed by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr">Transportation Article, Title 24, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Unit" means the Hauling Permits Unit located within the Motor Carrier Division at the Maryland State Highway Administration's Office of Traffic and Safety.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Permits Available.</heading>
    <text>A person may move an indivisible load of containerized cargo under a containerized cargo permit.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Determination of an Indivisible Load.</heading>
    <text>A truck tractor-semitrailer combination of vehicles carrying manifested international freight as the only load of the vehicle in a sealed, seagoing container on a semitrailer is deemed to be carrying an indivisible load if:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The vehicle does not exceed the following maximum gross vehicle weight or axle weight limits:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>22,400 pounds on a single axle;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>44,000 pounds on 2 consecutive axles at least 4 feet apart; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>90,000 pounds gross vehicle weight; and</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The maximum allowable gross weight limit is 80,000 pounds for a 20-foot container loaded on a 20-foot intermodal chassis, 90,000 pounds for a 20-foot container loaded on a 40-foot or longer intermodal chassis, and 90,000 pounds for a 40-foot container, provided that the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Vehicle is being operated only on the routes specified under <cite path="|11|04|11|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>, and other routes approved by the Unit and described in the permit;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Vehicle is being operated in compliance with the permit issued under these regulations; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Original permit issued to the appropriate permittee is being carried in the vehicle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Routes of Travel.</heading>
    <text>A containerized cargo permit is valid for travel on all interstate highways in Maryland and the following routes under the jurisdiction of the State or the City of Baltimore only after the Secretary of Transportation has the results of studies and determines that use of permits issued under these regulations will not cause extraordinary damage to the roads and structures on the routes:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Between the Dundalk Marine Terminal and the Maryland-Pennsylvania State Line as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Harbor Tunnel (I-895) Routes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>From the Dundalk Marine Terminal, north on Broening Highway, west on Keith Avenue to Interstate-95 North to Boston Street Exit 57, to north on Interstate Avenue, west on the O'Donnell Street Cut-Off to Interstate-895 Harbor Tunnel Thruway to Interstate-695 (Towson) to Harbor Tunnel Thruway to Interstate-695 (Towson) to Interstate-70 west to the Maryland-Pennsylvania State Line;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>From the Maryland-Pennsylvania State Line travel east on Interstate-70 to Interstate-695 (Glen Burnie) to Interstate-895 Harbor Tunnel Thruway to the Holabird Avenue Exit East to travel south on Broening Highway to the Dundalk Marine Terminal.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Fort McHenry Tunnel (I-95) Routes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>From the Dundalk Marine Terminal, north on Broening Highway, west on Keith Avenue to Interstate-95 South (Washington) through the Fort McHenry Tunnel to Interstate-695 (Towson) to Interstate-70 west to the Maryland-Pennsylvania Line;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>From the Maryland-Pennsylvania Line travel east on Interstate-70 to Interstate-695 (Glen Burnie) to Interstate-95 North (New York) through the Fort McHenry Tunnel to Keith Avenue Exit 56, east on Keith Avenue to Broening Highway, south on Broening Highway to the Dundalk Marine Terminal.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Between the Dundalk Marine Terminal and the Maryland-Delaware State Line as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>From the Dundalk Marine Terminal, north on Broening Highway, west on Keith Avenue to Interstate-95 North to the John F. Kennedy Memorial Highway to the Maryland-Delaware State Line;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>From the Maryland-Delaware State Line travel the John F. Kennedy Memorial Highway to Interstate-95 South to the Keith Avenue Exit East to travel south on Broening Highway to the Dundalk Marine Terminal.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Between the CSX Intermodal Ramp and the Maryland-Pennsylvania State Line as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Harbor Tunnel (I-895) Routes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>From the CSX Intermodal Ramp, west on Newgate Avenue, north on Newkirk Street to O'Donnell Street, east on O'Donnell Street to Interstate-895 Harbor Tunnel Thruway to Interstate-695 (Towson) to Interstate-70 west to the Maryland-Pennsylvania State Line;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>From the Maryland-Pennsylvania State Line travel east on Interstate-70 to Interstate-695 (Glen Burnie) to Interstate-895 Harbor Tunnel Thruway to O'Donnell Street west to Newkirk Street, south on Newkirk Street to Newgate Avenue, east on Newgate to the CSX Intermodal Ramp.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Fort McHenry Tunnel (I-95) Routes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>From the CSX Intermodal Ramp, east on Newgate Avenue, north on Vail Street to Keith Avenue, west on Keith Avenue to Interstate-95 South (Washington) through the Fort McHenry Tunnel to Interstate-695 (Towson) to Interstate-70 west to the Maryland-Pennsylvania Line;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>From the Maryland-Pennsylvania Line travel east on Interstate-70 to Interstate-695 (Glen Burnie) to Interstate-95 North (New York) through the Fort McHenry Tunnel to Keith Avenue Exit 56, east on Keith Avenue to Vail Street, south on Vail to Newgate Avenue, west on Newgate to the CSX Intermodal Ramp.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Between the CSX Intermodal Ramp and the Maryland-Delaware State Line as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>From the CSX Intermodal Ramp, east on Newgate Avenue, north on Vail Street to Keith Avenue, west on Keith Avenue to Interstate-95 North to the John F. Kennedy Memorial Highway to the Maryland-Delaware State Line;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>From the Maryland-Delaware State Line travel the John F. Kennedy Memorial Highway to Interstate-95 South to the Keith Avenue Exit East to travel south on Vail Street to Newgate Avenue, west on Newgate to the CSX Intermodal Ramp.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Between the South Locust Point Marine terminal and the Maryland-Pennsylvania State Line:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>From the South Locust Point Marine Terminal west on McComas Street to Interstate-95 South (Washington) to Interstate-695 (Towson) to Interstate-70 west to the Maryland-Pennsylvania Line;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>From the Maryland-Pennsylvania Line travel east on Interstate-70 to Interstate-695 (Glen Burnie) to Interstate-95 North (New York) to Key Highway Exit 55, east on McComas to the South Locust Point Marine Terminal.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Between the South Locust Point Marine Terminal and the Maryland-Delaware State Line:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Harbor Tunnel (I-895) Routes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>From the South Locust Point Marine Terminal west on McComas Street to south on Hanover/Potee Streets, east on Frankfurst Avenue north to I-895 Harbor Tunnel Thruway to Interstate-95 North (New York) to the John F. Kennedy Memorial Highway to the Maryland-Delaware State Line,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>From the Maryland-Delaware State Line travel the John F. Kennedy Memorial Highway to Interstate-95 South to Interstate-895 Harbor Tunnel Thruway to Frankfurst Avenue, west on Frankfurst Avenue to Hanover Street, north on Hanover Street to McComas Street, east on McComas Street to the South Locust Point Marine Terminal;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Fort McHenry Tunnel (I-95) Routes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>From the South Locust Point Marine Terminal to Interstate-95 North (New York), through the Fort McHenry Tunnel to the John F. Kennedy Memorial Highway to the Maryland-Delaware State Line,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>From the Maryland-Delaware State Line travel the John F. Kennedy Memorial Highway to Interstate-95 South (Washington) through the Fort McHenry Tunnel to Key Highway Exit 55, south on Key Highway to E. McComas Street, east on McComas Street to the South Locust Point Marine Terminal.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Intra-city routes between the Dundalk Marine Terminal and the South Locust Point Marine Terminal are as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Harbor Tunnel (I-895) Routes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>From the Dundalk Marine Terminal, north on Broening Highway, west on Keith Avenue to Interstate-95 North to Boston Street Exit 57, to north on Interstate Avenue, west on the O'Donnell Street Cut-Off to I-895 Harbor Tunnel Thruway to Frankfurst Avenue, west on Frankfurst Avenue to Hanover Street, north on Hanover Street to McComas Street, east on McComas Street to the South Locust Point Marine Terminal,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>From the South Locust Point Marine Terminal, west on McComas Street, south on Hanover/Potee Streets, east on Frankfurst Avenue to Interstate-895 Harbor Tunnel Thruway to east on O'Donnell Street, south on Interstate Avenue to Interstate-95 South, to east on Keith Avenue, south on Broening Highway to the Dundalk Marine Terminal;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Fort McHenry Tunnel (I-95) Routes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>From the Dundalk Marine Terminal, north on Broening Highway, west on Keith Avenue to Interstate-95 South (Washington) through the Fort McHenry Tunnel to Key Highway Exit 55, south on Key Highway to E. McComas Street, east on McComas Street to the South Locust Point Marine Terminal,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>From the South Locust Point Marine Terminal to Interstate-95 North (New York) through the Fort McHenry Tunnel to Keith Avenue Exit 56, east on Keith Avenue to Broening Highway, south on Broening Highway to the Dundalk Marine Terminal.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Intra-city routes between the Dundalk Marine Terminal and Norfolk Southern Intermodal Ramp are as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>From the Dundalk Marine Terminal, north on Broening Highway, west on Keith Avenue to Interstate-95 North to the Eastern Avenue Exit, west on Eastern Avenue to Kane Street, north on Kane Street to Lombard Street, west on Lombard Street to the Norfolk Southern Intermodal Ramp opposite Oldham Street;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>From the Norfolk Southern Intermodal Ramp, east on Lombard Street to Kane Street, south on Kane Street to Interstate-95 South to the Keith Avenue Exit east to Broening Highway, south on Broening Highway to the Dundalk Marine Terminal.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Intra-city routes between the Dundalk Marine Terminal and the Port Covington CSX Railhead:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Harbor Tunnel (I-895) Routes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>From the Dundalk Marine Terminal north on Broening Highway, to west on Keith Avenue, to Interstate-95 North to O'Donnell Street Cut-Off, west on O'Donnell Street Cut-Off, to I-895 Harbor Tunnel Thruway, to Frankfurst Avenue, west on Frankfurst Avenue to north on Hanover Street, to east on Cromwell Street, north on Charles Street to Port Covington CSX Railhead,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>From Port Covington CSX Railhead, south on Charles Street to west on Cromwell Street, south on Hanover/Potee Streets, to east on Frankfurst Avenue, to I-895 Harbor Tunnel Thruway, to O'Donnell Street Exit, east on O'Donnell Street Cut-Off to south on Interstate Avenue, to Interstate-95 South, to east on Keith Avenue, to south on Broening Highway to the Dundalk Marine Terminal;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Fort McHenry Tunnel (I-95) Routes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>From the Dundalk Marine Terminal, north on Broening Highway to Keith Avenue, west on Keith Avenue to Interstate-95 South (Washington) through the Fort McHenry Tunnel to Key Highway Exit 55, west on McComas Street to Hanover Street, south on Hanover Street to Cromwell Street, east on Cromwell Street to Charles Street, north on Charles Street to Port Covington CSX Railhead,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>From Port Covington, south on Charles Street to Cromwell Street, west on Cromwell Street to Hanover Street, north on Hanover Street to McComas Street, east on McComas Street to Interstate-95 North (New York), through the Fort McHenry Tunnel to Keith Avenue Exit 56, east on Keith Avenue to Broening Highway, south on Broening Highway to the Dundalk Marine Terminal.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Intra-city routes between the Dundalk Marine Terminal and the CSX Intermodal Ramp:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>From the Dundalk Marine Terminal north on Broening Highway, west on Keith Avenue, south on Vail Street, west on Newgate Avenue to the CSX Intermodal Ramp on the south side of Newgate Avenue opposite Newkirk Street;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>From the CSX Intermodal Ramp, east on Newgate Avenue, north on Vail Street, east on Keith Avenue, south on Broening Highway to the Dundalk Marine Terminal.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Intra-city routes between the South Locust Point Marine Terminal and Port Covington CSX Railhead are as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>From the South Locust Point Marine Terminal, west on McComas Street to to Hanover Street, south on Hanover Street to Cromwell Street, into jughandle for east on Cromwell Street, north on Charles Street to Port Covington CSX Railhead;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>From Port Covington CSX Railhead, south on Charles Street to Cromwell Street, west on Cromwell Street to Hanover Street, north on Hanover Street to McComas Street, east on McComas Street to the South Locust Point Marine Terminal.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Intra-city routes between the South Locust Point Marine Terminal and the CSX Intermodal Ramp:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Harbor Tunnel (I-895) routes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>From the South Locust Point Marine Terminal west on McComas Street to south on Hanover/Potee Streets, to east on Frankfurst Avenue to I-895 Harbor Tunnel Thruway north to O'Donnell Street, east on the O'Donnell Street Cut-Off, south on Interstate Avenue to I-95 South to Keith Avenue, east on Keith Avenue, south on Vail Street, west on Newgate Avenue to the CSX Intermodal Ramp,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>From the CSX Intermodal Ramp, west on Newgate Avenue, north to Newkirk Street to O'Donnell Street, east on O'Donnell Street to I-895 Harbor Terminal Thruway south to Frankfurst Avenue exit, west on Frankfurst Avenue to north on Hanover Street, to east on McComas Street to the South Locust Point Marine Terminal;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Fort McHenry Tunnel (I-95) Routes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>From the South Locust Point Marine Terminal to Interstate-95 North (New York) through the Fort McHenry Tunnel to Keith Avenue Exit 56, east on Keith Avenue to Vail Street, south on Vail to Newgate Avenue, west on Newgate to the Sea-Land Terminal,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>From the Sea-Land Terminal, east on Newgate Avenue, north on Vail Street to Keith Avenue, west on Keith Avenue to Interstate-95 South (Washington) through the Fort McHenry Tunnel to Key Highway Exit 55, south on Key Highway to E. McComas Street, east on McComas Street to the South Locust Point Marine Terminal.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>Intra-city routes between the South Locust Point Marine Terminal and the Norfolk Southern Intermodal Ramp are as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Harbor Tunnel (I-895) Routes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>From the South Locust Point Marine Terminal, west on McComas Street, south on Hanover/Potee Streets, east on Frankfurst Avenue to I-895 Harbor Tunnel Thruway north to Lombard Street, west on Lombard Street to Norfolk Southern Intermodal Ramp on north side of Lombard Street opposite Oldham Street,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>From the Norfolk Southern Intermodal Ramp, east on Lombard Street, south on Ponca Street to I-895 Harbor Tunnel Thruway, south to Frankfurst Avenue, west on Frankfurst Avenue to north on Hanover Street, to east on McComas Street to the South Locust Point Marine Terminal;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Fort McHenry Tunnel (I-95) Routes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>From the South Locust Point Marine Terminal to Interstate-95 North (New York) through the Fort McHenry Tunnel to the Eastern Avenue Exit, west on Eastern Avenue to Kane Street, north on Kane Street to Lombard Street, west on Lombard Street to Norfolk Southern Intermodal Ramp opposite Oldham Street,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>From the Norfolk Southern Intermodal Ramp, east on Lombard Street to Kane Street, south on Kane Street to Interstate-95 South (Washington) through the Fort McHenry Tunnel to Key Highway Exit 55, south on Key Highway to E. McComas Street, east on McComas Street to the South Locust Point Marine Terminal.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>Intra-city routes between the CSX Intermodal Ramp and Norfolk Southern Intermodal Ramp are as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>From the CSX Intermodal Ramp, east on Newgate Avenue, north on Vail Street, west on Keith Avenue to Interstate-95 North, to the Eastern Avenue Exit, west on Eastern Avenue to Kane Street, north on Kane Street, west on Lombard Street to the Norfolk Southern Intermodal Ramp opposite Oldham Street;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>From the Norfolk Southern Intermodal Ramp, east on Lombard Street to Kane Street, south on Kane Street to Interstate-95 South, to the Keith Avenue Exit, east on Keith Avenue, south on Vail Street, west on Newgate Avenue to the CSX Intermodal Ramp.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>Intra-city routes between the CSX Intermodal Ramp and the Port Covington CSX Railhead are as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Harbor Tunnel (I-895) Routes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>From the CSX Intermodal Ramp, west on Newgate Avenue, north on Newkirk Street to O'Donnell Street, east on O'Donnell Street to Interstate-895 Harbor Tunnel Thruway to Frankfurst Avenue, west on Frankfurst Avenue to north on Hanover Street, east on Cromwell Street, north on Charles Street to the Port Covington CSX Railhead,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>From the Port Covington CSX Railhead, south on Charles Street, west on Cromwell Street, south on Hanover/Potee Streets to east on Frankfurst Avenue, north on Interstate-895 Harbor Tunnel Thruway, to west on O'Donnell Street, south on Newkirk Street to Newgate Avenue, east on Newgate to CSX Intermodal Ramp;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Fort McHenry Tunnel (I-95) Routes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>From the CSX Intermodal Ramp, east on Newgate Avenue, north on Vail Street to Keith Avenue, west on Keith Avenue to Interstate-95 South (Washington) through the Fort McHenry Tunnel to Key Highway Exit 55, west on McComas Street, south on Hanover Street to Cromwell Street, into jughandle for east on Cromwell Street, north on Charles Street to the Port Covington CSX Railhead,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>From the Port Covington CSX Railhead, south on Charles Street, west on Cromwell Street, north on Hanover Street to McComas Street, east on McComas Street to Interstate-95 North (New York) through the Fort McHenry Tunnel to Keith Avenue Exit 56, east on Keith Avenue, south on Vail Street, west on Newgate to the CSX Intermodal Ramp.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>P.</num>
      <text>Routes using Interstate-83 to and from the Maryland-Pennsylvania State Line:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Using the appropriate route from §§A through F of this regulation to reach Interstate-95 North, to Interstate-695 (Pikesville) to Interstate-83 (York) to the Maryland-Pennsylvania State Line;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>From the Maryland-Pennsylvania State Line travel Interstate-83 (Baltimore) to Interstate-695 (Essex) to Interstate-95 South then use the appropriate route from §§A through F of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>Q.</num>
      <text>Between the Port of Baltimore and Cambridge, Salisbury, the Maryland-Delaware State Line and Federalsburg:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Between the Port of Baltimore and Cambridge and Salisbury via U.S. Route 50:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Harbor Tunnel (I-895) Routes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Using the appropriate routes from §§G through O of this regulation to reach the Interstate-895 Harbor Tunnel Thruway, travel south to Maryland Route 3 to Maryland Route 100, to Maryland Route 2 South, to U.S. Route 50 East across the William Preston Lane, Jr. Memorial (Bay) Bridge, continue on U.S. Route 50 to Cambridge or Salisbury.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>From Cambridge or Salisbury travel U.S. Route 50 West across the William Preston Lane, Jr. Memorial (Bay) Bridge, continue on U.S. Route 50 West to Maryland Route 2 (Baltimore) to Maryland Route 100, to Maryland Route 3 to the Interstate-895 Harbor Tunnel Thruway then use the appropriate routes from §§G through O of this regulation.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Fort McHenry Tunnel (I-95) Routes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Using the appropriate routes from §§G through O of this regulation to reach Interstate-95 South (Washington)/Fort McHenry Tunnel, travel to Interstate-695 (Glen Burnie) to Maryland Route 3 South (Annapolis/Bay Bridge) to Maryland Route 100, to Maryland Route 2 South, to U.S. Route 50 East across the William Preston Lane, Jr. Memorial (Bay) Bridge, continue on U.S. Route 50 to Cambridge or Salisbury.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>From Cambridge or Salisbury travel U.S. Route 50 West across the William Preston Lane, Jr. Memorial (Bay) Bridge, continue on U.S. Route 50 West to Maryland Route 2 (Baltimore) to Maryland Route 100, to Maryland Route 3, to Interstate-695 North (Baltimore) to Interstate-95 North (New York)/Fort McHenry Tunnel then use the appropriate routes from §§G through O of this regulation.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Auxiliary routes between U.S. Route 50 and the Maryland-Delaware State Line:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>From U.S. Route 50 East travel Maryland Route 404 East, to Maryland Route 313 North, to Maryland Route 317 East to the Maryland-Delaware State Line.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>From the Maryland-Delaware State Line travel Maryland Route 317 West to Maryland Route 313 South to Maryland Route 404 West to U.S. Route 50 West.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Auxiliary routes between U.S. Route 50 and Federalsburg:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>From U.S. Route 50 East travel Maryland Route 331 East to Maryland Route 318 East to Federalsburg.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>From Federalsburg travel Maryland Route 318 West to Maryland Route 331 to U.S. Route 50 West.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>R.</num>
      <text>Additional authorized containerized cargo access routes are:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Interstate-68 east and west and Interstate-70 east and west to existing containerized cargo and return;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Taneytown, Maryland Route 140 north and south, Maryland Route 97 north and south, and Interstate-70 east and west to existing containerized cargo routes and return;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Hanover, Maryland, Candlewood Road, Maryland Route 176 east and west and Interstate-97 north and south to existing containerized cargo routes and return;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>From the Maryland—Virginia Line, Interstate-495 north and south, and Interstate-95 north and south to existing containerized cargo routes and return;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Snowden River Parkway, Maryland Route 175 east and west to Interstate-95 north and south to existing containerized cargo routes and return;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>North Langley Road to Maryland Route 2, Maryland Route 270, Maryland Route 10, and Interstate-695 Dundalk Exit 44 over the Francis Scott Key Bridge; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Federalsburg, Maryland to Maryland Route 307 south to Maryland Route 331 south (Hurlock, Maryland) to Maryland Route 392 west to Maryland Route 16 south to the intersection of U.S. Route 50 (Cambridge, Maryland), and return via Maryland Route 16 north to Maryland Route 392 east (Hurlock, Maryland) to Maryland Route 331 north to Maryland Route 307 north (Federalsburg, Maryland).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Authority to Issue Permit.</heading>
    <text>The Unit may issue permits to allow the movement of overweight vehicles hauling an indivisible load of containerized cargo as described in <cite path="|11|04|11|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Procedures.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>To obtain a containerized cargo permit, the applicant shall submit, directly to the Unit, an original signed and completed application on a form and in a manner prescribed by the Unit. The applicant shall allow 5 working days for processing the permit request.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Unit may issue a containerized cargo permit that is valid for 1 year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Unit shall complete all blanks on the face of the containerized cargo permit before issuing the permit directly to the applicant.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The permittee shall sign the permit upon receipt.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The permittee or user of a containerized cargo permit shall carry the original (not a copy) of the permit on the overweight vehicle when moving the vehicle on a highway in the State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The permit vehicle may travel permitted routes on a 24-hour daily basis.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A permittee shall comply with all restrictions attached to the permit as well as any hauling permit restrictions posted on the Motor Carrier Division and CHART websites found at www.marylandroads.com. It is the responsibility of the permittee to review these websites for current hauling permit restrictions prior to any move being made under authority of this permit.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Fees.</heading>
    <text>A permit issued under this chapter may be issued at no cost to the applicant.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Denial of Permit.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Unit may not issue a containerized cargo permit unless the vehicle has 5 axles or more.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A permit may not be issued for more than one container on a truck tractor-semitrailer combination of vehicles.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>For any vehicle exceeding 80,000 pounds gross vehicle weight up to and including the maximum 90,000 pounds gross vehicle weight, the distance measured horizontally between the vertical center lines of the second axle and the last axle shall measure at least 36 feet.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Repealed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A vehicle weighing 80,000 pounds or more gross vehicle weight shall be registered for the maximum gross weight in its state of registration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Vehicles weighing less than 80,000 pounds gross vehicle weight shall be registered for not less than their actual gross vehicle weight.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The permit vehicle and load may not exceed the vehicle size limits allowed by the Maryland <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr">Transportation Article, Title 24, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Miscellaneous Conditions.</heading>
    <text>The following conditions apply to every containerized cargo permit:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The conditions specified in this regulation apply to every containerized cargo permit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A permit does not authorize a vehicle to travel upon roadways and bridges when the gross vehicle weight exceeds the posted weight restriction.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The permittee or user shall comply with the vehicle laws of Maryland (except those weight limits from which the permit authorizes departure) and with all the conditions of the permit and these regulations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A permit vehicle may not be operated at speeds greater than 50 miles per hour.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Failure to Comply.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Failure to comply with permit conditions or these regulations shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Void the permit and subject the permittee or user to the full assessment of fines under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|27-105">Transportation Article, §27-105, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, as if the permit were not issued;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Cause the permit to be subject to immediate revocation and confiscation by any officer or authorized civilian employee of the Maryland State Police, any officer of the Maryland Transportation Authority Police, or any other police officer; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Cause the load subject to reduction in compliance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr">Transportation Article, Title 24, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If an officer confiscates a permit, the officer shall immediately notify the Unit and return the permit to the Unit after it has been used as evidence in any law enforcement proceedings.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The permittee or user shall present the permit for inspection, upon request, to an officer or authorized civilian employee of the Maryland State Police, an officer of the Maryland Transportation Authority Police, or any other police officer; and the permit shall be open to inspection by a State, county, municipal, or other public official and to a person involved in an accident in which the vehicle was involved.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Suspension.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If a permittee has violated these regulations, or the terms of a permit two times within a 6-month period, the Unit may suspend for 30 days the permittee from use of a containerized cargo permit issued and outstanding.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If a permittee has violated these regulations, or the terms of a permit three times within a 12-month period, the Unit may suspend for 60 days the permittee from use of a containerized cargo permit issued and outstanding.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If a permittee has violated these regulations, or the terms of a permit more than three times within a 12-month period, the Unit may revoke permanently the permittee from use of a containerized cargo permit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Unit determines initially all violations of these regulations or the terms of a permit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the Unit determines that there has been a violation, it shall notify the permittee by certified mail of the specific violations, of a period of suspension, of a revocation, and of the opportunity for appeal and to be heard.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The permittee has 7 business days from receipt of the written notice of violation to file a written appeal with the Director, Office of Traffic and Safety, State Highway Administration. An appeal will not be accepted unless it is in writing and filed within the prescribed time limit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If an appeal is filed, the Director, Office of Traffic and Safety, State Highway Administration, shall review the entire record relating to the violation charged. If the appellant specifically requests a hearing, the Director shall grant a hearing. If the appellant fails to appear at the hearing, the Director, Office of Traffic and Safety, State Highway Administration, may proceed by a review of the record.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>After reviewing the record and any evidence submitted at a hearing, the Director shall affirm, amend, or reverse the findings of the Unit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The decision of the Director, Office of Traffic and Safety, is the final decision of the State Highway Administration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>False Statement in Permit Application.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If an application for a containerized cargo permit contains a false statement of a material fact, the Unit may deny that permit and any future permits to the permittee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If the Unit determines that an application contains a false statement of a material fact, the Unit shall notify the permittee by certified mail of its determination, the status of suspension from future permits, the duration of the suspension as provided in <cite path="|11|04|11|.10">Regulation .10 of this chapter</cite>, and the opportunity for appeal and to be heard.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The permittee has 7 business days from receipt of the written notice of violation to file a written appeal to the Director, Office of Traffic and Safety, State Highway Administration. Only a written appeal filed within the time specified will be accepted.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If an appeal is filed, the Director, Office of Traffic and Safety, State Highway Administration, shall review the entire record relating to any violation charged. If the appellant specifically requests a hearing, the Director, Office of Traffic and Safety, State Highway Administration, shall grant a hearing. If the appellant fails to appear the hearing, the Director, Office of Traffic and Safety, State Highway Administration, may proceed by a review of the record.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3-1)</num>
        <text>After reviewing the record and any evidence submitted at any hearing, the Director, Office of Traffic and Safety, State Highway Administration, shall affirm, amend, or reverse the decision of the Unit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The decision of the Director, Office of Traffic and Safety, is the final decision of the State Highway Administration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Costs and Damages for which Permittee is Responsible.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The permittee is responsible for payment of each of the following items:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All damage that the vehicle causes, either directly or indirectly, to any road surface, bridge, signs, or other structure, whether maintained by the Administration or by another entity;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The cost of all correspondence, whether telephonic or written, made in connection with the permit;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any additional expense incurred by the Administration in connection with the permit or the movement authorized by the permit.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall repair or correct all damage caused to any property owned by or maintained by it and shall collect the expense of the repairs or corrections from the permittee. This includes but is not limited to road surfaces, approaches, embankments, drainage areas, ditches, bridges, signs, structures of any kind, and other property not specifically listed.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|2-103">2-103</cite>(b), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|4-204">4-204</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|4-205">4-205</cite>(f), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|8-204">8-204</cite>(b)—(d) and(i), 24-112, 24-113, and 24-113.1, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-12-15">Regulations <cite path="|11|04|11|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|11|04|11|.12">.12</cite> adopted as emergency provision effective September 24, 1986 (13:21 Md. R. 2312); adopted permanently effective December 15, 1986 (13:25 Md. R. 2662)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1988-04-18"><cite path="|11|04|11|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended as emergency provision effective December 15, 1987 (15:1 Md. R. 16); emergency status extended to April 18, 1988 (15:9 Md. R. 1107); adopted permanently effective April 18, 1988 (15:8 Md. R. 1015)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1988-08-08"><cite path="|11|04|11|.04|Q.">Regulation .04Q</cite> amended as emergency provision effective April 11, 1988 (15:10 Md. R. 1197); adopted permanently effective August 8, 1988 (15:16 Md. R. 1916)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-08-06"><cite path="|11|04|11|.04|Q.">Regulation .04Q</cite> amended as emergency provision effective April 10, 1990 (17:8 Md. R. 971); adopted permanently effective August 6, 1990 (17:15 Md. R. 1861)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1988-04-18"><cite path="|11|04|11|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended as emergency provision effective December 15, 1987 (15:1 Md. R. 16); emergency status extended to April 18, 1988 (15:9 Md. R. 1107); adopted permanently effective April 18, 1988 (15:8 Md. R. 1015)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-12-22" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective December 22, 2003 (30:25 Md. R. 1849)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-03-22"><cite path="|11|04|11|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective March 22, 2010 (37:6 Md. R. 479)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-03-22"><cite path="|11|04|11|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective March 22, 2010 (37:6 Md. R. 479)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-03-22"><cite path="|11|04|11|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective March 22, 2010 (37:6 Md. R. 479)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-03-22"><cite path="|11|04|11|.06|A.">Regulation .06A</cite> amended effective March 22, 2010 (37:6 Md. R. 479)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-03-22"><cite path="|11|04|11|.06|G.">Regulation .06G</cite> adopted effective March 22, 2010 (37:6 Md. R. 479)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-03-22"><cite path="|11|04|11|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective March 22, 2010 (37:6 Md. R. 479)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-03-22"><cite path="|11|04|11|.08">Regulation .08</cite> amended effective March 22, 2010 (37:6 Md. R. 479)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-03-22"><cite path="|11|04|11|.09|E.">Regulation .09E</cite> amended effective March 22, 2010 (37:6 Md. R. 479)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-03-22"><cite path="|11|04|11|.10|A.">Regulation .10A</cite> amended effective March 22, 2010 (37:6 Md. R. 479)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-03-22"><cite path="|11|04|11|.11">Regulation .11</cite> amended effective March 22, 2010 (37:6 Md. R. 479)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
