<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>18</num>
  <heading>Joint Trenching of Broadband</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Broadband provider” means a telecommunications entity deploying broadband-related infrastructure such as conduit, fiber, or similar infrastructure.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Department” means the Department of Transportation, including the State Highway Administration, the Maryland Transportation Authority, and the Maryland Transit Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Joint trenching” means the Department or a local government laying or installing conduit, fiber, or similar infrastructure concurrently with one or more broadband providers.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Trenching.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Trenching” means a governmental construction project in which a highway right-of-way surface is opened or removed for the purpose of laying or installing conduit, fiber, or similar infrastructure for but not limited to broadband deployment in excess of 1 mile in length.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Trenching” does not include a project for construction or maintenance of a highway facility, including drainage or culvert work.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Applicability.</heading>
    <text>This chapter applies to the Department and local governments that are located outside of the Washington Suburban Sanitary District.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Procedures for Joint Trenching.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Department shall maintain a list of broadband providers interested in joint trenching under this chapter on an opt-in basis via email to OOC_Utilities@mdot.maryland.gov.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>As soon as is practicable once a local government’s trenching project plans are determined, a local government shall provide the location, scope, and nature of any trenching opportunity under this chapter to the Department for notification to interested broadband providers. Notice to the Department shall be sent via email to OOC_Utilities@mdot.maryland.gov.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Department shall notify the list of broadband providers maintained by the Department of any eligible joint trenching opportunity under this chapter and include the date by which the broadband provider must express interest in participating in the trenching project. To express their interest in participation, broadband providers shall send an email to OOC_Utilities@mdot.maryland.gov. The Department shall provide necessary information for an interested broadband provider to apply for necessary permits or approvals from the Department or, in the case of a local government project, a point of contact within the local government to proceed with necessary permits or approvals.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A broadband provider shall comply with any other requirements of the Department or local government that would otherwise apply independent of joint trenching.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|8-654">Transportation Article, §8-654(e), </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-06-27">Effective date: June 27, 2022 (49:16 Md. R. 688)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
