<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Executive Orders</prefix>
  <num>1990</num>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Maryland Main Street Designation Program</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The "Maryland Main Street Designation" Program is hereby established within the Department of Housing and Community Development and will provide recognition and designation of certain commercial areas within the State as "Maryland Main Street" areas, and the Secretary of Housing and Community Development is hereby directed to consult with the Secretaries of Transportation, Natural Resources and Employment and Economic Development in the development of the program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Department of Transportation through its State Highway Administration is hereby directed to work in cooperation with the Department of Housing and Community Development to accommodate special design needs in areas designated as "Maryland Main Streets" and in historic districts that have been listed by the Maryland Historical Trust in the Maryland Register of Historic Properties pursuant to Article 83B, ยง5-615 of the Annotated Code or have been established by a county or municipality pursuant to Article 66B, Title 8, or other applicable provisions of the Annotated Code.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Department of Employment and Economic Development, through its tourism and promotional activities, is hereby directed to provide special marketing and promotional assistance as well as assistance which may be available through relevant programs of its Department to areas and communities containing designated "Maryland Main Streets."</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Department of Natural Resources through its programs related to State open space, open areas, and State waters is hereby directed to work cooperatively with the Department of Housing and Community Development to assist areas designated as "Maryland Main Streets" which border on or otherwise affect State waters, open space, or open areas, as those terms are defined in Title 8, Subtitle 1, and Title 5, Subtitle 12 of the Natural Resources Article.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="1990-08-16">Effective date: August 16, 1990 (17:18 Md. R. 2166)</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</container>
