<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Executive Orders</prefix>
  <num>1993</num>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Regulatory Reform to Support Manufacturing and Technology-Related Industries</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The purpose of this Executive Order is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To establish general policy guidelines for Executive agencies regarding the enforcement and enactment or modification of regulations affecting manufacturing and technology-related industries.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>To provide accountability mechanisms that apply to State agencies to ensure that these general policy guidelines are implemented.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Policy Guidelines.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>State agencies that regulate manufacturing and technology-related industries (regulatory agencies) shall provide opportunities for consultations with affected industries prior to publishing a proposed regulation in the Maryland Register.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Agencies should make technical assistance to help businesses comply with regulatory requirements a priority service.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Regulatory agencies shall, to the extent practicable, provide businesses that are first-time violators of an agency regulation, a reasonable opportunity to take corrective action rather than issue fines (unless required by Federal or State law) and shall provide appropriate guidance to assist a business in correcting the violation and avoiding future violations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>When businesses are required to obtain multiple permits from, or submit to multiple inspections by, State and local agencies, regulatory agencies shall coordinate with other State and local agencies to streamline permitting and inspection processes and eliminate duplicative requirements.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>State agencies shall establish and maintain review and decision timetables for permit applications.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Accountability Mechanisms.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Departments of Environment, Licensing and Regulation, Natural Resources, and Economic and Employment Development shall form a working group to coordinate and oversee the implementation of this Executive Order.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Each regulatory agency shall, by December 31, 1993, submit to the working group a technical assistance plan that examines its current capacity to provide technical assistance to affected industries, identifies the degree of unmet technical assistance, and presents a plan to address any unmet needs. This plan shall be updated and submitted to the working group by December 31 of each subsequent year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>In cooperation with local officials, the working group shall identify problems and solutions in the permitting and inspection processes in State and local government agencies.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Each State agency that is a part of the working group shall provide performance data on its success in meeting the review and decision timetables for permit applications that are required by this Executive Order.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The working group shall ensure that the views of the affected industries and local officials are considered in its ongoing activities.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>This Executive Order is not intended to and may not be construed to confer any right, privilege, or status on any private party cognizable by a court in any proceeding. No action of a State agency may be deemed, held, or otherwise considered to be unenforceable due to a failure to comply with the terms of this Executive Order.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="1993-03-19">Effective date: March 19, 1993 (20:8 Md. R. 678)</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.20</num>
    <heading>Alternative Fueled Vehicles</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Purchase of Alternative Fueled Vehicles.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To the greatest extent practicable, and consistent with operational requirements and the provisions and requirements of this Executive Order, the State shall purchase vehicles that operate on alternative fuels in order to meet the requirements of the National Energy Policy Act of 1992.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In consultation with the Alternative Fuels Work Group, the Department of Budget and Fiscal Planning shall approve for State agencies vehicle specifications in order to provide reasonable and practical options for the purchase of alternative fueled vehicles. The University of Maryland System shall approve similar specifications for the purchase of alternative fueled vehicles within the University System. Specifications are to be balanced appropriately with operating needs and budgets.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Department of General Services and the University of Maryland System shall procure, for State agencies and the University of Maryland System and its constituent institutions, respectively, approved alternative fueled vehicles and shall ensure that refueling capacity for alternative fuels is available to State agency fleets and the University of Maryland System.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Department of Budget and Fiscal Planning shall advise agencies and The University of Maryland System concerning specific applications of alternative fuels and assist agencies in specifying alternative fueled vehicles in accordance with approved specifications and guidelines.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Department of Transportation shall ensure that regulatory prohibitions to alternative fuels are reviewed and addressed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Cabinet secretaries and the heads of independent agencies shall develop goals for the introduction of dedicated alternative fueled vehicles into their agencies following the approval of vehicle specifications under Section A(1) of this Order. Such goals shall be submitted to the Director of the Maryland Energy Administration beginning with Fiscal Year 1994 and each fiscal year thereafter, and shall take into consideration the number and location of alternative fuel stations.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Alternative Fuels Work Group.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>There is established an Alternative Fuels Work Group.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Work Group shall be composed of representatives of the following agencies, to be appointed by the agency head:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Department of Budget and Fiscal Planning;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Maryland Energy Administration;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Department of the Environment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Department of General Services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The Department of Transportation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The Public Service Commission;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>The Department of Natural Resources;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>The University of Maryland System; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>The Department of Agriculture.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Director of the Maryland Energy Administration shall be the chairperson of the Work Group.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Alternative Fuels Work Group shall evaluate and recommend to the Governor and the executive agencies alternative fuels for use in the State fleet, and examine issues related to the use of those fuels in the State fleet.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Department of the Environment shall provide guidance to the Alternative Fuels Work Group on the air quality benefits of various alternative fuels in various applications and otherwise assist in the achievement of a strong alternative fuels vehicle program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>In implementing this Executive Order, strict compliance with all applicable air quality standards and regulations shall be maintained.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The Work Group shall consult with the Comptroller of the Treasury and other State agencies as appropriate.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Implementation of Executive Order. The Maryland Energy Administration shall be responsible for coordinating the requirements of this Executive Order and for informing and encouraging county and local governments to join in purchasing alternative fueled vehicles from the State contract.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="1993-08-03">Effective date: August 3, 1993 (20:17 Md. R. 1342)</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.22</num>
    <heading>State Postsecondary Review Entity</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Maryland Higher Education Commission is designated as the State Postsecondary Review Entity (SPRE) under Sections 494 through 494C of the Higher Education Act of 1965, as added by the Higher Education Amendments of 1992, Pub. L. No. 102-325, 20 U.S.C. ยง1099a to 1099a-3, and shall perform all of the functions described therein on behalf of the State of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Commission and the Secretary of Higher Education may enter into any contracts, agreements or understandings, may adopt whatever rules, regulations or policies, and may perform all other acts necessary or appropriate to fulfill its functions as the Maryland SPRE.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>All affected State agencies, departments, units, and employees shall cooperate fully with the Commission and the Secretary in the performance of their functions under the SPRE program.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="1993-08-23">Effective date: August 23, 1993 (20:19 Md. R. 1467)</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.24</num>
    <heading>Maryland Statewide Independent Living Council</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>There is a Maryland Statewide Independent Living Council (hereafter referred to as Council), established in accordance with the requirements of Chapter I of Title VII of the Federal Rehabilitation Act, as amended (hereafter referred to as Act). The Council shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Work in conjunction with the Maryland State Division of Rehabilitation Services in submitting, monitoring, and evaluating the implementation of the Independent Living Rehabilitation Services State Plan; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Carry out other duties as stipulated in Section 705(c) of the Act to support the implementation of the State Plan.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Membership and Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The members of the Council shall be appointed by the Governor, and conform to the requirements of Section 705(b)(2) of the Act concerning representation and consultation with interested groups and individuals.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Members currently serving on the Statewide Independent Living Council, as constituted in 1988 under the Division of Rehabilitation Services, shall serve as the Governor's initial appointees to the Council established under this Executive Order. Thereafter, future appointments shall be made in accordance with the requirements of the Act.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Council shall annually elect a chairperson from among its members.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Members may serve up to two consecutive three-year terms, which shall be staggered on initial appointment. A member selected to fill a vacancy serves only for the balance of a term remaining at the time of appointment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A majority of the Council shall constitute a quorum for the transaction of business. The Council may adopt other rules and procedures to ensure the orderly conduct of business.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The Division of Rehabilitation Services shall provide staffing and resources as may be determined necessary to support the operation and duties of the Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Members of the Council may be reimbursed for reasonable and necessary expenses associated with attendance at meetings and performance of duties of the Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The Council shall continue to operate so long as required by the provisions of the Act.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="1993-09-24">Effective date: September 24, 1993 (20:21 Md. R. 1633)</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.28</num>
    <heading>State Employee Payroll Deductions (Amended COMAR 01.01.1986.14)</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General Limitations on Voluntary Deductions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Voluntary deductions are provided by the State for the benefit of a reasonable number of employees. Voluntary deductions must be within the capacity of the Central Payroll Bureau's system that serves the employees and must conform to the Central Payroll Bureau's forms and procedures. When the net amount payable to the employee is not sufficient to cover all of the voluntary deductions, deductions will be made in accordance with the sequence of the items listed in Section B.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All permitted voluntary deductions made on behalf of an employee organization or association (including deductions for insurance programs sponsored by the organization or association) will be provided at no charge as long as only one deduction is used. If additional deductions are requested by an organization or association, it will be required to pay a reasonable charge established by the Central Payroll Bureau taking into account personnel, computer and material costs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>No Department, Board, Commission, or Agency (hereafter referred to as Agency), may authorize solicitation of employees for insurance purposes at the place of employment unless the soliciting agents represent an approved employee organization or association. Payroll deductions shall not be authorized for any insurance premiums which are not included in one of the categories within Section B. Twice a year on a day selected by the Agency, representatives of employee organizations or associations and their insurance agents may be permitted to establish information desks centrally located convenient to State employees for soliciting and giving information about insurance programs. The information desks may be made available to State employees before or after working hours and during lunch and break periods.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Employees shall request all voluntary payroll deductions in writing on Central Payroll Bureau approved forms and all subsequent changes or cancellations shall similarly be in writing on an approved form.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Central Payroll Bureau shall be held harmless if it deducts, amends or cancels payroll deductions, in accordance with the written request of the employee. All disputes regarding payroll deductions, including refunds and missed deductions, are a matter between the employee and the organization or association receiving the deduction.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Contractual employees are only afforded voluntary deductions for deferred compensation, United States Savings Bonds, Maryland Charity Campaign for State Employees and Retirees, and contributions to labor organizations or associations of management officials which meet the criteria of Section B(9) of this Order.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Categories of Voluntary Deductions Permitted by the State of Maryland.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Health Insurance Premiums. The State offers a health program for its employees in certain categories. The premiums for this program are subsidized by the State as directed by the Secretary of Personnel. Deductions are initiated by the employee through the employee's Agency personnel office.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Dependency Support. Deductions for alimony and child support have previously been available only pursuant to a Court Order. In order to avoid the cost of Court Orders to the employee and the State, the State will also honor voluntary deductions for dependency support when the employee enters into an agreement with a support enforcement agent of the Department of Human Resources and it is within the capacity of the Central Payroll Bureau to process the deduction.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Deferred Compensation. The Maryland State Employees Deferred Compensation Program is administered by a Board of Trustees and includes a variety of options, including a savings account, fixed annuity, variable annuity, mutual fund and life insurance. Deductions are initiated, changed or cancelled through the Plan Administrator, currently the Public Employees Benefit Services Corporation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>State Employees Credit Union and MTA Employees Credit Union, Inc. The State encourages savings by its employees, making available deduction for the Credit Unions chartered to serve its employees, retirees, and their dependents. Deductions are initiated, changed or canceled as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Except as provided in item (b) of this paragraph, for State employees, through the State Employees Credit Union; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For Mass Transit Administration employees of the Department of Transportation, through the State Employees Credit Union and the MTA Employees Credit Union, Inc.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Maryland Charity Campaign for State Employees and Retirees. The State sponsors a single annual Maryland Charity Campaign for State employees and retirees and makes payroll deduction available for this purpose. The deduction for each annual contribution is made available under the following conditions:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The annual contribution is to be deducted over a term of one year beginning with the first pay period which begins in January or the initial date of employment, if later, and ending with the last pay period which begins in December.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An equal amount is to be deducted each pay period.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The employee may not change the amount deducted each pay period during the one year life of the deduction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The employee shall be informed of these restrictions before the deduction is requested.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The employee may voluntarily discontinue the deduction at any time, but a discontinued deduction may not be reinstated.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>United States Savings Bonds. The State of Maryland cooperates with the United States Treasury Department in making payroll deductions available for up to three different United States Savings Bonds.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Tax Deferred Annuities and Disability Plans. The State of Maryland offers to employees of the institutions of higher education various tax deferred annuities, life insurance plans and disability plans that have been approved by  Morgan State University, St. Mary's College of Maryland, the Maryland Higher Education Commission, or the Board of Regents of the University of Maryland System. In addition, the Maryland State Retirement Systems also offer a tax deferred annuity. No expansion in these deductions is permitted without the concurrence of the appropriate governing body and the support of the Central Payroll Bureau.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Insurance Afforded to Federal Civil Service Employees. The State of Maryland affords an insurance payroll deduction to Federal Civil Service employees who are currently paid by the State since it is a condition of their employment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Deductions for Employee Organizations and Associations. Subject to the general limitations stated in this Order, any employee labor organization or association of management officials or supervisors is entitled to payroll deduction privileges provided the organization or association meets all of the following criteria:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>It is organized for purposes other than obtaining insurance coverage.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>It serves the interest of employees and the State as an employer as certified by the Secretary of Personnel.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>It has at least 1,000 members who agree to payroll deduction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>In order to provide payroll deduction to small organizations or associations, one additional deduction per employee is allowed for an organization or association that meets the criteria of(a) and (b) above if 50% of the eligible members of the organization or association who are members of the same occupational group of employees, as determined by the Secretary of Personnel, agree to a payroll deduction. This additional deduction is subject to the general limitations stated in Section A. The Secretary of Personnel shall act as the Governor's designee for purposes of granting approval under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsp|6-402">ยง6-402(B)(2) of the State Personnel and Pensions Article of the Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Insurance Programs Sponsored by Employee Organizations or Associations. Insurance programs that require employee organization or association membership as a condition of entitlement will be paid in the same deduction as the employee organization or association unless the employee organization or association pays the charge for an additional deduction as specified in Section A(2).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>State University and College Fund Raising Campaigns. One deduction per employee is offered for use by any State institution of higher education for capital or annual fund campaigns that have been approved by the appropriate governing body and which are within the capability of the Central Payroll Bureau.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Existing Deductions that do not Meet These Criteria. Existing organizations and associations which currently have payroll deduction privileges and do not meet the criteria of this Order will be allowed to continue payroll deduction for existing employees but will not be permitted to add new employees or to increase existing deductions.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Publication of Executive Order on Payroll Deductions. Copies of this Executive Order, as amended, shall be distributed to all State officials and employees and copies shall be posted in conspicuous locations in all State facilities.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="1983-01-24">Effective date: January 24, 1983 (10:4 Md. R. 267)</annotation>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="1993-10-18">Amended effective April 1, 1985 (12:9 Md. R. 797); October 20, 1986 (13:23 Md. R. 2467); October 18, 1993 (20:23 Md. R. 1782)</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.33</num>
    <heading>Alcohol and Tobacco Advertising on Property Owned or Leased by the Mass Transit Administration of the Maryland Department of Transportation</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Advertising Policy. The Mass Transit Administration of the Maryland Department of Transportation may not permit or contract for any advertising or promotions of any kind which encourage the public to use or consume alcoholic beverages or tobacco products or any similar advertisement on any property which the agency owns, leases, or otherwise controls.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Existing contracts which are inconsistent with this policy shall not be renewed or extended unless contract terms are revised to reflect this policy.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="1993-12-20">Effective date: December 20, 1993 (21:1 Md. R. 14)</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</container>
