<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Executive Orders</prefix>
  <num>1994</num>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>State Agencies—Internal Audits</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The appointing authority of each agency that currently performs internal audits shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Designate an individual to act as a chief internal auditor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Implement an effective program of internal audits that includes, as the agency head determines to be necessary, professional and support staff that have the technical proficiency and educational background appropriate for the performance of audits; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Seek from the Legislature sufficient funding to cover the related costs incurred by the agency in the performance of these duties.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The chief internal auditor of an agency shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Report directly to the agency head;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Develop an annual audit plan to carry out internal audits;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Provide written policies and procedures to guide the performance of internal audits;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>In conjunction with the Committee on Fraud, Waste, and Abuse's biannual self-assessment evaluation, maintain an ongoing internal quality assurance program to evaluate the operation of internal audits;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Prepare internal audit reports that shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be submitted to the Governor and agency head; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Be available for review, except for any part of a report that is privileged from disclosure under the Public Information Act;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Conduct follow-up reviews of internal audit findings to ascertain that appropriate action has been taken on findings contained in internal audit reports; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Make available and coordinate a continuing professional education program to ensure that the agency's internal auditors have access to current information concerning internal audit policies, procedures, and techniques and to provide general technical and audit assistance to the agency's internal auditors.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Each agency that performs internal audits shall establish a program that is conducted in accordance with internal auditing standards.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The chief internal auditor and the internal audit staff, shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Subject to the approval of the appointing authority, have access to all personnel and any data, records, and other information of the State agency that the chief internal auditor deems necessary to carry out the internal audit; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Maintain the confidentiality of any public records that are made confidential by law and be subject to the same penalties as the custodian of the public records for a violation of a confidentiality law applicable to the records.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="1994-02-04">Effective date: February 4, 1994 (21:5 Md. R. 313)</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Fetal Alcohol Syndrome</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Maryland State Department of Education will work with local health curriculum supervisors to increase the number of school systems that are using educational resources through organizations including, but not limited to, Blue Cross/Blue Shield, the Association of Retarded Citizens and the March of Dimes to address the growing need for staff development inservice training and classroom instruction to prevent FAS-related birth defects.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Governor's Office shall design and distribute a poster that expresses the risk of FAS to pregnant women. The poster shall be distributed to various locations aimed at increasing women's awareness of FAS. The locations shall include restaurants, bars, liquor stores, and schools.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="1994-05-16">Effective date: May 16, 1994 (21:12 Md. R. 998)</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.25</num>
    <heading>Grievance Procedure—State Employees</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The DOP may be made a party in a grievance when the appointing authority, in its decision at the conclusion of the first step of the grievance proceeding, pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsp|10-207">State Personnel and Pensions Article, §10-207(c), </cite>states that the DOP has taken an action adverse to the employee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In cases where the DOP has been named as a party by the appointing authority under paragraph A, the employee may submit the grievance to the second step of the grievance process, pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsp|10-208">State Personnel and Pensions Article, §10-208(a), </cite>and name the DOP as a party at that step. When the DOP has been named as a party, the grievant's department or unit head shall hold a conference with the grievant and a representative of the DOP. The decision of the grievant's department or unit head shall identify any areas of disagreement between the grievant, the appointing authority, and the DOP that have not been resolved.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the DOP has been named as a party under the terms of paragraphs A and B of this Order, the DOP may be named a party at step three of the grievance process.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Whenever the DOP has been named a party under this Order, the DOP, the appointing authority, and the grievant shall make every effort to resolve the grievance at the lowest level possible of the grievance process.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Nothing in this Order shall be construed to expand the scope of issues that are grievable or of the jurisdiction of the Secretary of Personnel (or of the Office of Administrative Hearings under a delegation of authority from the Secretary) to hear and decide grievances.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Officers and employees of the State may assist the Secretary of Personnel as deemed necessary by the Secretary to accomplish the purposes of this Order. Nothing in this Order shall be construed as modifying the authority of the Secretary to establish policy in personnel matters or the duty of officers and employees of the State in assisting the Secretary in carrying out State personnel laws and policies.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The Secretary of Personnel and the appointing authorities shall take all actions necessary or desirable to implement this Order.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="1994-09-08">Effective date: September 8, 1994 (21:20 Md. R. 1722)</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</container>
