<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Executive Orders</prefix>
  <num>1996</num>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Maryland Charity Campaign for State Employees and Retirees (Amended COMAR 01.01.1993.01)</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Administration.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Maryland Charity Campaign for State Employees and Retirees ("the Campaign") shall be administered on an annual basis by the Secretary of State in conformity with the provisions of Executive Order No. <cite path="01.01.1983.03">01.01.1983.03</cite> issued on January 24, 1983, as may be amended, which are not inconsistent with this Order.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of State shall develop instructions and procedures applicable to voluntary charitable organizations which may desire to participate in the Campaign in accordance with the eligibility criteria set forth herein.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of State shall select a qualified operating agency and execute an agreement with such agency for the conduct of the Campaign in accordance with the provisions of this Executive Order.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Solicitation Period.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Solicitations of current and retired State employees shall be limited to a 10-week period in the fall of each year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The heads of all boards, commissions, agencies and departments of State government shall cooperate with the Secretary of State and the operating agency to promote the efficient conduct of the Campaign and to ensure that employee participation in the Campaign is clearly voluntary and free of coercion.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Eligibility Criteria. In order to be designated as a participating agency in the Campaign, a charitable organization shall apply to the Secretary of State and shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Operate in compliance with all applicable federal, State, and local laws;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Operate under currently valid articles of incorporation or other organizing instrument and by-laws or other governing instrument; a copy of each being submitted with the application, if not already filed with the Secretary of State as part of a prior application or registration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Hold and maintain a currently valid designation by the Internal Revenue Service (I.R.S.) as a ยง501(C)(3) organization, and be eligible to receive tax deductible contributions under Section 170 of the Internal Revenue Code; a copy of the I.R.S. designation letter being submitted with the application to the Secretary of State, if not already filed, as part of a prior application for registration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Submit a duplicate copy of its I.R.S. Form 990 for its most recently completed fiscal year; or if not required by I.R.S. to file a Form 990, a copy of a financial report on a form provided by the Secretary of State, signed and certified by its chief executive officer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>State and certify the percentage of its total revenue from the preceding fiscal year which was spent on management and fund-raising expenses;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>If the percent of revenue spent by a charitable organization on management and fund-raising expenses exceeded 25 percent, submit a statement demonstrating that its expenses for these purposes were reasonable under all the circumstances in its case;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Submit a copy of its current operating budget signed and certified by its chief executive officer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Demonstrate that it has provided a significant level of service to the residents of the State of Maryland or to those in need of such services in other countries for a period of not less than two years immediately preceding the calendar year of the Campaign. Agencies providing services in other countries must provide evidence of financial support from Maryland residents within the past five years;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Certify that it will use funds from the Campaign solely for the provision of services to the residents of the State of Maryland, or to people in other countries, including reasonable administrative costs of these programs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Beginning with the 1997 Campaign, certify the amount of money received from the most recent Maryland Charity Campaign, and certify how that money was spent to provide services to residents of Maryland or to people in other countries;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Have a majority of its governing body serving without compensation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Make available to the public upon request its annual financial report.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Technical Assistance and Reconsideration of Application.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of State may call upon the operating agency for technical assistance in the administration of the Campaign.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An agency which submits an application for participation in the Campaign which is denied by the Secretary of State may within 10 days of the denial submit a petition for reconsideration. The Secretary of State's disposition of the petition shall be conclusive and final.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Operating Agency Criteria. The operating agency shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Demonstrate its administrative capability to manage and operate an extensive fund-raising campaign among the State's current and retired employees in an efficient manner;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Demonstrate its financial capability to manage and operate a fund-raising campaign in an efficient manner yielding contributions comparable to those made by State employees and retirees in the past;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Demonstrate its public accountability by certifying that it annually submits to a financial audit by a certified public accountant; make its audited financial statement, or a summary thereof, available to the public upon request; provide evidence that it has engaged in sound management practices that indicate that contributions donated by the public have been utilized with the utmost integrity; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Demonstrate that it has established a broad base of community support in the State and has established ongoing and cooperative relations with a significant number of the State's charitable organizations.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Operating Agency Responsibilities. The operating agency shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Promote and publicize the Campaign among the State's current and retired work force;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Publish brochures, informational materials and related matters sufficient for each potential contributor to fairly identify the participating agencies and their principal activity or charitable purpose(s), and the methods to be used for indicating the dollar amount of payroll deduction they wish to contribute;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Cooperate with the Office of the Comptroller, Central Payroll Division and comply with its payroll deduction policies and procedures;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Distribute contributions to participating agencies in accordance with the expressed intention of contributors; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Agree to the review of its financial activities by authorized representative of the State of Maryland, and, within 180 days of the close of a Campaign, submit to the Secretary of State a complete audited financial statement prepared in accordance with the standards of accounting and financial reporting for voluntary health and welfare organizations.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Undesignated Gifts. Where contributors do not specify one or more participating agencies as the beneficiary of their gift, or when a designated participating agency ceases to operate, the operating agency shall distribute such contributions in accordance with policies and programs of the Secretary of State, as described in Campaign literature.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Accountings. The Secretary of State or the operating agency may require from participating agencies an accounting of the programmatic and financial utilization of Campaign funds.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Disqualification. The Secretary of State may delete from the list of approved participating agencies those charitable organizations which fail to establish and maintain compliance with the provisions of this Executive Order and with the criteria, instructions and procedures of the Secretary of State.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="1984-04-13">Effective date: April 13, 1984 (11:9 Md. R. 785)</annotation>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="1985-03-26">Sections 3 and 4 amended effective March 26, 1985 (12:8 Md. R. 795)</annotation>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="1996-02-26">Amended effective February 21, 1992 (19:6 Md. R. 652); January 11, 1993 (20:3 Md. R. 210); February 26, 1996 (23:6 Md. R. 422)</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Procedures for Labor-Management Relations in the Executive Branch of State Government</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in paragraph B., this Executive Order applies to all employees of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The principal departments within the Executive Branch;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Maryland Insurance Administration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The State Department of Assessments and Taxation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The State Lottery Agency.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This Executive Order does not apply to employees of the Mass Transit Administration, as that term is defined in ยง7-601(a)(2) of the Transportation Article.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Employees of the Executive Branch shall have the right to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Organize, form, join or assist any employee organization;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Bargain collectively through representatives of their own choosing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Engage in other concerted activities for the purpose of collective bargaining or other mutual aid or protection insofar as any such activity is not prohibited by any other law of the State of Maryland or this Executive Order.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The mediation unit of the Department of Labor, Licensing, and Regulation shall be designated by the Governor to administer this Order and shall have the power, to the fullest extent permitted by law, to do the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Hold hearings and conduct elections;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Make determinations regarding certification and decertification of exclusive bargaining representatives;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Resolve other issues that may arise under this Order; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Promulgate such guidelines and establish such procedures as may be necessary for the proper implementation of this Order.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The following terms shall have the meanings indicated:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Collective bargaining," to "bargain collectively," or to "negotiate" mean the mutual obligation of the employer and the employee exclusive bargaining organization to negotiate in good faith at reasonable times and places with respect to wages, hours, and other terms and conditions of employment. The parties, upon the completion of negotiations, shall execute a written memorandum of understanding incorporating the terms of any agreement reached, and, to the extent they require legislative approval or the appropriation of funds, such terms shall be recommended to the Legislature for approval or the appropriation of funds, as may be necessary. The duty to bargain shall include the obligation to negotiate in good faith for the purpose of resolving any questions arising under an existing memorandum of understanding. Notwithstanding the foregoing, the employer shall not be required to negotiate with regard to any matter that would be inconsistent with applicable law, and the employer may negotiate and reach agreement with regard to any such matter only if it is understood that the agreement with respect to such matter cannot become effective unless the applicable law is amended to eliminate any such inconsistency.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Employee" means an individual employed by the Executive Branch, unless the individual is any of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A student employee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A temporary employee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A member of a board or commission;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A confidential employee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>A managerial employee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>A supervisory employee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>An individual in the custody of the Department of Public Safety and Correctional Services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>The chief administrative or executive officer of an agency.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Confidential employee" means an employee:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Who has access to confidential or discretionary information regarding the formulation of policy or procedures;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Whose functional responsibilities or knowledge concerning employee relations makes the employee's membership in an employee organization incompatible with the employee's duties; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Who is the personal secretary of the chief administrative or executive officer of an agency.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Managerial employee" means an individual who is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Engaged predominantly in executive and management functions; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Charged with the responsibility of directing the effectuation of management policies and practices.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Professional employee" means an employee engaged in work:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Predominantly intellectual and varied in character;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Involving the consistent exercise of discretion and judgement in its performance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Of such character that the result accomplished cannot be standardized in relation to a given period of time; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Requiring knowledge of an advanced type in a field of science or learning customarily acquired by a prolonged course of specialized intellectual instruction in an institution of higher learning or a hospital.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Supervisor" means an individual having authority in the interest of the Executive Branch to hire, transfer, suspend, lay off, recall, promote, discharge other employees, or effectively to recommend such action, if, in connection with the foregoing, the exercise of such authority is not of a merely routine or clerical nature but requires the use of independent judgement.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Temporary employee" means an individual who is employed in a temporary position for not more than 90 days.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Employee organization" means an organization in which employees participate and which exists for the purpose, in whole or in part, of dealing with employers concerning grievances, labor disputes, wages, hours, and other terms and conditions of employment of such employees.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Employee exclusive bargaining representative" and "exclusive bargaining representative" mean an organization certified as the exclusive bargaining representative pursuant to the provisions of this Order.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Appropriate bargaining unit" means one of the following units:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Labor and trades;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Administrative, technical, and clerical;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Regulatory, inspection, and licensure;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Health and human service nonprofessionals;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Health care professionals;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Social and human service professionals;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Engineering, scientific, and administrative professionals;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Public safety and security; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Sworn police officers.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Secretary of Personnel, or such other official or officials as may be designated by the Governor for this purpose, shall determine the assignment of each employee to an appropriate unit, based on the employee's job classification and position. In determining the appropriateness of the assignment of an employee to an appropriate unit, the following factors shall be considered:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The principles of efficient administration of government, including limiting the fragmentation of government administrative authority;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The existence of a community of interest among the employees assigned to the bargaining unit;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The recommendations of the parties involved.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The official or officials designated by the Governor to administer this Order may certify an employee organization as the exclusive bargaining representative of the members in an appropriate bargaining unit when the employee organization has been selected by a majority of those voting in a representation election conducted among the employees in the unit. Such official or officials shall have the authority to resolve any objections to the conduct of any representation election held pursuant to this Order; provided, that in any election involving more than one employee organization, such organizations can agree, subject to the approval of such officials, that disputes regarding specified issues will be resolved by an impartial third party arbitrator selected in accordance with such agreement, and the decision or decisions of such arbitrator shall be final and binding on such organizations; and provided further, that any such agreement shall provide that the costs of the arbitrator shall be shared equally by the employee organizations involved.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>An employee organization may petition for certification by submitting a petition for representation to the official or officials designated by the Governor to administer this Order. The petition must be accompanied by a showing of interest supported by 30 percent of the employees in the appropriate unit indicating their desire to be exclusively represented by the petitioner for the purpose of collective bargaining. No petition for certification may be filed prior to August 21, 1996.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Within 5 days of determination that valid petition has been submitted, the official or officials designated by the Governor to administer this Order shall notify interested employee organizations on the pending election petition.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Any interested employee organization that wishes to intervene must submit a petition of intervention which must be accompanied by a showing of interest supported by 10 percent of the employees in the appropriate bargaining unit indicating their desire to be exclusively represented by the intervenor for the purpose of collective bargaining, which petition must be filed within 15 days of notice of the pending election petition.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>An election under this Order shall be held in any unit within 90 days after the filing of a valid petition for election in such unit in accordance with guidelines established by the official or officials designated by the Governor to administer this Order. In any initial representation election conducted pursuant to this Order, the choice of "no representative" shall appear on the ballot. In the event that none of the alternatives listed on the ballot receives a majority of the valid ballots cast in any initial representation election held pursuant to this Order, a run-off election shall be held between the two choices that received the highest number of votes cast in the initial election.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Certification of an employee exclusive bargaining representative shall continue so long as such organization satisfies the criteria of this Order and subsequent guidelines applicable to certification. A petition to decertify an existing exclusive bargaining representative may be filed in the same manner as a petition for certification, as provided in paragraph H. of this Order, except that no decertification petition may be filed for any bargaining unit if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An exclusive bargaining representative for that bargaining unit has been certified within the preceding 2 years; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The bargaining unit has in effect a valid memorandum of understanding that, by its terms, does not exceed 3 years in duration; provided, that the limitation imposed by this paragraph shall not bar the filing of a decertification petition within the 90-day period immediately preceding the expiration of such memorandum of understanding.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>If a decertification petition is filed, the existing exclusive bargaining representative shall be deemed an intervenor on that petition and will not be required to submit the showing of interest that would otherwise be required by paragraph J. of this Order. Nothing in this paragraph shall require that a representation election be conducted in any unit within 12 months after a valid election with respect to such unit had been held pursuant to the provisions of this Order.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>Certification of an employee exclusive bargaining representative shall not preclude any employee or group of employees, regardless of employee organization membership, from bringing matters of personal concern to the attention of appropriate officials with a representative of his/her own choosing in a grievance proceeding held pursuant to a memorandum of understanding.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>An employee organization certified as the exclusive bargaining representative of employees of an appropriate bargaining unit shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Entitled to speak on behalf of all employees in the unit and shall be responsible for representing the interests of all such employees without discrimination and without regard to employee organization membership;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Exclusively permitted to have organizational membership dues collected by payroll deduction upon signed written request of employee conforming to law; except that any other organization that qualifies for payroll deduction of dues pursuant to ยง6-402 of the State Personnel Article of the Annotated Code of Maryland shall continue to be eligible to receive payroll deduction of dues for as long as it remains so qualified; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Entitled to meet and negotiate with the Governor or the Governor's designee on wages, hours, and working conditions in an effort to reach an agreement subject to the approval of the Governor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>P.</num>
      <text>Managerial and supervisory employees are directed to refrain, to the fullest extent permitted by law, from:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Interfering with, restraining, or coercing Executive Branch employees in the exercise of rights granted by this Order;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Interfering with, restraining, or coercing an Executive Branch employee with respect to selecting a representative for purposes of negotiating collectively or the adjustment of grievances;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Refusing to bargain collectively with the employee exclusive bargaining representative as required in this Order; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Refusing to negotiate in good faith or to execute or implement any memorandum of understanding negotiated pursuant to this Order.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>Q.</num>
      <text>It shall be a violation of this Order for any employee organization which has been certified as the exclusive representative of employees under this Order to engage in a strike or work stoppage against the State of Maryland. An employee organization shall forfeit its status as the exclusive representative of employees under this Order if the organization engages in a strike or work stoppage against the State of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>R.</num>
      <text>This Order may be revoked or amended by the Governor at any time.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>S.</num>
      <text>The provisions of this Order shall in no way diminish or infringe any rights, responsibilities, power or duties conferred by <cite doc="Md. Const.">the Constitution of the State of Maryland</cite> and the Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>T.</num>
      <text>In the event that a challenge to any provision of this Order results in a judicial determination that such provision is contrary to law, such provision shall be deemed separable from all other provisions of this Order.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="1996-05-24">Effective date: May 24, 1996 (23:13 Md. R. 923)</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</container>
