<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Executive Orders</prefix>
  <num>1998</num>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Smart Growth and Neighborhood Conservation Policy</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Purpose. This Executive Order establishes the Smart Growth and Neighborhood Conservation Policy, as defined in this Executive Order and effectuates the State Economic Growth, and Resource Protection and Planning Policy mandated and adopted by the General Assembly in 1992 (Chapter 437 of the Acts of 1992).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Smart Growth and Neighborhood Conservation Policy. The Policy provides that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>State agencies give priority to central business districts, downtown cores, empowerment zones and revitalization areas when funding infrastructure projects or locating new facilities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>State agencies review, evaluate and coordinate programs, services and activities in Priority Funding Areas to enhance and support community revitalization;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>State agencies work with local jurisdictions to ensure that programs and activities in rural areas will sustain the character of villages in the area;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>State agencies encourage locating workshops, conferences and other meetings in Priority Funding Areas and support available businesses in these areas when planning such activities; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>State agencies encourage federal agencies to adopt flexible regulations and standards which are more responsive to State and local policies and can be used to support the Smart Growth policies.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Scope and Implementation of the Policy.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All State agencies will implement the Smart Growth and Neighborhood Conservation Policy established in this Executive Order and pursuant to Acts 1 and 2 (Brownfields), Acts 755 and 756 (Job Creation Tax Credit), Acts 757 and 758 (Rural Legacy), and Act 759 (Priority Funding Areas) of the Laws of Maryland 1997.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Policy will apply to all decisions made by an agency when statute or other law confers decision-making discretion to the agency.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>State agencies will continue to implement the State Economic Growth and Resource Protection and Planning Policy.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Smart Growth and Neighborhood Conservation Sub-Cabinet.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>There is a Smart Growth and Neighborhood Conservation Sub-Cabinet. The Sub-Cabinet will consist of the following members:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Secretary of Agriculture;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Secretary of Budget and Management;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Secretary of Business and Economic Development;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Secretary of the Environment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Secretary of General Services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Secretary of Housing and Community Development;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Assistant Secretary of the Office of Neighborhood Revitalization;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Secretary of Natural Resources;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Director of the Office of Planning;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Secretary of Transportation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Special Assistant to the Governor for Smart Growth; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>One Additional Representative of the Governor's Office.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Director of the Maryland Office of Planning will serve as Chairman of the Sub-Cabinet and will schedule meetings. Principal staff support for the Sub-Cabinet will be provided by the Office of Planning.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Sub-Cabinet will:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Assist in the implementation of the Smart Growth Policy and recommend to the Governor changes in State law, regulations and procedures needed to support this Policy;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Provide a forum for discussion of interdepartmental issues relating to activities that affect growth, development, neighborhood conservation and resource management;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Establish a mechanism, using the Maryland Office of Planning Parcel Mapping System, Maryland Property View, for identification and coordination of all State activities and projects within Priority Funding Areas and ensure that all State actions that influence redevelopment and growth are identified and submitted for review during project planning;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Develop procedures to review projects of extraordinary circumstances as defined in §5-7B-05 of the State Finance and Procurement Article prior to submittal before the Board of Public Works;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Work with the Office of Planning and the Department of Transportation to develop a procedure for notification, review and comment in accordance with §5-7B-06 of the State Finance and Procurement Article, which provides for State funding of certain projects not in Priority Funding Areas as exceptions without the approval of the Board of Public Works;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Maintain, and when necessary, review and revise procedures established pursuant to §5-7A-02 of the State Finance and Procurement Article for the review of State projects and agency determinations of project consistency or inconsistency with the 1992 Growth Act; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Work together using all available resources to promote the understanding of the Smart Growth Initiatives.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Procedures for review and coordination of projects and activities in Priority Funding Areas.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Maryland Office of Planning will:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Provide mapping and other technical assistance, as requested, to counties and municipalities when mapping certified Priority Funding Areas;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Help local governments establish an opportunity for public review of proposed Priority Funding Areas prior to certification;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Provide local governments a standard GIS digital protocol for use when developing the map illustrating the precise location of the certified Priority Funding Area;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Consider the capacity of land areas available for growth, including in-fill development and the analysis of the land area needed to satisfy growth needs for development when commenting on Priority Funding areas certified by local governments;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Provide comments to each State agency on Priority Funding Areas certified by local governments and provide State agencies with maps illustrating areas certified by local governments as Priority Funding Areas; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Establish a schedule for annual updates of the maps.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All State agencies will:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Refer to the maps provided by the Office of Planning when making decisions to fund projects proposed in a certified Priority Funding Area;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Prior to funding a growth-related project, obtain from the affected local government a written statement that the proposed growth-related project is located within a Certified Priority Funding Area. When applicable this statement should provide documentation to demonstrate that non-State funding of planned water and sewer is committed and moving forward in advance of, or concurrent with, State funding;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Assist the Office of Planning in conducting surveys of Municipal, County and State Governments infrastructure needs as Provided in §5-7b-09(b) of the State Finance and Procurement Article including information relating to the financial capacity of the affected unit of government to undertake such projects.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>When making funding decisions, State agencies will consider:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Whether the proposed project is located in a Priority Funding Area;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Whether the project will enhance or support other activities targeted by State agencies to a community within a Priority Funding Area, such as the Brownfields-Voluntary Cleanup and Revitalization Incentive Program and tax credits targeted to revitalization areas;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Whether the project is located in a Designated Neighborhood in accord with the requirements of the Neighborhood Business Development Program of the Department of Housing and Community Development;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Whether the project supports existing neighborhoods and communities;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Whether the project will promote the use of mass transit;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Whether the project is consistent with any adjacent jurisdiction's Smart Growth plans;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Whether the project reduces or promotes sprawl; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Other guidelines developed by the Smart Growth and Neighborhood Conservation Sub-Cabinet.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Each agency shall, where appropriate, adopt regulations implementing §5-7A-02 and §5-7B of the State Finance and Procurement Article. Each agency shall identify opportunities to modify existing regulations to carry out the purposes of this policy and the 1992 Growth Act.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>State agencies and the State Clearinghouse for Intergovernmental Review and Coordination Process will, when possible, coordinate review of federal projects in relation to their location in Priority Funding Areas and to encourage compliance with the Federal Executive Order 12072-Federal Space Management, which directs federal agencies to locate facilities in urban areas.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The Office of Planning and the Department of Transportation will adopt procedures for the review of transportation projects as provided in §5-7B-05 of the State Finance and Procurement Article and jointly determine compliance with that section, prior to the submission of a request for funding to the Board of Public Works.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The Department of Business and Economic Development will consider the jurisdiction's comprehensive plan, the location of the site in relation to available sewer and water and other Priority Funding Areas when reviewing applications for a new Enterprise Zone.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Procedures for Annual Reports. The Office of Planning, with the assistance of all affected State agencies, will evaluate and report annually to the Governor, the General Assembly and the State Economic Growth, Resource Protection, and Planning Commission on the implementation of the Smart Growth Policy.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Agencies will provide an annual report to the Office of Planning that should include the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A description of projects/programs and costs of activities located in Priority Funding Areas;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A description of projects/programs and costs of activities funded under the exceptions allowed in §5-7B-06 of the State Finance and Procurement Article;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Projects submitted to the Board of Public Works for funding outside Priority Funding Areas under the extraordinary circumstances exception in accordance with §5-7B-05 of the State Finance and Procurement Article and the impact of these projects upon this policy;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A list of programs and policies reviewed and changed to ensure compliance with the Policy; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>A list of projects or programs approved and funded under §2 of Chapter 759 of the Acts of 1997.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The Smart Growth and Neighborhood Conservation Coordinating Subcommittee. Each State agency will identify a staff person responsible for the implementation of the Smart Growth Policy. This person will be empowered to make policy recommendations and changes to ensure that the Policy is implemented throughout the agency and reflected in all future actions. This person will also serve as a member of the Smart Growth and Neighborhood Conservation Coordinating Subcommittee.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Members will consist of staff designated to participate in this Subcommittee by the Secretaries and Directors of the following agencies:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Maryland Office of Planning;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Housing and Community Development;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Transportation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Environment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>General Services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Aging;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Human Resources;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Crime Control and Prevention;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Office of the Attorney General;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Public School Construction;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Education;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>Health and Mental Hygiene;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>Natural Resources;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(n)</num>
          <text>State Police;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(o)</num>
          <text>Juvenile Justice;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(p)</num>
          <text>Higher Education;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(q)</num>
          <text>Insurance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(r)</num>
          <text>Budget and Management;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(s)</num>
          <text>Military Department;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(t)</num>
          <text>State Police;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(u)</num>
          <text>Labor, Licensing, and Regulation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(v)</num>
          <text>Children, Youth, and Families;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(w)</num>
          <text>Public Safety and Correctional Services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(x)</num>
          <text>Business and Economic Development;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(y)</num>
          <text>Office for Individuals with Disabilities;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(z)</num>
          <text>Forum for Rural Maryland;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(aa)</num>
          <text>Minority Affairs; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(bb)</num>
          <text>Agriculture.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Subcommittee will be chaired by the Office of Planning and will meet at least quarterly. Membership may be revised to include additional units of government or reflect changes in State government.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Subcommittee will be staffed by the Office of Planning.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Subcommittee will:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Develop a list of existing programs, projects and activities that will be used in Priority Funding Areas;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Identify, develop and adopt methods and procedures that will coordinate these programs within targeted communities in Priority Funding Areas; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Undertake tasks as assigned by the Smart Growth and Neighborhood Conservation Sub-Cabinet.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>This Executive Order is not intended to and may not be construed to confer any right, privilege or status on any private party cognizable by a court in any proceeding. No bond, note, debt, leasing, financing arrangement, or other debt obligation of any kind of the State, a State agency or a local jurisdiction may be deemed, held or otherwise considered to be unenforceable due to a failure to comply with the terms of this Executive Order.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="1998-01-23">Effective date: January 23, 1998 (25:4 Md. R. 207)</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>The Governor's Committee on Employment of People With Disabilities (Amended COMAR 01.01.1996.15)</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>There is a Governor's Committee on Employment of People with Disabilities within the Office for Individuals with Disabilities in the Executive Branch of the government.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Governor's Committee on Employment of People with Disabilities is affiliated with the President's Committee on Employment of People with Disabilities located in Washington, D.C.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Staff support for the Governor's Committee on Employment of People with Disabilities shall be provided by the Office for Individuals with Disabilities.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The membership of the Committee shall consist of a total of 36 members including:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>One representative of the Department of Human Resources;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Two representatives of the Department of Budget and Management, including an expert in State personnel issues;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Two representatives of the Maryland State Department of Education, including a representative of the Division of Rehabilitation Services;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>One representative of the Executive Department Office for Individuals with Disabilities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>One representative of the Senate of Maryland;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>One representative of the Maryland House of Delegates;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>One representative of the Maryland Department of Transportation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>One representative of the Department of Labor, Licensing, and Regulation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>One representative of the Department of Health and Mental Hygiene;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>One representative of the Department of Housing and Community Development;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>One representative of the Maryland Human Relations Commission;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>One representative of the Maryland Department of Business and Economic Development;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Members appointed by the Governor to represent business and industry, labor, consumers, consumer advocacy groups, private agencies with disabled client populations, the news media, fraternal and religious groups, the medical community and others within the community interested in the goals and objectives of the Committee; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>At least 14 members of the Committee must be individuals with disabilities.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Members appointed by the Governor shall serve 3-year staggered terms. A member may not serve consecutively more than 2 three-year terms. All other members shall serve so long as they continue to hold agency representation as provided under §D(1) through (12) of this Executive Order.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Governor shall designate a Chairperson who shall serve at the pleasure of the Governor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The Chairpersons of the County Committees on Employment of People with Disabilities shall be entitled to ex-officio membership on the Committee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>All members are subject to Article 41, §1-203 of the Maryland Annotated Code which contains provisions governing attendance at meetings.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>The purpose and objectives of this Committee shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To promote meaningful employment opportunities for qualified individuals with mental, physical, and emotional disabilities as defined by the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 as amended;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>To promote a climate of public awareness and understanding of both the barriers to employment faced by people with disabilities and the laws ensuring equal opportunity to this employment; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>To promote a better understanding among people with disabilities of opportunities available for habilitation and rehabilitation in order that more and more will have marketable job skills.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>The functions of the Committee shall be to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Plan and carry out year-round education programs designed to promote a climate of public awareness and understanding of the attitudinal, architectural, educational, housing, transportation, and other barriers to employment and life quality faced by people with disabilities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Stimulate state and local community interest by securing the active cooperation and participation of such "public" entities as business and industry, labor, government, educators, public and private agencies serving people with disabilities, consumers, consumer advocates and civic organizations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Plan and carry out/or participate in special events and programs designed to highlight abilities of qualified people with disabilities and programs to facilitate employment of such persons;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Encourage and facilitate the development and functioning of local committees on employment of people with disabilities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Coordinate with and participate in activities of other public and private agencies; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Cooperate with the President's Committee on Employment of People with Disabilities in programs and activities initiated at the national level.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>The Governor's Committee on Employment of People with Disabilities shall promulgate and adopt a set of By-Laws and operating procedures that are consistent with the intent of this Executive Order and these By-Laws shall be on file in the Governor's Appointment Office.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="1979-11-20">Effective date: November 20, 1979 (6:25 Md. R. 1967)</annotation>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="1998-02-10">Amended effective July 31, 1980 (7:17 Md. R. 1659); December 26, 1983 (11:2 Md. R . 104); October 20, 1989 (13:23 Md. R . 2468); March 11, 1987 (14:8 Md. R. 920); August 9, 1989 (16:18 Md. R. 1990); June 28, 1996 (23:15 Md. R. 1073); February 10, 1998 (25:6 Md. R. 390)</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Debt Issued by State Entities (Rescinded COMAR 01.01.1989.13)</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definitions. In this Executive Order the following words have the meanings indicated:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Board" means the Board of Public Works;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Department" means the Department of Budget and Management;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Secretary" means the Secretary of the Department of Budget and Management;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"State entity" means any agency or instrumentality of the State other than the Board of Public Works;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Debt" means a bond, note, bond anticipation note, capital lease, or any other evidence of indebtedness; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Transaction" means the issuance of debt.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Duties of the Department of Budget and Management. The Department is assigned the responsibility for monitoring levels of debt of certain State entities. Specifically, the Department shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Recommend to the Governor the level of annual debt issuances for certain State entities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Report annually on the levels of debt issued and outstanding by certain State agencies;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Serve as the coordinating agency for issuances of debt by State agencies and instrumentalities; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Arrange for centralized procurement, when appropriate.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Issuance Amounts.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>After consultation with the State entities, each year the Department shall recommend to the Governor for the next fiscal year the amount of debt, net of refunding debt, that may be issued by each of the following entities:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Maryland Environmental Service;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Maryland Food Center Authority;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Maryland Transportation Authority; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Maryland Water Quality Financing Administration.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>On or before March 15 of each year, the Department shall notify the affected State entities and the Board of the amounts as set by the Governor for the next fiscal year and shall cause the amounts to be published in the Maryland Register.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>During the fiscal year, the Governor may increase or decrease the amounts by notice to the Department. The Department shall notify the affected State entity and the Board of any change and shall cause such changes to be published in the Maryland Register.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If a State entity does not issue all of its approved amounts during the fiscal year, such unused portion may not be used in any succeeding fiscal year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Secretary may add other State entities that issue non-tax supported debt not otherwise limited by law to those listed in §C(1) of this Executive Order.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Reporting Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>No later than October 1 of each year, each State entity that issues debt not otherwise limited in amount by State law shall report to the Department for the previous fiscal year:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>For each transaction, the title, amount, and other information required by the Department; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The amount of debt outstanding at the beginning of the fiscal year, issued during the fiscal year, redeemed, refunded, or otherwise retired during the fiscal year, and outstanding at the end of the fiscal year.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>By November 1, the Department shall report to the General Assembly, subject to the provisions of §2-1312 of the State Government Article, and to the Board on the transactions, the level of outstanding debt, and the levels of debt issued and redeemed in the preceding fiscal year.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Notification. Any State entity planning a transaction of $25,000,000 or greater principal amount shall provide notice to the Department at least 30 days prior to the transaction. The notice may take the form of a preliminary official statement, if available. If no such statement is available, the notice shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The purpose of the transaction;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The proposed sale date;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The nature of the transaction;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The proposed principal amount of the transaction; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Any other information which the Department may request.</text>
        <text>This notice shall be in addition to any notice required under other provisions of law or regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Financial Services and Technical Assistance.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Upon recommendation of the Governor, the Board may delegate to the Treasurer procurement of any financial services and technical assistance required in connection with the issuance of debt, but the fees for such services shall be paid from the proceeds of the transaction or other funds as provided.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>At the request of the Governor, the Treasurer may issue debt on behalf of a State entity.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Compliance with Executive Order.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Secretary may waive or extend any deadlines for action under this Executive Order, other than any action to be taken by the Governor. Any waiver or extension shall be in writing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>At the request of any State entity, the Secretary shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Certify the amount of debt that may be issued by such State entity as of the date of such certification; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Certify compliance with §E of this Executive Order.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="1998-02-10">Effective date: February 10, 1998 (25:6 Md. R. 391)</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.25</num>
    <heading>Domestic Violence and the Workplace</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>That each department and agency of the State of Maryland shall within the next year adopt policies and procedures which:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Clearly direct that State agencies will not tolerate domestic violence;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Instruct employees on how to offer assistance to domestic violence victims in an expedient, meaningful and confidential manner;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Provide for the conspicuous posting of information about domestic violence and available resources;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Provide for domestic violence awareness training for employees; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Prohibit unfair treatment of employees by the employers based solely on their status as victims of domestic violence.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The provisions of this Executive Order are not intended to alter any existing collective bargaining agreements or to supersede applicable federal or State law.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="1998-10-01">Effective date: October 1, 1998 (25:23 Md. R. 1684</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</container>
