<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Executive Orders</prefix>
  <num>2001</num>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Sustaining Maryland's Future with Clean Power, Green Buildings and Energy Efficiency</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Clean Energy Procurement Goal.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For purposes of this Executive Order, "Green Energy" is defined as energy generated from the wind, solar photovoltaic, solar thermal, biomass, landfill gas and the combustion of municipal solid waste.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For the procurement of electricity for use within State owned facilities, the State of Maryland has a goal of 6% to be generated from Green Energy. No more than 50% of the total Green Energy procurement shall be derived from the combustion of municipal solid waste.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>In the selection of a power generation contractor chosen through the procurement process, priority consideration should be given to companies that produce green power in Maryland. The chosen contractor shall obtain certification from a State approved accreditation process that the company has met the Green Energy goal.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>High Efficiency Green Buildings Program.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The State shall develop a High Efficiency Green Buildings Program committed to utilizing energy efficient and environmentally responsible approaches in the design, construction, operations, maintenance and deconstruction of all new and, to the extent possible, existing State owned and leased facilities.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>There is a "Maryland Green Buildings Council" (the Council). The Council shall be Chaired by the Secretary of the Department of General Services and include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Secretary, or a designee of the following agencies:</text>
          <para>
            <num>i.</num>
            <text>The Department of Budget and Management;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>ii.</num>
            <text>The Department of the Environment;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>iii.</num>
            <text>The Department of Natural Resources;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>iv.</num>
            <text>The Department of Public Safety and Correctional Services;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>v.</num>
            <text>The Department of Transportation;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>vi.</num>
            <text>The Department of Housing and Community Development;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>vii.</num>
            <text>The Department of Planning;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>viii.</num>
            <text>The Maryland Energy Administration;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>ix.</num>
            <text>The Public School Construction Program; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>x.</num>
            <text>The University System of Maryland.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Six members appointed by the Governor to represent environmental, business and citizen interests, one of whom has expertise in energy conservation and/or production. Members appointed by the Governor shall serve at his pleasure for renewable and staggered 4-year terms.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Members appointed by the Governor may not receive compensation, but may receive reimbursement for necessary and proper expenses directly related to their duties on the Council, in accordance with the Standard State Travel Regulations as provided in the State budget.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Staff support to the Council shall be provided by the Department of General Services, with assistance as necessary to be furnished by other involved agencies and units of State government.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Council is charged with creating the High Efficiency Green Buildings Program. Within 180 days of its inception, the Council shall make recommendations to the Governor regarding appropriate criteria, standards and a numeric rating system (modeled after the United States Green Building Council's Leadership in Energy and Environmental Design (LEED) Green Building Rating System and the federal Energy Star Program) for use by the Program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Upon acceptance of the appropriate criteria, standards, and a numeric rating system, the High Efficiency Green Buildings Program shall be fully adopted in the design, construction, operations, maintenance and deconstruction of new State owned and leased facilities. Reasonable effort should be made to incorporate these standards into the construction of all new facilities designed before the issuance of this executive order.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>For all existing State owned, leased and operated buildings, reasonable efforts shall be made to maximize the use of energy efficiency and resource conservation techniques.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The Council shall also have the following additional responsibilities:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Council shall annually reevaluate the Clean Energy Procurement Goal contained in Section A above;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Council shall consider additional State energy efficiency, energy production and sustainability issues and policies;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Council shall develop a comprehensive set of initiatives known as the "Maryland Greenhouse Gas Reduction Action Plan;" and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Council shall report annually to the Governor and to the General Assembly on the efforts of State agencies in the implementation of High Efficiency Green Buildings Program goals, Clean Energy Procurement Goal, the Greenhouse Gas Reduction Plan, and other energy efficiency, energy production and sustainability issues or policies the Council may have considered.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Additional Energy Efficiency Goals.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Energy Efficiency Improvement Goal: The State, through cost-effective energy measures, shall reduce energy consumption per gross square foot of its facilities by 10% by 2005 and 15% by 2010 relative to 2000 baseline.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Renewable Energy Project Goal: The State shall expand the use of renewable energy within its facilities, including supporting the federal Million Solar Roofs program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Efficient Product Purchase Goal: The State shall purchase Energy Star products when purchasing energy-using products, including computers, printers, copiers and other office equipment, or shall purchase products in the top 25% in energy efficiency for products where labels are not available.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Pollution Prevention Goal: Beginning on January 1, 2003, State agencies shall annually divert or recycle at least 20% of the waste they generate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Alternative Fuel Vehicles Goal: Consistent with the goals of the Chesapeake 2000 Agreement, the State shall revise fleet policy and purchasing guidelines to offer more flexibility in purchasing, where practical, low emission and alternative fuel vehicles for its fleet. The State shall ensure that for fleet units operating bi-fuel or flex-fuel vehicles (vehicles that operate on either motor gasoline or an alternative fuel, as defined by the Federal Energy Policy Act) an average of 50% of the fuel used by those vehicles shall be alternative fuel. The State shall help develop the refueling and maintenance infrastructure required to make certain types of alternative fuel vehicles practical and may provide technical assistance and other incentives to use clean technology, where practical, in State transit fleets.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2001-03-13">Effective date: March 13, 2001 (28:7 Md. R. 675)</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Water Conservation by State Agencies</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Water Conservation Goal.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>State agencies, through water conservation measures, shall reduce water consumption by at least seven percent (7%) by the year 2003, at least eight percent (8%) by the year 2005, at least nine percent (9%) by the year 2007, and at least ten percent (10%) by the year 2010, relative to baseline water use in the year 2000.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For the purposes of this Executive Order, water conservation measures will apply to facilities owned, leased or managed by any State agency. This Executive Order does not apply to water production and supply functions.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Water Use Audit.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A water use audit, which is a measurement and accounting of the amount of water conveyed through the water distribution system to water users, shall be conducted annually at all State owned or leased facilities by the State agency responsible for the lease or maintenance of the facility. Additionally, the audit will inventory all water fixtures and other water use devices to determine which are inefficient and the results shall be reported to the Maryland Department of the Environment (MDE) by July 1, 2001.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>During the water use audit, the State agency shall also identify any water conservation measures for immediate implementation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Water Conservation Plan.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each State agency responsible for the lease or maintenance of a facility shall immediately designate a water conservation coordinator who is responsible for the annual development and implementation of the agency's water use audit and water conservation plan. An agency coordinator may further designate coordinators for each facility, who will ensure that all aspects of the plan are appropriately implemented. Each responsible State agency will complete and submit to MDE a water conservation plan by October 1, 2001. A water conservation plan shall include the following fundamental elements and explain how each element is to be implemented:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An annual water audit: The use of flow meters or other methods to routinely account for water use shall be used to demonstrate that the water use reduction goals are achieved and that inefficient water fixtures and water use devices are being eliminated; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Identify and select specific water conservation measures that need to be employed to improve water management and water use efficiency to achieve the water conservation goal of this Executive Order.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Additionally, each responsible State agency shall address the following measures in its water conservation plan:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The purchase of water-efficient plumbing fixtures, appliances and other products when new or replacement products are needed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The timely detection and repair of leaks in distribution lines and plumbing fixtures;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Wastewater reclamation and recycling of water for nonpotable applications;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Management of system pressure so as to reduce usage;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Retrofit programs and fixture replacement; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Installation of efficient landscape design and irrigation techniques.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All leases, beginning in FY02, by any State agency shall include water conservation measures as a term of the lease.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Water Conservation Education.</text>
      <text>In support of the goal to reduce water consumption, all agencies will conduct an information and education program for both public and staff users designed to promote increased efficiency of water use at State facilities to be completed on or before December 1, 2001. The information and education program shall use visual displays, distribution of written material, dissemination of information through existing employee communications and other appropriate mans to raise employee and citizen user awareness of the importance of water conservation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Water Conservation Reporting.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>On December 1, 2001, and every year thereafter, each responsible State agency shall report to the Maryland Green Buildings Council and MDE in a format provided by the Department on measures taken to reduce water use at each of its State-owned and State-leased facilities. The reports should include results from the water use audit and steps outlined in the water conservation plan.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The agency reports shall be reviewed to ensure that the most appropriate water conservation measures are implemented. The Green Buildings Council, in consultation with MDE, shall determine and approve appropriate water conservation measures. The Green Buildings Council, in consultation with MDE, will annually reevaluate the water conservation goal contained in Section A above, and may waive water conservation requirements where an agency is able to demonstrate that water conservation has been optimized and further reductions are not structurally feasible.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Each year the Maryland Green Buildings Council and MDE shall submit a report to the Governor regarding the effectiveness of State agencies' water conservation measures in meeting the overall water use reduction goals.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2001-05-17">Effective date: May 17, 2001 (28:12 Md. R. 1099)</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.18</num>
    <heading>Maryland State Rehabilitation Council (Amends Executive Order 01.01.1993.25)</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>There is a Maryland State Rehabilitation Council, hereafter referred to as the Council.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Membership and Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The membership of the Council shall be appointed by the Governor after soliciting recommendations from representatives of organizations representing a broad range of individuals with disabilities and organizations interested in individuals with disabilities, and shall include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>At least one representative of the Statewide Independent Living Council, who may be the chairperson or other designee of the Council;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>At least one representative of a parent training and information center;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>At least one representative of the client assistance program established under section 112 of the Rehabilitation Act, as amended;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>At least one vocational rehabilitation counselor with knowledge of and experience with vocational rehabilitation programs, who shall serve as an ex officio, nonvoting member of the Council if the counselor is an employee of the Division of Rehabilitation Services (DORS);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>At least one representative of a community rehabilitation program service provider;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Four representatives of business, industry, and labor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Representatives of disability advocacy groups representing a cross section of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Individuals with physical, cognitive, sensory, and mental disabilities; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Parents, family members, guardians, advocates, or authorized representatives of individuals with disabilities who have difficulty in representing themselves or are unable due to their disabilities to represent themselves;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Current or former applicants for, or recipients of, vocational rehabilitation services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>The Director of DORS, who shall be an ex officio member of the Council;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>At least one representative of the Maryland State Department of Education, Division of Special Education/Early Intervention Services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>At least one representative of the Governor's Work Force Investment Board; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>Any additional representatives required under Title I of the Rehabilitation Act, as amended.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>To the extent practicable, the Governor shall also consider the extent to which minority populations are represented on the Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A majority of the Council members shall be individuals with disabilities and not employed by DORS.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Council shall select a chairperson from among the membership of the Council.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Appointments to the Council.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Governor will appoint members to the Council for terms of three years with such terms staggered upon initial appointment so that one-third of the Council will be appointed each year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>No member of the Council, other than a representative of the Client Assistance Program, may serve more than two consecutive full terms except that a member appointed to fill a vacancy occurring prior to the expiration of the term for which a predecessor was appointed shall be appointed for the remainder of such term.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A majority of the Council shall constitute a quorum for the transaction of business. The Council may adopt other rules or procedures necessary to ensure the orderly conduct of business.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Any vacancy occurring in the membership of the Council shall be filled in the same manner as the original appointment. The vacancy shall not affect the power of the remaining members to execute the duties of the Council.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Functions of the Council. The Council shall, after consulting with the Governor's Work Force Investment Board:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Review, analyze, and advise DORS regarding the performance of the responsibilities of DORS, particularly related to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Eligibility (including order of selection);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The extent, scope and effectiveness of services provided; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Functions performed by DORS that affect or that potentially affect the ability of individuals with disabilities in achieving rehabilitation goals and objectives under the Rehabilitation Act, as amended.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In partnership with DORS:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Develop, agree to and review State goals and priorities; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Evaluate the effectiveness of the Vocational Rehabilitation Program and submit reports of progress to the Commissioner of the Federal Rehabilitation Services Administration.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Advise DORS regarding activities authorized to be carried out under Title I of the Rehabilitation Act, as amended, and assist in the preparation of applications, the State plan and amendments to the plan, reports, needs assessments, and evaluations required by this Title;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>To the extent feasible, conduct a review and analysis of the effectiveness of, and consumer satisfaction with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The functions performed by DORS;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Vocational rehabilitation services provided by State agencies and other public and private entities responsible for providing vocational rehabilitation services to individuals with disabilities under the Rehabilitation Act, as amended; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Employment outcomes achieved by eligible individuals receiving vocational rehabilitation services, including the availability of health and other employment benefits in connection with such employment outcomes.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Prepare and submit an annual report to the Governor and the Commissioner of the Federal Rehabilitation Services Administration on the status of vocational rehabilitation programs operated within the State, and make the report available to the public;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Coordinate with other councils within the State, including the Statewide Independent Living Council established under section 705 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973, as amended; the State Special Education Advisory Council established under section 613(a)(12) of the Individuals with Disabilities Education Act (20 U.S.C. 1413(a)(12), the State Developmental Disabilities Council, the State mental health planning council established under section 1916(e) of the Public Health Service Act, and the Governor's Work Force Investment Board;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Advise DORS and provide for coordination and the establishment of working relationships between DORS and the Statewide Independent Living Council and centers for independent living within the State;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Perform such other functions consistent with the purpose of the Council and that are comparable to the other functions performed by the Council;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Perform such other functions as required under Title I of the Rehabilitation Act, as amended; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Prepare, in conjunction with DORS, a plan for the provision of such resources including such staff and other personnel as may be necessary to carry out the functions of the council as outlined in this Executive Order.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Resources.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Supervision and Evaluation. The Council shall, consistent with State personnel laws, supervise and evaluate such staff and other personnel as may be necessary to carry out its functions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Personnel Conflict of Interest. While assisting the Council in carrying out its duties, staff and other personnel shall not be assigned duties by DORS or any other agency or office of the state, that would create a conflict of interest.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Resolution of Disagreements. To the extent that there is a disagreement between the Council and DORS in regard to the resources necessary to carry out the functions of the Council, the disagreement shall be resolved by the Governor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Compensation and Expenses. The Council may use funds to reimburse members of the Council for reasonable and necessary expenses of attending Council meetings and performing Council duties (including child care and personal assistance services), and to pay compensation to a member of the Council, if such member is not employed or must forfeit wages from other employment, for each day the member is engaged in performing the duties of the Council.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Meetings of the Council. The Council shall convene at least four meetings a year in such places as it determines to be necessary to conduct Council business and conduct such forums or hearings as the Council considers appropriate. The meetings, hearings, and forums shall be publicly announced. The meetings shall be open and accessible to the general public unless there is a valid reason for an executive session.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Members serve at the pleasure of the Governor and may be removed for any reason adversely affecting the member's performance or the business of the Council. Members who fail to attend 50 percent of the regular meetings of the Council within a 12-month period shall be considered to have resigned.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Conflict of Interest. No member of the Council shall cast a vote on any matter that would provide direct financial benefit to the member or otherwise give the appearance of a conflict of interest under State law.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="1993-10-01">Effective date: October 1, 1993 (20:22 Md. R. 1703)</annotation>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2001-10-03">Amended effective October 3, 2001 (28:22 Md. R. 1925)</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.22</num>
    <heading>Stormwater Management on State Lands</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>All State agencies shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Establish an Institution/Agency Management Plan in accordance with the "Maryland Stormwater Management Guidelines for State and Federal Projects," issued by the Maryland Department of the Environment, July 1, 2001.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Identify existing developed State owned lands (e.g., all pervious and impervious surfaces) by December 31, 2002.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Identify the stormwater retrofit potential of these lands by December 31, 2003.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Implement the Institution/Agency Management Plan which includes retrofitting existing impervious surfaces with a goal of a 25% reduction in effective imperviousness by 2010.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2001-11-28">Effective date: November 28, 2001 (28:26 Md. R. 2264)</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</container>
