<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Executive Orders</prefix>
  <num>2002</num>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.19</num>
    <heading>Interstate Compact for Adult Offender Supervision</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>State Compact Administrator. The Director of the Division of Parole and Probation of the Maryland Department of Public Safety and Correctional Services shall be the Compact Administrator for Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>State Council.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Establishment. There is a Maryland State Council for Interstate Adult Offender Supervision.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Membership. The State Council is comprised of the following members to be supplemented by others that are deemed necessary by the Board:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Compact Administrator;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of the Department of Public Safety and Correctional Services or a designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A representative of the Senate of Maryland, appointed by the President of the Senate;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A representative of the House of Delegates, appointed by the Speaker of the House;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>A representative of the Judiciary, appointed by the Chief Judge of the Maryland Court of Appeals; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Such other members appointed by the Governor to provide representation from the law enforcement community, prosecutors, the public and private bar, victims' organizations and other interested groups.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Duties. The Maryland State Council for Interstate Adult Offender Supervision shall have the duties prescribed to it under the Maryland Annotated Code, Correctional Services Article, Section 6-205, including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Appointing the State Compact Administrator as the Commissioner to the National Interstate Commission;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Overseeing and advocating the participation of the State Council in the National Interstate Commission; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Developing policy concerning operations and procedures of the Interstate Compact for Adult Offender Supervision within the State.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Reports. The State Council shall provide an annual report to the Governor each December 31 concerning its activities.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2002-09-05">Effective date: September 5, 2002 (29:20 Md. R. 1570)</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</container>
