<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Executive Orders</prefix>
  <num>2004</num>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.21</num>
    <heading>Enhanced Forestry Management on the Department of Natural Resources-Owned Forest Lands</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Department of Natural Resources shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Undertake efforts to develop, upgrade and/or modify forest stewardship plans on all DNR-owned lands consistent with and responsive to scientifically based land use conservation goals attendant to watershed, wildlife, fish, biodiversity, recreation, wood fiber, and wilderness enhancement; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Confer with the Forest Stewardship Council and the Sustainable Forestry Initiative Board in order to determine the parameters of securing forest certification of the State's efforts in managing Maryland's State Forests in an environmentally responsible manner.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Department of Natural Resources shall submit its findings and recommendations and an action plan consistent with this effort to the Governor by June 1 of each year and report progress to the Governor on an ongoing basis as determined appropriate by the Department.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2004-03-29">Effective date: March 29, 2004 (31:9 Md. R. 693)</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.28</num>
    <heading>Terrorism Protection—Law Enforcement Services—Expanded Jurisdiction for Maryland Transportation Authority Police</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The primary responsibility for the provision of law enforcement services by the Maryland Transportation Authority Police shall remain the properties owned, operated by, or under the control of the Maryland Transportation Authority, the Maryland Aviation Administration, and the Maryland Port Administration as provided by Section 4-208(e) of the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr">Transportation Article of the Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Maryland Transportation Authority Police, while on duty, under the authority of the Chief of the Transportation Authority Police, shall, pursuant to Section 4-208(b)(4)(iii) of the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr">Transportation Article of the Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and by this Executive Order, have all the powers granted to a peace officer and a police officer of this State as provided by law, henceforth with expanded jurisdiction and authority to protect its facilities and areas of primary jurisdiction and to enhance the protection and safety of all publicly owned, commercial, and/or common carrier transportation assets throughout the State. The Maryland Transportation Authority shall adopt policies and procedures to implement the provisions of this Executive Order and to ensure the safe, efficient, and cooperative provision of law enforcement services in instances in which the expanded jurisdiction and authority is exercised in this State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>No provision of this Executive Order is intended to compromise or limit any of the powers, protections or immunities otherwise granted by law to Maryland Transportation Authority police or other law enforcement agencies of the State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>This Executive Order is effective upon signature and shall continue in effect unless and until amended, modified, terminated, or rescinded by the Governor, or by operation of law.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2004-05-18">Effective date: May 18, 2004 (31:12 Md. R. 892)</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.61</num>
    <heading>Non-Veteran Spousal Admission to Charlotte Hall Veterans Home</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definition. "Qualifying spouse" means:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The spouse of a veteran who is eligible for admission to Charlotte Hall Veterans Home; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The spouse of a deceased veteran who would otherwise be eligible for admission to Charlotte Hall Veterans Home.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In order to increase the number of applicants who will apply for currently unfilled beds and to provide care in the most home-like setting possible, the Charlotte Hall Veterans Home, which has heretofore only admitted veterans as residents, may also admit qualifying spouses, up to the limit allowed by the United States Department of Veterans Affairs. Qualifying spouses will be admitted under the following conditions:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A qualifying spouse must meet the qualifying admission criteria and produce proof of marriage to an eligible veteran;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A qualifying spouse may not be admitted once the Charlotte Hall Veterans Home's census reaches 90%, unless otherwise determined by the Maryland Veterans Home Commission and Maryland Department of Veterans Affairs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A qualifying spouse is not eligible for a federal Veterans' Affairs per diem provided for veteran residents, nor for the additional State subsidy provided veteran residents in Assisted Living;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The admission of a qualifying spouse must be at no cost to the State of Maryland, except under the State's Medicaid program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A qualifying spouse is to receive the same quality of care, appropriate to his or her needs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A qualifying spouse may remain a resident of Charlotte Hall Veterans Home if the veteran spouse, who is also a resident, either dies or is discharged; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>A qualifying spouse who is discharged for medical reasons may be eligible for readmission, provided an admission application is filed within 60 days of the preceding discharge. A qualifying spouse who is discharged for non-medical reasons may not be eligible for readmission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2004-11-11">Effective date: November 11, 2004 (31:24 Md. R. 1692)</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</container>
