<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Executive Orders</prefix>
  <num>2006</num>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Maryland Child Care Subsidy Coordinating Council</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Established. There is a Maryland Child Care Subsidy Coordinating Council convening on a regular basis for the purpose of developing, evaluating, and coordinating the administration of all State child care subsidy or voucher programs, including the Child Care Subsidy Program (commonly known as the Purchase of Care program) which is within the Maryland State Department of Education.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Membership. The Council shall consist of the following members:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Executive Director of the Governor's Office for Children;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The following representatives from the Maryland State Department of Education:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The State Superintendent of Schools;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The Director of the Office of Child Care;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The Assistant Superintendent for Finance; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>The Chief of the Office of Information Technology.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The following representatives of the Department of Human Resources:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The Secretary of Human Resources;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The Executive Director for Family Investment;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The Chief Financial Officer; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>The Chief Information Officer.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Executive Director of the Governor's Office for Children shall chair the Council and shall be responsible for the oversight, direction, and accountability of the work of the Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Maryland State Department of Education and the Maryland Department of Human Resources shall provide the primary staff support necessary for the completion of the Council's duties.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Council shall consult with other State departments and agencies as needed and as appropriate. All Executive departments and agencies shall cooperate with this Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Appropriate funding for the implementation of this Executive Order shall be apportioned among the existing budgets of affected Executive departments and agencies.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The Council shall meet at least once every calendar quarter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The Chair may establish subcommittees as needed to carry out the work of the Council.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Purpose. The Council shall have the following objectives:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To develop a comprehensive, coordinated, and collaborative approach for the use of State and Federal resources to assist low-income families to secure child care through the Child Care Subsidy Program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>To ensure the State meets all standards and requirements associated with Federal Funds expended on, by, or through the Child Care Subsidy Program, including but not limited to universal engagement and work force participation rates of the Temporary Assistance for Needy Families (TANF) program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>To increase access by low-income families receiving child care subsidies to quality early care and education programs, thereby increasing the probability that their children are entering school ready to learn;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>To promote the ongoing viability of the Child Care Subsidy Program and thereby maintain access to the program for low-income families; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>To ensure that the Child Care Subsidy Program continues to promote the transition of low-income families from public assistance to economic independence.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Duties. The Council shall carry out the following duties and responsibilities in meeting its objectives:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Oversee and govern the development and implementation of policies, procedures, and practices for the operation of the Child Care Subsidy Program pursuant to the stated objectives of the Council;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Oversee and govern the budget and fiscal management for the Child Care Subsidy Program, including establishing budget and funding priorities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Develop a Child Care Subsidy Program three-year improvement plan, which shall set benchmarks, identify resources and funding, and establish timelines for the improvement of the sustainability, accessibility, quality, and accountability of the Child Care Subsidy Program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Perform a comprehensive evaluation to determine the enrollment patterns of young children from the Child Care Subsidy Program clients in other State and local programs; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Perform other duties and responsibilities as assigned by the Governor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Reports. The Council shall report to the Governor by October 1, 2006 and annually thereafter.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2006-02-13">Effective date: February 13, 2006 (33:8 Md. R. 710)</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Maryland Dairy Industry Oversight and Advisory Council</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Established. There is a Maryland Dairy Industry Oversight and Advisory Council.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Membership. The membership of the Advisory Council shall be comprised of the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Voting Members.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Council shall consist of up to 15 voting members with interest and expertise in the dairy industry who are appointed by the Governor.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The members of the Council serve at the pleasure of the Governor for up to 2 consecutive 3-year terms.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>From among the voting members of the Council, the Governor shall designate a Chairperson.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Non-Voting Members. The following may serve in an advisory, non-voting capacity:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>One member of the Senate, appointed by President of the Senate;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>One member of the House of Delegates, appointed by the Speaker of the House;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>One representative of the Department of Agriculture, appointed by the Secretary;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>One representative of the Department of Health and Mental Hygiene, appointed by the Secretary;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>One local health officer who is a member of the Maryland Association of County Health Officers, appointed by the Secretary of Health and Mental Hygiene; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>One representative of the Maryland Cooperative Extension, appointed by the Dean of the University of Maryland College of Agriculture and Natural Resources.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Staffing. The Department of Agriculture and Department of Health and Mental Hygiene shall jointly provide staff support and resources to the Council, with additional assistance from other State agencies as requested.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Council shall meet at least four times annually.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A majority of voting members shall constitute a quorum for the transaction of any business before the Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Chairperson may establish committees and subcommittees and include representatives of interested public and private organizations on committees and subcommittees.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Members of the Council may not receive any compensation for their services. Voting members of the Council may be reimbursed for reasonable expenses incurred in the performance of their duties, in accordance with the Standard State Travel Regulations, and as provided in the State budget.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Duties and Responsibilities.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>General. The Council shall investigate and identify ways to improve the economic viability of the dairy industry in Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Specific. The Council shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Develop strategies for sustaining Maryland's dairy industry;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Evaluate and review the regulatory structure of the dairy industry;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Review and comment on federal and state regulatory changes impacting the dairy industry;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Identify and comment on quality assurance controls in the dairy industry;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Identify barriers to profitability in the dairy industry;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Identify technological changes affecting the dairy industry;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Encourage and facilitate collaboration among the State agencies responsible for regulating the dairy industry; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Perform other duties and responsibilities as assigned by the Governor.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Reporting. The Council shall report to the Governor by October 1 of each year with recommendations to support a coordinated State strategy for the dairy industry.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2006-07-10">Effective date: July 10, 2006 (33:16 Md. R. 1347)</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</container>
