<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Executive Orders</prefix>
  <num>2008</num>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Designation of Agency Representatives for Mid-Contract Negotiations</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>State law establishes a collective bargaining process which results in a written memorandum of understanding. During the time periods between ratified memoranda of understanding, the State maintains the obligation to negotiate changes that will substantially affect the working conditions of bargaining unit employees. Those issues are resolved through mid-contract negotiations pursuant to provisions in the negotiated memoranda of understanding.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Each Secretary or other agency head in the Executive Branch of State Government subject to collective bargaining pursuant to the Annotated Code of Maryland, State Personnel and Pensions Article, Section 3-102, or their respective designees, are hereby authorized in accordance with the Annotated Code of Maryland, State Personnel and Pensions Article, Section 3-501, to participate as parties during mid- contract negotiations regarding agency specific issues with the certified exclusive employee representatives.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Issues that may impact more than one agency and are not specific to an individual department or agency must be submitted to the Executive Director of the Office of Personnel Services and Benefits, Department of Budget and Management (Executive Director) for resolution with the certified exclusive employee representatives.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Any agreement arising from mid-contract negotiations that may result in a cost to the State or require the appropriation of funds is subject to the approval of the Secretary of Budget and Management.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Within 30 days of the effective date of this Order, the Secretaries of the principal departments and the heads of independent agencies in the Executive Branch of State Government shall forward the contact information for their designee, or, if they choose not to delegate this function, their own contact information, to the Executive Director. Within ten days of receiving that information, the Executive Director shall send the designee contact information to the head of any certified exclusive employee organization representing employees of that department or agency.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Designees shall serve as the representative of a principal department or agency for mid-contract negotiations at the pleasure of the Secretary or agency head. Should the Secretary or agency head revoke the designation, or if the designee leaves employment with the agency or department, the Secretary or agency head shall serve as the Department or agency representative until a new designee is identified to the Executive Director.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>This Executive Order is not intended to and will not alter in any way the rights and obligations of the State collective bargaining process as established in State Personnel and Pensions Article, Section 3-501 and Section 3-502.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2008-01-14">Effective date: January 14, 2008 (35:3 Md. R. 251)</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>State Employee Risk Management Administration (Rescinds Executive Order 01.01.2003.51)</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Program Established. There is a State Employee Risk Management Administration (SERMA) established that addresses workplace safety and workers' compensation risk management and loss control throughout Maryland State government. It shall have the following structure:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>SERMA is administered by the Injured Workers' Insurance Fund (IWIF), an independent State agency, as required by the Claims Administration Services Agreement between the Board of Commissioners of the Injured Workers' Insurance Fund and the State Board of Public Works.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>IWIF shall coordinate the administration of the SERMA program with the oversight of the Office of the Governor, and as needed with the State Treasurer as the Claims Administration Services Agreement administrator.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>IWIF shall compile, maintain, and make available as allowed by law all claims information on their Workers' Compensation database to carry out the intent of this Executive Order and provide reporting to support StateStat initiatives.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>IWIF shall house a unit of SERMA Risk Management Consultants, dedicated to the State to provide occupational and safety consultative services as described in Section C.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Responsibilities. Each State department or designated State agency shall, working with SERMA Risk Management Consultants:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Establish and maintain a proactive employee safety and health risk management program that is effective, efficient, and measurable; that has the support and endorsement of the agency head with a policy statement, and written policy and procedure directives that are communicated to all employees.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Maintain the designation or appointment of a Risk Manager to carry out the intent of this Executive Order; with full-time risk managers having a direct reporting relationship to the office of each department's secretary or agency head.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Establish safety and health committees to review agencies' safety and health safety programs, review injury trends and advise the agency leadership on corrective measures needed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Establish annual goals, objectives and performance measures to address work place safety and health, reductions in work place illnesses, accidents, and injuries. Key measurements will be claims frequency, accident frequency, accident leave, cost analysis and reporting time frame to IWIF.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Annually conduct an agency-wide safety and health risk assessment and program evaluation in accordance with guidelines established by the SERMA program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Conduct annual health and safety inspections of all facilities documenting the findings and corrective measures needed. These inspections will evaluate the use of personal protective equipment, preventive maintenance, unsafe work place behaviors, emergency evacuation procedures, and housekeeping issues.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Conduct safety and health training for all employees that is focused and directed towards all known work place health and safety hazards and establish appropriate preventive procedural guidelines to protect the health and safety of employees.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Promote occupational health and safety, within their organization, through the distribution of employee health and safety informational resources such as posters, pay roll stuffers, handouts, and Intra-agency Intranet.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Conduct thorough and complete accident investigations that are timely and contain the highest level of detail possible. All investigations will be fact-driven and contain a root-cause analysis. Maintain all first reports of injuries, investigative reports and documents in accordance with OSHA, MOSHA, and the Maryland Workers' Compensation Act.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Establish and communicate policy and procedures that enable all of its organizational units to be prepared for a variety of predictable and unpredictable emergencies.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Responsibilities of the SERMA program and the SERMA Risk Management Consultants, administered by IWIF are to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Support State department and agency efforts to establish and maintain a proactive employee risk management program that is effective, efficient, and measureable;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide guidelines for implementing a model risk management program in all agencies that are based upon best practices in both the public and private sectors;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Provide technical assistance, program consultation, education and training, and statistical analyses that support State departments and agencies in meeting their responsibilities under the provisions of this Executive Order and achieving their risk management performance goals;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Make recommendations to improve department-specific and agency-specific programs that are not effectively reducing risks and containing workers' compensation costs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Communicate and coordinate as needed with the Maryland State Employee Risk Management Committee; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Provide an annual report (fiscal year basis) to the office of the Governor and the Secretaries of the Maryland State Employee Risk Management Committee agencies.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Risk Management Committee Established. There is a Maryland State Employee Risk Management Committee (Committee).</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Membership. The Committee is comprised of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A representative from IWIF, appointed by its President, who shall serve as Committee Chair;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A representative from the Office of the Governor, appointed by the Governor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The supervisor of the SERMA Risk Management Consultants;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A representative from the Office of the Treasurer;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Department risk managers of the following State Departments as named by the Department Secretaries:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Department of Budget and Management;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Department of the Environment;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Department of General Services;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Department of Health and Mental Hygiene;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Department of Human Resources;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Department of Juvenile Services;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Department of Labor, Licensing and Regulation;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Department of Natural Resources;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ix)</num>
            <text>Department of Public Safety and Correctional Services;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(x)</num>
            <text>Department of Maryland State Police;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xi)</num>
            <text>Department of Transportation;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xii)</num>
            <text>Maryland Transit Administration;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xiii)</num>
            <text>University of Maryland, College Park;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xiv)</num>
            <text>University System of Maryland;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xv)</num>
            <text>Maryland Occupational Safety and Health Administration;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xvi)</num>
            <text>Department of General Services, Real Estate Office; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xvii)</num>
            <text>Any other unit designated by the Governor.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Staffing. IWIF shall provide staffing for the Committee as necessary.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Duties. The Committee shall work in partnership with the SERMA program in IWIF to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Share with other State departments and agencies best practices in the public and private sectors for risk management and loss control;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Identify available resources that would assist State departments and agencies to continuously improve their risk management programs;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Identify workers' compensation issues, and offer recommendations to the Governor's Office;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Recommend initiatives to the Governor's Office that will improve workplace safety and reduce the costs of workers' compensation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Ensure that the SERMA program is responsive to the risk management and loss control needs of State departments and agencies as defined in Section C of this Executive Order;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Plan and conduct the annual statewide State Employee Risk Management Conference; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Coordinate with and provide support to the Governor's Office and State agencies in addressing workplace safety and loss control issues.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Meetings. The Committee shall meet at least quarterly.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>This Executive Order on managing occupational injuries and illnesses in Maryland State Government shall be interpreted and implemented in a manner consistent with the efforts of established State health and safety regulations. Department and agency heads shall utilize existing management functions and programs to expand and improve management of risks within their respective units.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2008-02-15">Effective date: February 15, 2008 (35:6 Md. R. 672)</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Maryland Partnership for Children in Nature (Amends Executive Order 01.01.2008.06)</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Established. There is a Maryland Partnership for Children in Nature (The Partnership) to promote outdoor experiential activities and environmental education for Maryland's young people and to build a coalition of ongoing support for these endeavors.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Membership. The Partnership shall include the following members:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of Natural Resources, or the Secretary's designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Superintendent of the State Department of Education, or the Superintendent's designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>One representative of the Chesapeake Bay Trust;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Two representatives of non-profit organizations dedicated to environmental education;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>One representative of the Maryland Association for Environmental and Outdoor Education;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>One representative of a Parent Teacher Organization</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Two representatives of local governments that have demonstrated leadership in sustainable development practices;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>One representative (teacher or principal) from a Maryland Green School that has completed a Schoolyard Habitat project;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>One outdoor school principal;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>One school superintendent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>One environmental education teacher;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Two representatives of urban youth-based organizations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>One representative of the Maryland Recreation and Parks Association;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>One representative of the pediatric medical field;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>A former member of the Task Force on Minority Participation in the Environmental Community;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>Two representatives of the business community with demonstrated leadership in supporting children in nature; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>One representative of the National Wildlife Federation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Appointment and Terms. The members identified in B(3) through B(17) of this Executive Order shall be appointed by the Governor, with the advice of the Secretary of Natural Resources and the Superintendent of Education. Such members shall serve at the pleasure of the Governor for 2-year terms.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Meetings. The Partnership shall meet at the call of the Chairs.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Procedures. A majority of the Partnership constitutes a quorum for the transaction of any business. The Partnership may adopt any other procedures and by-laws necessary to ensure the orderly transaction of business.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Expenses. Members of the Partnership shall serve without compensation for their services, but they may receive reimbursement for reasonable expenses incurred in the performance of their duties in accordance with the Standard State Travel Regulations and as provided in the State budget.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Consultation. The Partnership shall consult with and engage leadership and staff from all other Maryland Executive Departments and independent agencies, federal and local government representatives.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Chair. The Partnership shall be co-chaired by the Secretary of Natural Resources, or the Secretary's designee, and the Superintendent of Education, or the Superintendent's designee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Staff Coordination. The Department of Natural Resources shall provide staff support for the Partnership in coordination with the State Department of Education and other State agencies and other partners as directed by the Chairs.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Working Groups. The Partnership shall be supported by working groups, to be established by the Chairs, to lead the major tasks identified under this Executive Order.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Responsibilities. The Partnership shall promote the well-being of youth by providing opportunities for increased time spent outdoors and environmental literacy through outdoor experiential activities and formal and non-formal environmental education. The Partnership shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Develop and implement a plan to provide youth with structured and unstructured opportunities for play, outdoor recreation, learning and scientific study to include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Strategies that provide increased support for Schoolyard Habitat Programs, which support the conversion of schoolyards to natural habitats for play and outdoor classrooms;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Creation of trails to connect communities, parks and schools via trail systems that encourage walking, biking and increased time outdoors by youth and families;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Greening initiatives that create nature play areas within communities to provide outdoor experiences for children close to home;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A statewide Civic Justice Corps to provide at-risk youth with opportunities to serve in conservation crews in State Parks and other public lands in partnership with the Maryland Department of Juvenile Services and community non-profit organizations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>An outdoor classroom program that provides voluntary curriculum-aligned programming and service learning opportunities on public lands in cooperation with local county school systems, local parks and non-profit organizations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Increased access to naturalists on State Parks and public lands to provide interpretive activities for children and families to enhance their discovery and enjoyment of Maryland's natural resources; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Increased opportunities for under-served communities to access Maryland State Parks and public lands through partnerships with organizations that serve minority students;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Develop and implement a State Environmental Literacy Plan to include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A review of current environmental education efforts in Maryland schools, including the environmental education bylaw, the Chesapeake 2000 commitments, and student environmental literacy levels;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Identification of curriculum necessary to develop environmentally literate students;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Identification of model outdoor field and service learning experiences that can be integrated into the regular school curriculum;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Professional development opportunities for in-service teachers, pre-service teachers, and non-formal environmental educators;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Methods to annually measure and report at the State and local level, progress of public school students toward becoming environmentally literate graduates; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>A process for revising or updating the environmental literacy plan every five years, or as needed;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Devise a method of measuring baseline data and increased time spent in nature by children;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Identify opportunities and barriers to support implementation of programs in local school systems and on public lands; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Present these plans and a status report on their implementation to the Governor by January 1, 2009.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2008-08-18">Effective date: August 18, 2008 (35:19 Md. R. 1688)</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Governor's Family Violence Council (Rescinds Executive Order 01.01.2006.01)</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Established. There is a Governor's Family Violence Council within the Governor's Office of Crime Control and Prevention. The Governor's Family Violence Council's mission is to provide the Governor with timely and accurate information on family violence with recommendations to reduce and eliminate abusive behaviors.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Membership.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Council shall have no more than 25 members consisting of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Lieutenant Governor or a designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Health and Mental Hygiene or a designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Human Resources or a designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Public Safety and Correctional Services or a designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Juvenile Services or a designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The State Superintendent of Schools or a designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of State Police or a designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>The Executive Director of the Governor's Office of Crime Control and Prevention or a designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>The Executive Director of the Governor's Office for Children or a designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>The Attorney General or a designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>A representative of the Maryland Judiciary, designated by the Chief Judge of the Court of Appeals;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>Two members of the Maryland Senate, one appointed by the President of the Senate and one appointed by the Minority Leader of the Senate;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>Two members of the Maryland House of Delegates, one appointed by the Speaker of the House and one appointed by the Minority Leader of the House of Delegates;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(n)</num>
          <text>A representative of the Maryland State's Attorneys' Association; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(o)</num>
          <text>Up to nine members with interest and expertise in issues related to domestic violence appointed by the Governor. These members may include representatives of service providers, the legal, advocacy, and faith communities, and victims and survivors of domestic or family violence.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(p)</num>
          <text>The Governor shall appoint the Chair and any Vice Chairs of the Council from among its members.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Members appointed by the Governor under B(1)(o) serve at the will of the Governor, and shall serve 3-year terms, staggered upon initial appointment. All other members shall serve so long as they hold the office or designation stipulated in B(1)(a) through (n).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>To the extent possible, the membership shall include representation from each of the major geographic regions of the State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Members of the Council may not receive any compensation for their services, but may receive reimbursement for reasonable expenses incurred in the performance of their duties in accordance with the Standard State Travel Regulations and as provided in the State budget.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If a member appointed by the Governor fails to attend more than half of the regularly scheduled meetings in one year, the member may be presumed to have resigned and the Governor may appoint a new member to fill out the remainder of the term.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Council shall meet at least two times per year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A majority of the Council's membership shall constitute a quorum for the transaction of any business.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Council may adopt rules consistent with this Executive Order, including the creation of subcommittees to carry out the Council's responsibilities.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Council may hold public hearings as deemed necessary and appropriate by the Chair.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Duties and Responsibilities. The Council shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Advise the Governor through the Executive Director of the Governor's Office of Crime Control and Prevention on matters related to family violence.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Identify and analyze State policies and programs relating to family violence, including but not limited to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Collecting data from State agencies relating to the prevention and reduction of domestic violence and related family violence;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Identifying resources available to reduce and prevent family violence through a statewide coordinated effort; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Identifying opportunities for collaboration between governmental units.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Examine, or cause to be examined, the relationship between family violence and other societal problems, including but not limited to juvenile delinquency, alcohol and substance abuse, truancy, and future criminal activity.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Identify best practices, research, and information pertaining to abuser intervention and related programs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Propose to the Governor, through the Executive Director of the Governor's Office of Crime Control and Prevention, legislative, regulatory, and policy changes to reduce and prevent the incidence of domestic violence and related family violence, to protect victims and to punish perpetrators.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Perform such other duties and functions as may be appropriate and necessary for the Council to address and implement the provisions of this Executive Order.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Staffing.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Governor's Office of Crime Control and Prevention shall provide staff for the Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Council may request and shall receive in a timely manner from any department, division, board, bureau, commission, or agency of the State such information and assistance as necessary to enable it to properly carry out its powers pursuant to this Executive Order, unless otherwise prohibited by law.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Council shall be funded by operating budgets of the Executive Department, and any federal funds or special State funds available, unless otherwise prohibited by law or regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Reporting. The Council shall issue an annual report to the Governor by December 1, which provides the status of family violence in Maryland and recommends improvements to the State's activities to prevent family violence.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2008-10-23">Effective date: October 23, 2008 (35:24 Md. R. 2060)</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.18</num>
    <heading>The Maryland Council for New Americans (Rescinds Executive Order 01.01.1996.18)</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>There is a Maryland Council for New Americans (the "Council"). The Council shall be a partnership among the public, private, and civic sectors to promote full immigrant integration into the economic and civic life of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Duties. The Council shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Review and recommend new policies and practices to expedite immigrant integration into the economic and civic life of the State;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide a Maryland Council for New Americans report and recommendations no later than nine months after the date of this Executive Order; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Perform any other duties that may be requested by the Governor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Membership.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The following members or their designees, shall be ex-officio members:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of the Department of Labor, Licensing and Regulation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of the Department of Business and Economic Development;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of the Department of Planning;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of the Department of Human Resources;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of the Department of Housing and Community Development;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The Executive Director of the Governor's Workforce Investment Board;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>The Executive Director of the Governor's Office of Community Initiatives;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>The Special Secretary of the Governor's Office of Minority Affairs;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>The Chair of the Maryland Commission on African American History and Culture; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>The Chair of each of the commissions on ethnic affairs that the Governor has established, or establishes in the future, including but not limited to the Governor's Commission on Hispanic Affairs, the Governor's Commission on Asian Pacific American Affairs, the Governor's Commission on Indian Affairs, and the Governor's Commission on Middle Eastern American Affairs.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The following members shall be appointed by the Governor, and shall serve at the pleasure of the Governor for up to two consecutive four year terms:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>One Maryland County Executive;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>One additional representative from county government;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>One representative from municipal government;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Three representatives from nonprofit social service organizations that reflect the ethnic diversity of the State;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Three representatives from private sector employers;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Ten representatives from faith-based organizations and the clergy;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>One representative from higher education;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>One representative with expertise in adult education and language acquisition;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>One representative from the banking and financial services sector;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>One representative from the healthcare sector;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>One representative from organized labor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(n)</num>
          <text>One representative from the small business sector;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(o)</num>
          <text>One representative from a national organization with expertise in demographic trends and public policy; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(p)</num>
          <text>One representative from the philanthropic sector.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Speaker of the Maryland House of Delegates shall appoint two members from among the members of the House.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The President of the Maryland Senate shall appoint two members from among the members of the Senate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Members of the Council may not receive any compensation for their services, but may be reimbursed for reasonable expenses incurred in the performance of their duties, in accordance with the Standard State Travel Regulations, and as provided in the State budget.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>In the event of a vacancy on the Commission, the Governor shall appoint a successor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>State government representatives shall not constitute a majority of members.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of the Department of Labor, Licensing and Regulation and the County Executive member shall co-chair the Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>There shall be an Executive Committee of the Council, which shall consist of the Secretary of the Department of Business and Economic Development or the Secretary's designee; the Secretary of the Department of Planning or the Secretary's designee; the Executive Director of the Governor's Office of Community Initiatives or the Director's designee; and the Executive Director of the Governor's Workforce Investment Board or the Director's designee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Council shall meet at the call of the Chairs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A majority of Council members shall constitute a quorum for the transaction of any business.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Council may adopt such other procedures and by-laws as may be necessary to ensure the orderly transaction of business.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Working Groups. In addition to any other groups the Council deems necessary to establish to accomplish its work, it shall establish the following working groups, which may include participants who are not Council members, to make recommendations to the Council to address specific challenges facing immigrants.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Workforce Working Group. The Workforce Working Group will focus on helping to address the State's workforce shortage by examining credential transfer, training, and the attraction of key workers to create the region's most competitive workforce; examining the role of "One Stop" employment centers in streamlining the economic integration of new Americans; and identifying best practices that expedite English as a second language, both for children in the public school system and for working adults.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Citizenship Working Group. The Citizenship Working Group will plan a broad, coordinated citizenship promotion and assistance program to naturalize Maryland's estimated 175,000 legal permanent residents who are eligible for naturalization at a faster pace.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Governmental Access Working Group. The Governmental Access Working Group will focus on how to improve accessibility of State and local government services to new Americans. This will include an assessment of resources necessary for compliance with Limited English Proficiency (LEP) requirements; an assessment of the availability of vital documents in other languages; and identifying best practices at the county, community, and municipal levels. This group is also charged with developing specific government wide StateStat measures to track capacity to serve these communities.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Financial Services Working Group. The Financial Services Working Group will examine strategies for increasing immigrants' access to mainstream financial services, stable homeownership, and family financial planning.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Operational Support. The Governor's Office of Community Initiatives and the Department of Labor, Licensing and Regulation shall provide publication, operational, and other support as needed to the Council.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The Maryland Office for New Americans within the Department of Human Resources is hereby renamed the Maryland Office for Refugees and Asylees. Its purpose is to administer Maryland's federally-funded refugee programs.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2008-12-03">Effective date: December 3, 2008 (35:26 Md. R. 2219)</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</container>
