<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Executive Orders</prefix>
  <num>2009</num>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>"Be a Driving Force for Safety" Program for State Employees</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>There is a "Be a Driving Force for Safety" Program for State employees.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each Secretary or Head of an Executive Branch agency shall identify and task an appropriate individual to implement the Program within the agency.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Each Executive Branch agency shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Encourage all State employees who drive fleet vehicles to take the "Driving Improvement Program," an e-learning application on safe driving skills;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Encourage all employees to comply with current seatbelt use laws;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Participate in National Drive Safely Work Week activities each October and other educational opportunities throughout the year; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Support the Program with internal e-mails, poster placement, and other appropriate communication methods.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Department of Budget and Management shall, subject to applicable legal requirements, issue a hands-free cell use policy for drivers of State vehicles. The policy shall prohibit hand-held cell phone use while driving, except in cases of emergency. The policy shall not apply to law enforcement officers or operators of authorized emergency vehicles.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Agency Coordination.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The State Fleet Safety Committee, in conjunction with the State Highway Administration, shall provide guidance to Executive Branch agencies on implementation of the Program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The State Highway Administration shall identify and provide appropriate relevant information and materials to the Committee for review and distribution to Executive Branch agencies in support of the Program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Each Executive Branch agency shall designate appropriate personnel: to coordinate with the State Fleet Safety Committee and the State Highway Administration regarding the implementation of the Program; and to support the distribution and communication of the information and materials described in Section C(2).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2009-05-21">Effective date: May 21, 2009</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>The Joint Enforcement Task Force on Workplace Fraud</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>There is a Joint Enforcement Task Force on Workplace Fraud (Task Force).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>For purposes of this Executive Order, "workplace fraud" means an employer's failure to properly classify an individual as an employee in violation of applicable law.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Task Force shall consist of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of Labor, Licensing and Regulation or the Secretary's designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Attorney General or the Attorney General's designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Comptroller or the Comptroller's designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Chair of the Workers' Compensation Commission or the Chair's designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Insurance Commissioner or the Commissioner's designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The Commissioner of Labor and Industry or the Commissioner's designee; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The Assistant Secretary for the Division of Unemployment Insurance or the Assistant Secretary's designee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Secretary of Labor, Licensing and Regulation or the Secretary's designee shall serve as the Chair of the Task Force.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Members of the Task Force may not receive any compensation for their services, but may be reimbursed for reasonable expenses incurred in the performance of their duties, in accordance with the Standard State Travel Regulations, and as provided in the State budget.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Department of Labor, Licensing and Regulation shall provide publication, operational, and other support as needed to the Task Force.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The Task Force may identify and add members from governmental units whose participation would further its mission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The Task Force shall coordinate the investigation and enforcement of workplace fraud. In fulfilling this mission, the Task Force shall have the following powers and duties:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To facilitate among Task Force members the timely sharing of information related to suspected workplace fraud to the maximum extent permitted by law;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>To pool, focus, and target investigative and enforcement resources;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>To assess existing methods and best practices, in both Maryland and other jurisdictions, with respect to workplace fraud prevention and enforcement, and to recommend that participating agencies adopt appropriate measures to improve their prevention and enforcement efforts;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>To develop strategies for systematic investigations of workplace fraud within those industries in which misclassification is most common;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>To identify and facilitate the filing of complaints against potential violators, including soliciting referrals and other relevant information from the public through the development of an education and outreach campaign;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>To identify significant cases of workplace fraud which should be investigated and addressed collaboratively, and to form joint enforcement teams to utilize the collective investigative and enforcement capabilities of the Task Force members;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>To establish protocols, consistent with applicable law, through which individual Task Force agencies investigating workplace fraud matters under their own statutory or administrative schemes will refer appropriate matters to other agencies for assessment of potential liability under all relevant statutory or administrative schemes;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>To establish referral procedures and solicit the cooperation and participation of local state's attorneys and other relevant agencies, where appropriate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>To coordinate efforts with federal agencies;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>To work cooperatively with business, labor, and community groups interested in reducing workplace fraud by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Developing ways to prevent workplace fraud through effective outreach, including notices and educational materials; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Enhancing mechanisms to identify and report workplace fraud;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>To increase public awareness that employee misclassification is illegal and causes harm;</text>
        <text>(l2) To work cooperatively with federal, State. and local social service agencies to provide assistance to individuals who have been harmed by workplace fraud; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>To consult with representatives of business, organized labor, and other agencies to improve and expand the operation and effectiveness of the Task Force and its members.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>The Task Force shall issue a report to the Governor by December 31 of each year which shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Describe the record and accomplishments of the participating agencies of the Task Force, including the amounts of wages, premiums, taxes, and other payments or penalties collected, as well as the number of employers cited for legal violations related to workplace fraud and the approximate number of employees affected;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Identify any administrative or legal barriers impeding the more effective operation of the Task Force, including any barriers to information sharing or joint action;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Propose, after consultation with representatives of business, organized labor, members of the General Assembly, and other affected agencies, appropriate administrative, legislative, or regulatory changes to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Reduce or eliminate any barriers to the Task Force's operations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Enhance the investigation, enforcement, and prevention of workplace fraud; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Identify successful strategies for preventing workplace fraud that reduce the need for greater enforcement.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Every agency, department, office, division, or public authority of the State shall cooperate with the Task Force and, to the fullest extent permitted by law, shall furnish such information and assistance as the Task Force determines is reasonably necessary to accomplish its purpose.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2009-07-14">Effective date: July 14, 2009</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Locating State Facilities To Stimulate Transit- Oriented Development</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>It is a policy of the State of Maryland to locate State office or laboratory space within a half-mile radius of transit stations at a transit-oriented development whenever appropriate and feasible without diminishing the accessibility of services to the citizens of the State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Definitions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Fixed guideway transit station" means a passenger boarding and alighting location of a public transportation facility using and occupying a dedicated right-of-way or rail for the use of public transportation and other high occupancy vehicles.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Transit-accessible site" means property, any part of which is located within one-half mile of a planned or existing fixed guideway transit station.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Transit-oriented development" has the meaning defined under Section 7-101 of the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr">Transportation Article of the Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Transit evaluation factor" means the evaluation points or weight given in a State lease or property acquisition solicitation to proposed sites located within a transit-accessible site or transit-oriented development.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Maryland Office and Laboratory Space Lease and Property Acquisition Proposals.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>This paragraph C applies to all new lease procurements and property acquisition proposals for more than 5,000 square feet of office space, laboratory space, or a combination of both, that are submitted to the Board of Public Works (BPW) by the Department of General Services (DGS) or the Maryland Department of Transportation (MDOT), its modal administrations and the Maryland Transportation Authority. It does not apply to proposals to renew or extend existing leases of space.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Except as provided herein, DGS and MDOT shall include a transit evaluation factor in all requests for proposals to lease or purchase office or laboratory space (solicitations) in the manner described below.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>When DGS or MDOT uses a point system to evaluate proposals, it shall award at least five percent of the total allocable points to proposals for office or laboratory space located in transit-accessible sites and at least an additional seven percent of the total allocable points to proposals for office or laboratory space located within a transit-oriented development.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>When DGS or MDOT does not use a point system to evaluate lease or property acquisition proposals for State office or laboratory space, then the transit evaluation factor shall be included in the solicitation as one of the most heavily weighted evaluation factors within the selection criteria as determined by the agency.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>DGS or MDOT may omit the transit evaluation factor from a request for proposal if it determines in its discretion that location of the particular office or laboratory space within a transit-accessible site or transit-oriented development would:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Not be feasible or not be appropriate for the intended use;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Hamper efficient or effective operations or delivery of State services;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Result in the State not being able to provide citizens with reasonable, convenient, and efficient access to State services in places where there are no fixed guideway transit stations;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Be unsafe or otherwise inconsistent with the character of a transit-accessible site or transit-oriented development;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Be contrary to the tenant agency's mission or its clientele's interests;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Contravene State or federal law, regulation, rule, or policy; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Otherwise not be in the public interest.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>For all proposals that recommend approval of a site that is not located at a transit-accessible site or a transit-oriented development, including those where a transit evaluation factor was not included in the solicitation, DGS and MDOT must provide a written explanation for not selecting such a site in their submission to the BPW.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2009-09-16">Effective date: September 16, 2009</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Governor's Commission on Suicide Prevention</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>There is a Maryland Commission on Suicide Prevention.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Membership. The Commission consists of the following voting members:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>One member of the Maryland Senate, appointed by the President of the Senate;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>One member of the Maryland House of Delegates, appointed by the Speaker of the House of Delegates;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Health and Mental Hygiene, or the Secretary's designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Deputy Secretary of Behavioral Health, Department of Health and Mental Hygiene, or the Deputy Secretary's designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The Deputy Secretary of Public Health Services, Department of Health and Mental Hygiene, or the Deputy Secretary's designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of the State Department of Education, or the Secretary's designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of the Department of Juvenile Services, or the Secretary's designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of the Department of Public Safety and Corrections, or the Secretary's designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of the Department of Aging, or the Secretary's designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of the Department of Veterans Affairs, or the Secretary's designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>The Executive Director of the Governor's Office for Children, or the Executive Director's designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of the Department of Disabilities, or the Secretary's designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>One representative of the Mental Health Association of Maryland;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(n)</num>
          <text>One representative of the National Organization for People of Color Against Suicide;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(o)</num>
          <text>One representative of the Maryland Addictions Directors Council;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(p)</num>
          <text>One representative of the faith community;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(q)</num>
          <text>One representative of the academic community;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(r)</num>
          <text>One representative of a suicide prevention group;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(s)</num>
          <text>One veteran;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(t)</num>
          <text>One family member of an individual who completed suicide; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(u)</num>
          <text>One local health officer.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The members identified in Sections B(c) through (u) shall be appointed by the Governor, and shall serve at the pleasure of the Governor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Members appointed by the Governor may serve up to two consecutive, three-year terms.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Governor shall designate the Chair from among the members.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>In the event of a vacancy on the Commission, the Governor shall appoint a successor to fill the remainder of the term.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Members of the Commission may not receive any compensation for their services but may be reimbursed for reasonable expenses incurred in the performance of their duties, in accordance with the Standard State Travel Regulations, and as provided in the State budget.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Commission will be staffed by the Mental Hygiene Administration of the Department of Health and Mental Hygiene.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The majority of voting members of the Commission shall constitute a quorum for the transaction of any business.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Commission may adopt such other procedures as may be necessary to ensure the orderly transaction of business, including the creation of committees or task forces.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Chair may, with the consent of the Commission, designate additional individuals, including interested citizens, elected officials, educators, or specialists with relevant expertise, to serve on any committee or task force.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The Commission may consult with State agencies to obtain such technical assistance and advice as it deems necessary to complete its duties. All Executive Department agencies shall cooperate with and assist the Commission in carrying out its responsibilities.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The Commission shall meet at least four times a year.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Purpose. The Commission shall have the following objectives:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To develop a comprehensive, coordinated, and strategic plan for suicide prevention, intervention, and post-suicide services across the State for individuals and their families;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>To develop a comprehensive baseline listing of existing support systems for survivors, attempters, and their families;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>To promote a coordinated, collaborative, and comprehensive effort by local and State agencies to ensure effective and efficient use of State and local resources for the delivery of a continuum of suicide prevention, intervention, and post-suicide services for Maryland citizens;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>To recommend adequate resources to address suicide prevention, intervention, and post-suicide service needs of Maryland citizens, including citizens involved in the criminal justice system; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>To identify and review the impact of suicide on the health and well-being of Maryland citizens; the economic and social costs of suicide; and effective and efficient practices in the organization and delivery of State and local suicide prevention, evaluation, and treatment services.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>State Plan.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Commission shall prepare a 2-year plan that establishes priorities and strategies for the organization, delivery, and funding of State suicide prevention, intervention and post-suicide services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Commission shall develop the plan taking into account, among other factors:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The identified needs of the citizens of the State, including the general public and the criminal justice population; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The strategies and priorities identified in the plans established by local jurisdictions.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The plan shall include recommendations for coordination and collaboration among State agencies in the organization, delivery, and funding of suicide prevention, intervention, and post-suicide services; promising practices and programs; training; and emerging needs for State suicide prevention, intervention, and post-suicide services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The plan shall be submitted to the Governor by June 1, 2011 and biannually thereafter. Any interim updates to the plan also shall be submitted to the Governor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2009-10-07">Effective date: October 7, 2009</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</container>
