<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Executive Orders</prefix>
  <num>2010</num>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>The Maryland State Council on Educational Opportunity for Military Children</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Established. There is the Maryland State Council on Educational Opportunity for Military Children (the Council), as required by Chapters  501 and 502 of the Acts of the General Assembly of 2009 - Interstate Compact on Educational Opportunity for Military Children.  The Council enables Maryland State agencies to collaborate and coordinate with other member states of the Interstate Compact on Educational Opportunity for Military Children (the Compact), the Interstate Commission on Educational Opportunity for Military Children (the Interstate Commission), local education agencies, and military installations to ensure a smooth transition of children of military families both in and out of Maryland schools.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Membership. The Council includes the following members:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The State Superintendent of Schools;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A Superintendent of a school district with a high concentration of military children;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A representative of a military installation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A representative of the Executive Branch;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A representative of a military family;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A representative of school based personnel responsible for managing the transition of military children into and out of the school system;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>One member of the Maryland Senate, appointed by the President of the Senate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>One member of the Maryland House of Delegates, appointed by the Speaker of the House of Delegates; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Representatives of other offices and stakeholder groups the Council deems appropriate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>The Compact Commissioner responsible for the administration and management of the State's participation in the Compact, and the Military Family Education Liaison are ex officio, voting members of the Council and serve at the pleasure of their appointing authority.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Appointment and Terms. The members identified in B(2) through B(6) of this Executive Order shall be appointed by the Governor, with the advice of a representative of the Governor's Subcabinet on Base Realignment and Closure (BRAC) and the State Superintendent of Schools. Such members shall serve at the pleasure of the Governor for two-year terms.   The members identified in B(7) through B(10) of this Executive Order shall serve at the pleasure of their appointing authorities.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Meetings. The Council shall meet at the call of the Chair.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Procedures. The Chair shall establish the format and procedures for the meetings of the Council.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Members of the Council may not receive any compensation for their services but may be reimbursed for reasonable expenses incurred in the performance of their duties, in accordance with the Standard State Travel Regulations, and as provided in the State budget.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Consultation. Members of the Council shall consult and coordinate with the Interstate Commission, the Council of State Governments' National Center for Interstate Compacts, the Maryland State Department of Education, other State agencies, the local schools systems, military installations, and other organizations as needed concerning the State's participation in and compliance with the Compact and Interstate Commission activities.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Chair. The Chair shall be determined by the Council.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Staff Coordination. The Council shall be staffed by the Maryland State Department of Education.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Working Groups. Working groups shall be established based on the needs of the Council.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Frequency of Meetings.  The Council shall meet at least twice a year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Responsibilities. The Council shall promote and support Maryland's participation as a member of the Compact.  The Compact enables Maryland to collaborate with other member states, providing much needed consistency to ensure that there are no barriers to educational success imposed on children of military families because of frequent moves and the deployment of their parents.  Consistent with the Compact, the Maryland Council will develop a set of recommendations and a plan to address, among other issues, the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Transfer of records;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Course sequencing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Graduation requirements;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Extra-curricular activities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Kindergarten and first grade entrance age;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Immunization; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Power of custodial parents while parents are deployed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The recommendations and plan shall be submitted to the Governor by January 12, 2011 and biannually thereafter.  Any interim updates to the recommendations and plan also shall be submitted to the Governor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2010-04-26">Effective date: April 26, 2010</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>State Coordinating Committee for Human Services Transportation</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Established. There is a State Coordinating Committee for Human Services Transportation (Committee).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Definitions. As used in this Executive Order, the following terms have the following meanings:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The term "agency" means an executive department, agency or office of the State of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The term "transportation-disadvantaged" means a person who qualifies for federally conducted or federally assisted transportation-related programs or services, as implemented and coordinated by a Maryland State agency, due to disability, income, or advanced age.  This term is directly connected with the definition provided in the Presidential Executive Order on Human Services Transportation Coordination dated February 24, 2004 and mirrors any subsequent federal interpretation of the definition.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Membership and Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Committee shall consist of the following members:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Transportation, or a designee, who shall Chair the Committee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Human Resources, or a designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Health and Mental Hygiene, or a designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Aging, or a designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of the Department of Disabilities, or a designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Housing and Community Development, or a designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Planning, or a designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>The State Superintendent of Schools, or a designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs, or a designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>The Director of the Governor's Office for the Deaf and Hard of Hearing, or a designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Labor, Licensing and Regulation, or a designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>The Executive Director of the Maryland Developmental Disabilities Council, or a designee; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>Additional members recommended to the Governor by the Chairperson of the Committee as needed to provide input from local governments, employers, agencies and organizations serving targeted populations, transportation providers, and consumers from targeted populations.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The members of the Committee named in (C )(1)(a) through (l) shall serve so long as they hold the office or designation specified in this Executive Order.  All other members shall serve at the pleasure of the Governor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The members of the Committee may not receive any compensation for their services.  The members may be reimbursed for reasonable expenses incurred in the performance of duties, in accordance with the Standard State Travel Regulations and as provided in the State budget.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Staff for the Committee will be provided by the Department of Transportation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Scope of the Committee.  The Committee shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Examine the transportation needs of citizens who are elderly, who have disabilities, and individuals requiring transportation to access jobs, medical and health appointments, senior citizens programs and other programs requiring the transportation of individuals who qualify as transportation-disadvantaged;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Coordinate Maryland's efforts to provide quality human services transportation services by working with appropriate federal, State and local agencies, transit customers and transportation providers to develop a cooperative, coordinated, and human services transportation system;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Devise a five-year human services transportation plan, which sets goals and objectives to help transportation-disadvantaged citizens access jobs, education and training programs, healthcare services and other activities by providing cost-effective, affordable, high capacity, high quality, easily understood, safe and accessible transportation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Serve as the clearinghouse for human services transportation coordination issues throughout the State of Maryland, identify and facilitate a resolution to local and statewide issues regarding human services transportation, participate in the identification of possible allocations of human services transportation resources during emergency evacuations, evaluate cost-saving measures, investigate the need for the establishment of standards for vehicles and drivers within the human services transportation program, and examine other appropriate areas that facilitate the development of a quality human services transportation system in Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Reports to the Governor.  The Committee shall provide an annual report to the Governor by September 1st of each year outlining its progress.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2010-04-26">Effective date: April 26, 2010</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</container>
