<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Executive Orders</prefix>
  <num>2012</num>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Recognition of the Maryland Indian Status of the Piscataway Conoy Tribe</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The State formally recognizes the Piscataway Conoy Tribe's Maryland Indian status.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Piscataway Conoy Tribe and its members shall be accorded all the rights and privileges to which formal State recognition of the Tribe's Maryland Indian status entitles them.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>This Executive Order should not be interpreted as creating any rights to land, entitlements of any kind, or any special privileges related to gaming.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2012-01-09">Effective date: January 9, 2012</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Recognition of the Maryland Indian Status of the Piscataway Indian Nation</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The State formally recognizes the Piscataway Indian Nation’s Maryland Indian status.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Piscataway Indian Nation and its members shall be accorded all the rights and privileges to which formal State recognition of the Nation's Maryland Indian status entitles them.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>This Executive Order should not be interpreted as creating any rights to land, entitlements of any kind, or any special privileges related to gaming.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2012-01-09">Effective date: January 9, 2012</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>State Law Enforcement Coordinating Council</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Established. There is a State Law Enforcement Coordinating Council (Council).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Membership.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Council shall include the following State law enforcement agencies (member agencies):</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>State Police;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Maryland Transportation Authority Police;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Mass Transit Administration Police;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Natural Resources Police;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>University of Maryland Department of Public Safety, and all police departments of the constituent institutions of the University System of Maryland listed in Section 12-101(b)(5) of the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged">Education Article of the Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The Morgan State University Police Force; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Maryland Capitol Police.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of State Police will serve as the Chair of the Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Council Chair shall select two chiefs from the member agencies who shall serve as Deputy Chairs for an appointment period not to exceed one year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Executive Committee will be comprised of the Chair and Deputy Chairs of the Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Membership of the Council may be expanded to include other State law enforcement agencies by the unanimous decision of the Executive Committee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The Advisory Group to the Council shall include, but is not limited to designated representatives from the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Governor’s Office of Crime Control and Prevention;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Maryland Highway Safety Office;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Maryland Police Training Commission;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Maryland Emergency Management Agency; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Governor’s Office of Homeland Security.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Council meetings shall be attended by designated representatives of each member agency and shall be held on a quarterly basis or as necessary.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Council shall adopt written policies and procedures to implement the provisions of this Executive Order, including policies and procedures to ensure the safe, efficient, and cooperative provision of law enforcement services in instances in which a member agency of the Council is operating with expanded jurisdiction as provided for in subsection E(1) of this Executive Order.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>As provided in subsection C(5), the Executive Committee shall approve actions of the Council under circumstances where coordination of State law enforcement agencies will serve to protect the public safety.   Council coordinated activity may include, but is not limited to, responding to crime trends of a statewide, regional or local nature by targeted enforcement or investigative activity, investigating specific criminal activity within the State, maintaining homeland security, responding to emergencies either natural or manmade, or undertaking such actions as may help to enhance the safety of the roadways or any mode of travel on public transportation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Executive Committee shall also decide which member agencies shall participate in each action, based upon the resources a particular member agency has available to participate, the location of the action and the particular expertise that the member agency has available to contribute to the action.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>All planned law enforcement actions of the Council shall be approved by a unanimous decision of the Executive Committee. An Executive Committee member who is not available to participate in any decision of the Committee shall designate a representative from within his or her agency. The scope and aims of each Council action shall be described in writing before it is carried out. The outcome shall be documented within a reasonable time following completion of the action. Any action for which the Executive Committee, because of an emergency or other time-sensitive situation, does not have time to prepare and approve a written document detailing the scope and aims in advance shall be approved upon the verbal authorization of a majority of the Executive Committee. The scope, aims, and outcome of the Council action shall be documented as soon thereafter as reasonably possible.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>On September 1 of each year, the Council shall submit a summary report to the Governor concerning all actions taken under this Executive Order for the previous fiscal year ending June 30, including the member agency participants and the location of each action.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Duties.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Council has the authority and responsibility to coordinate among its member agencies to further the safety and security of the people of Maryland and to improve the administration and enforcement of the laws of Maryland by ensuring that police resources are deployed across the State to address state-wide crime trends, regional and local crime, maintain homeland security, respond to any threats to homeland security, and to address emergencies either natural or man-made.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Council will explore opportunities for its member agencies to work collaboratively with local law enforcement agencies and seek to foster enhanced communications and working relations among all law enforcement agencies in the State to achieve a safer Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Council will seek efficiencies in administrative functions among its member agencies, including but not limited to the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Training;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Information Technology;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Communications;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Procurement;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Campus Security;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Homeland Security; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Development and implementation of emergency planning.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Jurisdiction.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Member agencies may exercise all the authority of a police officer of the Department of State Police as provided in Section 2-412 of the Public Safety Article when carrying out any action approved by the Council as provided for in this Executive Order and as authorized by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Section 7-207(b)(iii) of the Transportation Article for the Maryland Transit Administration Police;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Section 4-208(b)(4)(iii) of the Transportation Article for the Maryland Transportation Authority Police;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Section 13-601(b)(2)(iv) of the Education Article for the University of Maryland Police and the police departments of the constituent institutions of the University System of Maryland listed in Section 12-101(b)(5) of the Education Article; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Section 14-106(b)(2)(iii) for the Morgan State University Police Force.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A police officer of the Natural Resources Police shall have the full authority of a police officer of the State as provided in Section 1-204(a) of the Natural Resources Article, including the authority to enforce traffic laws when carrying out any action approved by the Council as provided for in this Executive Order.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A police officer of the Maryland Capitol Police as defined by Section 4-605(c) of the State Finance and Procurement Article shall have the full authority of a police officer to enforce the criminal laws of the State as provided by Section 2-102 of the Criminal Procedure Article when carrying out any action approved by the Council as provided for in this Executive Order.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>No provision of this Executive Order is intended to compromise or limit any of the powers, protections, or immunities otherwise granted by law to member agencies or other law enforcement agencies within Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2012-02-29">Effective date: February 29, 2012</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>One Maryland — One Map: Maryland Integrated Map</heading>
    <text class="center">(Rescinds Executive Order <cite path="01.01.2009.20">01.01.2009.20</cite>)</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Established. There is an Executive Committee to implement the Maryland Integrated Map (MD iMap). The Executive Committee is a subcabinet entity and shall advise the Governor on issues relating to MD iMap and geospatial policy.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Composition. The Executive Committee consists of the following members:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of the Department of Agriculture or a designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of the Department of Environment or a designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of the Department of Natural Resources or a designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of the Department of Planning or a designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of the Department of Transportation or a designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of the Department of Housing and Community Development or a designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of the Department of Business and Economic Development or a designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of the Department of General Services or a designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>The State Superintendent of Education or a designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of the Department of Health and Mental Hygiene or a designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of the Department of Information Technology;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of the Department of Public Safety and Correctional Services or a designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>The Superintendent of the Maryland State Police or a designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>The Director of Assessments and Taxation or a designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of Budget and Management or a designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>The Adjutant General of the Military Department or a designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>The Director of the Maryland Emergency Management Agency or a designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of the Department of Labor, Licensing and Regulations or a designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of the Department of Human Resources or a designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>The Director of the Governor's StateStat Office;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>The Governor’s Homeland Security Advisor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>The Executive Director of the Governor’s Office of Crime Control and Prevention or a designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>The Executive Director of the Maryland Institute for Emergency Medical Services Systems or a designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(24)</num>
        <text>The Governor may appoint as members of the Executive Committee five elected officials or employees from local government and/or public utilities who have knowledge and interest in geospatial data, technology, and policy. Such members shall serve at the pleasure of the Governor for up to two consecutive two-year terms.  Some initial appointments will be for three years so that subsequent turnover will be staggered. One appointment will represent each of the following geographic regions:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Western (Allegany, Frederick, Garrett, and Washington counties);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Eastern (Eastern Shore including Cecil County);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Southern (Anne Arundel, Calvert, Charles, and St. Mary’s counties);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Capital Region (Montgomery and Princes George’s counties); and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>North/Central (Harford, Baltimore, Baltimore City, Carroll, and Howard counties);</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(25)</num>
        <text>The Governor may appoint up to five members from the private, private utility, academic, and/or nonprofit sectors who have knowledge of and interest in geospatial data, technology, or policy.  Such members shall serve at the pleasure of the Governor for up to two consecutive two-year terms.  Some initial appointments will be for three years so that subsequent turnover will be staggered; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(26)</num>
        <text>The Governor shall request a representative from the Federal Geographic Data Committee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Executive Committee Leadership and Status.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Governor shall provide strategic direction to the Executive Committee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of the Department of Information Technology shall chair the Executive Committee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Director of the Governor's StateStat Office shall serve as vice chair of the Executive Committee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Executive Committee Duties.  The Executive Committee shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Develop and/or approve MD iMap policies, procedures, and guidance;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Respond to matters referred by the Technical Committee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Identify funding to support the MD iMap program, develop a budget that describes the collective cost of operating and investing in MD iMap, and provide advice to the Governor on budget matters;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Promote the sharing of geospatial data and services among all participants in the MD iMap program while taking into account privacy and security concerns;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Appoint and assign appropriate staff to oversee the development, maintenance, use, and promotion of the MD iMap program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Provide guidance to the Technical Committee on MD iMap policies, standards, and other deliverables; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Promote, advertise, and market the applications, capabilities, benefits, and results of the MD iMap program.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>State Geographic Information Officer.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>There is a State Geographic Information Officer (GlO).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The GlO shall be appointed by and serve at the pleasure of the Secretary of the Department of Information Technology.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The GlO shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Ensure that the MD iMap program supports the Governor's Policy Goals;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Facilitate and coordinate the planning, implementation, and maintenance of the MD iMap program (including MD iMap policies and procedures);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Develop, maintain, and operate an enterprise geospatial system, including the central store and catalog of MD iMap data and services available to agencies and the public;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Recruit the Technical Committee membership;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Appoint Technical Committee Chair(s);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Provide oversight for the development of the MD iMap program;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Establish and monitor MD iMap metrics;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Establish and manage a MD iMap communications plan;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Provide MD iMap education;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Maintain a liaison relationship with State, regional, county, and municipal organizations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Promote, advertise, and market applications, capabilities, benefits, and results of the MD iMap program; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>Assist in the identification and capturing of funding to support the MD iMap program.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Technical Committee.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Technical Committee shall consist of State agency personnel responsible for using and implementing MD iMap, local government, and private and nonprofit representatives in the field of geographical information systems.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Technical Committee shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Facilitate the development of MD iMap contents, policies, and procedures;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Establish and monitor MD iMap metrics;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Provide staff support to workgroups;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Provide MD iMap program status reports to the Executive Committee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Resolve issues identified by any work groups that have been established;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Ensure consistency in any contents, policies and procedures developed by work groups;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Submit MD iMap resources to the Executive Committee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Submit recommendations to the Executive Committee for changes, additions, or exceptions to MD iMap system infrastructure or data sets;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Identify matters that need to be referred to the Executive Committee for resolution;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Ensure the quality and timeliness of MD iMap resources;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Review and provide advice on GIS-related projects to the Executive Committee or the GIO;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>Provide planning and oversight support for MD iMap GIS projects;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>Provide advice on GIS-related issues associated with MD iMap projects;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(n)</num>
          <text>Review MD iMap GIS projects to ensure that they conform to the MD iMap program policies;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(o)</num>
          <text>Promote, advertise, and market the applications, capabilities, benefits, and results of MD iMap; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(p)</num>
          <text>Research new technologies.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Cooperation of State Agencies.  All State departments, agencies, commissions, and boards are directed to cooperate with the Executive Committee, the GIO, and the Technical Committee in implementing the provisions of this Executive Order.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2012-03-13">Effective date: March 13, 2012</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Governor's Family Violence Council</heading>
    <text class="center">(Amends Executive Order <cite path="01.01.2008.16">01.01.2008.16</cite>)</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Established. There is a Governor's Family Violence Council within the Governor's Office of Crime Control and Prevention.  The Governor’s Family Violence Council’s mission is to provide the Governor with timely and accurate information on family violence with recommendations to reduce and eliminate abusive behaviors.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Membership.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Council shall have no more than 28 members consisting of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Lieutenant Governor or a designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Health and Mental Hygiene or a designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Human Resources or a designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Public Safety and Correctional Services or a designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Juvenile Services or a designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The State Superintendent of Schools or a designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of State Police or a designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>The Executive Director of the Governor's Office of Crime Control and Prevention or a designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>The Executive Director of the Governor's Office for Children or a designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>The Attorney General or a designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>A representative of the Maryland Judiciary, designated by the Chief Judge of the Court of Appeals;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>Two members of the Maryland Senate, one appointed by the President of the Senate and one appointed by the Minority Leader of the Senate;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>Two members of the Maryland House of Delegates, one appointed by the Speaker of the House and one appointed by the Minority Leader of the House of Delegates;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(n)</num>
          <text>A representative of the Maryland State’s Attorneys’ Association; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(o)</num>
          <text>Up to twelve members with interest and expertise in issues related to domestic violence appointed by the Governor.  These members may include representatives of service providers, the legal, advocacy, and faith communities, and victims and survivors of domestic or family violence.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(p)</num>
          <text>The Governor shall appoint the Chair and any Vice Chairs of the Council from among its members.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Members appointed by the Governor under B(1)(o) serve at the will of the Governor, and shall serve 3-year terms, staggered upon initial appointment. All other members shall serve so long as they hold the office or designation stipulated in B(1)(a) through (n).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>To the extent possible, the membership shall include representation from each of the major geographic regions of the State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Members of the Council may not receive any compensation for their services, but may receive reimbursement for reasonable expenses incurred in the performance of their duties in accordance with the Standard State Travel Regulations and as provided in the State budget.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If a member appointed by the Governor fails to attend more than half of the regularly scheduled meetings in one year, the member may be presumed to have resigned and the Governor may appoint a new member to fill out the remainder of the term.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Council shall meet at least two times per year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A majority of the Council's membership shall constitute a quorum for the transaction of any business.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Council may adopt rules consistent with this Executive Order, including the creation of subcommittees to carry out the Council's responsibilities.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Council may hold public hearings as deemed necessary and appropriate by the Chair.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Duties and Responsibilities. The Council shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Advise the Governor through the Executive Director of the Governor's Office of Crime Control and Prevention on matters related to family violence.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Identify and analyze State policies and programs relating to family violence, including but not limited to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Collecting data from State agencies relating to the prevention and reduction of domestic violence and related family violence;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Identifying resources available to reduce and prevent family violence through a statewide coordinated effort; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Identifying opportunities for collaboration between governmental units.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Examine, or cause to be examined, the relationship between family violence and other societal problems, including but not limited to juvenile delinquency, alcohol and substance abuse, truancy, and future criminal activity.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Identify best practices, research, and information pertaining to abuser intervention and related programs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Propose to the Governor, through the Executive Director of the Governor's Office of Crime Control and Prevention, legislative, regulatory, and policy changes to reduce and prevent the incidence of domestic violence and related family violence, to protect victims and to punish perpetrators.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Perform such other duties and functions as may be appropriate and necessary for the Council to address and implement the provisions of this Executive Order.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Staffing.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Governor's Office of Crime Control and Prevention shall provide staff for the Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Council may request and shall receive in a timely manner from any department, division, board, bureau, commission, or agency of the State such information and assistance as necessary to enable it to properly carry out its powers pursuant to this Executive Order, unless otherwise prohibited by law.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Council shall be funded by operating budgets of the Executive Department, and any federal funds or special State funds available, unless otherwise prohibited by law or regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Reporting. The Council shall issue an annual report to the Governor by December 1, which provides the status of family violence in Maryland and recommends improvements to the State's activities to prevent family violence.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2012-03-27">Effective date: March 27, 2012</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</container>
