<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Executive Orders</prefix>
  <num>2013</num>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Governor's Commission on Service and Volunteerism</heading>
    <text class="center">(Rescinds Executive Order <cite path="01.01.2004.58">01.01.2004.58</cite>)</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definitions. In this Executive Order, the following terms have the meanings indicated:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Commission” means the Governor's Commission on Service and Volunteerism.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Office” means the Governor’s Office of Community Initiatives, as established in Executive Order <cite path="01.01.2007.25">01.01.2007.25</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Act” means the National and Community Service Trust Act of 1993, as amended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Executive Director” means the Executive Director of the Governor’s Office of Community Initiatives.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Established. There is a Governor's Commission on Service and Volunteerism within the Executive Branch. The Commission shall report to the Executive Director.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Membership and Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Voting Members. The Commission shall be comprised of the following voting members:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The State Superintendent of Schools, or a designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>14 to 24 voting members appointed by the Governor to include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A representative of community-based agencies or organizations within the State;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A representative of local government;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A representative of business;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>A representative of labor;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>A representative of a national service program;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>An individual between the ages of 16 and 25 who is a participant or supervisor in a volunteer service program;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>An individual with expertise in the educational, training and development needs of youth, particularly disadvantaged youth;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>An individual with experience in promoting the involvement of older adults in service and volunteerism; (ix) A representative of the volunteer sector; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(x)</num>
            <text>Members of the general public with interest, knowledge and experience in service and volunteerism.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Nonvoting Members. The Executive Director of the Office shall serve as a nonvoting member of the Commission. The Commission may also include nonvoting representatives of State agencies.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Corporation for National and Community Service shall designate one of its employees to serve as an ex-officio nonvoting representative on the Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>In accordance with the requirements of the Act, no more than 50 percent plus one of the voting members may be from the same political party, and no more than 25 percent of the voting members may be comprised of officers or employees of the State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>In accordance with the requirements of the Act, the Chairperson will be elected annually from among the Commission members and may be re-elected.  In the event of a vacancy between elections, the Governor shall designate an interim chairperson who shall serve until a successor has been duly elected.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Members appointed by the Governor shall serve at his pleasure for a term of three years. A member may be reappointed, but may not serve more than two complete consecutive terms. The terms of the members shall be staggered from initial appointment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>A member of the Commission shall serve without compensation, but may be reimbursed for reasonable and necessary travel expenses incurred while performing approved Commission duties, in accordance with the Standard State Travel Regulations and as provided in the State budget.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Scope of the Commission. The Commission shall have the following duties and responsibilities:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To direct the State’s participation in the implementation of the National and Community Service Trust Act of 1993, and appropriate successor acts, including approving the State's application for funding of service positions under the Act;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>To encourage the recognition of outstanding volunteer service and civic participation by individuals, schools, and organizations, with the goal of promoting greater participation in the community; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>To advise the Governor, Executive Director, and State agencies on issues related to volunteerism and service among the citizens of the State.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Staff Support. The Office shall provide support to the Commission in carrying out its duties, including:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Performing grant administration functions, including preparation of an annual comprehensive plan and State application for funding, and monitoring and evaluating funded programs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Serving as the State’s principal liaison to the Corporation for National and Community Service;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Providing technical assistance, education, information, and other support to organizations and institutions to encourage community service and volunteer participation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Working with individuals, communities and organizations to promote innovative programs and initiatives that address Maryland’s educational, public safety, human service, and environmental needs.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Reports. By December 31 of each year, the Commission shall make an annual report to the Executive Director concerning its activities, and any recommendations it may have for further promoting community service and volunteerism in the State.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2013-07-23">Effective date: July 23, 2013</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Public-Private Partnerships — Oversight</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Maryland Subcabinet for Public-Private Partnerships.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Established. This is a Maryland Subcabinet for Public-Private Partnerships. The Subcabinet shall consist of the following members:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Executive Director of the Maryland Subcabinet for Public-Private Partnerships, who is appointed by the Governor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Lt. Governor, or the Lt. Governor’s designee, who serves as Chair of Subcabinet;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Budget and Management, or the Secretary’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of General Services, or the Secretary’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Transportation, or the Secretary’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The Special Secretary of the Governor’s Office of Minority Affairs, or the Special Secretary’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>The Executive Secretary of the Maryland Transportation Authority, or the Executive Secretary’s designee; (h) The Chancellor of the University System of Maryland, or the Chancellor’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>The Executive Director of the Maryland Stadium Authority, or the Executive Director’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>The Executive Director of the Maryland Economic Development Corporation, or the Executive Director’s designee; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>The Executive Director of the Interagency Committee on School Construction, or the Executive Director’s designee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Maryland Subcabinet for Public-Private Partnerships shall establish a Public-Private Partnership Advisory Board to seek advice on future public-private partnership policy and opportunities. The membership of the Advisory Board is at the sole discretion of the Subcabinet. The Board shall be diverse and representative of the various groups and stakeholders that have experience and interest in public-private partnerships.  Its membership may include persons from the private and public sector, the labor community, the environmental community, historically black colleges and universities, minority communities, women, local and county government officials, the Maryland Senate, the Maryland House of Delegates and any other affected groups or businesses.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Responsibilities. The Maryland Subcabinet for Public-Private Partnerships and the Executive Director of the Subcabinet shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Coordinate the activities of the Subcabinet, execute the responsibilities enumerated in this Executive Order, and act as the State’s liaison to groups and individuals who are interested in learning about or pursuing public-private partnerships in Maryland;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Meet at least quarterly to review statewide public-private partnership projects, policies, and related issues;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Provide assistance, information, or advice to any reporting agency seeking assistance, information, or advice for potential public-private partnerships;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>As necessary, and in coordination with a reporting agency and the Department of Budget and Management, provide the Board of Public Works, the General Assembly, the Department of Legislative Services, the Office of the Comptroller and Office of the Treasurer with updates on any ongoing or future public-private partnerships;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Assist with the continued development and improvement of the State’s public-private partnership framework, including agency regulations and the criteria for project selection, as needed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Review, as needed, Maryland’s existing public-private partnership legislation or regulations that may constrain reporting agencies or Maryland’s ability to consider or execute public-private partnerships effectively, and recommend potential changes;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Analyze how to maximize the State’s use of public-private partnerships;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Conduct additional research into best practices for public-private partnerships within the United States and internationally;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Invite subject-matter experts, both from within and outside State government, to present to the Subcabinet;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Hold forums and similar educational or information-gathering events;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Ensure that the repository for public-private partnership information established under Section B of this Executive Order is updated on a timely basis, including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Key aspects and documents related to all State public-private partnerships that have reached final Agreement;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Details about each reporting agency’s pipeline of future public-private partnerships; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Any other pertinent information related to public-private partnerships;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>Commission the development of studies and reports including, but not limited to, a report submitted by December 1, 2013 to the Governor, Senate President and House Speaker that includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>An analysis of the State’s two capital improvement plans—including the Consolidated Transportation Program and Capital Improvement Program—to assist reporting agencies in determining which capital projects should be considered as a public-private partnership and their respective priority.  Consideration may also be given to capital projects that have been requested, but are not included in either of the State’s current capital improvement plans;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The advantages and disadvantages of establishing a formal Office of Public-Private Partnerships and/or Innovative Financing Office to oversee and manage future tax increment financing, public-private partnerships, smart growth investment funds, or other types of innovative financing, as well as the potential composition, location, staffing, and responsibilities of such an office or offices; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A description of possible uses of availability payments and their applicability in Maryland.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Staff support.  Staff support for the Maryland Subcabinet for Public-Private Partnerships will be provided by the Executive Director with support from:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Department of Transportation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Department of Budget and Management;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Department of General Services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The University System of Maryland; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Contractual assistance or experts in the field of public-private partnerships or other areas as needed.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Repository for Public-Private Partnership Information.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Executive Director in coordination with the subcabinet will create a centralized website to highlight information on the State’s knowledge and experience with public-private partnership policies, processes, projects and other best practices.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The website will be maintained jointly by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Maryland Subcabinet for Public-Private Partnerships;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Department of Transportation; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Department of General Services.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The website may include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Key aspects and documents of all public-private partnerships undertaken by the State or a reporting agency;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The pre-solicitation report of all future public-private partnerships, minus the  information deemed confidential, proprietary, or otherwise exempt from disclosure, in accordance with 10A-201(c)(1)(v) of the State Finance and Procurement Article;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Solicitation documents and the final public-private partnership agreement, minus the  information deemed confidential, proprietary, or otherwise exempt from disclosure, in accordance with 10A-203(b)(1)(i) of the State Finance and Procurement Article;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The contact information for the main public-private partnership point of contact for each reporting agency;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Report of the Joint Legislative and Executive Commission on Public-Private Partnerships;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Regulations relating to public-private partnerships for each of the reporting agencies;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>The process for submitting unsolicited proposals to the reporting agencies;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Information regarding recent public-private partnership activities, forums, meetings, and initiatives throughout the State;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Additional materials developed by the Maryland Subcabinet for Public Private Partnerships; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Details about each Reporting Agency’s pipeline of potential future public-private partnerships, including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Potential project delivery methods under consideration; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Estimated pre-solicitation and solicitation schedules for each potential public-private partnership.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Public Private Processes.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In accordance with the public-private partnership law, each reporting agency shall establish public-private partnership regulations for the development, solicitation, evaluation, award, and delivery of public-private partnerships.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For the development of regulations, reporting agencies may:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Use internal resources;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Use the report of the Joint Legislative and Executive Commission on Public-Private Partnerships;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Seek guidance from the Maryland Subcabinet for Public-Private Partnerships; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Seek guidance from experts in the field of public-private partnerships.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2013-08-05">Effective date: August 5, 2013</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Governor's Commission for Effective Community Inclusion of Individuals with Intellectual <br/>and Developmental Disabilities</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>There is a Maryland Commission for Effective Community Inclusion of Individuals with Intellectual and Developmental Disabilities.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Membership.  The Commission consists of the following voting members:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>One member appointed by the President of the Senate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>One member appointed by the Speaker of the House of Delegates;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of the Department of Disabilities, or the Secretary’s designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Superintendent of the Maryland State Police, or the Superintendent’s designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of the Department of Health and Mental Hygiene, or the Secretary’s designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The Executive Director of the Maryland Institute for Emergency Medical Services Systems, or the Executive Director’s designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of the Department of Juvenile Services, or the Secretary’s designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of the Department of Public Safety and Correctional Services, or the Secretary’s designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>The Executive Director of the Governor’s Office of Crime Control and Prevention, or the Executive Director’s designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>The Executive Director of the Police and Correctional Training Commissions, or the Executive Director’s designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>One representative from a State’s Attorney’s office;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>One representative from a city or county police department;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>One representative from a sheriff’s department;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>One representative of a Maryland organization that advocates for individuals with intellectual and developmental disabilities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>One representative of a national organization that advocates for individuals with intellectual and developmental disabilities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>One individual, a self-advocate, with an intellectual or developmental disability; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>Up to five members, no more than three of whom shall be full-time State employees, as appointed by the Governor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The members identified in Sections B(11) through (17) shall be appointed by the Governor and shall serve at the pleasure of the Governor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Members appointed by the Governor may serve up to two consecutive, three-year terms.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Governor shall designate the Chair from among the members.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>In the event of a vacancy on the Commission, the Governor shall appoint a successor to fill the remainder of the term.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Members of the Commission may not receive any compensation for their services but may be reimbursed for reasonable expenses incurred in the performance of their duties, in accordance with the Standard State Travel Regulations, and as provided in the State budget.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The majority of voting members of the Commission shall constitute a quorum for the transaction of any business.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Commission may adopt such other procedures as may be necessary to ensure the orderly transaction of business, including the creation of committees or task forces.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Chair may, with the consent of the Commission, designate additional individuals, including interested citizens, elected officials, educators, or specialists with relevant expertise, to serve on any committee or task force.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Commission may consult with State agencies to obtain such technical assistance and advice as it deems necessary to complete its duties.  All Executive Department agencies shall cooperate with and assist the Commission in carrying out its responsibilities.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The Commission shall meet at least four times per year.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Purposes.  The Commission shall have the following objectives:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Develop and issue recommendations about the types of policies, guidelines, or best practices that Maryland should adopt regarding law enforcement officials, paramedics, and other first responders’ responses to situations involving individuals with intellectual and developmental disabilities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Develop and issue recommendations about the types of statewide training standards that Maryland should adopt to educate individuals in positions of authority, particularly those in public sector positions such as law enforcement officials, paramedics, and other first responders, about the best approaches for safely managing situations involving individuals with intellectual and developmental disabilities.  If appropriate, the recommendations should include the method by which the standards would be implemented;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Develop a coordinated, collaborative, and comprehensive strategy for State and local officials, disability advocates, and other interested parties to ensure enhanced responses to situations involving individuals with intellectual and developmental disabilities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>In developing the strategy in paragraph (3), consider all available types of assistance that would be helpful, including the expansion of Crisis Intervention Teams and Mobile Crisis Teams; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>To consider other related matters as the Commission deems necessary.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Reports and Recommendations.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Commission shall issue an initial report addressing the purposes listed in Section H.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Commission may provide recommendations in the initial report as appropriate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The initial report on the work of the Commission shall be submitted to the Governor, the President of the Senate, and the Speaker of the House of Delegates, on January 9, 2014.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Commission shall issue an annual report addressing the purposes listed in Section H to the Governor, the President of the Senate, and the Speaker of the House of Delegates, on December 3rd of each year starting in 2014, and it may issue additional reports and recommendations as appropriate.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2013-09-17">Effective date: September 17, 2013</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</container>
