<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Executive Orders</prefix>
  <num>2017</num>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Sensible Paid Leave in the Executive Branch of State Government</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The following terms shall have the meanings indicated:</text>
      <para>
        <num>a.</num>
        <text>“Paid leave” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>i.</num>
          <text>personal leave with pay that may be used for any purpose; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>ii.</num>
          <text>is provided pursuant to this Order.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>b.</num>
        <text>“Temporary employee”:</text>
        <para>
          <num>i.</num>
          <text>Except for employees of the Maryland Department of Transportation, includes a temporary employee as designated by Section 1-101 of the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsp">State Personnel and Pensions Article of the Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>ii.</num>
          <text>For employees of the Maryland Department of Transportation, includes both:</text>
          <para>
            <num>1.</num>
            <text>employees hired for a specific period not to exceed 12 months or the limits established by a special employment program; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>2.</num>
            <text>employees whose conditions of employment and compensation are specified in personal services contracts.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This Order applies to all temporary employees of the Executive Branch’s principal departments, except those who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>a.</num>
        <text>Regularly work less than 30 hours a week;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>b.</num>
        <text>Are employed for less than 120 days during a 12-month period; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>c.</num>
        <text>Are covered by a bona fide collective bargaining agreement.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>This Order may not be construed to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>a.</num>
        <text>Require a temporary employee to be compensated for unused paid leave upon or after completing his or her employment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>b.</num>
        <text>Preempt, limit, or otherwise affect any workers’ compensations benefits that may be available to the temporary employee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>c.</num>
        <text>Affect the paid leave or benefits provided to State employees, other than temporary employees, pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsp">Title 9 of the State Personnel and Pensions Article of the Code of Maryland</cite>, Section 2-103.4 of the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr">Transportation Article of the Maryland Code</cite>, or any regulations authorized by those statutes; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>d.</num>
        <text>Otherwise diminish or infringe upon any rights, responsibilities, powers, or duties conferred by <cite doc="Md. Const.">the Constitution of the State of Maryland</cite> or the Laws of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Provision of Paid Leave.</text>
      <para>
        <num>a.</num>
        <text>Temporary employees shall receive paid leave at the same wage rate as the temporary employee normally earns.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>b.</num>
        <text>After a temporary employee has worked 120 days in a 12 month period, paid leave shall accrue at a rate of one hour for every 30 hours worked, not to exceed 40 hours of paid leave per calendar year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>c.</num>
        <text>Paid leave shall begin to accrue on and after July 1, 2017, for all temporary employees otherwise qualified to receive it.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>d.</num>
        <text>Formal approval shall not be required before a temporary employee’s use of paid leave.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>e.</num>
        <text>A temporary employee may use only paid leave that has been accrued.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>f.</num>
        <text>If a temporary employee has unused paid leave at the end of a calendar year, the temporary employee may carry, up to a total of 40 hours, the balance of the paid leave into the following year.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Department of Budget and Management and Maryland Department of Transportation shall, for the temporary employees within their respective authorities and management systems, administer this Order, and shall have the power, to the fullest extent permitted by law, to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>a.</num>
        <text>Make determinations regarding the receipt and use of paid leave;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>b.</num>
        <text>Resolve other issues that may arise pursuant to this Order; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>c.</num>
        <text>Promulgate such guidelines and establish such procedures as may be necessary for the proper implementation of this Order.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Grievance Procedures. The Secretary of Budget and Management and Secretary of Transportation shall, for the temporary employees within their respective authorities and management systems, provide grievance procedures for temporary employees who dispute their receipt or use of paid leave pursuant to this Order.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>This Order may be revoked or amended by the Governor at any time.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>In the event that a challenge to any provision of this Order results in a judicial determination that such provision is contrary to law, such provision shall be deemed separable from all other provisions of this Order.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2017-05-25">Effective date: May 25, 2017</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Renewal of Executive Order 01.01.2017.02 Regarding the Heroin, Opioid, and Fentanyl Overdose Crisis Declaration of Emergency</heading>
    <text>In response to this public health emergency, the following measures are enacted:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Governor will assign an individual in the Executive Branch to the Maryland Emergency Management Agency who will be designated to administer the Governor’s authority under the Maryland Emergency Management Agency Act and operationally address the heroin, opioid, and fentanyl overdose crisis (the “Crisis”), including:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Directing the Maryland Emergency Management Agency, the Maryland State Police, the Maryland Department of Health and Mental Hygiene, the Governor’s Office of Crime Control and Prevention, and/or any other appropriate State agency or unit, including the Heroin and Opioid Emergency Task Force, the Interagency Heroin and Opioid Coordination Council, and the Opioid Operational Command Center, to assist, engage, deploy, and coordinate available resources to address the Crisis;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Coordinating the preparation of plans, programs, and infrastructure for emergency management operations of the local political subdivisions of the State, employing their social service, law enforcement, and public health functions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Instituting public information and awareness programs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Authorizing the procurement of supplies and equipment necessary to control and eliminate the Crisis; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Taking other necessary steps to address this emergency.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This declaration shall be effective immediately, shall continue for thirty (30) days, and shall expire on March 31, 2017, unless sooner terminated or extended in writing by me.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2017-05-30">Effective date: May 30, 2017</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Waste Reduction and Resource Recovery Plan for Maryland</heading>
    <text class="center">(Rescinds Executive Order <cite path="01.01.2015.01">01.01.2015.01</cite>)</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definitions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Department” means the Maryland Department of the Environment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Source reduction” means the prevention of waste through changes in the way products are designed, manufactured, packaged, purchased, and used.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Sustainable Materials Management Policy. It is the policy of the State that solid waste and recycling planning should, to the extent practicable, seek to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Minimize the environmental impacts of materials management over their entire life cycles, including from product design to production, consumption, and end-of-life management;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Conserve and extend existing in-State disposal capacity through source reduction, reuse, and recycling;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Capture and make optimal use of recovered resources, including raw materials, water, energy, and nutrients; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Work toward a system of materials management that is both environmentally and economically sustainable in the long term.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Goals and Measurement.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Stakeholder Consultation. The Department shall consult with relevant stakeholders to assess and improve the State’s methodology for tracking waste generation, recycling, and source reduction in Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Following stakeholder consultation, the Department shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Recommend to the Governor a method of obtaining business source reduction and recycling data;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Establish an improved method of quantifying and tracking the statewide recycling and source reduction rates; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Establish voluntary statewide goals to encourage continuous improvement of sustainable materials management</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Building Partnerships for Sustainable Materials Management. In order to work toward the recycling and source reduction goals established herein, the Department shall pursue the following partnerships.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Department and the Maryland Department of Commerce shall work in cooperation with local economic development agencies to identify local markets for recycled materials and provide siting, permitting, and technical assistance for innovative recycling and resource recovery businesses.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Department shall work with the Maryland Department of Agriculture to support research and demonstration of innovative technologies for recovering nutrient resources in a manner protective of water quality.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Department shall work with the Maryland Energy Administration to research and promote methods of recovering energy from waste, including anaerobic digestion.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Department shall work with the Maryland Department of Transportation Port Administration to develop technical screening criteria and guidance to support innovative reuse and beneficial uses of dredged material removed from the Port of Baltimore’s shipping channels. State agencies shall consider innovative reuse and beneficial uses of dredged material when economically feasible and in conformance with all appropriate environmental standards.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Targeted Outreach Partnerships.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Based on the results of the statewide waste sort study, the Department shall identify key recyclable materials that continue to be disposed in significant quantities in Maryland.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Department shall seek opportunities to pool resources among producers of products, State and local government agencies, and environmental education organizations to conduct targeted outreach campaigns to reduce disposal for each of the key materials identified.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>This Executive Order rescinds Executive Order <cite path="01.01.2015.01">01.01.2015.01</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2017-06-27">Effective date: June 27, 2017</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Office of Rural Broadband</heading>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Establishment.</text>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>There is an Office of Rural Broadband (the “Office”) in the Department of Information Technology.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>The administrator of the Office shall be a Rural Broadband Director (“Director”) designated by the Governor and who shall serve at the pleasure of the Governor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>II.</num>
      <text>Duties.</text>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>The Office shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>Assist and support local Maryland jurisdictions in their improvement of access to high speed internet;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>Identify and coordinate the delivery of resources to local Maryland jurisdictions for the improvement of access to high speed internet, including identification of sources of funds, such as federal funding, that can be used to expand access to high speed internet, and assist those jurisdictions in applying to receive those funds;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>3.</num>
          <text>Work with local jurisdictions and economic-development organizations to identify areas with a demand for better internet service;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>4.</num>
          <text>Identify opportunities for productive partnerships, including public-private partnerships, that enable sharing of resources and further the goal of expanding access to high speed internet;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>5.</num>
          <text>Oversee projects that increase the availability of high speed internet service, including a demonstration project in Western Maryland and a demonstration project on the Eastern Shore, both of which will be completed by April 2018;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>6.</num>
          <text>Investigate and identify new technologies that would increase the availability of high speed internet service in Maryland;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>7.</num>
          <text>Collect, analyze, and share data relevant to increasing the availability of high speed internet service in Maryland;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>8.</num>
          <text>Develop recommendations for policy, regulations, or legislation to facilitate increased availability of high speed internet access in Maryland, as well as strategies for implementing those recommendations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>9.</num>
          <text>Support and complement the assessments, evaluations, studies, and other work of the Task Force on Rural Internet, Broadband, Wireless, and Cellular Service and act consistently with the goals and purposes of the Connecting Rural Maryland Act of 2017;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>10.</num>
          <text>In the performance of these duties, coordinate with:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>the following executive departments (the “Lead Agencies”):</text>
            <para>
              <num>1)</num>
              <text>The Department of Information Technology;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>2)</num>
              <text>The Maryland Department of Housing and Community Development;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>3)</num>
              <text>The Maryland Department of Commerce;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>4)</num>
              <text>The Maryland Department of Transportation; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>5)</num>
              <text>The Maryland Department of Planning; and</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>the following stakeholders:</text>
            <para>
              <num>1)</num>
              <text>County and municipal information technology officials;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>2)</num>
              <text>The Maryland Broadband Cooperative;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>3)</num>
              <text>The Rural Maryland Council;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>4)</num>
              <text>Mid-Shore Regional Council;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>5)</num>
              <text>Tri-County Council for the Lower Eastern Shore of Maryland;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>6)</num>
              <text>Upper Shore Regional Council;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>7)</num>
              <text>Tri-County Council for Southern Maryland;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>8)</num>
              <text>Tri-County Council for Western Maryland;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>9)</num>
              <text>Appalachian Regional Commission; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>10)</num>
              <text>Any other such stakeholders that the Director deems appropriate and invites to participate; and</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>11.</num>
          <text>Submit an annual report to the Governor on the progress of the State’s efforts to increase access to high speed internet and containing any relevant recommendations.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Each Lead Agency shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>Identify and coordinate resources and technology that can be used by local jurisdictions to increase the availability of high speed internet for their residents;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>To the maximum extent permitted by law, share with one another, the Office, and local jurisdictions data relevant to increasing the availability of high speed internet for Maryland citizens; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>3.</num>
          <text>Update the Director within 45 days of the date of this Executive Order, and biannually thereafter, on its efforts to identify and coordinate resources and technology, and share data.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>Designated agency liaisons. Each of the Lead Agencies shall designate an official liaison to assist and collaborate with the Director and Office in the fulfillment of the goals of this Executive Order.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2017-06-27">Effective date: June 27, 2017</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.17</num>
    <heading>Back River Midge Reduction</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Department of Agriculture (the “Department”), in consultation with the Department of Natural Resources, may use the services of a third-party vendor to disseminate, place, or spread Bti in areas of the Back River that have been identified as “hot spots” for midges.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In accordance with applicable budgetary and procurement laws, the Department may, to eradicate the infestation of midges on the Back River, expend general funds of the State, funds appropriated in the State budget, or funds otherwise available for use in controlling insects that are a menace to the welfare of the people of the State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In accordance with applicable budgetary and procurement laws, the Department may operate, sell, buy, lease, exchange, rent, or repair any vehicle, vessel, boat, net, or other equipment necessary for the retardation, eradication, elimination, or destruction of the infestation of midges on the Back River.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Work to eradicate the infestation of midges on the Back River may be executed by the Department by contract or open account, as is deemed in the State’s best interest.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>To eradicate the infestation of midges on the Back River, the Department may enter any public or private land or property, vehicle, vessel, or aircraft in the State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Department shall, in conjunction with the Department of Natural Resources, review the effectiveness of the efforts to eradicate the infestation of midges on the Back River.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The Department shall cooperate with agencies of the United States, other State agencies, and other persons in carrying out the eradication of the infestation of midges on the Back River.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The Department may, in conjunction with the Department of Natural Resources, adopt any regulations desirable to carry out the eradication of the infestation of midges on the Back River.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2017-08-10">Effective date: August 10, 2017</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.23</num>
    <heading>Maryland Disability Employment Awareness Month</heading>
    <text class="center">(Rescinds Executive Order <cite path="01.01.2009.10">01.01.2009.10</cite>)</text>
    <para>
      <num>(1)</num>
      <text>Each State department, board, agency, authority, board, or instrumentality controlled by the Governor (an “Executive unit”) shall annually observe October as Disability Employment Awareness Month to celebrate the many and varied contributions of people with disabilities.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>The Department of Disabilities, throughout the year, but with special emphasis during Disability Employment Awareness Month, shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>a.</num>
        <text>Reinforce the value and talents people with disabilities add to Maryland’s workplaces and communities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>b.</num>
        <text>Affirm Maryland’s commitment to an inclusive community;</text>
        <text>and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>c.</num>
        <text>Enhance Maryland’s stature as a national leader in disability employment policy and practice.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(3)</num>
      <text>The Department of Disabilities’ efforts shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>a.</num>
        <text>Increasing public awareness of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>How the many skills and talents of Marylanders with disabilities benefit Maryland businesses;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>The barriers Marylanders with disabilities face in obtaining employment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>3.</num>
          <text>The untapped potential of job seekers with disabilities; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>4.</num>
          <text>The potential for those with disabilities to obtain economic independence by becoming self-employed and to contribute to the State’s economy as business owners and employers;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>b.</num>
        <text>Research and development of best practices, and ongoing collaboration with other State units, to achieve inclusive, competitive, integrated employment for Marylanders with disabilities by connecting them with employers and expanding knowledge and opportunities for self-employment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>c.</num>
        <text>Coordinating the development and maintenance of a digital resource guide for State units and local jurisdictions that details best practices to increase employment, retention, self-employment, and business ownership of those with disabilities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>d.</num>
        <text>Support for events, including those sponsored by other State units, local governments, or private or nongovernmental organizations, that highlight how businesses benefit from the skills and talents of individuals with disabilities; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>e.</num>
        <text>Provision of related information and assistance to other Executive units, the Maryland State Department of Education, the University System of Maryland, Morgan State University, Saint Mary’s College of Maryland, public community colleges, and local governments.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(4)</num>
      <text>To promote individuals with disabilities’ access to technology, the Department of Disabilities shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>a.</num>
        <text>Hold special events, including those advancing assistive technology that expands employment in community integrated settings; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>b.</num>
        <text>Recommend the designation of a State agency, entity, or staff person to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>Provide accessibility technical assistance during State procurement processes; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>Address any accessibility concerns of State employees.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(5)</num>
      <text>Executive units shall otherwise encourage the citizens they serve to, throughout the year, participate in and promote events celebrating the rights, skills, and talents of those with disabilities.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2017-10-10">Effective date: October 10, 2017</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.25</num>
    <heading>Prohibiting Discriminatory Boycotts of Israel in State Procurement</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The following words have the meanings indicated:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>“Boycott of Israel” means the termination of or refusal to transact business activities, or other actions intended to limit commercial relations, with a person or entity because of its Israeli national origin, or residence or incorporation in Israel and its territories. “Boycott of Israel” does not include actions taken:</text>
        <para>
          <num>i.</num>
          <text>that are not commercial in nature;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>ii.</num>
          <text>for business or economic reasons;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>iii.</num>
          <text>because of the specific conduct of the person or entity;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>iv.</num>
          <text>against a public or governmental entity; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>v.</num>
          <text>that are forbidden by the United States pursuant to 50 U.S.C. § 4607.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>“Business entity” means any receiver, trustee, guardian, representative, fiduciary, partnership, firm, association, corporation, sole proprietorship, or company, including any bank, credit union, broker, developer, consultant, contractor, supplier, or vendor, individually or in any combination, that has submitted a bid or proposal for, has been selected to engage in, or is engaged in providing goods or services to the State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>“Commercial relations” means a business entity’s conduct of business, and the terms and conditions by which business is transacted, with a vendor, supplier, subcontractor, or other business entity.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4.</num>
        <text>“Contract” means an agreement by or on behalf of the State for a business entity to sell or lease supplies or goods, or to provide services, to the State in return for a fee, or any other form of compensation to be paid or provided by the State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>5.</num>
        <text>“Executive agency” means a State department, agency, authority, board, or instrumentality that is controlled by the Governor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>6.</num>
        <text>“Services” includes construction, real-estate development, financial management, insurance, and professional support.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Executive agencies may not execute a procurement contract with a business entity unless it certifies, in writing when the bid is submitted or the contract is renewed, that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>It is not engaging in a boycott of Israel; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>It will, for the duration of its contractual obligations, refrain from a boycott of Israel.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>All requests for bids or proposals issued for contracts with Executive agencies shall include the text of the following certification to be completed by the bidder: “The undersigned bidder hereby certifies and agrees that the following information is correct: In preparing its bid on this project, the bidder has considered all proposals submitted from qualified, potential subcontractors and suppliers, and has not, in the solicitation, selection, or commercial treatment of any subcontractor, vendor, or supplier, refused to transact or terminated business activities, or taken other actions intended to limit commercial relations, with a person or entity on the basis of Israeli national origin, or residence or incorporation in Israel and its territories. The bidder also has not retaliated against any person or other entity for reporting such refusal, termination, or commercially limiting actions. Without limiting any other provision of the solicitation for bids for this project, it is understood and agreed that, if this certification is false, such false certification will constitute grounds for the State to reject the bid submitted by the bidder on this project, and terminate any contract awarded based on the bid.”</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>All Executive agencies shall implement this Executive Order in a manner consistent with the important public policy favoring advancement of women- and minority-owned businesses as set forth in Title 14, Subtitle 3, of the State Finance &amp; Procurement Article of the Code of Maryland and related regulations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>All Executive agencies shall implement this Executive Order in a manner that is consistent with all applicable statutes and regulations. Nothing in this Executive Order shall operate to contravene any State or federal law or to affect the State’s receipt of federal funding. F. If any provision of this Executive Order or its application to any person, entity, or circumstance is held invalid by any court of competent jurisdiction, all other provisions or applications of the Executive Order shall remain in effect to the extent possible without the invalid provision or application. To achieve this purpose, the provisions of this Executive Order are severable.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2017-10-23">Effective date: October 23, 2017</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.30</num>
    <heading>Governor's Council on Gangs and Violent Criminal Networks</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Governor’s Council on Gangs and Violent Criminal Networks.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>There is a Governor’s Council on Gangs and Violent Criminal Networks.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Council consists of the following members:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>six State’s Attorneys, appointed by the Governor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>the Governor or the Governor’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>the Secretary of the Maryland State Police;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>the Secretary of the Department of Public Safety &amp; Correctional Services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>two police chiefs of a county or Baltimore City, appointed by the Governor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>the police chief of a municipal police department, appointed by the Governor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>two sheriffs, appointed by the Governor; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>the U.S. Attorney for the District of Maryland.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>To the extent practicable, in making appointments the Governor shall ensure geographic diversity among the membership of the Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The appointed members shall serve terms of two years.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The terms of the initial appointed members shall expire as follows:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>five members on December 31, 2018; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>six members on December 31, 2019.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>An appointed member is eligible for reappointment.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>At the end of a term, an appointed member continues to serve until the member is reappointed or a successor is appointed.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>A member who is appointed or reappointed after a term has begun serves only for the remainder of the term and until a successor is appointed and qualifies.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Any member appointed to the Council by the Governor shall serve on the Council at the Governor’s pleasure.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Governor shall appoint a Chair, who shall serve for one year, or until the Governor appoints a successor, whichever is later.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A quorum of the Council consists of five members.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Council shall meet at least four times a year.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A member of the Council:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>may not receive compensation for service on the Council; but</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>is entitled to reimbursement for expenses under the standard State travel regulations, as provided in the State budget.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The Council shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>provide leadership, policy oversight and the coordination of operational strategies to collect and share relevant data related to violent crime and victimization; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>provide support and assistance to programs and entities focused on identifying, disrupting and dismantling gangs and violent criminal networks through collaboration and comprehensive data sharing, both locally and statewide, with the ultimate goal of providing the information necessary to prosecutors for the development of gang-related and racketeer influenced and corrupt organizations charges;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>establish performance measures for successful data sharing and reporting for producing measurable results.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>On or before November 1, 2018, and annually thereafter, the Council shall report to the Governor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>The Governor’s Office of Crime Control and Prevention shall provide staff for the Council.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Data — Investigations and Public Safety.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The investigative components of the Departments of Public Safety and Correctional Services, State Police, Juvenile Services, Transportation, Natural Resources, General Services, Labor, Licensing, and Regulation, and Health shall adopt a data system that will alert agencies of common targets and common investigation locations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Governor’s Office of Crime Control and Prevention shall coordinate efforts to establish and make operational the data system described in paragraph(1) of this subsection.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Maryland State Police or an entity designated by the Maryland State Police shall be responsible for maintaining and operating the data system described in paragraph(1) of this subsection.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The data system shall be available to the units of State government specified in paragraph(1) of this subsection and other such units as approved by the data owning unit(s) of State government.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The centralized data system shall be fully operational within 12 months following the date of this Executive Order.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Data — Reports and Studies.</text>
      <text>The Governor’s Office of Crime Control and Prevention is authorized to make requests to the Departments of Public Safety and Correctional Services, State Police, Juvenile Services, Transportation, Natural Resources, General Services, and Health for individual record level data and aggregate data, both without personally identifiable information, in order to develop data driven policy recommendations and prepare reports and respond to requests by the Governor and other units of State government. The requested data may include information related to crime and crime reporting, traffic stops, deaths related to law enforcement and public safety activities, adult and juvenile arrests and prosecutions, use of criminal citations, diversion programs, domestic violence, victims, gangs and criminal networks, terrorist groups, interrogation rooms, DNA and other scientific evidence, seizures and forfeitures, warrant intercepts, sentencing, prison population, prison demographics, recidivism, community supervision, programs for inmates and former inmates on community supervision, parole and release information, alternatives to incarceration, substance use disorder and mental health programs related to criminal proceedings, overdose information, and decedent data. All units of State government that receive such requests shall fully cooperate so that data is provided in a timely and efficient manner. Data collected pursuant to this Paragraph shall be kept available for the centralized data system and shall be updated at least quarterly without request.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Limitations to Data.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>This Executive Order shall only apply to any data that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>pertains to crime, criminal offenders, or criminal activity;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>pertains to law enforcement activity related to crime, criminal offenders, or criminal activity;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>is used to conduct criminal investigations; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>is used for the case management of criminal offenders.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All data sharing under this Executive Order shall comply with all legal restrictions regarding such sharing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2017-12-05">Effective date: December 5, 2017</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</container>
