<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Executive Orders</prefix>
  <num>2018</num>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Access to Services for Human Trafficking Victims and Survivors</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each State Government unit and agency shall prominently display information on the homepage of their web sites regarding the National Human Trafficking Hotline and the BeFree Textline.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Maryland Department of Information Technology (DoIT) shall assist State Government units and agencies in this endeavor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Each State Government unit and agency shall complete this task by April 1, 2018.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2018-01-05">Effective date: January 5, 2018</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Reorganization of State Government — Office of Small Business Regulatory Assistance</heading>
    <para>
      <prefix>SECTION</prefix>
      <num>1.</num>
      <text>Be it ordered by the Governor of Maryland, pursuant to Article II, Section 24, of <cite doc="Md. Const.">the Constitution of Maryland</cite>, that Sections 14-201 through 14-205 of the Economic Development Article and the Subtitle “Office of the Business Ombudsman” be repealed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <prefix>SECTION</prefix>
      <num>2.</num>
      <text>And be it further ordered, that:</text>
      <include>
        <section>
          <num>2-103.1</num>
        </section>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>In this subtitle the following words have the meanings indicated.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>“Office” means the Office of Small Business Regulatory Assistance.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>“Executive Director” means an individual appointed by the Governor who directs the activities of the Office of Small Business Regulatory Assistance and serves as a liaison between businesses, economic development organizations, communities, and federal, State, and local units and agencies.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>There is an Office of Small Business Regulatory Assistance in the Department.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The purpose of the Office is to:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(I)</num>
              <text>Assist businesses with the implementation of the Maryland Healthy Working Families Act and other labor and licensing laws and regulations;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(II)</num>
              <text>Resolve problems encountered by businesses interacting with State agencies;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(III)</num>
              <text>Facilitate responsiveness of State government to business needs;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(IV)</num>
              <text>Serve as a central clearinghouse of information for business assistance programs and services available in the State;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(V)</num>
              <text>Assist businesses by referring businesses and individuals to resources that provide the business services or assistance requested;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(VI)</num>
              <text>Provide comprehensive permit information and assistance;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(VII)</num>
              <text>Establish and maintain metrics in order to monitor the progress of the Office and report the data to the Governor and the General Assembly; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(VIII)</num>
              <text>Report and make recommendations to the Governor and the General Assembly regarding breakdowns in the delivery of economic development resources and programs, including problems encountered by businesses interacting with State agencies.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>The Office shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Assist in the adoption of regulations necessary for the implementation of the Maryland Healthy Working Families Act;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Establish, maintain, and update each year a list of the business assistance programs and services in the State, including the names, locations, web site addresses, and telephone numbers of the entities providing the programs and services;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Implement a business fairness and responsiveness service that:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(I)</num>
              <text>Resolves problems encountered by businesses with other State agencies and regional and local economic development organizations;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(II)</num>
              <text>Coordinates programs and services implemented by federal, State, and local agencies;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(III)</num>
              <text>Facilitates responsiveness of State government to business needs; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(IV)</num>
              <text>Reports to the Governor and the General Assembly regarding any breakdowns in the delivery of economic development resources and programs;</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Develop and maintain a program to provide comprehensive information to the public regarding permits required for business initiatives, projects, and activities;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Establish and implement procedures to assist permit applicants who have encountered difficulties in obtaining timely and efficient permit review; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>Administer and oversee the State customer service and business development efforts training program under subsection (D) of this section.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(D)</num>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>There is a State Customer Service and Business Development Efforts Training Program.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The purpose of the Program is to increase the responsiveness of and improve customer service provided by State agencies to businesses and customers in the State.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>The Office shall develop State customer service standards that incorporate best practices for providing excellent customer service.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Each agency shall:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(I)</num>
              <text>Create a customer service improvement plan;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(II)</num>
              <text>Review and incorporate the Office’s State customer service standards in the agency’s customer service improvement plan;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(III)</num>
              <text>Develop and conduct customer service training for each employee who interacts with businesses and members of the public on a regular basis;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(IV)</num>
              <text>Adopt and distribute a standard customer service satisfaction survey for each person the agency serves;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(V)</num>
              <text>Establish an incentive or recognition program for employees who provide excellent customer service; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(VI)</num>
              <text>Report each year on:</text>
              <para>
                <num>1.</num>
                <text>The training provided to employees, including:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>A.</num>
                  <text>The number of trainings;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>B.</num>
                  <text>The frequency of trainings; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>C.</num>
                  <text>The specific subject of each training;</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>2.</num>
                <text>The responses received from customer service satisfaction surveys distributed under Paragraph (IV) of this subsection;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>3.</num>
                <text>The progress of the agency’s customer service, including the metrics the agency uses to assess the customer service of the agency; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>4.</num>
                <text>The agency’s measurable goals for continuing to improve customer service for the upcoming year.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Each year the Office shall evaluate the State Customer Service and Business Development Efforts Training Program and make recommendations regarding the Program.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(E)</num>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Each year, the Office shall submit a report to the Governor and, in accordance with §2–1246 of the State Government Article, the standing committees of the General Assembly having jurisdiction over economic development matters.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The report shall contain:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(I)</num>
              <text>Information regarding the performance of the Office, including data indicating the effectiveness of programs and procedures regarding permitting;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(II)</num>
              <text>Data specifying the number of businesses and individuals that have contacted the Office or used the services of the Office; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(III)</num>
              <text>Recommendations regarding improvements to existing laws relating to economic development.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>The report shall include information and recommendations developed for the State Customer Service and Business Development Efforts Training Program under Subsection (D) of this section.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(F)</num>
          <text>The Governor shall include funds in the State budget to implement this subtitle, including funds to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Employ a full–time Executive Director; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Operate and maintain an office.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </include>
    </para>
    <para>
      <prefix>SECTION</prefix>
      <num>3.</num>
      <text>And be it further ordered, that all persons who, as of the effective date of this Order, are employed in the Office of Business Ombudsman in the Office of the Governor are hereby transferred to the Office of Small Business Regulatory Assistance in the Department of Labor, Licensing, and Regulation without any change or loss of rights or status, and shall retain their merit system and retirement system status.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <prefix>SECTION</prefix>
      <num>4.</num>
      <text>And be it further ordered, that any transaction affected by or arising from any statute here amended, repealed, or transferred, and validly entered into before the effective date of this Order and every right, duty, or interest flowing from it remains valid after the effective date and may be terminated, completed, consummated, or enforced pursuant to law.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <prefix>SECTION</prefix>
      <num>5.</num>
      <text>And be it further ordered, that all rules and regulations, proposed rules and regulations, standards and guidelines, proposed standards and guidelines, orders and other directives, forms, plans, memberships, special funds, appropriations, grants, applications for grants, contracts, property, investigations, administrative and judicial proceedings, rights to sue and be sued, and all other duties and responsibilities associated with those functions transferred by this Order shall continue in effect under the Office of Small Business Regulatory Assistance upon transfer to the Department of Labor, Licensing, and Regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <prefix>SECTION</prefix>
      <num>6.</num>
      <text>And be it further ordered, that any unexpended appropriation for the purpose of financing the Office of the Business Ombudsman shall be transferred by approved budget amendment to the Department of Labor, Licensing, and Regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <prefix>SECTION</prefix>
      <num>7.</num>
      <text>And be it further ordered, that this Executive Order shall become effective and have the force of law on this 15th day of January, 2018, unless specifically disapproved within 50 days after submission, by a Resolution of Disapproval concurred in by a majority vote of all members of either House of the General Assembly.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2018-01-15">Effective date: January 15, 2018</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Gubernatorial Considerations in Parole of Inmates Serving Terms of Life Imprisonment</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In deciding whether to approve or disapprove a decision of the Maryland Parole Commission to grant parole to an inmate serving a term of life imprisonment, the Governor shall assess and consider, among other lawful factors deemed relevant by the Governor, the same factors and information assessed by the Maryland Parole Commission as provided by the Maryland Parole Commission’s governing statutes and regulations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the Governor disapproves parole for an inmate serving a term of life imprisonment, the Governor shall issue a written decision delivered to the Maryland Parole Commission confirming that the Governor has considered, among other relevant and lawful factors and information, the same factors and information assessed by the Maryland Parole Commission as provided by its governing statutes and regulations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Additional factors and information for juvenile offenders. In deciding whether to approve or disapprove a decision of the Maryland Parole Commission to grant parole to an inmate serving a term of life imprisonment with the possibility of parole for a crime committed before he or she reached 18 years of age (a “juvenile offender”), the Governor shall consider, in addition to other lawful factors deemed relevant by the Governor and the factors and information assessed by the Maryland Parole Commission as provided by the Maryland Parole Commission’s governing statutes and regulations:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <para>
          <num>i.</num>
          <text>The juvenile offender’s age at the time the crime was committed and the lesser culpability of juvenile offenders as compared to adult offenders;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>ii.</num>
          <text>The degree to which the juvenile offender has demonstrated maturity since the commission of the crime; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>iii.</num>
          <text>The degree to which the juvenile offender has demonstrated rehabilitation since the commission of the crime.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the Governor disapproves parole for a juvenile offender, the Governor shall issue a written decision delivered to the Maryland Parole Commission that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>i.</num>
          <text>confirms that the Governor has considered the applicable statutory and regulatory factors and information and the factors and information set forth in this executive order; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>ii.</num>
          <text>states reasons supporting the decision to disapprove parole.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>This executive order may not be construed to have any retroactive effect on any decision or recommendation of the Maryland Parole Commission or any decision of the Governor, made prior to the effective date of this order, to approve, disapprove, grant, deny, or modify the conditions of a parole.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2018-02-09">Effective date: February 9, 2018</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Active-Assailant Incident Preparedness and Coordination</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Executive Branch units subject to the supervision and direction of the Governor (“Executive agencies”), and persons who deal with or are under the jurisdiction of those units, shall systematically identify, assess, prepare for, prevent, protect from, respond to, recover from, and mitigate the risk and impacts of active-assailant incidents.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Each Executive agency shall participate in a coordinated active-assailant initiative and share threat information between and among all sectors.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Each Executive agency shall develop, review, or update internal plans, policies, and procedures related to active-assailant incidents.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Each Executive agency, and persons who deal with or are under the jurisdiction of each agency, shall develop, plan, and collaborate for active-assailant training relevant to each agency’s respective area of responsibility, involving public and nongovernmental participants when appropriate and feasible.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Using a “whole community” approach, Executive-agency public-safety officials shall conduct annual assessments to determine the need for mitigation, planning, and training appropriate for their agency’s jurisdiction.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Maryland’s public educational institutions shall be encouraged to share and coordinate their emergency plans with Executive-agency law enforcement, emergency management officials, and emergency responders.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Maryland’s private and nonpublic educational institutions shall be encouraged to share and coordinate their emergency plans with Executive-agency law enforcement, emergency management officials, and emergency responders.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The Maryland State Police shall seek to maintain its position as co-chair and member of the Maryland Active Assailant Interdisciplinary Work Group and use that role to promote the purposes and objectives of this Executive Order.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>The following Executive agencies shall seek to obtain or maintain membership in the Maryland Active Assailant Interdisciplinary Work Group and use that role to promote the purposes and objectives of this Executive Order:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>Governor’s Office of Homeland Security;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>Maryland Department of Health;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>Governor’s Office of Crime Control &amp; Prevention of Maryland;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4.</num>
        <text>Maryland Fire-Rescue Education and Training Commission; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>5.</num>
        <text>Maryland Emergency Management Agency.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>The Maryland Active Assailant Interdisciplinary Work Group shall be encouraged to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>Update the State’s existing “Guidance to First Responders for the Active Assailant Incident” (the “Active-Assailant Guidance”), issued October 2, 2014, to incorporate protocols for prevention, protection, information-sharing, community preparedness, outreach, and education;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>Continue to monitor best practices and revise the Active-Assailant Guidance as needed to ensure Maryland remains prepared and resilient;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>Include in its membership subject matter experts from State and federal departments and agencies including, but not limited to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>i.</num>
          <text>Maryland Center for School Safety;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>ii.</num>
          <text>Maryland State Department of Education;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>iii.</num>
          <text>Maryland Higher Education Commission;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>iv.</num>
          <text>U.S. Department of Homeland Security;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>v.</num>
          <text>U.S. Secret Service; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>vi.</num>
          <text>U.S. Department of Defense; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4.</num>
        <text>Meet at least quarterly to identify, update, and share best practices and current activities, and maintain the Active-Assailant Guidance.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>The Maryland Emergency Management Agency shall provide leadership, policy oversight, support, and assistance to Executive agencies and other applicable persons in their efforts to comply with this Executive Order.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2018-02-28">Effective date: February 28, 2018</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.17</num>
    <heading>Student Loan Repayment Benefits to Relieve State Workforce Shortages</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Establishment.</text>
      <text>There shall be State employee loan repayment benefits for eligible employees working in critical workforce shortage areas for units in the State Personnel Management System and the Transportation Services Human Resources System.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Eligibility.</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>Applicants for the benefits must:</text>
        <para>
          <num>i.</num>
          <text>work in a critical workforce shortage area, as designated by the Secretary; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>ii.</num>
          <text>have remained in the service of the employing unit for a duration established by the Secretary.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>A participating employee whose employment is terminated is not eligible to receive further benefits.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Administration.</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>The Secretary of the Department of Budget and Management shall administer the benefits to enhance the recruitment and retention of employees in critical workforce shortage areas.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>The benefits shall be administered centrally by the Department of Budget and Management’s Office of Personnel Services and Benefits.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>The Secretary may delegate the administration of the benefits for the Transportation Services Human Resources System to the Secretary of the Department of Transportation or the Secretary’s designee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4.</num>
        <text>By January 1, 2019, the Secretary shall establish guidelines for the administration of the benefits.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2018-06-16">Effective date: June 16, 2018</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.19</num>
    <heading>Statewide Human Trafficking Response Director</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Director.</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>There is a Statewide Human Trafficking Response Director (the “Director”) at the Governor’s Office of Crime Control and Prevention (the “Office”).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>The Director shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>Serve as the Governor’s coordinator for human trafficking issues and provide information and policy guidance to the Governor, the Governor’s Cabinet, and the executive director of the Office;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>Collaborate with State units, local governments and departments of social services, child advocacy centers and other nonprofit entities, law enforcement agencies, and other appropriate parties identified by the Director to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>1)</num>
            <text>Promote statewide coordination of:</text>
            <para>
              <num>a)</num>
              <text>Supportive services and resources for victims of human trafficking;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>b)</num>
              <text>Law enforcement responses to human trafficking;</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>2)</num>
            <text>Collect, maintain, and disseminate to stakeholders information about human trafficking and related supportive services in Maryland;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>3)</num>
            <text>Map current local supportive services and resources that provide care to victims of human trafficking; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>4)</num>
            <text>Establish statewide best practices for serving victims of human trafficking;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c.</num>
          <text>Monitor and pursue, on behalf of the State, federal funding for efforts to combat human trafficking;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>d.</num>
          <text>Serve as the Governor’s liaison to the Maryland Human Trafficking Task Force; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>e.</num>
          <text>Serve as the Governor’s liaison to the Crime Research and Innovation Center at the University of Maryland to assist its efforts to provide research to the State about human trafficking, including best practices in collecting data to identify victims of human trafficking.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>By December 1 of each year, the Director shall provide to the Governor a report on the status of the Director’s work including:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>Progress made in establishing statewide best practices for serving victims of human trafficking;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>A summary of State and federal funding available to serve and support victims of human trafficking;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>An update on the work of the Crime Research and Innovation Center at the University of Maryland related to human trafficking; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4.</num>
        <text>Recommendations for administrative, regulatory, or statutory changes that would further the State’s efforts to address human trafficking.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Office shall dedicate a portion of its funding to serve victims of human trafficking.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2018-08-09">Effective date: August 9, 2018</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.26</num>
    <heading>Governor's Commission on Suicide Prevention</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Governor's Commission on Suicide Prevention shall continue and be constituted as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>The Commission consists of the following Executive Branch members, with all designees approved by the Secretary of Health:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>The Deputy Secretary for Behavioral Health or the Deputy Secretary’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>The Deputy Secretary for Public Health Services or the Deputy Secretary’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c.</num>
          <text>The Secretary of the Department of Juvenile Services or the Secretary’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>d.</num>
          <text>The Secretary of the Department of Public Safety and Correctional Services or the Secretary’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>e.</num>
          <text>The Secretary of the Department of Aging or the Secretary’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>f.</num>
          <text>The Secretary of the Department of Veterans Affairs or the Secretary’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>g.</num>
          <text>The Executive Director of the Governor’s Office for Children or the Executive Director’s designee; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>h.</num>
          <text>The Secretary of the Department of Disabilities or the Secretary’s designee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>The State Superintendent of Schools shall be invited to be an ex officio member or submit a designee as an ex officio member.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>The President of the Maryland Senate and Speaker of the Maryland House of Delegates shall each be invited to appoint a member of their respective chambers to serve as an ex officio member.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4.</num>
        <text>The following organizations shall also be invited to designate a representative as an ex officio member:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>The Mental Health Association of Maryland;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>The National Organization for People of Color Against Suicide; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c.</num>
          <text>The Maryland Addictions Directors Council.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>5.</num>
        <text>The Maryland Association of County Health Officials shall be invited to select a local health officer to serve as an ex officio member.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>6.</num>
        <text>Governor’s Appointments.</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>The following members shall be appointed by the Governor for no more than two consecutive four-year terms:</text>
          <para>
            <num>i.</num>
            <text>One representative of the faith community;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>ii.</num>
            <text>One representative of the academic community;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>iii.</num>
            <text>One representative of a suicide-prevention group;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>iv.</num>
            <text>One active or former member of the U.S. Armed Forces;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>v.</num>
            <text>One member of either police, local corrections, or fire and rescue services;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>vi.</num>
            <text>One member of the LGBTQ community;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>vii.</num>
            <text>One young adult between the ages of 18 and 25;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>viii.</num>
            <text>One representative of the substance-abuse recovery community;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>ix.</num>
            <text>One survivor of a suicide attempt;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>x.</num>
            <text>One family member of an individual who died by suicide;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>xi.</num>
            <text>One representative of the American Indian community;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>xii.</num>
            <text>One representative of the Asian Pacific American community; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>xiii.</num>
            <text>One representative of the Hispanic or Latino community.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>High-School Member.</text>
          <para>
            <num>i.</num>
            <text>The Governor shall appoint a high-school student in his or her junior or senior year as a member.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>ii.</num>
            <text>The High-School Member is appointed for a term of one academic year.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>iii.</num>
            <text>The High-School Member may be reappointed, while he or she is still in high school, to a second term ending in the July following his or her graduation.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c.</num>
          <text>The Governor’s Appointments serve at the Governor’s pleasure.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>d.</num>
          <text>In the event of a vacancy among the Governor’s Appointments, the Governor shall appoint a successor to fill the remainder of the term.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>7.</num>
        <text>Chair and Vice-Chair.</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>The Governor shall designate a Chair from among the members.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>The Chair serves in that position at the pleasure of the Governor.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c.</num>
          <text>The Commission may designate a Vice Chair from the remaining membership.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Commission shall be staffed by the Maryland Department of Health as determined by the Secretary of Health.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Commission shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>Assess suicide’s economic and social costs, and impact on the health and wellbeing of Maryland citizens;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>Establish a list of existing support systems for survivors, attempters, and their families;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>Develop a comprehensive, coordinated, and strategic plan for suicide prevention, intervention, and post-suicide services across the State;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4.</num>
        <text>Identify the resources needed to adequately provide those services; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>5.</num>
        <text>Promote the delivery of those services by local and State agencies through collaborative efforts that ensure effective and efficient use of local and State resources.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>State Plan.</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>The Commission shall prepare a two-year plan that establishes, for the organization, delivery, and funding of suicide prevention, intervention, and post-suicide services:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>Emerging needs;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>Priorities and strategies;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c.</num>
          <text>Promising practices and programs;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>d.</num>
          <text>Recommendations for coordination and collaboration among State agencies; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>e.</num>
          <text>Training.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>The plan shall be developed in consideration of the priorities and strategies in plans established by local jurisdictions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>The plan shall be submitted to the Governor by December 1, 2018, and biennially thereafter, with interim updates provided as deemed appropriate.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Meetings.</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>The Commission shall meet at least four times a year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>The Chair may schedule additional work sessions as necessary.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>A majority of members of the Commission shall constitute a quorum for the transaction of any business.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Commission may adopt such procedures as may be necessary to ensure the orderly transaction of business, including the creation of committees or task forces.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Members of the Commission may not receive any compensation for their services, but may be reimbursed for reasonable expenses incurred in the performance of their duties, in accordance with the Standard State Travel Regulations and as provided in the State budget.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The Chair may, with the consent of the Commission, designate additional individuals — including interested citizens, educators, or specialists with relevant expertise — to serve on any committee or task force.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>The Commission may consult with State units to obtain technical assistance and advice as it deems necessary to fulfill its duties.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>All Executive Branch units subject to the supervision and direction of the Governor shall cooperate with and assist the Commission in fulfilling its duties.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2018-10-11">Effective date: October 11, 2018</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</container>
