<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Executive Orders</prefix>
  <num>2019</num>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Maryland Opportunity Zone Leadership Task Force</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>There is a Maryland Opportunity Zone Leadership Task Force (the “Task Force”).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Membership.</text>
      <para>
        <num>1)</num>
        <text>The Task Force shall consist of the following voting members:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a)</num>
          <text>The Lieutenant Governor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of the Department of Housing and Community Development, or the Secretary’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of the Department of Commerce, or the Secretary’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>d)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of the Department of Labor, Licensing, and Regulation, or the Secretary’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>e)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of the Department of Planning, or the Secretary’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>f)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of the Maryland Department of Transportation, or the Secretary’s designee; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>g)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of the Maryland Department of Human Resources, or the Secretary’s designee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2)</num>
        <text>The following shall be invited to be, and shall be upon acceptance, voting members of the Task Force:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a)</num>
          <text>The Superintendent of the Maryland State Department of Education, or the Superintendent’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of the Maryland Higher Education Commission, or the Secretary’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c)</num>
          <text>The Executive Director of the Maryland Stadium Authority, or the Executive Director’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>d)</num>
          <text>The Chancellor of the University System of Maryland, or the Chancellor’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>e)</num>
          <text>An appointee of the Maryland Association of Counties;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>f)</num>
          <text>An appointee of the Maryland Municipal League;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>g)</num>
          <text>An appointee of the Maryland Economic Development Corporation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>h)</num>
          <text>An appointee of the Maryland Technology Development Corporation; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>i)</num>
          <text>An appointee of the Maryland Association of Community Colleges.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3)</num>
        <text>The Governor shall designate the Chair from among the members.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4)</num>
        <text>Members of the Task Force serve at the pleasure of the Governor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>5)</num>
        <text>A vacancy shall be filled in the same manner that the initial appointments are made.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>1)</num>
        <text>The majority of voting members of the Task Force shall constitute a quorum for the transaction of any business.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2)</num>
        <text>The Task Force shall hold publicly announced meetings at such times and such places as it deems necessary. The meetings shall be accessible to the general public in accordance with the Maryland Open Meetings Act or other applicable law.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3)</num>
        <text>The Task Force may adopt such other procedures as may be necessary to ensure the orderly transaction of business, including the creation of committees.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4)</num>
        <text>The Chair may, with the consent of the Task Force, designate additional individuals, including interested citizens, elected officials, educators, or specialists with relevant expertise, to serve on any committee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>5)</num>
        <text>The Task Force may consult with the principal departments of the Executive Branch of the State government to obtain such technical assistance and advice as it deems necessary to complete its duties.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Duties. The Task Force shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1)</num>
        <text>Advise the Governor on all matters assigned to the Task Force and be responsible for carrying out the Governor’s policies on those matters;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2)</num>
        <text>Conduct regional summits in various parts of the State, including the Eastern Shore, Southern Maryland, Western Maryland, and Central Maryland, to enable citizens to share information, market prospectuses, and solicit and offer opportunities and possibilities for Opportunity Zone investment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3)</num>
        <text>Provide an electronic portal for citizens to submit their comments to the Task Force;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4)</num>
        <text>Develop a clearinghouse for local government, developers, and other interested parties to learn of and access Opportunity Zone resources;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>5)</num>
        <text>Develop a community marketing strategy and an economic-development policy brief for Opportunity Zones;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>6)</num>
        <text>Develop an “Opportunity Plan” that sets broad goals for Opportunity Zones aligned with State economies, priorities, and culture;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>7)</num>
        <text>Outline development of Opportunity Zones with a multi-year timeline that is subject to measurement and assessment on an annual basis;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>8)</num>
        <text>Provide recommendations for legislation to enhance Opportunity Zone incentives;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>9)</num>
        <text>Devise innovative methods for incorporating Opportunity Zones into existing State programs, including, but not limited to, More Jobs for Marylanders and EARN Maryland; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>10)</num>
        <text>Coordinate participation with local governments to best align local resources with Opportunity Zone investment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Units of State and local government shall retain all budgeting and funding authority to undertake initiatives in Opportunity Zones.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Reports and Recommendations.</text>
      <para>
        <num>1)</num>
        <text>The Task Force shall summarize its progress in fulfilling its duties in a report submitted to the Governor, the President of the Maryland Senate, and the Speaker of the Maryland House of Delegates, no later than October 1, 2019.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2)</num>
        <text>The Task Force may issue additional reports as directed by the Governor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2019-01-03">Effective date: January 3, 2019</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>(Amends Executive Order 01.01.2019.02)</heading>
    <text class="center">Commission to Study Mental and Behavioral Health in Maryland</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Establishment. There is a Governor’s Commission to Study Mental and Behavioral Health in Maryland (the “Commission”).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Membership.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Commission shall consist of the following members:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Lieutenant Governor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Two appointees of the President of the Maryland Senate;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Two appointees of the Speaker of the Maryland House of Delegates;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A representative of the Judicial system of the State, appointed by the Chief Judge of the Court of Appeals;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of the Department of Health, or the Secretary’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The Deputy Secretary for Behavioral Health, or the Secretary’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of the State Police, or the Secretary’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Public Safety and Correctional Services, or the Secretary’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Human Services, or the Secretary’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>The Maryland Insurance Commissioner, or the Commissioner’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>The Executive Director of the Opioid Operational Command Center;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Disabilities, or the Secretary’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>The State Superintendent of Schools, or the Superintendent’s designee; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(n)</num>
          <text>Six public members, to be appointed by the Governor, representing a range of experience related to mental health, including lived experiences, clinical expertise, work within the criminal justice system, and the provision of social services.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The members serve at the pleasure of the Governor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Staff members from the Offices of the Governor and Lieutenant Governor, the Governor’s Office of Crime Control and Prevention, and the Maryland Department of Health will also be regular participants.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Chair may also invite other units of State or U.S. government, including law enforcement agencies, to designate representatives for participation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Duties. The Commission shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Advise and assist the Governor in improving access to a continuum of mental-health services across the State;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Consider the findings of the Maryland Behavioral Health Advisory Council 2017 Strategic Plan: 24/7 Crisis Walk-in and Mobile Crisis Team Services;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Conduct regional summits in various parts of the State to study how mental illness may impact parts of the State differently;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Submit an interim report no later than six months from the date of this Executive Order on its findings relating to access to mental-health treatment services in the State; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Submit an annual report to the Governor on or before December 31, that includes, but is not limited to, recommendations for policy, regulations, or legislation to address the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Improving the statewide, comprehensive crisis response system; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Ensuring parity of resources to meet mental-health needs.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Lieutenant Governor shall be Chair of the Commission. The Chair shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Oversee the implementation of this Executive Order and the work of the Commission;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Determine the Commission’s agenda; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Identify additional support needs of the Commission.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Commission shall convene within 90 days of this Executive Order and meet as frequently as necessary to satisfy the deadlines established herein.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A majority of the Commission shall constitute a quorum for the transaction of any business.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Commission may adopt other procedures as necessary to ensure the orderly transaction of business.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2019-05-28">Effective date: May 28, 2019</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Maryland Cyber Defense Initiative</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>There is a Maryland Cyber Defense Initiative to strengthen the State’s ability to manage the consequences of a cybersecurity incident.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>State Chief Information Security Officer.</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>There is a State Chief Information Security Officer (“SCISO”).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>The SCISO shall be appointed by, and serve at the pleasure of, the Governor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>The SCISO shall report to, and be supervised by, the Secretary of Information Technology and serve as the Department of Information Technology (“DoIT”) chief information security officer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4.</num>
        <text>The SCISO shall provide cybersecurity advice, recommendations, and consultation to the Governor when requested.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Office of Security Management.</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>There is an Office of Security Management within DoIT that is managed and supervised by the SCISO.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>The Office is responsible for the direction, coordination, and implementation of the overall cybersecurity strategy and policy for the Executive Branch of State government (“State Government”), including, but not limited to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>i.</num>
          <text>Standards to categorize all information and information systems collected or maintained by or on behalf of each unit of State Government;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>ii.</num>
          <text>Guidelines governing the types of information and information systems to be included in each category;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>iii.</num>
          <text>Security requirements (i.e., management, operational, and technical controls) for information and information systems in each category;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>iv.</num>
          <text>Assessing the categorization of systems and data, and the associated implementation of information security requirements;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>v.</num>
          <text>Determining whether a system should be allowed to continue to operate or be connected to the network created pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|3A-404">§3A-404 of the State Finance and Procurement Article of the Code of Maryland</cite> if the SCISO concludes that there are security vulnerabilities or deficiencies in the implementation of information security requirements;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>vi.</num>
          <text>Management of security awareness training for all appropriate employees of State Government;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>vii.</num>
          <text>Assisting in the development of data management, data governance, and data specification standards to promote standardization and reduce risk; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>viii.</num>
          <text>Assisting in the development of a digital identity standard and specification applicable to all parties communicating, interacting, or conducting business with or on behalf of State Government.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Maryland Cybersecurity Coordinating Council.</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>There is a Maryland Cybersecurity Coordinating Council (“MCCC”).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>The MCCC shall provide advice and recommendations to the SCISO about:</text>
        <para>
          <num>i.</num>
          <text>The strategy and implementation of cybersecurity initiatives and recommendations; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>ii.</num>
          <text>Building and sustaining the State’s capability to identify, mitigate, and detect cybersecurity risk, and respond to and recover from cybersecurity-related incidents.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>Each of the following State officials, or a senior staff member designated by each official, shall be a member of the MCCC:</text>
        <para>
          <num>i.</num>
          <text>The Director of the Governor’s Office of Homeland Security;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>ii.</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Budget and Management;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>iii.</num>
          <text>The Secretary of General Services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>iv.</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Human Services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>v.</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Public Safety and Correctional Services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>vi.</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Health;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>vii.</num>
          <text>The Adjutant General;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>viii.</num>
          <text>The Director of the Maryland Emergency Management Agency;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>ix.</num>
          <text>The Superintendent of State Police; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>x.</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Transportation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4.</num>
        <text>The Chair of the MCCC is the SCISO.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>5.</num>
        <text>The MCCC shall meet at least quarterly upon request of the Chair.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>6.</num>
        <text>The MCCC may consult with outside experts, including but not limited to experts in the private sector, government agencies, and institutions of higher education.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2019-06-18">Effective date: June 18, 2019</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</container>
