<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Executive Orders</prefix>
  <num>2023</num>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>(Rescinds Executive Order 01.01.2015.08)</heading>
    <text class="center">Standards of Conduct for Executive Branch Employees</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Employees shall exhibit exemplary conduct and use honest efforts in the performance of their duties.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An employee shall not, except as permitted by applicable law or regulation, solicit, or accept any gift or other item of monetary value from any person or entity seeking official action from, doing business with, or conducting activities regulated by the employee’s agency, or whose interests may be substantially affected by the performance or nonperformance of the employee’s duties.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Employees shall not hold financial interests that conflict with the conscientious performance of duty.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Employees shall not knowingly make unauthorized commitments or promises of any kind purporting to bind the Government.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Employees shall not engage in financial transactions using nonpublic Government information or allow the improper use of such information to further any private interest.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Employees shall act impartially in all their affairs and shall not give preferential treatment to any private organization or individual.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Employees shall protect and conserve State property and shall not use it for other than authorized activities.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Employees shall not engage in outside employment or activities, including seeking or negotiating for employment, which conflict with official Government duties and responsibilities.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Employees shall disclose waste, fraud, abuse, and corruption to the appropriate authorities.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Employees shall satisfy in good faith their obligations as citizens, including all just financial obligations, including federal, State, or local taxes that are imposed by law.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Consistent with all applicable laws, all employees shall be treated with dignity and respect and shall not be discriminated against on the basis of race, color, creed, religion, ancestry, national origin, sex, age, marital status, sexual orientation, gender identity or expression, disability, or genetic information.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Employees shall endeavor to avoid any actions creating the appearance that they are violating applicable law or the ethical standards in applicable regulations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>Employees shall conduct intra-agency and interagency relations with civility, collaboration, and cooperation. These same principals shall apply to interactions with officials and employees of the legislative and judicial branches.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>Upon leaving State service, executive branch employees shall be bound by the restrictions of the Annotated Code of Maryland, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|5-504">General Provisions §5-504, </cite>with respect to lobbying and other forms of representation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>All departments and agencies of the State shall immediately refer to the Principal Counsel or the Assistant Attorney General of the department or agency or to the Deputy Attorney General with supervisory responsibility for the Attorney General’s Criminal Investigations Division, any instance of possible criminal or unethical conduct by any employee or contractor of this State, for such action as the Office of the Attorney General deems appropriate.  All departments and agencies shall also immediately advise the Chief Legal Counsel to the Governor of any such referrals.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>P.</num>
      <text>All departments and agencies shall require each employee to report to the Secretary or Director of such department or agency as to any arrest of an employee and as to each legal proceeding in which an employee is involved, as a party or otherwise, if the arrest or legal proceeding affects, or reflects on, the employee’s job fitness or performance.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>Q.</num>
      <text>Consistent with all applicable substantive and procedural laws, violations of this Executive Order are grounds for employee disciplinary action, including termination from State employment..</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2023-01-19">Effective date: January 19, 2023</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Reorganization of State Government — The Department of Service and Civic Innovation</heading>
    <para>
      <prefix>SECTION</prefix>
      <num>1.</num>
      <text>Be it ordered by the Governor of Maryland, pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Const." path="II|§24">Article II, Section 24 of the Constitution of Maryland</cite>, that the laws of Maryland read as follows:</text>
      <include>
        <container name="education">
          <prefix>Article</prefix>
          <heading>Education</heading>
          <section>
            <num>15–106.9.</num>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>For in–State tuition purposes, a public senior higher education institution shall waive the in–State residency requirement for an individual who has completed:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>All service hours for an AmeriCorps Program in the State; or</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>A service program under the Maryland Corps Program under Title 9, Subtitle 28 of the State Government article.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
          </section>
        </container>
        <container name="state-government">
          <prefix>Article</prefix>
          <heading>State Government</heading>
          <section>
            <num>8–201.</num>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>The Executive Branch of the State government shall have not more than 21 principal departments, each of which shall embrace a broad, functional area of that Branch.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>The principal departments of the Executive Branch of the State government are:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Aging;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Agriculture;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>Budget and Management;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>Commerce;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(5)</num>
                <text>Disabilities;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(6)</num>
                <text>Emergency Management;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(7)</num>
                <text>the Environment;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(8)</num>
                <text>General Services;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(9)</num>
                <text>Health;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(10)</num>
                <text>Housing and Community Development;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(11)</num>
                <text>Human Services;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(12)</num>
                <text>Information Technology;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(13)</num>
                <text>Juvenile Services;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(14)</num>
                <text>Labor;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(15)</num>
                <text>Natural Resources;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(16)</num>
                <text>Planning;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(17)</num>
                <text>Public Safety and Correctional Services;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(18)</num>
                <text>Service and Civic Innovation;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(19)</num>
                <text>State Police;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(20)</num>
                <text>Transportation; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(21)</num>
                <text>Veterans Affairs.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
          </section>
        </container>
        <container>
          <prefix>Title</prefix>
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Miscellaneous Agencies</heading>
          <container>
            <prefix>SUBTITLE</prefix>
            <num>28.</num>
            <heading>DEPARTMENT OF SERVICE AND CIVIC INNOVATION.</heading>
            <container>
              <prefix>PART</prefix>
              <num>I.</num>
              <heading>GENERAL PROVISIONS</heading>
              <section>
                <num>9-2801.</num>
                <para>
                  <num>(A)</num>
                  <text>In this subtitle the following words have the meanings indicated.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(B)</num>
                  <text>“Department” means the Department of Service and Innovation.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(C)</num>
                  <text>“Secretary” means the Secretary of Service and Innovation.</text>
                </para>
              </section>
              <section>
                <num>9-2802.</num>
                <para>
                  <num>(A)</num>
                  <text>There is a Department of Service and Civic Innovation.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(B)</num>
                  <text>The purpose of the Department is to promote service and volunteerism in the State.</text>
                </para>
              </section>
              <section>
                <num>9-2803.</num>
                <para>
                  <num>(A)</num>
                  <text>The Secretary of Service and Civic Innovation shall be appointed by the Governor with the advice and consent of the Senate.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(B)</num>
                  <text>The Secretary is the head of the Department and a member of the Governor’s Executive Council.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(C)</num>
                  <text>The Secretary shall take the oath required by Article I, §9 of the Constitution before taking office.</text>
                </para>
              </section>
              <section>
                <num>9-2804.</num>
                <para>
                  <num>(A)</num>
                  <text>The Secretary serves at the pleasure of the Governor and is responsible directly to the Governor.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(B)</num>
                  <text>The Secretary shall advise the Governor on all matters assigned to the Department and is responsible for carrying out the Governor’s policies on those matters.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(C)</num>
                  <text>The Secretary is responsible for the operation of the Department and shall establish guidelines and procedures to promote the orderly and efficient operation of the Department.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(D)</num>
                  <text>The Secretary may establish, reorganize, or abolish areas of responsibility in the Department as necessary to fulfill the duties assigned to the Secretary.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(E)</num>
                  <text>The Secretary is entitled to the compensation provided in the State Budget.</text>
                </para>
              </section>
              <section>
                <num>9-2805.</num>
                <para>
                  <num>(A)</num>
                  <text>The Secretary shall:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(1)</num>
                    <text>Promote service and volunteerism in the State by partnering with the federal government, local governments, and nongovernmental entities to fulfill the purposes of this subtitle; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(2)</num>
                    <text>Identify and expand initiatives to increase service and volunteerism in the State to create opportunities and strengthen communities.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(B)</num>
                  <text>The Secretary may adopt regulations to carry out the provisions of law that are within the jurisdiction of the Secretary.</text>
                </para>
              </section>
              <section>
                <num>9-2806.</num>
                <text>The Department shall:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>Promote the use of volunteers in State and local government, businesses, and nonprofit entities;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>Coordinate and oversee the activities of the Maryland Corps Program, Governor’s Commission of Service and Volunteerism and Governor’s Office on Service and Volunteerism;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <text>Develop model programs for Statewide clearinghouse, skill banks, or information centers for volunteers and projects in the State and implement such programs;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <text>Plan and execute volunteer recognition events for State volunteers and provide technical assistance and support for  recognition events in the private section in order to increase the visibility and status of volunteers and their accomplishments;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <text>Administer the Maryland Service Corps Program, the Executive Fellows program, and other volunteer programs as may be recommended by or designated by the Governor or otherwise provided by law;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(6)</num>
                  <text>Maintain liaison with national and State volunteerism groups to obtain information on federal, State and private resources that may enhance volunteer projects within the State;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(7)</num>
                  <text>Conduct studies and make recommendations to improve volunteer recruitment and training, volunteer retention, and accountability of volunteer programs; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(8)</num>
                  <text>Provide staff support to the Governor’s Volunteer Council.</text>
                </para>
              </section>
              <section>
                <num>9-2807.</num>
                <para>
                  <num>(A)</num>
                  <text>The Attorney General is the legal advisor to the Department.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(B)</num>
                  <text>The Attorney General shall assign to the Department the number of assistant attorneys general that are authorized by law.</text>
                </para>
              </section>
              <section>
                <num>9-2808.</num>
                <text>On or before December 1 of each year, the Secretary shall report to the Governor, and in accordance with §2-1257 of the State Government Article, the General Assembly on the activities on the Department.</text>
              </section>
              <section>
                <num>9-2809.</num>
                <heading>Reserved.</heading>
              </section>
              <section>
                <num>9-2810.</num>
                <heading>Reserved.</heading>
              </section>
            </container>
          </container>
        </container>
      </include>
    </para>
    <para>
      <prefix>SECTION</prefix>
      <num>2.</num>
      <text>And be it further ordered, that Section(s) 24-1101 through 24-1110, respectively, and the subtitle “Subtitle 11. Maryland Corps Program” of Article — <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged">Education of the Annotated Code of Maryland</cite> be transferred to be Section(s) 9-2811 through 9- 2821, respectively, and the part “Part II. Maryland Corps Program” of Article—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government of the Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <prefix>SECTION</prefix>
      <num>3.</num>
      <text>And be it further ordered, that Section(s) 9.5-201 through 9.5-206, respectively, and the subtitle “Subtitle 2. Governor’s Office on Service and Volunteerism” of Article—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government of the Annotated Code of Maryland</cite> be renumbered to be Section (s) 9-2824 through 9-2829, respectively, and the part “Part III. Governor’s Office of Service and Volunteerism”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <prefix>SECTION</prefix>
      <num>4.</num>
      <text>And be it further ordered, that Section(s) 9.5-204(5) through 9.5-204(10 of Article – <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government of the Annotated Code of Maryland</cite> be repealed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <prefix>SECTION</prefix>
      <num>5.</num>
      <text>And be it further ordered, that all persons who, as of the effective date of this Order, are employed in the Maryland Corps Program or the Governor’s Office of Service and Volunteerism are hereby transferred to the Department of Service and Civic Innovation without any change or loss of rights or status, and shall retain their merit system and retirement system status.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <prefix>SECTION</prefix>
      <num>6.</num>
      <text>And be it further ordered, that any transaction affected by or arising from any statute here amended, repealed, or transferred, and validly entered into before the effective date of this Order and every right, duty, or interest flowing from it remains valid after the effective date and may be terminated, completed, consummated, or enforced pursuant to law.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <prefix>SECTION</prefix>
      <num>7.</num>
      <text>And be it further ordered, that all rules and regulations, proposed rules and regulations, standards and guidelines, proposed standards and guidelines, orders and other directives, forms, plans, memberships, special funds, appropriations, grants, applications for grants, contracts, property, investigations, administrative and judicial proceedings, rights to sue and be sued, and all other duties and responsibilities associated with those functions transferred by this Order shall continue in effect under the Maryland Corps Program and the Governor’s Office of Service and Volunteerism upon transfer to the Department of Service and Civic Innovation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <prefix>SECTION</prefix>
      <num>8.</num>
      <text>And be it further ordered, that any unexpended appropriation for the purpose of financing the Maryland Corps Program or the Governor’s Office of Service and Volunteerism shall be transferred by approved budget amendment to the Department of Service and Civic Innovation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <prefix>SECTION</prefix>
      <num>9.</num>
      <text>And be it further ordered, that the publisher of the Annotated Code of Maryland, in consultation with and subject to the approval of the Department of Legislative Services, shall correct, with no further action required by the General Assembly, cross-references and terminology rendered incorrect by this Executive Order. The publisher shall adequately describe any correction that is made in an editor’s note following the section affected.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <prefix>SECTION</prefix>
      <num>10.</num>
      <text>And be it further ordered, that the provisions of this Order shall in no way diminish or infringe any rights, responsibilities, power or duties conferred by <cite doc="Md. Const.">the Constitution of the State of Maryland</cite> and the Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <prefix>SECTION</prefix>
      <num>11.</num>
      <text>And be it further ordered, that this executive order shall become effective and have the force of law on the 19th day of January, 2023, unless specifically disapproved within 50 days after submission by a resolution of disapproval concurred in by a majority vote of all members of either House of the General Assembly.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2023-01-19">Effective date: January 19, 2023</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Reporting of Procurement Activity and Minority Business Enterprise Compliance</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definitions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>“Participating Agencies” means those procurement units required to report MBE participation and compliance data to the Governor’s Office of Small, Minority, and Woman Business Affairs (GOSBA).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>“Jurisdiction” means each of Maryland’s 23 counties and Baltimore City.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Within sixty (60) days of the issuance of this Executive Order, all Participating Agencies shall submit a report to the Governor detailing the Participating Agency’s procurement activity since July 1, 2022. The report shall include the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>The quantity of procurement solicitations issued;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>The quantity and the cumulative dollar value of contract awards;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>The quantity and the cumulative dollar value of contract modifications;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4.</num>
        <text>The quantity and the cumulative dollar value of contract renewal options exercised;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>5.</num>
        <text>The quantity of procurement solicitations issued with MBE goals;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>6.</num>
        <text>The quantity of contract awards with MBE goals;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>7.</num>
        <text>The number of contracts modified that had MBE goals;</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>The number of contracts that met their MBE goals at the time of the modification;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>The number of contracts that did not met their MBE goals at the time of the modification;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>8.</num>
        <text>The number of contracts whose renewal options were exercised that had MBE goals;</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>The number of renewed contracts that met their MBE goals at the time of the renewal option being exercised;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>The number of renewed contracts that did not meet their MBE goals at the time of the renewal option being exercised.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Within sixty (60) days of the issuance of this Order, all Participating Agencies shall submit a report to the Governor detailing the outreach and marketing efforts to MBE firms that the Participating Agency conducted related to procurement solicitations from July 1, 2022, to the date of the issuance of this Order.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Within sixty (60) days of the issuance of this Executive Order, the Maryland Department of Transportation, in its capacity as the State’s official MBE certification agency, shall submit a report to the Governor with the following information:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>By jurisdiction, the total number of businesses certified as an MBE;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>By jurisdiction, the total number of Maryland-based businesses certified as an MBE;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>By jurisdiction, the number of African American-owned businesses certified as an MBE;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4.</num>
        <text>By jurisdiction, the number of Hispanic-owned businesses certified as an MBE;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>5.</num>
        <text>By jurisdiction, the number of Asian-owned businesses certified as an MBE;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>6.</num>
        <text>By jurisdiction, the number of Native American-owned businesses certified as an MBE;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>7.</num>
        <text>By jurisdiction, the number of Woman-owned businesses certified as an M​BE; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>8.</num>
        <text>By jurisdiction, the number of Disabled-owned businesses certified as an MBE</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Any Participating Agencies who are required to submit MBE performance and compliance reporting data to GOSBA for Fiscal Year 2022 but have not done so by the date of the issuance of this Executive Order, must submit the mandatory data to GOSBA within 15 days of the issuance of this Executive Order</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Participating Agencies shall implement this Executive Order in a manner that is consistent with all applicable statutes and regulations. Nothing in this Executive Order shall operate to contravene any State or federal law or to affect the State’s receipt of federal funding.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>If any provision of this Executive Order or its application to any person, entity, or circumstance is held invalid by any court of competent jurisdiction, the provisions or applications of the Executive Order are severable, and all others shall remain in effect to the extent possible without the invalid provision or application.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2023-02-16">Effective date: February 16, 2023</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Judicial Nominating Commissions</heading>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>(Rescinds Executive Order <cite path="01.01.2019.05">01.01.2019.05</cite>)</strong>
    </text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this Executive Order, the following words have the meanings indicated:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Appellate Court” means the Appellate Court of Maryland or the Supreme Court of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“County” means a county of the State or Baltimore City.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Immediate family” includes a spouse, child, sibling, parent, grandparent, grandchild, stepparent, stepchild, step-sibling, or any adopted relative.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Trial Court” means the District Court of Maryland or the Circuit Court for a county.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Appellate Courts Judicial Nominating Commission.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Creation and Composition.</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>The Appellate Courts Judicial Nominating Commission is hereby established as part of the Executive Department. It consists of seventeen persons chosen as follows:</text>
          <para>
            <num>i.</num>
            <text>Twelve persons appointed by the Governor; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>ii.</num>
            <text>Five members of the Maryland State Bar Association appointed by the Governor from 10 such persons submitted by the Association president by a date established by the Governor’s Office of Legal Counsel.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>No more than one lawyer from the same firm or legal office may serve on the Appellate Courts Judicial Nominating Commission at the same time.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c.</num>
          <text>No person may serve on the Appellate Courts Judicial Nominating Commission while simultaneously serving on a Trial Courts Judicial Nominating Commission.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>d.</num>
          <text>No person may serve on the Appellate Courts Judicial Nominating Commission who:</text>
          <para>
            <num>i.</num>
            <text>Holds an elected office in local, State, or federal government;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>ii.</num>
            <text>Is an employee of the Office of the Governor;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>iii.</num>
            <text>Hears cases as an active or senior member of the State or federal judiciary or of a State or federal commission or agency; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>iv.</num>
            <text>Holds an office in a political party.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>e.</num>
          <text>In making appointments, the Governor shall consider the racial, ethnic, gender, and geographic diversity of Maryland.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>f.</num>
          <text>In submitting persons for appointment, the president of the Maryland State Bar Association shall consider the racial, ethnic, gender, and geographic diversity of Maryland.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>g.</num>
          <text>If the president of the Maryland State Bar Association submits fewer than 10 persons for appointment the Association’s appointments shall be decreased by the number not submitted and the Governor shall make the appointments.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>h.</num>
          <text>If a vacancy occurs on the Appellate Courts Judicial Nominating Commission by reason of death, resignation, removal, or disqualification, a successor will be appointed by the Governor.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Chair of the Appellate Courts Judicial Nominating Commission will be designated by the Governor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Terms.</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>The terms of the members of the Appellate Courts Judicial Nominating Commission shall extend to the date of the qualification of the Governor at the next quadrennial election.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>At the end of a term, a member continues to serve until a successor is appointed and qualifies.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c.</num>
          <text>If the Appellate Courts Judicial Nominating Commission meets on two or more occasions during any calendar year, and if, during that year, a member fails to attend at least half of the meetings in which that member is not otherwise disqualified from participating, the member may be removed by the Governor.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>An Appellate Courts Judicial Nominating Commission member shall not be appointed to an Appellate Court during the term for which the member was appointed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Trial Courts Judicial Nominating Commissions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Creation and Composition.</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>A Trial Courts Judicial Nominating Commission is hereby established as part of the Executive Department for each of the Commission Districts set forth below:</text>
          <para>
            <num>i.</num>
            <text>Commission District 1 – Somerset, Wicomico, and Worcester Counties;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>ii.</num>
            <text>Commission District 2 – Cecil, Kent, and Queen Anne’s Counties;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>iii.</num>
            <text>Commission District 3 – Baltimore County;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>iv.</num>
            <text>Commission District 4 – Harford County;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>v.</num>
            <text>Commission District 5 – Allegany and Garrett Counties;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>vi.</num>
            <text>Commission District 6 – Washington County;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>vii.</num>
            <text>Commission District 7 – Anne Arundel County;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>viii.</num>
            <text>Commission District 8 – Carroll County;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>ix.</num>
            <text>Commission District 9 – Howard County;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>x.</num>
            <text>Commission District 10 – Frederick County;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>xi.</num>
            <text>Commission District 11 – Montgomery County;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>xii.</num>
            <text>Commission District 12 – Calvert and St. Mary’s Counties;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>xiii.</num>
            <text>Commission District 13 – Prince George’s County;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>xiv.</num>
            <text>Commission District 14 – Baltimore City;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>xv.</num>
            <text>Commission District 15 – Charles County; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>xvi.</num>
            <text>Commission District 16 – Caroline, Dorchester, and Talbot Counties.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>Each Trial Courts Judicial Nominating Commission shall consist of thirteen persons chosen as follows:</text>
          <para>
            <num>i.</num>
            <text>Nine persons appointed by the Governor; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>ii.</num>
            <text>Four members of the Bar Associations for the counties for which the Trial Courts Nominating Commission is responsible, appointed by the Governor from seven such persons submitted collectively by the presidents of those Associations by a date established by the Governor’s Office of Legal Counsel.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c.</num>
          <text>No more than one lawyer from the same firm or legal office may serve on the same Trial Court Judicial Nominating Commission at the same time.  The Governor’s Office of Legal Counsel may, in its sole discretion, waive this restriction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>d.</num>
          <text>No person may serve on a Trial Courts Judicial Nominating Commission while simultaneously serving on the Appellate Courts Judicial Nominating Commission or another Trial Courts Judicial Nominating Commission.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>e.</num>
          <text>No person may serve on a Trial Courts Judicial Nominating Commission who:</text>
          <para>
            <num>i.</num>
            <text>Holds an elected office in local, State, or federal government;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>ii.</num>
            <text>Is an employee of the Office of the Governor;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>iii.</num>
            <text>Hears cases as an active or senior member of the State or federal judiciary or of a State or federal commission or agency; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>iv.</num>
            <text>Holds an office in a political party.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>f.</num>
          <text>In making appointments, the Governor shall consider the racial, ethnic, and gender diversity of the Commission District.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>g.</num>
          <text>In submitting persons for appointment, the presidents of the Bar Associations shall consider the racial, ethnic, and gender diversity of the Commission District.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>h.</num>
          <text>In selecting persons to submit for appointment, the presidents of the Bar Associations shall consult with the presidents of other bar organizations that may operate in the Commission District.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>i.</num>
          <text>If the presidents of the Bar Associations submit fewer than seven persons for appointment to a Trial Courts Judicial Nominating Commission, the Associations’ appointments shall be decreased by the number not submitted and the Governor shall make the appointments.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Chair of each Trial Courts Judicial Nominating Commission will be designated by the Governor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Terms.</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>The terms of the members of each Trial Courts Judicial Nominating Commission shall extend to the date of the qualification of the Governor at the next quadrennial election.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>At the end of a term, a member continues to serve until a successor is appointed and qualifies.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c.</num>
          <text>If a Trial Courts Judicial Nominating Commission meets on two or more occasions during any calendar year, and if, during that year, a member fails to attend at least half of the meetings in which that member is not otherwise disqualified from participating, the member may be removed by the Governor.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If a vacancy occurs on a Trial Courts Judicial Nominating Commission by reason of the death, resignation, removal, or disqualification, a successor will be appointed by the Governor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A Trial Courts Judicial Nominating Commission member shall not be appointed to a Trial Court during the term for which the member was appointed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Code of Conduct.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Appellate and Trial Courts Judicial Nominating Commission members shall agree to abide by the Code of Conduct during their term of service.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Code of Conduct shall be established by the Governor’s Office of Legal Counsel and shall at a minimum include provisions relating to: impartiality, confidentiality, ex parte communications, conflicts of interest, and prohibited discriminatory practices.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The chair of each Commission may request the technical assistance of the Administrative Office of the Courts in providing:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Training to Commission members;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Notification of when a vacancy occurs or is about to occur;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Standardized interview practices and questions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Recommendations as to standardized application requirements and forms; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Any other assistance the chair deems appropriate, including the provision of reasonable accommodations to Commission members or judicial applicants.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>For each judicial vacancy, the Governor shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Reappoint the incumbent judge;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Appoint an applicant who was recommended for a prior vacancy in the same position, if the appointment for the prior vacancy was made within two years of the occurrence of the current vacancy; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Accept applications from new candidates for the vacancy.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Commission Responsibilities and Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If applications are accepted from new candidates for the vacancy, a Commission shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>Advertise the vacancy using print and electronic media, in coordination and consultation with the Administrative Office of the Courts.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>Encourage qualified candidates from diverse backgrounds including, but not limited to, race, ethnicity, gender, religion, sexual orientation, gender identity, gender expression, disability, or economic status to apply for judicial appointments;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c.</num>
          <text>Encourage qualified candidates from diverse practice areas to apply for judicial appointments;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>d.</num>
          <text>Notify the Maryland State Bar Association and other appropriate county and specialty bar associations of the vacancy and request that they advertise the vacancy to their membership;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>e.</num>
          <text>Seek recommendations from interested citizens and from its own members; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>f.</num>
          <text>Set a closing date for submission of applications.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If there are fewer than three applicants for a vacancy, the vacancy shall be automatically re-advertised to new candidates. If, after re-advertisement, there remain fewer than three applicants, the Governor shall determine whether to re-advertise or may direct the Commission to proceed with evaluating the applicants.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A Commission shall review all applications submitted and evaluate each applicant. In the course of its evaluation, the Commission may:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>Seek information beyond that contained in the materials submitted by an applicant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>Obtain pertinent information from the Attorney Grievance Commission, judges, courts, personal references given by the applicant, criminal justice agencies, knowledgeable persons known to Commission members, county or specialty bar associations, and other sources; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c.</num>
          <text>Request criminal history record information from a criminal justice agency, including the Central Repository, for the purpose of evaluating an applicant.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A Commission shall interview each applicant:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>In person, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>Via video teleconference, if:</text>
          <para>
            <num>i.</num>
            <text>Extraordinary circumstances prevent the applicant from appearing in person; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>ii.</num>
            <text>The Governor gives prior approval.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>There shall be no monetary cost or Bar membership required for a candidate to be interviewed by a local bar association or specialty bar association.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A Commission shall consider the applicant’s integrity, maturity, temperament, diligence, legal knowledge, intellectual ability, professional experience, community service, and any other qualifications that the Commission deems important for judicial service, as well as the importance of having a diverse and impartial judiciary.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>In evaluating applications to fill a vacancy on a Trial Court, the Trial Courts Judicial Nominating Commission shall give the same consideration to eligible applicants regardless of whether an applicant’s legal practice is located outside of the county in which the applicant resides.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>A Commission member is disqualified from participating in the consideration, evaluation, or recommending of applicants for a vacancy in which an applicant is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>In the member’s immediate family;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>A current business or law partner;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c.</num>
          <text>A lawyer in the same firm or legal office as the member, unless the Commission by a majority vote of the remaining Commission members determines that the member is capable of impartially considering the applicant; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>d.</num>
          <text>Otherwise known to the member and the member believes they are incapable of impartially considering the applicant.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>A voting session of a Commission shall be attended by at least three-fifths of the members who are qualified to participate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>No applicant may be recommended to the Governor for appointment unless by vote of a majority of members present and qualified to participate at a voting session of the appropriate Commission, as taken by secret ballot. A Commission may conduct more than one round of balloting during its deliberations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>If a Commission determines that fewer than three applicants are legally and professionally qualified, the Commission shall notify the Governor, who shall direct the Commission:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>To re-advertise the vacancy to new candidates, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>To submit the names of the qualified applicants.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>If a Commission determines that at least three applicants are legally and professionally qualified, it shall report in writing to the Governor the names of at least three applicants recommended by the Commission as the most fully professionally qualified to fill the vacancy. The names of these recommended applicants shall be listed in alphabetical order. The Commission shall release this list to the public concurrently with submission of its report to the Governor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Upon request of the Governor, a Commission shall reconvene for further deliberations, or re-advertise a vacancy to new applicants.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Confidentiality.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A Commission shall not disclose to the public the names of candidates who have submitted applications to fill a vacancy until after the closing date for submission of applications.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Materials submitted by an applicant, or obtained from other sources in connection with the evaluation of an applicant, are confidential and may not be released to the public.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Each Commission member shall maintain the confidentiality of the Commission’s evaluation of candidates, including its interviews, deliberations, and voting, and, except as provided in Section G (12), shall not disclose the Commission’s evaluation of candidates to the public.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Reasonable accommodations shall be made for qualified Commission members or judicial applicants with a disability unless the accommodation would impose an undue hardship. Examples of a reasonable accommodation include, but are not limited to: providing, adjusting, or modifying written materials, equipment or devices; and making a readily accessible facility available for interviews.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2023-03-07">Effective date: March 7, 2023</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Maryland Council on Innovation and Impact</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Establishment. There is hereby established a Maryland Council on Innovation and Impact (“Council”), housed in the Executive Office of the Governor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Function. The principal function of the Council, to the extent permitted by law, is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To ensure that the resources and expertise of innovative social sector organizations can be leveraged, deployed, and aligned with the efforts of the State to meet challenges;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>To infuse all of the State’s innovation and impact work with the best available evidence, and to ensure the State measures results and contributes to the existing evidence base where possible.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>To identify and explore ways in which partnerships can be developed and strengthened, ensuring the flow of innovation, talent, and resources across social and government sectors;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>To identify and encourage policies that increase and sustain charitable giving, volunteerism, and State service; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>To bring ideas and policy options to the Governor for developing, leveraging, and maintaining partnerships across social and government sectors to deliver community services and accelerate the pace of positive change at the community level in Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Membership.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>There shall be a Senior Advisor on Innovation and Impact who shall be appointed by the Governor and shall chair the Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Governor may appoint additional individuals as honorary co-chairs of the Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Council shall consist of the heads of the following principal departments, or their designee, and the heads of any such other principal departments as the Governor may designate:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Department of Health;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Department of Human Services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Department of Juvenile Services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Department of Housing and Community Development;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The Department of Service and Civic Innovation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The head of each principal department in the Executive Branch shall designate a liaison to support the work of the Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Other State agencies, units, and offices may be asked to participate at the invitation of the Chair.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The Council shall also consist of no more than twenty-five (25) members, appointed by the Governor, representing Maryland’s broad and diverse range of innovative and impactful organizations from all sectors.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Members appointed by the Governor shall serve at the pleasure of the Governor for up to two consecutive two year terms.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Council members shall serve without compensation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Staff members from the Office of the Governor and Lieutenant Governor will also be regular participants.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Duties.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Council shall continuously identify and explore the ways in which the relationship between social sector organizations, companies, and State government can be strengthened and improved;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Council shall foster and maintain relationships with social sector organizations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Council shall develop recommendations for leveraging powerful cross-sector partnerships, including policy, regulatory, or legislative recommendations to facilitate such partnerships;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Council shall update the Governor within six months of this Executive Order, and biannually thereafter, on the Council’s efforts, goals, and impact on the state and residents.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Council Chair shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Oversee the implementation of this Executive Order and the work of the Council;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Determine the Council’s agenda; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Identify additional support as needed.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Council Chair may adopt other procedures as necessary to ensure the orderly transaction of business.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Council may seek advice and recommendations from an Advisory Board. The Council Chair will select members of the Advisory Board that have a deep understanding of issues facing the citizens and State of Maryland and experience in local, national, or international organizations. Advisory Board members shall provide such advice and recommendations voluntarily, free of any compensation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Council shall meet on a quarterly basis, or more frequently if the members deem appropriate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A majority of the Council members present shall constitute a quorum for the transaction of any business.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The Executive Office of the Governor shall provide administrative support for the Council, consistent with applicable law and subject to the availability of appropriations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The Council shall submit an annual report to the Governor and the public outlining the achievements of each partnership.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>This Executive Order shall be implemented in a manner that is consistent with all applicable statutes and regulations. Nothing in this Executive Order shall operate to contravene any State or federal law or to affect the State's receipt of federal funding.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>If any provision of this Executive Order or its application to any person, entity, or circumstance is held invalid by any court of competent jurisdiction, all other provisions or applications of the Executive Order shall remain in effect to the extent possible without the invalid provision or application. To achieve this purpose, the provisions of this Executive Order are severable.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2023-05-05">Effective date: May 5, 2023</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Leading by Example in State Government</heading>
    <text class="center">(Rescinds Executive Order <cite path="01.01.2018.08">01.01.2018.08</cite>)</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>There is an energy-savings initiative with the goal of, by Fiscal Year 2031, reducing energy consumption in State-owned buildings by 20 percent compared to a Fiscal Year 2018 baseline.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Maryland Green Building Council shall update the High-Performance Green Building Program to ensure that all new buildings and major renovations subject to the Program align with the State’s goal to achieve net zero greenhouse gas emissions by 2045.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>DGS shall identify potential candidates for energy savings performance contracts at State-owned facilities, and agencies shall provide onsite support to work with DGS at facilities that DGS identifies as suitable candidates.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Each year, DGS shall analyze all State-owned buildings to identify the buildings with the highest energy use per square foot and the greatest greenhouse gas emissions.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Audit.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each year, DGS shall conduct an energy and greenhouse gas emissions audit of at least 2 million square feet of State-owned buildings.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The audit shall include best practices and identify low-cost measures for increasing energy efficiency and reducing greenhouse gas emissions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A copy of the audit shall be provided to the head of each unit of State government that occupies the space audited.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Each unit of state government that occupies the space audited shall, to the fullest extent practicable, implement the measures identified in the audit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>For one year following such implementation, DGS shall monitor the unit’s energy use and greenhouse gas emissions, track any changes resulting from the measures, and calculate any savings on energy costs and or reductions in emissions.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Utility Database.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Reductions in energy consumption and greenhouse gas emissions resulting from the energy-savings initiative shall be recorded in a Comprehensive Utility Records Management Database (the “Utility Database”).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Each unit of State government shall, each month, or upon request, provide DGS with access to available data about its facility and copies of the unit’s utility bills.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>DGS shall report to the Governor’s Office annually on each unit of the State government’s data compliance.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>DGS shall gather the data and information necessary to fully populate, update, and maintain the Utility Database.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>All units of State government shall, in support of their core missions, implement projects and initiatives to conserve energy and reduce their greenhouse gas emissions.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Provisions promoting the State’s energy efficiency and greenhouse gas emissions reduction goals shall be included in requests for proposals that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Are made after the date of this Executive Order;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Are for the leasing of space to the State; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Would obligate the State to pay the utility bills for the leased space.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>DGS shall report to the Governor each fiscal year on the State’s progress toward achieving the 20 percent reduction goal.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Executive Order <cite path="01.01.2018.08">01.01.2018.08</cite> is hereby rescinded.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2023-05-17">Effective date: May 17, 2023</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Leading by Example in State Government</heading>
    <text class="center">(Rescinds Executive Order <cite path="01.01.2019.08">01.01.2019.08</cite>)</text>
    <text class="center">(Amends Executive Order <cite path="01.01.2023.06">01.01.2023.06</cite>)</text>
    <text class="center">(Reinstating Executive Order <cite path="01.01.2018.08">01.01.2018.08</cite>)</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>There is an energy-savings initiative with the goal of, by Fiscal Year 2031, reducing energy consumption in State-owned buildings by 20 percent compared to a Fiscal Year 2018 baseline.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Maryland Green Building Council shall update the High-Performance Green Building Program to ensure that all new buildings and major renovations subject to the Program align with the State’s goal to achieve net zero greenhouse gas emissions by 2045.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>DGS shall identify potential candidates for energy savings performance contracts at State-owned facilities, and agencies shall provide onsite support to work with DGS at facilities that DGS identifies as suitable candidates.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Each year, DGS shall analyze all State-owned buildings to identify the buildings with the highest energy use per square foot and the greatest greenhouse gas emissions.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Audit.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each year, DGS shall conduct an energy and greenhouse gas emissions audit of at least 2 million square feet of State-owned buildings.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The audit shall include best practices and identify low-cost measures for increasing energy efficiency and reducing greenhouse gas emissions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A copy of the audit shall be provided to the head of each unit of State government that occupies the space audited.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Each unit of state government that occupies the space audited shall, to the fullest extent practicable, implement the measures identified in the audit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>For one year following such implementation, DGS shall monitor the unit’s energy use and greenhouse gas emissions, track any changes resulting from the measures, and calculate any savings on energy costs and or reductions in emissions.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Utility Database.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Reductions in energy consumption and greenhouse gas emissions resulting from the energy-savings initiative shall be recorded in a Comprehensive Utility Records Management Database (the “Utility Database”).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Each unit of State government shall, each month, or upon request, provide DGS with access to available data about its facility and copies of the unit’s utility bills.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>DGS shall report to the Governor’s Office annually on each unit of the State government’s data compliance.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>DGS shall gather the data and information necessary to fully populate, update, and maintain the Utility Database.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>All units of State government shall, in support of their core missions, implement projects and initiatives to conserve energy and reduce their greenhouse gas emissions.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Provisions promoting the State’s energy efficiency and greenhouse gas emissions reduction goals shall be included in requests for proposals that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Are made after the date of this Executive Order;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Are for the leasing of space to the State; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Would obligate the State to pay the utility bills for the leased space.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>DGS shall report to the Governor each fiscal year on the State’s progress toward achieving the 20 percent reduction goal.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Executive Order <cite path="01.01.2019.08">01.01.2019.08</cite> is hereby rescinded.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2023-05-19">Effective date: May 19, 2023</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Protecting the Right to Seek Gender-Affirming Treatment in Maryland</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definitions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>“Gender-Affirming Treatment” means any medically necessary treatment consistent with current clinical standards of care prescribed by a licensed health care provider for the treatment of a condition related to the individual's gender identity.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>“State Agency” means a department, agency, commission, board, council, or other body of state government subject to the direction and supervision of the Governor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>All state agencies shall, to the fullest extent within their authority, take whatever action is necessary and coordinate to protect people or entities in Maryland providing, receiving, assisting in providing or receiving, seeking, or traveling to obtain gender-affirming treatment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Except as required by court order issued by a Maryland or federal court, or as required by Maryland or federal law, no state agency shall provide information, including patient medical records, patient-level data, or related billing information, or expend or use time, money, facilities, property, equipment, personnel, or other resources in furtherance of any investigation or proceeding that seeks to impose civil or criminal liability or professional sanctions upon a person or entity solely for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>The provision of, securing of, receipt of, inquiry into, or responding to any inquiry concerning gender-affirming treatment that is permitted under the laws of this State; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>The provision of any assistance to any individual or entity that relates to the provision of, securing of, receipt of, inquiry into, or responding to any inquiry concerning gender-affirming treatment that is permitted under the laws of this State; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>Traveling to Maryland to obtain, provide, receive, or inquire into gender-affirming treatment that is permitted under the laws of this State.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Except as required by a court order issued by a Maryland or federal court, or as required by Maryland or federal law, no state agency shall comply with a subpoena issued by another state, knowing that the subpoena seeks information solely because an individual or entity provided, received, assisted in providing or receiving, sought, inquired or responded to an inquiry about, or traveled to Maryland to obtain gender-affirming treatment that is permitted under the laws of this State for themselves or a child for whom they are the parent or legal guardian.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Pursuant to the discretion afforded me under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcp|9-106">§ 9-106(a) of the Criminal Procedure Article of the Maryland Code</cite>, I shall refuse to surrender, on demand of the executive authority of any other state, any person who: (i) is found in this State; (ii) was not present in the demanding state at the time of the commission of the alleged offense and has not fled therefrom; and (iii) is charged with a criminal violation of a law of another state where the violation alleged involves the provision of, assistance with, securing of, or receipt of gender- affirming treatment that is permitted under the laws of this State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Except when in conflict with any State or federal laws, a health occupations board shall not refuse to admit a person to an examination and shall not revoke, suspend, discipline, take an adverse action against, or refuse to issue or renew a license, certification, or other authorization to practice for any health care practitioner in whole or in part because of the provision of, authorization of, participation in, referral for, or assistance with gender-affirming treatment for a person who resides in a jurisdiction where the provision, authorization, participation, referral, or assistance is illegal, if the provision, authorization, participation, referral, or assistance would not be a basis for refusing to admit a person to an examination or for revoking, suspending, disciplining, taking an adverse action against, or refusing to issue or renew a license, certification, or other authorization to practice in this State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>This Executive Order shall not be construed to preclude a health occupations board from investigating an alleged violation of the applicable practice act by a Maryland-licensed practitioner that occurs in Maryland or from taking appropriate action against that practitioner.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2023-06-05">Effective Date: June 5, 2023.</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Maryland Economic Council</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Establishment. There is hereby established a Maryland Economic Council (“Council”).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Membership. The Council shall consist of the following members:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Lieutenant Governor or the Lieutenant Governor’s designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of Budget &amp; Management or the Secretary’s designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of Commerce or the Secretary’s designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Chief Data Officer or the Chief Data Officer’s designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of Labor or the Secretary’s designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>No fewer than five (5) and no more than fifteen (15) members, appointed by the Governor, with training, knowledge, and experience in analyzing and interpreting economic data, developments and trends, appraising programs and activities of the government, recommending economic policy in light of the international, national and State macroeconomic environment, and proposing strategies to build a more equitable economy; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Such other officials of executive departments and agencies as the Governor may from time to time designate.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Chair. The Governor shall appoint the Chair from among the members. The Chair shall serve at the pleasure of the Governor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Meetings of the Council.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Council shall meet as often as its duties require, but no less than quarterly.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Council Chair may convene meetings of the Council and shall preside over the meetings.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Functions. The principal functions of the Council are to provide economic policy advice and recommendations to the Governor by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Identifying and tracking the underlying economic factors impacting the macroeconomic environment (such as interest rates, systematic risks in the banking system, disruptions to the global supply chain, gross domestic product, unemployment rates, and inflation);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Analyzing the projected impacts of State policy issues, such as tax policy and specific investment proposals, on the competitiveness of the State’s economy and strengthening key economic metrics;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Evaluating the State’s current economic development policies and activities to identify additional techniques to foster greater economic and business development and support commerce;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Examining existing economic policy instrumentalities, boards and commissions within the State (including, but not limited to, the Maryland Economic Development Corporation (MEDCO), Maryland Technology Development Corporation (TEDCO), and Maryland Economic Development Commission (MEDC)), develop a plan to coordinate each entity’s distinct mandates, and identify potential areas for collaboration to meet desired goals;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Reviewing current economic policies through an equitable lens to ensure fairness and help eliminate the racial wealth gap; and,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Assessing and highlighting the economic and competitive impact of Maryland’s commitment to policies of inclusivity, openness, and diversity.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Administration.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Council may function through established or ad hoc committees.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Council shall be staffed by the Maryland Department of Commerce. The Council shall have such staff and other assistance as may be necessary to carry out the provisions of this order.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All executive departments and agencies shall cooperate with the Council and provide such assistance, information, and advice to the Council as the Council may request, to the extent permitted by law.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Council Chair shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>Oversee the implementation of this Executive Order and the work of the Council;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>Determine the Council’s agenda; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c.</num>
          <text>Identify additional support as needed.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Council Chair may adopt bylaws, rules, and other procedures necessary to ensure the orderly transaction of business.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A majority of the members present shall constitute a quorum for the transaction of any business of the Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Council shall submit an annual report to the Governor on or before January 1, 2024, and by October 1st each year thereafter, outlining the current economic conditions impacting the macroeconomic environment, evaluating their impact on Maryland’s economy, and recommending courses of action consistent with its’ duties under section E of this order.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Duration. This Executive Order shall remain in effect until January 20, 2027, unless earlier modified or rescinded by the Governor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>This Executive Order shall be implemented in a manner that is consistent with all applicable statutes and regulations. Nothing in this Executive Order shall operate to contravene any State or federal law or to affect the State's receipt of federal funding.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>If any provision of this Executive Order or its application to any person, entity, or circumstance is held invalid by any court of competent jurisdiction, all other provisions or applications of the Executive Order shall remain in effect to the extent possible without the invalid provision or application. To achieve this purpose, the provisions of this Executive Order are severable.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2023-06-08">Effective Date: June 8, 2023</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Maryland 250 Commission</heading>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>(Rescinds Executive Order <cite path="01.01.2021.03">01.01.2021.03</cite>)</strong>
    </text>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>(Amended by Executive Order <cite path="01.01.2024.29">01.01.2024.29</cite>)</strong>
    </text>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>There is a Maryland 250 Commission (the “Commission”).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>II.</num>
      <text>Membership</text>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>The Commission shall consist of the following members:</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>The Lieutenant Governor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Budget and Management, or the Secretary’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>3.</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Commerce, or the Secretary’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>4.</num>
          <text>The Secretary of General Services, or the Secretary’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>5.</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Natural Resources, or the Secretary’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>6.</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Planning, or the Secretary’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>7.</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Service and Civic Innovation, or the Secretary’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>8.</num>
          <text>The Secretary of State, or the Secretary’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>9.</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs, or the Secretary’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>10.</num>
          <text>The State Superintendent of Schools, or the Superintendent’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>11.</num>
          <text>The State Archivist, or the Archivist’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>12.</num>
          <text>The State Historic Preservation Officer, or the Officer’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>13.</num>
          <text>The Executive Director of the Governor’s Office of Community Initiatives, or the Executive Director’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>14.</num>
          <text>The Executive Director, Maryland State Arts Council, or the Executive Director’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>15.</num>
          <text>The Administrative Director of the Maryland Commission on Indian Affairs, or the Administrative Director’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>16.</num>
          <text>The Executive Director of the Maryland Commission on African American History and Culture, or the Executive Director’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>17.</num>
          <text>The Director of the Maryland Commission for Women, or the Director’s designee; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>18.</num>
          <text>Up to five members of the general public appointed by the Governor.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>The following are invited to be, and shall be upon acceptance, members of the Commission:</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>Two members appointed by the President of the Maryland Senate;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>Two members appointed by the Speaker of the Maryland House of Delegates;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>3.</num>
          <text>The Executive Director of the Maryland Association of Counties, or Executive Director’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>4.</num>
          <text>The Executive Director of the Maryland Municipal League, or Executive Director’s designee; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>5.</num>
          <text>Up to three members from the nonprofit community, selected from the Maryland Center for History and Culture, the Maryland Humanities Council, Preservation Maryland, or other similar organizations.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>The Governor shall appoint the Chair and the Vice Chair of the Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>D.</num>
        <text>Members serve at the pleasure of the Governor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>III.</num>
      <text>The Maryland Department of Planning shall provide the Commission with resources and staff as feasible and necessary for administering and facilitating the work of the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>IV.</num>
      <text>Members of the Commission may not receive any compensation for their services but may be reimbursed for their reasonable expenses incurred in the performance of duties in accordance with the State Standard Travel Regulations and as provided in the State budget.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>V.</num>
      <text>The Commission shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Adopt administrative and financial procedures for the transaction of business, including, but not limited to, the establishment of advisory groups, committees, or working groups that address the themes of history, service, and civics.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Hold at a minimum semi-annual meetings,</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>At times and places to be determined by the Chair;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>That are conducted in accordance with the Open Meetings Act; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>3.</num>
          <text>That allow for remote meetings and electronic voting.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>Coordinate, engage, and liaise with the U.S. Semiquincentennial Commission, and other local, county, and state commissions, and private and public partner organizations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>D.</num>
        <text>Serve as the State of Maryland’s official representative for the Semiquincentennial, and all related activities, communications, and events.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>E.</num>
        <text>Solicit, accept, use and dispose of donations, funds and gifts in conformance with the Public Ethics Law, to support the goals and purposes of the Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>F.</num>
        <text>Invite broad-based public input on the meaning, significance, and opportunities of this anniversary that will inform development of commemoration activities, programs, and events.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>G.</num>
        <text>Acknowledge that the confiscation of Indigenous land and displacement of Indigenous people is central to the United States’ origin story and recognize the persistence and contributions of these communities today.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>H.</num>
        <text>Honor the legacy of both free and enslaved African Americans in the making of Maryland and the nation, whose untold stories of heroism and perseverance are critical to the understanding of our shared past and present.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>I.</num>
        <text>Support the identification and enhancement of cultural assets that tell the story of who we are as Marylanders and promote place-based visitor experiences for residents and visitors alike.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>J.</num>
        <text>Engage youth, new Americans, and lifelong learners in programs designed to encourage the search for meaning behind America and deepen engagement in civic life.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>K.</num>
        <text>Celebrate service to country and community, and create opportunities that promote social responsibility, compassion and understanding that will unite and strengthen Maryland’s diverse communities for the benefit of all.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>VI.</num>
      <text>The Commission shall further:</text>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Submit an Action Plan to the Governor and General Assembly by December 31, 2023, that outlines the Commission’s goals, mission, and recommendations; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Produce by December 31 of each year an annual report to the Governor and General Assembly that includes an update on the Action Plan, implementation benchmarks, related deadlines and schedules, and an accounting and enumeration of all contracts, donations, and gifts.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>VII.</num>
      <text>The Commission shall terminate on December 31, 2027.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>VIII.</num>
      <text>This Executive Order shall be implemented in a manner that is consistent with all applicable statutes and regulations. Nothing in this Executive Order shall operate to contravene any State or federal law or to affect the State's receipt of federal funding.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>IX.</num>
      <text>If any provision of this Executive Order or its application to any person, entity, or circumstance is held invalid by any court of competent jurisdiction, all other provisions or applications of the Executive Order shall remain in effect to the extent possible without the invalid provision or application. To achieve this purpose, the provisions of this Executive Order are severable.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2023-07-03">Effective Date: July 3, 2023</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Governor’s Council on the Chesapeake and Coastal Bays Watershed</heading>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>(Amends Executive Order <cite path="01.01.1985.02">01.01.1985.02</cite>)</strong>
    </text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Establishment. There is a Governor’s Council on the Chesapeake and Coastal Bays Watershed (“Council”).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Membership. The Council shall consist of the following members:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of Natural Resources;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of the Environment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of Health;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of Agriculture;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of Planning;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The Director of the Maryland Energy Administration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The Executive Director of the Maryland Environmental Service;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The State’s Chief Resilience Officer; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Other officials of the Executive Branch that the Governor may designate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>The President of the University of Maryland Center for Environmental Sciences is invited to be, and shall be upon acceptance, a member of the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Chair. The Governor shall appoint a Chair from among the members of the Council.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Meetings of the Council.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Council shall meet at least quarterly to receive information and discuss issues of Chesapeake and Coastal Bays Watershed management.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Council Chair may convene meetings of the Council and shall preside over the meetings.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Functions.  The principal functions of the Council are to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Advise and provide periodic recommendations to the Governor about matters related to the management of the Chesapeake and Coastal Bays Watershed and surrounding areas, including but not limited to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>Progress in meeting the annual Statewide implementation plan;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>Need for programmatic and budgetary adjustments;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c.</num>
          <text>The results and conduct of Chesapeake and Coastal Bays Watershed monitoring programs;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>d.</num>
          <text>Establishment of annual Chesapeake and Coastal Bays Watershed research priorities; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>e.</num>
          <text>Maryland's participation on regional issues of Chesapeake and Coastal Bays Watershed management;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Promote interagency coordination and integration of Chesapeake and Coastal Bays Watershed related programs to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>Guide the State’s restoration and water quality improvement programs consistent with the most up-to-date scientific knowledge and technologies;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>Accelerate the restoration of the Chesapeake and Atlantic Coastal Bays and local watersheds to ensure that all Marylanders have clean drinking water and accessible clean waterways;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c.</num>
          <text>Promote equity by focusing on the long-term, collective benefits of healthy watersheds and their connection to the health of Maryland’s environment, economy and people;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>d.</num>
          <text>Ensure that investments in watershed restoration provide important climate resiliency benefits; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>e.</num>
          <text>Develop strategies to address the challenges and opportunities that the State’s population growth presents to Bay restoration and the environment overall;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Develop and oversee the State’s coordinated environmental, cultural and natural resources infrastructure while pursuing innovative partnerships and funding opportunities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Seek regular input of Maryland citizens and stakeholders, particularly those representing underserved and overburdened communities.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Administration.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Council may establish working groups as necessary.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Council shall be staffed by Executive Department staff.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Council shall establish appropriate procedures to seek advice on issues related to research, management, and public participation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>This Executive Order shall be implemented in a manner that is consistent with all applicable statutes and regulations. Nothing in this Executive Order shall operate to contravene any State or federal law or to affect the State’s receipt of federal funding.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>If any provision of this Executive Order or its application to any person, entity, or circumstance is held invalid by any court of competent jurisdiction, all other provisions or applications of the Executive Order shall remain in effect to the extent possible without the invalid provision or application. To achieve this purpose, the provisions of this Executive Order are severable.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2023-07-20">Effective Date: July 20, 2023</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Maryland’s Oyster Shell and Substrate Taskforce</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Establishment. There is a Maryland’s Oyster Shell and Substrate Taskforce (“Taskforce”), housed in the Department of Natural Resources.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Membership. The Taskforce shall be comprised of members, appointed by the Governor, representing the following sectors:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of Natural Resources or their designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Secretary of Commerce or their designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A local government official;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The University of Maryland Center for Environmental Science;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A commercial waterman;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A recreational fisherman;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>An economist from one of the State’s Historically Black Colleges and Universities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The Oyster Recovery Partnership;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>A seafood company owner;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>A private oyster hatchery owner;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>The State’s aquaculture industry; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>The State’s conservation community.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Chair. The Governor shall appoint a Chair from among the members of the Taskforce.  The Chair shall serve at the pleasure of the Governor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Functions. The principal functions of the Taskforce are to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Identify strategies and solutions to retain shell, increase abundance and create an overall additive situation for oyster substrate across the Chesapeake Bay;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Evaluate strategies based on the ability to meet the demand from the public fishery, aquaculture industry and restoration component in the near term and focusing on meeting needs for the growth of all three components; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Evaluate the economic impacts substrate has on the State and develop recommendations that take into consideration costs and benefits for the fishery.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Taskforce shall meet monthly.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Taskforce Chair may convene meetings of the Taskforce and shall preside over the meetings.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A majority of the Taskforce members shall constitute a quorum for the transaction of any business.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Taskforce may adopt other procedures as necessary to ensure the orderly transaction of business.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Taskforce shall be staffed by the Department of Natural Resources.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Reports.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Taskforce shall submit a report to the Governor containing recommendations for achieving a positive oyster shell and substrate environment by December 1, 2024.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Taskforce shall hire a consultant to facilitate the reporting to the Governor, in a manner consistent with applicable law and subject to the availability of appropriations.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>This Executive Order shall be implemented in a manner that is consistent with all applicable statutes and regulations. Nothing in this Executive Order shall operate to contravene any State or federal law or to affect the State's receipt of federal funding.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>If any provision of this Executive Order or its application to any person, entity, or circumstance is held invalid by any court of competent jurisdiction, all other provisions or applications of the Executive Order shall remain in effect to the extent possible without the invalid provision or application. To achieve this purpose, the provisions of this Executive Order are severable.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2023-07-20">Effective Date: July 20, 2023</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>State of Maryland Workplace Substance Abuse Policy</heading>
    <text class="center">(Rescinds Executive Order <cite path="01.01.1991.16">01.01.1991.16</cite>)</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <heading>Scope.</heading>
      <text>This policy applies to all individuals employed by the Executive Branch of the Maryland State Government.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <heading>Definitions.</heading>
      <text>The following words have the meanings indicated:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>“Alcohol” means any form of ethanol, or any beverage or substance containing ethanol.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>“Alcohol-Related Offense” means a crime that requires alcohol possession or consumption as an element of the offense.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>“Cannabis” means the plant Cannabis Sativa L. and any part of the plant, including all derivatives, extracts, cannabinoids, isomers, acids, salts, and salts of isomers, whether growing or not, with a delta-9-tetrahydrocannabinol concentration greater than 0.3% on a dry weight basis. Cannabis includes cannabis products but does not include hemp or hemp products as defined by § 14–101 of the Agriculture Article.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4.</num>
        <text>“Cannabis-Related Offense” means any crime that involves the use, sale, possession, distribution, dispensation, manufacture, or transfer of cannabis under Md. Code Ann., Crim. Law §§ 5-101 through 5-1101, excluding civil use offenses set forth in Crim. Law 5-601(c)(2)(ii).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>5.</num>
        <text>“Controlled Dangerous Substance” means any substance, excluding cannabis, that is controlled under the Federal Controlled Substances Act, 21 U.S.C. § 801, et seq., as amended, and/or the Maryland Controlled Dangerous Substances Act, Md. Code Ann., Crim. Law §§ 5-101 through 5-1101.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>6.</num>
        <text>“Controlled Dangerous Substance Offense” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>A controlled dangerous substance violation, under Md. Code Ann., Crim. Law §§ 5-101 through 5-1101.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>An offense of the law of any other jurisdiction if the prohibited conduct would be a controlled dangerous substance violation if committed in this State;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c.</num>
          <text>Driving or attempting to drive while under the influence of a controlled dangerous substance under Md. Code Ann., Transp. § 21-902; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>d.</num>
          <text>Operating or attempting to operate a vessel while impaired by a controlled dangerous substance under Md. Code Ann., Nat. Res. § 8-738.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>7.</num>
        <text>“Conviction” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>A judgment of conviction, whether entered upon a finding of guilt or acceptance of a guilty plea or plea of nolo contendere, and the imposition of sentence; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>The staying of the entry of judgment and the placing of the defendant on probation after a finding of guilty or the acceptance of a plea of nolo contendere.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>8.</num>
        <text>“Drug” means any controlled dangerous substance, non-prescription drug, or prescription drug, taken into the body, which may impair one’s mental faculties and/or change one’s mood and/or physical performance.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>9.</num>
        <text>“Drug-Related Offenses” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>Crimes listed under the Maryland Controlled Dangerous Substances Act, Md. Code Ann., Crim. Law §§ 5-101 through 5-1101.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>Driving or attempting to drive while under the influence of drugs or drugs and alcohol under Md. Code Ann., Transp. § 21-902.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c.</num>
          <text>Operating or attempting to operate a vessel while under the influence of drugs or drugs and alcohol under Md. Code Ann., Nat. Res. § 8-738.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>10.</num>
        <text>“Employee” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>A merit-protected (classified), at will (unclassified), contractual, key employee, or other employee or official in the Executive Branch;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>A volunteer who provides a service to or for a unit in the Executive Branch; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c.</num>
          <text>A member of a Board or Commission in the Executive Branch.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>11.</num>
        <text>“Impaired” means reduced cognitive or physical ability that results from use of drugs, alcohol, cannabis, or controlled dangerous substances.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>12.</num>
        <text>“Intoxicating Cannabinoid” means a product intended for human consumption or inhalation that contains more than 0.5 milligrams of tetrahydrocannabinol per serving.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>13.</num>
        <text>“Medical Cannabis” means all parts of any plant of the genus cannabis, whether growing or not, including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>The seeds of the plant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>The resin extracted from any part of the plant; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c.</num>
          <text>Any compound, manufacture, salt, derivative, mixture, or preparation of the plant, its seeds, or resin including tetrahydrocannabinol and all other naturally produced cannabinoid derivatives, whether produced directly or indirectly by extraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>d.</num>
          <text>Medical cannabis does not include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>i.</num>
            <text>Hemp, as defined in Md. Code Ann., Agric. § 14-101;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>ii.</num>
            <text>Mature stalks of the plant or fiber produced from the mature stalks;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>iii.</num>
            <text>Oil or cake made from the seeds of the plant;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>iv.</num>
            <text>Any other compound, manufacture, salt, derivative, mixture, or preparation of the mature stalks, fiber, oil, or cake; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>v.</num>
            <text>The sterilized seed of the plant that is incapable of germination.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>14.</num>
        <text>“Non-Prescription Drug” means any over-the-counter drug that is available without a written prescription by an authorized medical professional.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>15.</num>
        <text>“Prescription Drug” means a drug that may be dispensed only on the prescription of a health practitioner who is authorized by law to prescribe the drug.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>16.</num>
        <text>“Safety-Sensitive Employee” means an employee who operates heavy machinery and includes, but are not limited to, an operator of a crane, winch, or top loader and a driver of hustler or forklift.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>17.</num>
        <text>“Sensitive Employee” means an employee whose classification or position has been designated sensitive by the Secretary of Budget and Management or the Secretary's designated representative, or the employee’s appointing authority.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>18.</num>
        <text>“Sensitive Classification” means a classification in which the Secretary of Budget and Management or the Secretary's designated representative has determined that any of the following conditions exists:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>An employee in the classification has a substantially significant degree of responsibility for the safety of others and there is a potential that impaired performance of the employee could result in death of or injury to the employee or others;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>An employee in the classification is required to carry a firearm;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c.</num>
          <text>An employee in the classification is directly involved in efforts to interdict the flow of narcotics; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>d.</num>
          <text>An employee in the classification is directly involved with narcotics law enforcement.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>19.</num>
        <text>“Sensitive Position” means a position for which an appointing authority has determined that any of the conditions listed in Section B(17) of this executive order exists, but which is not in a sensitive classification.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>20.</num>
        <text>“Substance” means alcohol, drugs, or cannabis.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>21.</num>
        <text>“Substance Abuse” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>The use of an illegal drug;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>The intentional misuse of any legal drug that results in workplace impairment and/or impaired job performance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c.</num>
          <text>The intentional use of any prescription drug in a manner inconsistent with its medically prescribed, intended use, or under circumstances where its use is not permitted;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>d.</num>
          <text>The use of alcohol where such use results in workplace impairment and/or impairs job performance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>e.</num>
          <text>The use of cannabis where such use results in workplace impairment and/or impairs job performance; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>f.</num>
          <text>The intentional and inappropriate use of any substance, legal or illegal, which impairs job performance.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>22.</num>
        <text>“Workplace” means any place where an employee is performing work for the State of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>23.</num>
        <text>“Work Time” means time during which an employee:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>Is on duty, whether at the employee’s principal work site or at a remote location as part of the State's telecommuting program;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>Participates in training activities as a job assignment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c.</num>
          <text>Is on the employer's premises and is on call and waiting for work;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>d.</num>
          <text>Is not on the employer's premises, but is on call and waiting for work, and the employee's personal activities are substantially restricted;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>e.</num>
          <text>Is changing into and removing program-specified clothing and equipment necessary for the performance of the job;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>f.</num>
          <text>Participates in activities that are job-related immediately before the beginning or immediately after the end of an assigned shift;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>g.</num>
          <text>Travels to and from work after being recalled to work by the appointing authority or the appointing authority's designated representative after the employee has completed the standard workday;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>h.</num>
          <text>Travels to and from work after being called to work by the appointing authority or the appointing authority's designated representative on the employee's scheduled day off if the employee works fewer than 8 hours as a result of being called on the employee's scheduled day off;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>i.</num>
          <text>Travels between home and a work site other than the assigned office, in accordance with the Standard Travel Regulations,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>j.</num>
          <text>Work time includes any other time defined as work time under the Fair Labor Standards Act, 29 U.S.C. §201 et seq., if applicable.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <heading>General Policy.</heading>
      <text>The State of Maryland establishes the following Substance Abuse Policy for the Executive Branch of State Government:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>All employees in the workplace must be capable of performing their duties. An employee shall not report to work, or spend any work time, in an unfit condition to perform their duties.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>Substance abuse by any employee is prohibited at all times.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>Employees experiencing substance use problems are encouraged to seek assistance through:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>Their employer;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>Referral to the Employee Assistance Program (“EAP”);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c.</num>
          <text>Self-referral to the MyMDCares program or similar state-sponsored assistance program; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>d.</num>
          <text>Self-referral to an alternative certified rehabilitation program.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <heading>Alcohol &amp; Cannabis Abuse Policy.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Alcohol &amp; Cannabis.</heading>
        <text>An employee shall not report to work, or spend any work time, under the influence of alcohol, cannabis, or intoxicating cannabinoids. Any employee who reports to work, or spends any work time, with their mental or physical abilities impaired by alcohol or cannabis, is in violation of this policy and shall be subject to disciplinary action.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>Employees may not consume alcohol or consume, smoke, or otherwise ingest cannabis or intoxicating cannabinoid on State property, at any worksite, or during work hours or while on work time. This conduct is also prohibited for employees on official business, whether on or off State Property.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>The unlawful manufacture, distribution, dispensation, possession, or use of cannabis or intoxicating cannabinoids is prohibited on State property, at any worksite, or during work hours or while on work time.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4.</num>
        <text>Employees are prohibited from consuming alcohol and/or cannabis and/or being under the influence of alcohol, cannabis, or an intoxicating cannabinoid while operating State equipment, vehicles, or other property.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>5.</num>
        <text>Employees are prohibited from committing alcohol or cannabis-related offenses or offenses relating to intoxicating cannabinoids.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>6.</num>
        <text>Employees who plead guilty, accept a plea of nolo contendere, receive a probation before judgment, or are convicted of an alcohol or cannabis-related offense or an offense relating to intoxicating cannabinoids are in violation of this policy and must report the disposition of the case to their supervisor and/or appointing authority no later than five (5) workdays after the disposition.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Medical Cannabis.</heading>
        <text>Employees who are registered and certified medical cannabis patients may not possess, consume, smoke, or otherwise ingest cannabis on State property, at any worksite or during Work Time.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>8.</num>
        <text>Employees who are registered and certified medical cannabis patients are responsible for consulting the certifying provider to ascertain whether the medical cannabis will interfere with the safe performance of their job duties.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>9.</num>
        <text>If the use of any medical cannabis could compromise an employee’s performance or the safety of the employee, fellow employees, or the public, it is the employee’s responsibility to notify their supervisor and/or appointing authority and use appropriate leave to avoid unsafe work practices.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <heading>Drug Abuse Policy.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Prescription &amp; Over-The-Counter Drugs.</heading>
        <text>Prescription and over-the-counter drugs must be taken in standard dosage and/or according to a physician’s prescription.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>Employees who take prescribed or over-the-counter medications are responsible for consulting the prescribing physician and/or pharmacist to ascertain whether the medication will interfere with the safe performance of their job duties.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>If the use of any prescription or over-the counter drug could compromise an employee’s performance or the safety of the employee, fellow employees, or the public, it is the employee’s responsibility to notify their supervisor and/or appointing authority and use appropriate leave to avoid unsafe work practices.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4.</num>
        <text>An employee shall not report to work, or spend any work time, under the inappropriate influence of prescription or over-the-counter drugs. Any employee who reports to work, or spends any work time, with their mental or physical abilities inappropriately impaired by prescription or over-the-counter drugs is in violation of this policy and shall be subject to disciplinary action.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Controlled Dangerous Substances.</heading>
        <text>Any employee who reports to work, or spends any work time, with their mental or physical abilities impaired by a controlled dangerous substance is in violation of this policy and shall be subject to disciplinary action.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>6.</num>
        <text>The unlawful manufacture, distribution, dispensation, possession, or use of controlled dangerous substances is prohibited on State property, at any worksite, or during work hours or while on work time.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>7.</num>
        <text>Employees are prohibited from committing controlled dangerous substance offenses.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>8.</num>
        <text>Employees who plead guilty, accept a plea of nolo contendere, receive a probation before judgment, or are convicted of a controlled dangerous substance offense, are in violation of this policy and must report the disposition of the case to their supervisor and/or appointing authority no later than five (5) workdays after the disposition.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>General Drug Abuse Policies.</heading>
        <text>Employees are prohibited from committing drug-related offenses.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>10.</num>
        <text>Employees who plead guilty, accept a plea of nolo contendere, receive a probation before judgment, or are convicted of a drug-related offense, are in violation of this policy and must report the disposition of the case to their supervisor and/or appointing authority no later than five (5) workdays after the disposition.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <heading>General Sanctions.</heading>
      <text>Any employee in violation of this Executive Order shall be subject to appropriate progressive disciplinary action up to and including termination.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <heading>Specific Sanctions.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>A sensitive or safety-sensitive employee shall be suspended for fifteen (15) days and required to successfully participate in an alcohol or cannabis treatment program designated by an EAP the first time the employee is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>Convicted of an at-the-workplace alcohol or cannabis-related offense; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>Found under the influence of alcohol or cannabis while at-the-workplace.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>A sensitive or safety-sensitive employee convicted of an out-of-workplace alcohol or cannabis-related offense, and a non-sensitive or safety-sensitive employee convicted of any alcohol or cannabis-related offense shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>On the first conviction be referred to an EAP and subject to any other appropriate disciplinary actions;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>On the second conviction, at a minimum, be suspended for at least five (5) days, be referred to an EAP, be required to participate successfully in a treatment program, and be subject to any other appropriate disciplinary actions, up to and including termination;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c.</num>
          <text>On the third conviction, be terminated.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>A sensitive or safety-sensitive employee convicted of any controlled dangerous substance offense shall be terminated.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4.</num>
        <text>A sensitive or safety-sensitive employee who tests positive for a controlled dangerous substance as a result of a random drug test shall be suspended for fifteen (15) workdays and be required to successfully participate in a drug treatment program designated by an EAP, as provided for by the appointing authority's drug testing protocol.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>5.</num>
        <text>A sensitive or safety-sensitive employee who abuses a legally prescribed drug or an over-the-counter drug shall, on the first offense:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>Be suspended for five (5) workdays; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>Be required to participate successfully in a drug treatment program designated by an EAP.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <heading>Assistance &amp; Treatment.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>An employee may request referral to the EAP for access to confidential professional assistance for substance use problems or may self-refer to the MyMDCares program or similar state-sponsored assistance program to receive confidential professional assistance.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>Employees will not be terminated solely for requesting referral to the EAP or voluntarily obtaining other assistance and/or treatment for a substance use problem. The State of Maryland encourages any employee who needs such assistance and treatment to seek and obtain it. However, participation in a treatment or recovery program will neither relieve employees from the requirement of satisfactory job performance, nor insulate them from termination or adverse personnel actions for failing to comply with any of the State’s policies and procedures.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>Substance abuse-related disciplinary actions, up to and including termination, may be, but do not have to be, held in abeyance pending an employee’s completion of an assistance and treatment program. The option of holding a disciplinary action in abeyance is not an employee entitlement or right but is a privilege to be granted at the discretion of the appointing authority, in consultation with the Department of Budget and Management, or the individual responsible for Human Resources for the respective State agency under appropriate circumstances.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <heading>Implementation.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>The Secretary of Budget &amp; Management and the head of every other personnel system in the Executive Branch shall adopt such policies and regulations as are necessary or desirable for the implementation of this Executive Order.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>All appointing authorities and supervisory employees are responsible for implementing, enforcing, and monitoring compliance with the requirements of this Executive Order.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>All employees are required to acknowledge receipt of a copy of this Executive Order by returning an acknowledgement of receipt to their supervisor for insertion in their personnel file.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <heading>Enforcement.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>If a supervisor or appointing authority observes any signs of possible substance abuse in any employee during working hours, this shall constitute reasonable grounds for an investigation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>If a non-supervisory employee observes any signs of possible substance abuse in any employee during working hours and reports it to a supervisor or appointing authority, this shall constitute reasonable grounds for an investigation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>A supervisor and/or appointing authority, on observing such signs or receiving a report, in consultation with the Department of Budget and Management, or the individual responsible for Human Resources for the respective State agency, should investigate by appropriate measures.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4.</num>
        <text>If the supervisory investigation supports a conclusion of substance abuse by the investigated employee(s), the supervisor and/or appointing authority shall consult the Department of Budget and Management, the individual responsible for Human Resources for the respective State agency, or the State Medical Director to determine the appropriate next steps, which may include testing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>5.</num>
        <text>When an appointing authority learns or based on observation or reliable information, suspects that an employee has committed an alcohol-related offense, cannabis-related offense, controlled dangerous substance offense, or other drug-related offense, the appointing authority shall refer the matter to the appropriate law enforcement authority for further investigation and prosecution.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>6.</num>
        <text>All employees shall cooperate fully with law enforcement authorities in the investigation and prosecution of suspected criminal violations.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <heading>Employee Education.</heading>
      <text>All appointing authorities shall educate and inform their employees about:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>The dangers of drug and alcohol abuse in the workplace;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>The State of Maryland's policy of maintaining a drug-free workplace;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>Any drug and alcohol abuse counseling, rehabilitation, and EAP that is available; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4.</num>
        <text>The penalties that may be imposed upon employees for violations of this Executive Order.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>This policy does not constitute or create an express or implied contract. It is not intended to, and does not, create contractual obligations with respect to any matter it covers.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>This Executive Order shall be implemented in a manner that is consistent with all applicable statutes and regulations. Nothing in this Executive Order shall operate to contravene any State or federal law or to affect the State's receipt of federal funding.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>If a State entity is subject to a federal law or regulation that conflicts with this Executive Order, the federal law or regulation shall take precedence.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>If any provision of this Executive Order or its application to any person, entity, or circumstance is held invalid by any court of competent jurisdiction, all other provisions or applications of the Executive Order shall remain in effect to the extent possible without the invalid provision or application. To achieve this purpose, the provisions of this Executive Order are severable.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2023-11-08">Effective Date: November 8, 2023</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.17</num>
    <heading>Commission to Establish a Memorial to Veterans of the Global War on Terrorism</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Establishment. There is a Commission to Establish a Memorial to Veterans of the Global War on Terrorism.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Membership. The Commission consists of the following members:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, or the Secretary’s designee, who shall serve as Chair of the Commission;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>the Secretary of General Services, or the Secretary’s designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>two representatives of the Maryland Veterans Commission, designated by the  Secretary of Veterans Affairs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>four representatives of veteran services organizations, designated by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>one representative of the Maryland National Guard, designated by the Adjutant General of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Duties. The Commission shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provide recommendations for the funding, design, construction, and placement of an appropriate memorial dedicated to Marylanders who fought in the Global War on Terrorism and their families;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>On or before April 1, 2024, submit a preliminary report on its findings and recommendations to the Governor and, in accordance with § 2-1257 of the State Government Article, to the General Assembly; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>On or before December 1, 2024, submit a final report on its findings and recommendations to the Governor and, in accordance with § 2-1257 of the State Government Article, to the General Assembly.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Operational Support. The Department of Veterans Affairs shall provide staff for the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Expenses. A member of the Commission may not receive compensation for their services, but may be reimbursed for reasonable expenses incurred in the performance of their duties, in accordance with the Standard State Travel Regulations, as provided in the State budget.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Commission Chair may convene meetings of the Commission and shall preside over the meetings.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Commission shall conduct its first meeting following the submission of the final report of the Commission to Establish a Maryland Women Veterans Memorial.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Commission shall meet as often as its duties require.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A majority of the Commission members shall constitute a quorum for the transaction of any business;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Commission may adopt such other procedures and by-laws as may be necessary to ensure the orderly transaction of business.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>This Executive Order shall be implemented in a manner that is consistent with all applicable statutes and regulations. Nothing in this Executive Order shall operate to contravene any State or federal law or to affect the State's receipt of federal funding.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>If any provision of this Executive Order or its application to any person, entity, or circumstance is held invalid by any court of competent jurisdiction, all other provisions or applications of the Executive Order shall remain in effect to the extent possible without the invalid provision or application. To achieve this purpose, the provisions of this Executive Order are severable.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2023-11-09">Effective Date: November 9, 2023.</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.18</num>
    <heading>Preventing Suicide Among Military Service Members, Veterans and Their Families</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Secretary of Health and the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, or their respective designees (the “Secretaries”), shall jointly lead Maryland’s efforts to prevent suicide among service members, veterans and their families.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Secretaries of Health and Veterans Affairs shall convene an annual meeting at a time and place to be determined, to discuss and assess the State’s efforts to prevent suicide among service members, veterans and their families.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Within 30 days of the issuance of this Executive Order, the Secretaries of Health and Veterans Affairs shall conduct a review of the State’s short term suicide prevention strategy to identify any necessary adjustments.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Thereafter, in cooperation and in consultation with the appropriate State Agencies, the Secretaries shall launch a statewide “Ask the Question” campaign to provide standardized tools to all State Agencies, local governments, private sector entities, and non-profit organizations to screen constituents and customers for a military service connection in order to provide opportunities for appropriate referrals and assessment for suicide risk.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Secretaries shall, though outreach and other appropriate means, elevate awareness of available funding for Maryland counties to advance goals set forth in the Governor’s Challenge, including developing a coordinated intervention plan to respond to service members, veterans, and their families experiencing mental health crises, and help identify counties ready to implement the Challenge.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Secretaries shall engage with the VA and SAMHSA to facilitate community and State-level efforts to prevent suicide by service members, veterans, and their families, using all available resources.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Every agency, department, office, division, or public authority of the State shall cooperate with the Secretaries, and, to the fullest extent permitted by law, shall furnish such information and assistance as the Secretaries determine is reasonably necessary to accomplish the purposes of this Executive Order.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>This Executive Order shall be implemented in a manner that is consistent with all applicable statutes and regulations. Nothing in this Executive Order shall operate to contravene any State or federal law or to affect the State’s receipt of federal funding.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2023-11-09">Effective Date: November 9, 2023</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.19</num>
    <heading>Procurement Guidelines: Authorizing Project Labor Agreements for Large-Scale Public Work Contracts and Promoting Apprenticeship Agreements and Community Hiring</heading>
    <text class="center">(Rescinds Executive Order <cite path="01.01.2013.05">01.01.2013.05</cite>)</text>
    <text class="center">(Amended by Executive Order <cite path="01.01.2024.18">01.01.2024.18</cite>)</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text><u>Scope.</u> These guidelines apply to any State department, agency, authority, board, or instrumentality, within the executive branch of the Maryland State Government, that is under the control of the Governor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text><u>Definitions.</u> The following words have the meanings indicated:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>“Community Benefit Agreement” means a contract signed by one or more recognized community association(s) and a labor organization that requires the labor organization to provide specific amenities, mitigations, economic impacts, local workforce training guarantees and/or other benefits in exchange for community support of a project.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>“Construction” means the (1) process of building, altering, improving, or demolishing an improvement to real property and (2) includes any major work necessary to repair, prevent damage to, or sustain existing components of an improvement to real property, as defined in Md. Code Ann., State Fin. &amp; Proc. § 11-101(f)(1)-(2).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>“Labor Organization” means a labor organization as defined in Md. Code Ann., State Gov't § 20-601(i)(1)-(2) of which building and construction employees are members.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4.</num>
        <text>“Large-scale public work contract” means a contract for construction of a public work, as defined in Md. Code Ann., State Fin. &amp; Proc. § 17-201(k), for which the total monies committed by the State, including direct funding, issuance of bonds, and tax increment financing is $20 million or more.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>5.</num>
        <text>“Project Labor Agreement” is a pre-hire collective bargaining agreement between the successful bidder on a large-scale public work contract and one or more labor organizations that establishes terms and conditions of employment for all crafts performing work on a specific construction project.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>6.</num>
        <text>“Recognized Community Association” means a community group located in an area impacted by the large-scale public work contract that is organized collectively around particular interests for the purpose of addressing issues and interests common to that community.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>7.</num>
        <text>“Registered Apprenticeship Program” means a program that is registered with, and approved by, the U.S. Department of Labor or the Maryland Department of Labor, evidenced by a certificate of registration or other appropriate document as meeting the apprenticeship standards.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>8.</num>
        <text>“Socioeconomic Procurement Programs” refer collectively to the State’s Minority Business Enterprise Program; Veteran-owned Small Business Enterprise Program; and Small Business Reserve Program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>9.</num>
        <text>“Socioeconomic Procurement Program Goals” refer to the State’s goals of directing 29% of all procurement expenditures towards certified Minority Business Enterprise firms and 1% towards certified Veteran-Owned Small Business Enterprise firms.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>10.</num>
        <text>“Unit of State government” means an agency or unit of the Executive Branch of State government.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <aftertext>
      <u>Authorizing Project Labor Agreements for Large-Scale Public Work Contracts</u>
    </aftertext>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A unit of State government shall consider either (1) requiring the use of a project labor agreement or (2) including the use of a project labor agreement as an evaluation factor in connection with a large-scale public work contract that meets the criteria established in this Order.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The decision to require the use of a project labor agreement or include the use of a project labor agreement as an evaluation factor in connection with a large-scale public work contract shall be made on a project-by-project basis.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The decision to require the use of a project labor agreement or include the use of a project labor agreement as an evaluation factor in connection with a large-scale public work contract shall be made only where such an agreement will advance the State’s interest in cost-effectiveness, efficiency, quality, health, safety, timeliness, employing a skilled labor force, and producing labor stability.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>In making the decision whether to require the use of a project labor agreement or include the use of a project labor agreement as an evaluation factor in connection with a large-scale public work contract, the following factors must be considered:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>The potential for labor disruptions, such as strikes, lockouts, or slowdowns, which could affect completion of the project;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>The number of trades and crafts anticipated to be used on the project;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>The need and urgency of the project and the harm to the public if completion of the project is delayed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4.</num>
        <text>The size and complexity of the project;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>5.</num>
        <text>The funding sources for the project and whether the project includes federal funds;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>6.</num>
        <text>The impact on project costs, if any, and the State’s obligation to encourage maximum practicable competition favoring open competitive bidding during the procurement process;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>7.</num>
        <text>The impact on the State’s socioeconomic policies, including the policy to advance women and minority-owned businesses and their ability to compete.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The decision to require the use of a project labor agreement or include the use of a project labor agreement as an evaluation factor in connection with a large-scale public work contract shall be made prior to selecting the method of contracting for the project and shall be supported by written findings that clearly demonstrate how the use of a project labor agreement will benefit the project and the interests of the public and the State from a cost-effective, efficiency, quality, safety and timeliness standpoint. The fact that a project labor agreement will be used or included as an evaluation factor shall be set forth in the solicitation of bids issued for the project.</text>
    </para>
    <aftertext>
      <u>Requirements for Project Labor Agreements</u>
    </aftertext>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Any project labor agreement reached pursuant to this Order shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>Bind all contractors and subcontractors on the construction project through the inclusion of appropriate bid specifications in all relevant solicitation provisions and contract documents;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>Allow all union and non-union contractors, subcontractors, and material suppliers who agree to abide by the terms of the project labor agreement to compete for work to be performed and materials to be provided without regard to whether they are otherwise parties to collective bargaining agreements;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>Contain guarantees against strikes, lockouts, slowdowns, or other similar disruptions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4.</num>
        <text>Set forth effective, prompt, and mutually binding procedures for resolving labor disputes arising before the work is completed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>5.</num>
        <text>Guarantee equal opportunities in employment and prohibit discrimination in recruiting, interviewing, hiring, upgrading, setting work conditions, or discharging employees or workers as required by federal and State law;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>6.</num>
        <text>Demonstrate access to a reliable supply of properly trained labor personnel who possess the requisite skill and safety training to ensure successful project delivery;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>7.</num>
        <text>Provide other mechanisms for labor-management cooperation on matters of mutual interest and concern, including productivity, quality or work, safety, and health;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>8.</num>
        <text>Outline a diversity plan that details efforts and commitments to conduct outreach and recruitment for employment and apprenticeship positions in the large-scale public work contract for minority group members, members of disadvantaged communities, and women; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>9.</num>
        <text>Outline a plan that details how expenditures for the large-scale public work contract will support the State’s Socioeconomic Procurement Program Goals.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>10.</num>
        <text>Fully conform to all State and federal statutes, regulations, and executive orders.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <aftertext>
      <u>Incorporating Community Benefit Agreements</u>
    </aftertext>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>If a unit of State government decides to require the use of a project labor agreement in connection with a large-scale public work contract, the State unit shall consider requiring bidders to incorporate a community benefit agreement for appropriate projects.</text>
    </para>
    <text>
      <u>Project Labor Agreements Not Required</u>
    </text>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>This Order does not require a unit of State government to use or include the use of a project labor agreement as an evaluation factor in connection with a large-scale public work contract.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>This Order does not promote the selection of any union, trade council, or labor organization.</text>
    </para>
    <aftertext>
      <u>Apprenticeship Programs for Public Projects and Public-Private Partnerships</u>
    </aftertext>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>A unit of State government shall consider whether it is in the best interest of the State to use contractors who participate in registered apprenticeship programs and offer a reliable plan for labor staffing on a public project or public-private partnership.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>The decision to require or encourage the use of contractors who participate in registered apprenticeship programs and offer a reliable plan for labor staffing on a public project or public-private partnership shall be made on a project-by-project basis.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>The decision to require or encourage the use of contractors who participate in registered apprenticeship programs and offer a reliable plan for labor staffing on a public project or public-private partnership shall be made only where such an agreement will advance the State’s interest in cost-effectiveness, efficiency, quality, health, safety, timeliness, employing a skilled labor force, and producing labor stability.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>In making the decision to require or encourage the use of contractors who participate in registered apprenticeship programs and offer a reliable plan for labor staffing on a public project or public-private partnership, the unit of State government shall consider the totality of the circumstances, including the following factors:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>The number of trades and crafts anticipated to be used on the project;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>The need and urgency of the project and the harm to the public if completion of the project is delayed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>The size and complexity of the project;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4.</num>
        <text>The impact on project costs, if any, and the State’s obligation to encourage maximum practicable competition favoring open competitive bidding during the procurement process;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>5.</num>
        <text>The impact on the State’s socioeconomic procurement program policies, including the policy to advance women and minority-owned businesses and their ability to compete; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>6.</num>
        <text>The impact on workforce development and construction and the potential for generating skills training and employment opportunities for state residents.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>P.</num>
      <text>The decision to require or encourage the use of contractors who participate in registered apprenticeship programs and offer a reliable plan for labor staffing on a public project or public-private partnership shall be made prior to selecting the method of contracting for the project or partnership and shall be supported by written findings that set forth the justification.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>Q.</num>
      <text>For public projects or public-private partnerships where the use of contractors who participate in registered apprenticeship programs and offer a reliable plan for labor staffing will be required or encouraged, applicable procurement documents shall clearly:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>Specify whether such qualifications are mandatory or will be used as an evaluation factor in awarding the contract; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>State any applicable apprenticeship utilization targets or thresholds that will be considered in the determination.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>R.</num>
      <text>The Maryland Department of Labor shall determine whether a proffered apprenticeship program is in compliance with applicable program requirements before the contracting agency makes a decision.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>S.</num>
      <text>A successful bidder shall demonstrate how the bidder will have access to the reliable supply of properly trained labor personnel who possess the requisite skill and safety training to ensure successful delivery through either sponsoring an apprenticeship program that will supply apprentices to the project or reaching an agreement with an entity that operates a registered apprenticeship program that will ensure such supply.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>T.</num>
      <text>The bidder’s fulfillment of the requirements under section (S) of this Order must be approved by the State unit overseeing the project.</text>
    </para>
    <aftertext>
      <u>Community Hiring in High Unemployment Areas</u>
    </aftertext>
    <para>
      <num>U.</num>
      <text>On public projects or public-private partnerships with projected costs exceeding $5 million, a unit of State government shall consider whether all or a substantial part of the project is within an area of higher than average unemployment and, if so, whether it is in the best interest of the State to weigh as a factor in the procurement or public notice of solicitation whether a bidder voluntarily submits a community hiring, training, and/or outreach plan for high unemployment areas.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>V.</num>
      <text>If a unit of State government determines based on the totality of the circumstances, that it is in the best interests of the State to encourage the voluntary submission of a community hiring, training and/or outreach plan on a public project or public-private partnership, the decision shall be accompanied by the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>A written finding that sets forth the reasons supporting the decision</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>A definition of “high unemployment area” and delineation of that area for purposes of the procurement or public notice of solicitation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>An explanation of how the proffer of a community hiring, training, and/or outreach plan will be evaluated and weighed in the procurement or public notice of solicitation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <aftertext>
      <u>General Provisions</u>
    </aftertext>
    <para>
      <num>W.</num>
      <text>The guidelines contained in this Executive Order do not constitute or create an express or implied contract. It is not intended to, and does not, create contractual obligations with respect to any matter it covers.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>X.</num>
      <text>Nothing in this Executive Order shall preclude a unit of State government from considering either (1) requiring the use of a project labor agreement or (2) including the use of a project labor agreement as an evaluation factor in connection with a large-scale public work contract where the State commitment is below $20 million.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>Y.</num>
      <text>This Executive Order shall be implemented in a manner that is consistent with all applicable statutes and regulations. Nothing in this Executive Order shall operate to contravene any State or federal law or to affect the State's receipt of federal funding.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>Z.</num>
      <text>If any provision of this Executive Order or its application to any person, entity, or circumstance is held invalid by any court of competent jurisdiction, all other provisions or applications of the Executive Order shall remain in effect to the extent possible without the invalid provision or application. To achieve this purpose, the provisions of this Executive Order are severable.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2023-11-17">Effective Date: November 17, 2023.</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.20</num>
    <heading>State of Preparedness</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definitions. In this Executive Order, the following terms have the meaning indicated.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“State Agency” means a department, agency, commission, board, council or other body of state government subject to the direction and supervision of the Governor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“State Coordinating Functions” provide the structure for coordinating State interagency support for State preparedness, response, and recovery efforts. They are comprised of one or more Lead State agencies and one or more Support State agencies as defined in the Maryland Consequence Management Operations Plan.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Public Emergency” as defined in the Maryland Emergency Management Act, Md. Code, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|14-301">Public Safety Article, § 14-301</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Declaring a State of Preparedness. When the Governor determines there is significant risk of a Public Emergency, the Governor by Executive Order may declare a State of Preparedness.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Upon declaring a State of Preparedness, the Department of Emergency Management shall, as necessary:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Establish a common operating understanding of the incident or event’s level of risk as supported by information provided by State Coordinating Functions, county emergency management officials, and other credible sources;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Convene State Coordinating Function leads and county emergency management officials;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Convene a Senior Policy Group to streamline critical decisions and advise the Governor related to the risk, potential impacts, and preparedness actions of State Government; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Coordinate resource management in accordance with established systems to provide quick response in the event an emergency develops.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Under a State of Preparedness, State Agencies, through each State Coordinating Function, shall at a minimum:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provide all known or available information pertinent to the identified risk and associated hazards to the Maryland Department of Emergency Management to support its development of a common operating understanding for the potential emergency incident or event;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Make available their existing subject matter experts related to the risk, potential hazards, and potential emergency responses;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Assign personnel to an Advance Team, State Emergency Operations Center activation, or other coordinating entity identified by the Maryland Department of Emergency Management as requiring support; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Seek to fulfill resource requests with existing State resources prior to requesting aid from the Maryland Department of Emergency Management without limiting resource fulfillment to only those assets within the direct control of the department or agency assigned the request.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Nothing herein shall limit, abrogate, or preempt local authority for responding to an emergency unless:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>the emergency involves more than one political subdivision and one or more of the political subdivisions involved makes a request for State-level authority to coordinate or intervene;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>the political subdivision or subdivisions in which the emergency occurs issues a request from the senior elected official for the State to assume authority for the emergency;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>evidence exists that the political subdivision is overwhelmed by the emergency; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>the Governor or the Governor's designee determines that additional resources are necessary to protect the public interest.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Nothing herein shall be construed to limit or abrogate the ongoing existing responsibilities of executive branch state agencies to coordinate, prepare and plan for emergencies and imminent threats and hazards to the state in coordination with the Maryland Department of Emergency Management.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>At all times, in the absence of a declaration, State of Preparedness, or State of Emergency, executive branch state agencies will coordinate with the Maryland Department of Emergency Management for the public peace, safety and health of the State of Maryland, by engaging in emergency preparedness, disaster risk reduction, and consequence management operations and activities of the state as defined in the Maryland Department of Emergency Management’s Consequence Management Operations Plan and State of Maryland Hazard Mitigation Plan.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>A State of Preparedness shall terminate:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>within thirty days (30);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>upon a State or federal declaration of a State of Emergency;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>upon a Presidential Disaster Declaration; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>upon the Governor’s rescinding of the State of Preparedness.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>This Executive Order shall be implemented in a manner that is consistent with all applicable statutes and regulations. Nothing in this Executive Order shall operate to contravene any State or federal law or to affect the State’s receipt or federal funding.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>If any provision of this Executive Order is held invalid, or its application to a person, event or circumstances is held invalid by any court of competent jurisdiction, all other applications or provisions of the Executive Order shall remain in effect to the greatest extent possible without the invalid provision or application. To achieve this purpose, the provisions of this Executive Order are severable.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2023-11-20">Effective Date: November 20, 2023.</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.21</num>
    <heading>Maryland’s Office of Overdose Response</heading>
    <text class="center">(Rescinds Executive Orders <cite path="01.01.2022.07">01.01.2022.07</cite>, <cite path="01.01.2022.05">01.01.2022.05</cite>, <cite path="01.01.2018.30">01.01.2018.30</cite>, <cite path="01.01.2017.01">01.01.2017.01</cite>, and <cite path="01.01.2015.13">01.01.2015.13</cite>)</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Maryland’s Office of Overdose Response</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>There is a Maryland’s Office of Overdose Response (the “Office”) within the Maryland Department of Health.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Office shall be managed by a Special Secretary of Overdose Response, who serves at the pleasure of the Governor. The Special Secretary shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Direct the daily operation and administration of the Office;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Act as a coordinating liaison to the Maryland Overdose Response Advisory Council;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Provide advice and recommendations to the Governor on matters related to overdose; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Coordinate with federal and local governments to strengthen overdose prevention and response programs and initiatives.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Staffing.  The Special Secretary shall select, organize, and direct the staff of Maryland’s Office of Overdose Response.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Duties.  The Office shall be responsible for the following activities:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Facilitate statewide coordination of overdose prevention and response efforts across Maryland’s 24 local jurisdictions and State agencies;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Coordinate the interagency process to develop the Governor's policy agenda affecting overdose prevention and response programs and initiatives;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Support local jurisdictions through grant funds to their Overdose Prevention Teams, as established by Section C, below;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Conduct and coordinate public outreach on behalf of the Governor to encourage greater involvement and participation by community organizations and constituent groups;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Assist in the identification of funding opportunities for State and local agencies and community organizations to implement initiatives that further the State’s goal of reducing overdose morbidity and mortality;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Coordinate and consult on matters relating to overdose prevention and response initiatives across State government; emphasize communication and cooperation with federal and local governments on all overdose-related concerns; and provide recommendations to enhance intergovernmental prevention and response efforts;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Coordinate and facilitate data sharing among State and local sources while maintaining the privacy and security of sensitive personal information; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Provide staff to the Maryland Overdose Response Advisory Council.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Maryland’s Office of Overdose Response is the successor agency of the Opioid Operational Command Center.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Overdose Prevention Teams</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Prior to receiving funds from the Office, each county and the City of Baltimore shall establish an Overdose Prevention Team that meets at least quarterly and reports activities and data to Maryland’s Office of Overdose Response annually.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An Overdose Prevention Team shall include, but is not limited to, individuals with experience in:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Health;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Social services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Education;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Public safety agencies, including law enforcement, fire service, and emergency services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Harm reduction programs;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Recovery support programs;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Substance use treatment; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Community and faith-based organizations.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Maryland Overdose Response Advisory Council</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>There is a Maryland Overdose Response Advisory Council (the “Council”).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Membership.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Council shall include individuals from the following State agencies:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Maryland’s Office of Overdose Response;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Department of Health;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Department of Human Services;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Department of Housing and Community Development;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Department of Labor;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Department of Commerce;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Department of Education;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Department of Public Safety and Correctional Services;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ix)</num>
            <text>Department of Juvenile Services;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(x)</num>
            <text>Department of Emergency Management;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xi)</num>
            <text>Department of Veterans Affairs;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xii)</num>
            <text>Department of Aging;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xiii)</num>
            <text>Department of Disabilities;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xiv)</num>
            <text>Governor’s Office of Crime Prevention, Youth and Victim Services;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xv)</num>
            <text>Institute for Emergency Medical Services Systems;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xvi)</num>
            <text>Office of the Public Defender;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xvii)</num>
            <text>Maryland Judiciary; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xviii)</num>
            <text>Maryland State Police.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Staff members from the Offices of the Governor and Lieutenant Governor will also be regular participants.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Other State agencies may be asked to participate at the invitation of the Chair.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Duties. The Council shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Facilitate data sharing among respective agencies;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Identify emerging challenges related to the provision of substance use disorder services and develop recommendations to address those challenges;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Promote equity in the provision of substance use disorder services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Share data related to equity among all relevant agencies;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Coordinate the implementation of recommendations of Maryland’s Commission for Health Equity related to overdose mortality and the Racial Disparities in Overdose Taskforce; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Submit a report to the Governor annually by November 1.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Procedures.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Lieutenant Governor shall chair the Council. The Chair shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Oversee the work of the Council;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Determine the Council’s agenda; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Identify additional support as needed.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Council shall meet on a quarterly basis, at minimum.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A majority of the Council members shall constitute a quorum for the transaction of any business.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Council may adopt other procedures as necessary to ensure the orderly transaction of business.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Members from the Offices of the Governor and Lieutenant Governor will be regular participants.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Other state agencies as needed.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Maryland’s Office of Overdose Response shall provide staff to the Council.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>All State departments, agencies, commissions, and boards are directed to cooperate with Maryland’s Office of Overdose Response in implementing the provisions of this Executive Order, including but not limited to, sharing relevant data.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Reports. Maryland’s Office of Overdose Response shall submit a report to the Governor and the public in the form of an interagency coordination plan by December 1, 2024, and thereafter annually by December 1.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>This Executive Order shall be implemented in a manner that is consistent with all applicable statutes and regulations. Nothing in this Executive Order shall operate to contravene any State or federal law or to affect the State's receipt of federal funding.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>If any provision of this Executive Order or its application to any person, entity, or circumstance is held invalid by any court of competent jurisdiction, all other provisions or applications of the Executive Order shall remain in effect to the extent possible without the invalid provision or application. To achieve this purpose, the provisions of this Executive Order are severable.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2023-12-14">Effective Date: December 14, 2023.</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.22</num>
    <heading>Governor's Workforce Development Board</heading>
    <text class="center">(Rescinds Executive Order <cite path="01.01.2015.19">01.01.2015.19</cite>)</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Establishment. There is a Governor's Workforce Development Board (the “Board”).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Duties and Responsibilities.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board shall serve as the Governor’s chief strategic and policy-making body for workforce development by engaging key business, labor, education, community, and State and local government leaders to collaborate on business-led workforce approaches that advance Maryland’s economic competitiveness and build pathways to work, wages and wealth for all Marylanders.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The priorities of the Board shall include, but are not limited to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Building talent pipelines to supercharge growth in Maryland’s key industry sectors;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Addressing barriers to employment experienced by underserved populations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Expanding access to affordable, high-quality, career-connected experiential learning and industry-recognized credentials, including apprenticeship and career and technical education opportunities;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Aligning systems, services and resources to strategically leverage Maryland’s assets; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Supporting collaboration with local workforce development boards and other local stakeholders to ensure those closest to workforce challenges are central to the solutions.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Board shall execute the duties and responsibilities enumerated in the 2014 Act, including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Help to set and communicate the Governor’s workforce development vision, goals, and strategy;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Align activities of key business, labor, education, workforce development, cabinet and local stakeholders to execute that vision;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Develop industry partnerships to support workforce development goals;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Direct or recommend funding to support those activities as appropriate;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Offer policy recommendations to the Governor’s office for consideration;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Support the continuous improvement of workforce development system and program performance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Develop other policies as may promote statewide objectives for and enhance the performance of the workforce development system in the State;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Assist and advise the Governor on the development, implementation, and modification of the State Plan under the 2014 Act;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Develop the statewide workforce and labor market information system described in the Wagner-Peyser Act; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Prepare the 2014 Act annual reports.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Membership. The Board shall include but is not limited to the following members:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Governor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>One member of the Maryland Senate, appointed by the President of the Senate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>One member of the Maryland House of Delegates, appointed by the Speaker of the House;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The following Maryland Officials:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Labor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Commerce;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Higher Education;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The State Superintendent of Schools;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Two chief elected officials, who collectively represent both cities and counties, and,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Any individual that may be required by Annotated Code of Maryland, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|21-209">Education §21-209(d)</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Members appointed by the Governor, which must include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A majority of the Board membership representing businesses in the State including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>At least one representative who is selected from nominations by State business organizations and business trade associations;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Owners of businesses, chief executives or operating officers of business, or other business executives or employers with optimum policymaking or hiring authority, and who, in addition, may be members of a local workforce development board; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Representatives of businesses, or organizations representing businesses described in this section, that provide employment opportunities that include high-quality, work-relevant training and development in in-demand industry sectors or occupations in the State; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>At least one member representing small businesses as defined by the U.S. Small Business Administration.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Not less than 20 percent of the Board membership representing workforce within the State appointed by the Governor including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>At least two representatives of labor organizations nominated by state labor federations;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>At least one representative who is a member of a labor organization or a training director from a joint labor-management apprenticeship program;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>One president from a community college;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>The President of the Maryland Workforce Association; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Other representatives of the workforce or workforce development community that may include community-based organizations with demonstrated experience and expertise in addressing the employment, training or education needs of youth and adults, particularly those with barriers to employment, such as returning citizens, veterans and individuals with disabilities.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The Board shall also include the following ex officio, non-voting members who are asked to serve in an advisory capacity and to partner on relevant initiatives of the Board:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Aging;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Service and Civic Innovation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Disabilities;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Health;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Housing and Community Development;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Human Services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Juvenile Services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Public Safety and Correctional Services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Transportation; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The membership and operations of the Board shall conform to the requirements set forth in the federal Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act of 2014.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>To the extent practicable, the membership of the Board shall reflect the race, gender, age, and geographic diversity of the population of the State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Members appointed by the Governor under C(5)(a), C(5)(b)(i) through (iii), and C(5)(b)(v) shall serve four-year staggered terms. All other members shall serve so long as they hold the office or designation stipulated under C(1) through (4), C(5)(b)(iv), and C(6).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>The Governor shall designate a Chairperson who shall serve at the pleasure of the Governor. The Chairperson shall be a business representative serving pursuant to C(5)(a) and may not be an elected official or an employee of the State of Maryland or any local government.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Members of the Board may not receive any compensation for their service, but may receive reimbursement for reasonable expenses incurred in the performance of their duties in accordance with the State Travel Regulations and as provided in the State budget.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Members of the Board are subject to the State Public Ethics Law and are required to file annual financial disclosures unless otherwise exempted by law.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board shall hold publicly announced meetings at such times and such places as it deems necessary. The meetings shall be open and accessible to the general public in accordance with Maryland’s Open Meetings Act or other applicable law.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A quorum for voting purposes shall be the presence of a majority of the members of the Board. Board members cannot delegate their authority and cannot send a representative in their place for quorum or voting purposes.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Board is authorized to obtain such professional, technical, and clerical personnel and assistance as may be necessary to carry out its functions, in accordance with the appropriate State budgetary and administrative requirements.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Board may establish an Executive Committee composed of members appointed by the Chairperson as designated in the bylaws. At least 51 percent of the members of the Executive Committee must be business members appointed under C(5)(a).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Board may delegate to the Executive Committee any of the powers of the Board except those powers which are required by law to be exercised by the Board. The Chairperson may also appoint ad-hoc committees as appropriate as provided in the bylaws.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Board members who do not attend at least two-thirds of the scheduled Board meetings in a twelve month period are considered to have resigned unless a waiver is granted by the Governor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The Board members and staff shall collaborate with staff of the State’s workforce development agency on workforce development strategies, policies, and programs as needed to ensure that the Board’s functions regarding statewide strategy, policy, partnerships and workforce system governance are well-coordinated with the operations of key workforce development programs, and to ensure that Maryland’s businesses, residents, local workforce development boards and other workforce development stakeholders experience a coherent and coordinated workforce system that supports economic competitiveness, talent pipelines for businesses, and access to opportunity for all Marylanders.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The Board is authorized to explore public-private partnership opportunities and, as it deems necessary, to establish processes or mechanisms, conforming with State law, by which to accept financial resources from philanthropic organizations to support the Board’s capacity to conduct activities related to the responsibilities above.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Reporting: The Board shall submit an annual report to the Governor and the General Assembly as soon as possible after January 1 of each year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>This Executive Order shall be implemented in a manner that is consistent with all applicable statutes and regulations. Nothing in this Executive Order shall operate to contravene any State or federal law or to affect the State's receipt of federal funding</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2023-12-21">Effective Date: December 21, 2023.</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</container>
