<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Plant Inspection, Audit and Retention of Records</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Right to Inspect.</heading>
    <text>Designees of the procurement agency, the Department of Legislative Services, or any other State unit authorized by law, may inspect at reasonable times the plant, place of business, or jobsite of any bidder or offeror, contractor, prospective subcontractor or assignee, or subcontractor or assignee.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Audits.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Audit of Cost or Pricing Data. Designees of the procurement agency, the Department of Legislative Services, or any other State unit authorized by law may audit during the record retention period the books and records of any person who has submitted cost or pricing data to the extent that the books and records relate to the cost or pricing data.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Contract Audit. Designees of the procurement agency, the Department of Legislative Services, or any other State unit authorized by law shall be entitled to audit the books and records of a contractor or any subcontractor under any negotiated contract or subcontract other than a firm fixed-price contract to the extent that the books and records relate to the performance of the contract or subcontract, or if the agency has reason to believe, from an audit of a cost type contract, that costs have been inappropriately assigned to a cost type contract from a fixed price contract.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Record Retention.</heading>
    <text>The contractor or subcontractor shall maintain books and records that relate to the cost or pricing data for 3 years from the date of final payment under the contract, unless a longer period is otherwise specified in the contract.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">State Finance and Procurement Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|12-101">12-101</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|15-108">15-108</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|15-109">15-109</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1981-07-01">Effective date: July 1, 1981 (8:13 Md. R. II-5)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-01-09">Chapter revised effective January 9, 1989 (15:27 Md. R. 3138)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
