<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>Procedures</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this subtitle, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Activities and services" means performing the psychological activities or services that are required training for completing the program in psychology.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Applicant” means an individual seeking a license or registration to practice psychology in Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Board" means the State Board of Examiners of Psychologists.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Central repository” means the Criminal Justice Information System Central Repository of the Department of Public Safety and Correctional Services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Criminal history records check” means the performance of both a State criminal history check by the Central Repository and a national criminal history check by the Federal Bureau of Investigation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Criminal history records information” means information provided by the criminal history records check regarding an applicant’s criminal arrests, charges, convictions, and the disposition of other pending criminal charges.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Fellow.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Fellow" means an individual who has obtained the doctoral degree in psychology, or who has completed all of the academic course requirements for a doctoral degree in psychology, and is gaining additional training and experience in a postdoctoral training program in psychology.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Fellow" includes the term resident.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Intern" means an individual who is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Matriculated in a doctoral degree program in psychology; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Fulfilling program requirements by completing a predoctoral internship training program in psychology.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Practice-oriented program" means a clinical, counseling, or school psychology program, or a combination thereof, or a respecialization program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Student" means an individual who is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Matriculated in a master's or doctoral degree program in psychology; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Fulfilling program requirements by gaining field or practicum experience.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Supervised course of study" means an organized post-baccalaureate program in psychology with identified faculty and training objectives.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Application Required for Licensure or Registration.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An application packet for licensure is complete when the following conditions are met:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The completed application packet is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Submitted to the Board and notarized; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Accompanied by the required nonrefundable application fee in the form of a personal check, cashier’s check or money order;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An application packet includes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Answers to application questions;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Documentation of supervised professional experience;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Attestations of supervised professional experience submitted to the Board by the persons providing the references;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Official transcripts of all post-baccalaureate studies submitted to the Board by the educational institutions;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>An Examination for Professional Practice in Psychology (EPPP) score, if applicable, submitted to the Board by the Association of State and Provincial Psychology Boards (ASPPB); and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Criminal history records check reports are received by the Board; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An applicant who is a nonresident or is not employed within the State submits a statement to show the reasons for seeking licensure in the State.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An application packet for registration is complete when the following conditions are met:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The application packet is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Submitted to the Board and notarized; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Accompanied by the required nonrefundable application fee in the form of a personal check, cashier’s check, or money order;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Official transcripts of all studies are submitted to the Board by the educational insitutions; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Criminal history records check reports are received by the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The official date of receipt of the application is the date on which the Board receives both the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Completed application form; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Required, nonrefundable application fee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Board shall notify the applicant of missing required documents not more than 15 business days after receipt of the application.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An application is terminated when:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The application has not been completed within 1 year of the date the application is submitted; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The applicant fails either the EPPP, if applicable, or the Maryland examination.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Review of Completed Applications by the Board.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board shall review an application after the required documents are on file.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the applicant for licensure is applying for limited practice reciprocity, as described in <cite path="|10|36|01|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite>, the application shall be reviewed within 15 business days after the required documents are on file.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Board may request additional information or documentation from the applicant for clarification purposes.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>An applicant shall be sent notification of the action taken by the Board, to accept or to reject the application.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>An applicant who is informed of acceptance shall be notified of the time and place of the examinations required in <cite path="|10|36|01|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>An applicant who is informed of acceptance shall submit the required examination fees to the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The Board may not approve an applicant for licensure or registration until the Board has:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Received and reviewed the criminal history records information; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Approved the application.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>An applicant whose application for licensure or registration is rejected shall be notified of the basis for that rejection.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>An applicant may appeal a rejection of application for licensure or registration by notifying the Board in writing, by certified mail, within 60 days of receipt of the Board’s decision, and by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Submitting new or additional evidence to verify or clarify qualifications; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Requesting an informal hearing before the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>An applicant who fails an examination may begin the application process again by submitting:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A new application for licensure or registration along with the required application fee; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>At least one current letter of reference.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Abbreviated Application.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A psychologist who holds an active license to practice psychology in good standing in another state and is certified by the American Board of Professional Psychology or credentialed as a Health Service Psychologist by the National Register of Health Service Psychologists may apply for licensure with the Board on an abbreviated application.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An abbreviated application for licensure as a psychologist with the Board shall include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Proof of good standing as a licensed psychologist in another state;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Proof of certification by the American Board of Professional Psychology or credentialing as a Health Service Psychologist by the National Register of Health Service Psychologists;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A passing score on the Maryland Jurisprudence Examination as set forth in <cite path="|10|36|01|.06|A.|(2)">Regulation .06A(2) of this chapter</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A criminal history records check; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The required, nonrefundable application fee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Board may not issue a license on an abbreviated application unless the Board has received the results of the applicant’s criminal history records check.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Education Required for Licensure.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The applicant for licensure shall have a doctoral degree in psychology as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|18-101">Health Occupations Article, §18-101(c), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The applicant for registration as a psychology associate shall meet the educational requirement as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|18-302">Health Occupations Article, §18-302(g), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Professional Supervised Experience Required for Licensure — General.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant for licensure shall present evidence of having completed 2 years of supervised professional experience before taking the examinations required in <cite path="|10|36|01|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The 2 years of supervised professional experience shall consist of a minimum of 3,250 hours.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Supervision Generally.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A minimum of 75 percent of the applicant's supervised professional experience shall be supervised by a psychologist qualified to supervise the activities being performed or the services being rendered.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The supervisor shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Licensed to practice psychology in Maryland;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Exempt from licensure under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|18-102">Health Occupations Article, §18-102(3) </cite>or 18-301(b), Annotated Code of Maryland;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Licensed, certified, or exempt from licensure or certification in the state or country in which the supervised professional experience is obtained; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A student, fellow, intern, or resident while pursuing a supervised course of study that the Board approves as qualifying training or experience as provided in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|18-301">Health Occupations Article, §18-301(b)(3), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, provided that the student, fellow, intern, or resident is supervised by an individual meeting criteria of §C(2)(a), (b) or (c) of this regulation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The supervisor shall ensure that any additional supervision is by an individual who has the requisite skills and training to provide supervision.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Psychology associates accruing supervised professional experience toward licensure shall receive the required amount of supervision specified in <cite path="10.36.07.03">COMAR 10.36.07.03</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The applicant shall ensure that there is adequate documentation of the supervised professional experience.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The Board may require additional information to be submitted by the applicant or supervisor to assess the extent and quality of the applicant's supervised professional experience.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04-1</num>
    <heading>Supervised Professional Experience — Programs That Are Not Practice-Oriented.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>For applicants for licensure graduating from programs that are not practice-oriented, supervised professional experience may be accrued in professional work in psychology using the methods, principles, and procedures of psychology, including, but not limited to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Teaching;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Research; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Industrial or organizational consultation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In order for the experience to qualify as full-time supervised professional experience, the applicant shall receive a minimum of 1 hour of individual supervision per week at a face-to-face meeting with the supervisor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In exceptional circumstances, the Board may waive the requirement for face-to-face supervision:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For pre-doctoral experience, if the academic program director attests to the nature of the circumstances and assures the Board that the quality of the supervision was not compromised; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For post-doctoral experience, if the applicant:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Petitions the Board for a waiver before beginning the supervised experience; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Offers an alternative modality for supervision, including but not limited to televideo conferencing that does not substantially diminish the adequacy of the supervision.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04-2</num>
    <heading>Supervised Professional Experience — Practice-Oriented Programs.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>For applicants for licensure graduating from practice-oriented programs, supervised professional experience may be accrued through:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Pre-internship;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Internship;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Pre-doctoral post-internship; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Post-doctoral experiences.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The academic training program director or the post-doctoral training supervisor shall attest to the hours accrued to meet the requirements of this regulation on a form required by the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An applicant may utilize pre-internship and pre-doctoral post-internship experience:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To accrue up to 1,500 hours toward the supervised professional experience required for licensure; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>That occurs following the completion of the first year of the doctoral program.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Pre-internship and pre-doctoral post-internship experiences shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Consist of an organized sequence of training that is of increasing complexity to prepare the student for internship;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Follow appropriate academic preparation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Be overseen by the graduate training program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Be an extension of the student's academic coursework and within the scope of education received;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Be in service-related activities such as treatment, assessment, interviews, report writing, case presentations, supervision, and consultation for at least 50 percent of the training experience; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Be devoted to face-to-face client contact for at least 25 percent of the training experience.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Pre-internship and pre-doctoral post-internship experiences shall contain a written training plan that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Includes the responsibilities of the student, training site, and graduate training program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Describes how the student's time will be allotted;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Ensures the quality, breadth, and depth of the training experience by specifying the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Goals and objectives of the training experience;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Methods of evaluation of the student's performance; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Rules governing the training experience;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Specifies the requirements of supervision to include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The nature of supervision;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The identities of supervisors; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The form and frequency of feedback from the agency supervisor to the training faculty;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Provides rationale for the training experience based on previous academic preparation and previous training to ensure that the overall experience is organized and sequential; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>May be provided to the Board with the application to document the pre-internship or pre-doctoral post-internship experience.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Pre-internship and Pre-doctoral Post-internship Supervision Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Every 20 hours of pre-internship experience and pre-doctoral post-internship shall include the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>At least 2 hours of regularly scheduled, formal, face-to-face individual supervision that addresses the direct psychological services provided by the student; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>At least 2 hours of other learning activities such as:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Case conferences;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Seminars on applied issues;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Conducting co-therapy with a staff person including discussion of the case; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Group supervision.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In exceptional circumstances, the Board may waive the requirement for face-to-face supervision if the academic program director attests to the nature of the circumstances and assures the Board that the quality of supervision was not compromised.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Internship experiences shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Consist of a minimum of 1,750 hours of supervised experience; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Be completed within 24 months.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The internship program shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Accredited by the American Psychological Association (APA) or the Canadian Psychological Association (CPA);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A member program of the Association of Psychology Postdoctoral Internship Centers (APPIC); or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Part of an academic program that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is approved or designated by the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>APA;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>CPA; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Association of State and Provincial Psychology Boards (ASPPB)/National Register; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Includes an internship that is approved by the program's academic training director as meeting its criteria for an internship.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Post-Doctoral Supervised Professional Experience—Practice-Oriented Programs.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A maximum of 1,500 hours of the professional supervised experience may be obtained through post-doctoral supervised experience.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Post-doctoral supervised experience shall be completed if an applicant does not have 3,250 hours of pre-doctoral supervised experience.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04-3</num>
    <heading>Post-Doctoral Supervised Professional Experience — General.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A supervisor is ethically and legally responsible for all supervisee work covered by a written supervision agreement.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Supervisees shall use titles indicating their training status, such as "psychology resident", "psychology intern", or "psychology supervisee".</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Supervised experience shall be appropriate to the area or areas of professional activity in which the supervisee intends to practice.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>There shall be at least 1 hour of individual supervision for every 20 hours of service related activities.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The supervisor and the supervisee shall keep records of experience and supervision hours.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>At the conclusion of the post-doctoral supervision experience:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The supervisor shall prepare a written evaluation, including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The hours spent in various service related activities;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The number of successfully completed supervised hours; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Any hours not successfully completed; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If any hours were not successfully completed, the Board may require additional hours of supervision.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Supervision shall be face-to-face with an on-site supervisor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Under exceptional circumstances, and before beginning a supervised professional experience, an applicant for licensure may petition the Board to waive the requirement for face-to-face supervision or to receive supervision from a psychologist not on site.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>The Board may waive the requirement for face-to-face supervision only when the alternative modality for supervision, including but not limited to televideo conferencing, does not substantially diminish the adequacy of the supervision.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>If a supervisee is accruing post-doctoral supervision as a registered psychology associate, the supervisee shall also comply with the requirements of <cite path="|10|36|01|.04-4">Regulation .04-4 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04-4</num>
    <heading>Post-Doctoral Supervised Professional Experience as a Registered Psychology Associate.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant accruing post-doctoral supervised experience in an activity that is not exempt under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|18-301">Health Occupations Article, §18-301 </cite>or 18-102(3), Annotated Code of Maryland, shall apply to the Board for registration as a psychology associate in accordance with <cite path="|10.36.07">COMAR 10.36.07</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Exempted activities under Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|18-301">18-301</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|18-102">18-102</cite>(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|3">3</cite>), Annotated Code of Maryland, include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Activities as a student, intern, resident, or fellow while pursuing a supervised course of study in psychology that the Board approves as qualifying training and experience;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Activities under the supervision of, and in connection with, a psychologist employed by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Any agency of the federal government;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Maryland Department of Juvenile Services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A political subdivision of this State; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A chartered educational institution; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Non-profit activities of a bona fide religious organization that is exempt from taxation under Section 501(c)(3) of the Internal Revenue Code.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Registered psychology associates accruing post-doctoral supervised professional experience toward licensure shall obtain supervision in accordance with the requirements of <cite path="|10.36.07">COMAR 10.36.07</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Applications for Licensure from Nonresidents.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>When submitting an application for licensure, an applicant who is a nonresident or does not practice psychology in Maryland and who does not intend to reside or practice in Maryland, shall submit a statement showing that the applicant's licensure would be in the interest of the citizens or government of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board shall determine whether to accept or reject the statement.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In the event of unfavorable determination, the Board shall notify the applicant that the application for licensure has been rejected.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The applicant may appeal this rejection as specified in <cite path="|10|36|01|.02">Regulation .02 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Until licensed to practice psychology in Maryland, an applicant may not practice psychology in Maryland by virtue of holding a valid license or certification to practice psychology in another state unless the Board authorizes a specific exception.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Examinations Required for Licensure or Registration.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board requires applicants for licensure to receive passing scores of at least:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A scaled score of 500 on the Examination for Professional Practice in Psychology (EPPP) for examinations administered on or after January 1, 2002, or a score of 73 percent on the Examination for Professional Practice in Psychology (EPPP) prepared and scored before January 1, 2002; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>75 percent on the Maryland Examination prepared and scored by the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board requires applicants for registration to receive a passing score of at least 75 percent on the Maryland Examination prepared and scored by the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Board shall ensure that the Maryland Examination tests applicants for licensure or registration on:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Code of Ethics and Professional Conduct; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Other regulations and laws pertaining to the practice of psychology.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Board shall provide each applicant access to all regulations and laws tested on the Maryland Examination.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An applicant is required to take examinations administered by the Board or the Board's agent at the designated times and places.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Board shall refund the examination fee if a written request to cancel the application or examination is received from the applicant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At least 2 weeks before the examination date; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>At a later time if the Board determines there was good cause.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Limited Examination Reciprocity for Licensure Applicants.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board shall determine the required examinations for each applicant, although the Maryland Examination may not be waived.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Examination for Professional Practice in Psychology may be waived for an applicant authorized by law to practice psychology in another state that did not require the Examination for Professional Practice in Psychology, if the applicant is currently licensed or certified for the independent practice of psychology in another state.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Examination for Professional Practice in Psychology (EPPP) shall be waived for an applicant licensed or certified for the independent practice of psychology in another state who submits evidence of having attained a score of at least 73 percent on any administration of the Examination for Professional Practice in Psychology (EPPP) before January 1, 2002, or a scaled score of 500 on any administration of the Examination for Professional Practice in Psychology (EPPP) on or after January 1, 2002.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The examination for Professional Practice in Psychology shall be waived for an applicant who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is licensed to practice psychology in another state; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has met the requirements for and holds a current Certificate of Professional Qualification in Psychology issued by the Association of State and Provincial Psychology Boards.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Exceptions to Licensure.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A student, intern, or fellow may qualify for an exception to licensure while performing the activities and services of a supervised course of study in psychology with the following requirements:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The identified faculty shall provide the supervision;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The individual shall receive the amount of supervision:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Set by the educational or internship program; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>In accordance with <cite path="|10|36|01|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite> for:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Students or interns who want to obtain the professional supervised experience required for licensure, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Fellows;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The individual providing psychological services under this exception shall use one of the following titles:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Psychology student;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Psychology intern;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Psychology resident; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Psychology fellow; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>This exception to licensure terminates when the requirements of the training program in psychology are completed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Limited Practice Reciprocity.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A nonresident certified or licensed to practice psychology may be granted a temporary exception to practice psychology in Maryland if the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Board receives from the applicant a completed application and application fee within 90 days of establishing residence in Maryland and on or before the next application due date;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Completed application includes a verification from another state licensing Board or authority that the applicant's license or certification to practice psychology in the other state is in good standing;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Applicant is scheduled to take the next Board-administered examinations required for licensure;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Board approves the application and sends notification of its action not later than 35 days before the scheduled examination; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Applicant pays the required examination fee to the Board at least 30 days before the scheduled examination.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Board shall withdraw the temporary exception to practice psychology if the applicant fails an examination required by the Board.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>In granting an extension for examination set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|18-301">Health Occupations Article, §18-301(c), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the Board shall determine whether the applicant has good cause for being unable to take the first scheduled examination for which the applicant is eligible.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>In authorizing an exception set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|18-301">Health Occupations Article, §18-301(d), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the Board:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Shall determine whether the circumstances warrant an exception to licensure, taking into account the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Qualifications of the nonresident psychologist,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Psychological services to be provided, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Duration of the exception to licensure; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>May impose any limitations on the psychologist's practice of psychology that the Board considers to be appropriate.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|36|01|.08">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>License Renewal, Expiration, and Inactive Status.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Renewal.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A license shall expire on March 31, unless it is renewed for an additional term as provided in this section.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A license may not be renewed for a term longer than 2 years.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>At least 90 days before the license expires, the Board shall send a renewal notice to the licensee:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>By first class mail to the last known address of the licensee; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If requested by the licensee, by electronic means to the last known electronic mail address of the licensee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If a renewal notice sent by electronic means under <cite path="10|36|01|.08|A.|(3)|(b)">§A(3)(b) of this regulation</cite> is returned to the Board as undeliverable, the Board shall send a renewal notice to the licensee by first–class mail to the last known address of the licensee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The renewal notice shall state:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The procedure to follow;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Continuing education requirements;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The date on which the current license expires;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The date by which the renewal application must be received by the Board for the renewal to be issued and mailed before the license expires; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The amount of the renewal fee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A licensee who did not submit to a criminal history records check upon initial licensure with the Board shall submit to a criminal history records check upon the licensee’s first renewal with the Board after January 1, 2019.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Every 6 years following the initial submission of a criminal history records check to the Board, a licensee applying for renewal shall submit to a criminal history records check.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Upon receipt of a licensee’s criminal history records information in accordance with §A(6) and (7) of this regulation, the Board shall consider the following factors in determining whether to renew a license:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The age at which the crime was committed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The circumstances surrounding the crime;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The length of time that has passed since the crime;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Subsequent work history;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Employment and character references, if provided; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Other evidence that demonstrates whether the licensee poses a threat to the public health or safety.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>The Board may not renew a license if the Board has not received the results of a criminal history records check required pursuant to §A(6) and (7) of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Expiration. A license automatically expires when the psychologist fails to meet the renewal requirements by March 31.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Inactive Status.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A psychologist in good standing may request inactive status for 2 years upon:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Notification to the Board; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Payment of the required fee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A licensee on inactive status may apply to have the inactive license status extended for an additional 2 years upon payment of the inactive status fee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The license on inactive status may be reinstated by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Completing an application for renewal;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Paying the renewal fee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Verifying that continuing education requirements have been satisfied as set forth in <cite path="|10.36.02">COMAR 10.36.02</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Submitting to a criminal history records check, if the license has been on inactive status for a period of 1 year or more.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|36|01|.09">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Registration Renewal and Expiration.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Renewal.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A registration shall expire on March 31 unless it is renewed for an additional term as provided in this section.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A registration may not be renewed for a term longer than 2 years.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>At least 90 days before the registration expires, the Board shall send a renewal notice to the registrant:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>By first class mail to the last known address of the registrant; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>By electronic means to the last known electronic mail address of the registrant.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The renewal notice shall state:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The date the registration expires;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Continuing education requirements;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The date by which the renewal application must be received by the Board for the renewal to be issued and mailed before the registration expires; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The amount of the renewal fee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Every 6 years following the initial submission of a criminal history records check to the Board, a registrant applying for renewal shall submit to a criminal history records check.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Upon receipt of a registrant’s criminal history records information in accordance with <cite path="10|36|01|.09|A.|(5)">§A(5) of this regulation</cite>, the Board shall consider the following factors in determining whether to renew a registration:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The age at which the crime was committed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The circumstances surrounding the crime;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The length of time that has passed since the crime;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Subsequent work history;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Employment and character references, if provided; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Other evidence that demonstrates whether the registrant poses a threat to the public health or safety.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The Board may not renew a registration if the Board has not received the results of a criminal history records check required pursuant to <cite path="10|36|01|.09|A.|(5)">§A(5) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Expiration. A registration automatically expires when the psychology associate fails to meet the renewal requirements by March 31.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Petitioning for Reinstatement Following Revocation.</heading>
    <text>The Board may not consider a petition for reinstatement of a license or registration to practice psychology that has been revoked until at least 5 years have passed from the date of revocation.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Board Meetings.</heading>
    <text>The Board shall meet a minimum of six times a year with additional meetings being scheduled as the business of the Board may require.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Annual Report of the Board.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Chairman of the Board shall submit an annual report to the Board for approval before the Board's submission of the report to the Secretary of Health.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board shall include in the report:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A summary of the more important actions of the Board;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Relevant statistical and fiscal data; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A summary of concerns or anticipated future changes in the course of action of the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Petitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Any person may petition the Board in writing for an interpretation of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 18, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text><cite path="|10.36.01">COMAR 10.36.01</cite>—10.36.07.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A copy of the Board's interpretation or decision shall be mailed to the petitioner.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|18-206">18-206</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|18-301">18-301</cite>(b)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|3">3</cite>) and (d), 18-302—18-305, 18-309, and 18-317, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1970-07-25">Effective date: July 25, 1970</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1976-12-23"><cite path="|10|36|01|.05|G.">Regulation .05G</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective December 23, 1976 (4:2 Md. R. 73); emergency status expired</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1982-12-20" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|10|36|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|36|01|.17">.17</cite> repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|10|36|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|36|01|.15">.15</cite> adopted effective December 20, 1982 (9:25 Md. R. 2484)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-09-25"><cite path="|10|36|01|.02">Regulation .02</cite> repealed effective September 25, 1995 (22:19 Md. R. 1473)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1987-10-23"><cite path="|10|36|01|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective October 23, 1987 (14:23 Md. R. 2412); emergency status extended at 15:7 Md. R. 848</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1988-05-16"><cite path="|10|36|01|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective May 16, 1988 (15:10 Md. R. 1202)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-09-25"><cite path="|10|36|01|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective September 25, 1995 (22:19 Md. R. 1473)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-10-29"><cite path="|10|36|01|.11">Regulation .11</cite> repealed and new Regulation .11 adopted effective October 29, 1990 (17:21 Md. R. 2530)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-05-01" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|10|36|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|36|01|.15">.15</cite> repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|10|36|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|36|01|.12">.12</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective January 1, 2000 (27:3 Md. R. 325); adopted permanently effective May 1, 2000 (27:8 Md. R. 798)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-03-21"><cite path="|10|36|01|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective September 1, 2010 (37:14 Md. R. 938); March 21, 2011 (38:6 Md. R. 395)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-12-24"><cite path="|10|36|01|.02|L.">Regulation .02L</cite> adopted effective December 24, 2001 (28:25 Md. R. 2192)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-06-24"><cite path="|10|36|01|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective April 1, 2002 (29:7 Md. R. 617); amended permanently effective June 24, 2002 (29:12 Md. R. 928)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-03-21"><cite path="|10|36|01|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective March 21, 2011 (38:6 Md. R. 395)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-06-24"><cite path="|10|36|01|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective April 1, 2002 (29:7 Md. R. 617); amended permanently effective June 24, 2002 (29:12 Md. R. 928)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-09-01"><cite path="|10|36|01|.04">Regulation .04</cite> repealed and new Regulation .04 adopted effective September 1, 2010 (37:14 Md. R. 938)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-09-01">Regulations <cite path="|10|36|01|.04-1">.04-1</cite>—<cite path="|10|36|01|.04-4">.04-4</cite> adopted effective September 1, 2010 (37:14 Md. R. 938)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-12-24"><cite path="|10|36|01|.06|G.">Regulation .06G</cite> amended effective December 24, 2001 (28:25 Md. R. 2192)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-06-24"><cite path="|10|36|01|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective April 1, 2002 (29:7 Md. R. 617); amended permanently effective June 24, 2002 (29:12 Md. R. 928)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-12-12"><cite path="|10|36|01|.08|A.">Regulation .08A</cite> amended effective December 12, 2013 (40:24 Md. R. 2017)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-03-21"><cite path="|10|36|01|.08|C.">Regulation .08C</cite> amended effective March 21, 2011 (38:6 Md. R. 395)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-05-25" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective May 25, 2015 (42:10 Md. R. 684)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-02-12"><cite path="|10|36|01|.02|L.">Regulation .02L</cite> amended effective February 12, 2018 (45:3 Md. R. 157)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-02-12"><cite path="|10|36|01|.08|A.">Regulation .08A</cite>, C amended effective February 12, 2018 (45:3 Md. R. 157)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-02-12"><cite path="|10|36|01|.09|A.">Regulation .09A</cite> amended effective February 12, 2018 (45:3 Md. R. 157)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
