<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Tenant House or Replacement Dwelling House Approval for a Farm Subject to an Agricultural Land Preservation Easement</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter establishes the criteria and eligibility for the approval of a tenant house or replacement dwelling house, or both, on a farm subject to an agricultural land preservation easement held by the Maryland Agricultural Land Preservation Foundation.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Existing dwelling” means a building, structure, or mobile home that was designated by the Foundation and a county as an existing dwelling at the time of the execution of an agricultural land preservation district agreement or agricultural land preservation easement.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Fully engaged in the operation of a farm" means the tenant is committed to an average of at least 30 hours per week over a continuous 12-month period.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Replacement dwelling house” means a residential structure that may be built in lieu of a new tenant house if the Foundation has approved the conversion of an existing dwelling house into a tenant house.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Tenant.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Tenant" means an individual fully engaged in the operation of a farm.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Tenant" does not include a landowner or a person who has a financial interest in the landowner, including a shareholder interest, partnership interest, or membership interest, full, limited, or otherwise.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Tenant house" means an accessory structure in service to a farm operation, approved or designated by the Foundation to be restricted to residential use by a tenant or tenants on the property.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Tenant House Eligibility.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The approval for the construction of a tenant house by the Foundation is not an absolute right of a landowner, and requests shall be reviewed by the Foundation on a case-by-case basis. Each request shall be reviewed to determine if a proposed tenant house is necessary based on the nature of the farming operation. When applying for approval of a tenant house, a landowner shall demonstrate to the Foundation a current and compelling need. To do so, a landowner shall show:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The nature of the farm operation and the reasons why one or more tenant is necessary to carry out farm operations; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>That one or more tenants will be fully engaged in the operations of the farm.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Farm Size.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A request for a tenant house may not be considered by the Foundation for any farm of less than 100 acres, unless the Foundation grants an exception based on a showing of compelling need.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Not more than one tenant house per full 100 acres may be considered by the Foundation for a farm, for example, one house for 100—199.99 acres, two houses for 200—299.99 acres, etc.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A tenant house may be approved for and occupied only by tenants of whom one or more is fully engaged in the operation of the farm.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Foundation shall approve the location and size of a tenant house as an accessory structure. Unless the Foundation approves otherwise, a tenant house:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall be located in the vicinity of other farm buildings;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>May not be located on a farm field;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>May not be larger in size than at least one nontenant dwelling house on the property, if any exist; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>May not be more than 2,000 square feet in size, calculated by first multiplying the exterior footprint of the portions of the structure with multiple stories by the number of stories with windows, and then adding the exterior footprint of any portions of the structure with one story, but excluding basements, attics, and porches not used as living space, garages, or unenclosed decks.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A tenant house, including its size and location, may not be approved by the Foundation unless it conforms to local planning and zoning regulations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A tenant house and the land where it is constructed may not be subdivided and separately conveyed from the farm subject to the easement.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The Foundation may not approve the construction of a tenant house solely for the purpose of producing rental income.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Tenant House Application Procedure.</heading>
    <text>Before the Foundation may consider a request for a tenant house, a landowner shall submit the following:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An application, completed and signed by each titled landowner, which addresses the criteria in Regulation .03;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An unmarked copy of the tax map, or boundary survey, which outlines the entire Foundation district or easement property;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A second copy of the tax map, which shall include the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Property boundaries of the Foundation district or easement property;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Location of, and access to, the proposed tenant house; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Location of, and access to, all preexisting dwellings, lot exclusions, tenant houses, and farm buildings;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A written statement from the landowner indicating:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The tenant will be compensated for the tenant's work;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The duties and responsibilities of the tenant relative to the farming operation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The time commitment that the tenant will have to the farming operation stated as average hours per week and total hours over a continuous 12-month period.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Written verification from the county program administrator describing:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The current overall farm operation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The need for the proposed tenant housing to support the current operation;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A letter of recommendation from the local agricultural land preservation advisory board;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A written statement from the local planning and zoning office or the county program administrator indicating that the proposed tenant house may be constructed under current local regulations; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>A written statement or plan from the landowner stating the size of the proposed tenant house as calculated by first multiplying the exterior footprint of the portions of the structure with multiple stories by the number of stories with windows, and then adding the exterior footprint of any portions of the structure with one story, but excluding basements, attics, and porches not used as living space, garages, or unenclosed decks.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Replacement Dwelling House Eligibility.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The approval for the construction of a replacement dwelling house by the Foundation is not an absolute right of a landowner. The Foundation shall only approve a request for a replacement dwelling house if the Foundation:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Has approved the application for a tenant house; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Has approved an existing dwelling house as a tenant house.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A replacement dwelling house may be approved and used only for the current or future landowner’s personal residential use.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Foundation shall approve the location and size of a replacement dwelling house as a residential structure. Unless the Foundation approves otherwise, a replacement dwelling house:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall be located in the vicinity of other farm buildings;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>May not be located on a farm field;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>May not be smaller in size than the existing dwelling approved to be redesignated as a tenant house; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>May not be more than 3,500 square feet in size, calculated by first multiplying the exterior footprint of the portions of the structure with multiple stories by the number of stories with windows, and then adding the exterior footprint of any portions of the structure with one story, but excluding basements, attics, and porches not used as living space, garages, or unenclosed decks.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A replacement dwelling house, including its size and location, may not be approved by the Foundation unless it conforms to local planning and zoning regulations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The property owner must execute an agreement with the Foundation to prohibit a replacement dwelling house and the land where it is constructed from being separately conveyed from the farm subject to the easement. The agreement will also specify that the replacement dwelling house will be for the personal residential use of the current or future landowners. The agreement shall be recorded among the county land records and shall bind future owners of the property.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>In counties that require subdivision of nontenant dwelling houses, the subdivision plat will state that the parcel is not to be separately conveyed from the property.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>If the Foundation approves a replacement dwelling house that is smaller than 3,500 square feet, any proposed additions are subject to the Foundation’s prior review and approval.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>This section does not apply to applications to replace an existing dwelling house damaged or destroyed by fire, water, or natural causes.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Replacement Dwelling House Application Procedure.</heading>
    <text>Before the Foundation may consider a request for the construction of a replacement dwelling house, a landowner must first obtain approval from the Foundation for a new tenant house. A landowner must submit the following information:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An application for conversion of an existing dwelling to a tenant house and for construction of a replacement dwelling house, completed and signed by each titled landowner;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An unmarked copy of the tax map, or boundary survey, which outlines the entire Foundation district or easement property;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A second copy of the tax map, which shall include the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Property boundaries of the Foundation district or easement property;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Location of, and access to, the proposed replacement dwelling house;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Location of, and access to, the existing dwelling which will house the tenant or tenants which made it necessary to construct a replacement dwelling house; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Location of, and access to, all preexisting dwellings, lot exclusions, tenant houses, and farm buildings;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A letter of recommendation from the local agricultural land preservation advisory board;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A written statement from the local planning and zoning office or the county program administrator indicating that the proposed replacement dwelling house may be constructed under current local regulations;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A signed statement from the landowner acknowledging that the replacement dwelling may only be approved and used for the current or future landowner’s personal residential use; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A written statement or plan from the landowner stating the size of the proposed replacement dwelling house as calculated by first multiplying the exterior footprint of the portions of the structure with multiple stories by the number of stories with windows, and then adding the exterior footprint of any portions of the structure with one story, but excluding basements, attics, and porches not used as living space, garages, or unenclosed decks.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Agriculture Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-504">2-504</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-513">2-513</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-02-03">Regulations <cite path="|15|15|03|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|15|15|03|.04">.04</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective October 11, 2002 (29:23 Md. R. 1808); adopted permanently effective February 3, 2003 (30:2 Md. R. 76)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-07-17"><cite path="|15|15|03|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective July 17, 2008 (35:14 Md. R. 1247)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-07-17"><cite path="|15|15|03|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite>, B amended effective July 17, 2008 (35:14 Md. R. 1247)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-03-07" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|15|15|03|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|15|15|03|.04">.04</cite> repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|15|15|03|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|15|15|03|.06">.06</cite> adopted effective March 7, 2011 (38:5 Md. R. 319)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
