<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>06</num>
  <heading>Lot Released from Easement for Landowner or Child</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter applies to any lot released by the Foundation to an eligible landowner or landowner's child for the landowner's or landowner's child's use and occupancy on a farm. This chapter describes release procedures and explains when the lot may be conveyed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The lots permitted to be released from the deed of easement under this chapter are:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Restricted under the terms of each agricultural land preservation easement; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Intended only for the limited purpose of constructing a dwelling for the eligible landowner who sold or transferred an easement to the Foundation or for the child of a landowner or landowners, thereby allowing immediate family members to live on the farm.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Except as provided by this chapter, these dwellings or lots may not be transferred or conveyed to any other person.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>This chapter does not apply to an unrestricted lot released by the Foundation from the deed easement.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms has the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Child" means the child of an eligible landowner who sold or transferred an agricultural land preservation easement to the Foundation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Dwelling" means the dwelling house, including lot acreage, allowed to be released under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-513">Agriculture Article, §2-513, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and under the terms of an agricultural land preservation easement, for the use and occupancy of an eligible landowner or landowner's child on the farm.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Farm" means the land encumbered by the agricultural land preservation easement.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Landowner" means the landowner or landowners who sold or transferred an agricultural land preservation easement to the Foundation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Lot Eligibility.</heading>
    <text>Upon approval and release by the Foundation, only a landowner who sold or transferred an easement to the Foundation or a landowner’s child is eligible to construct a dwelling on a lot on the farm for the bona fide use and occupancy of the landowner or the child.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Lot Approval and Release.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Before a lot may be released from an easement’s restrictions for the construction of a dwelling house, the landowner shall submit a signed application to the Foundation. The application shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A declaration that the lot and dwelling are for the use only of the landowner or the landowner’s child, whichever is the case;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the application is for an owner’s lot and there is more than one landowner, a statement acknowledging that the right to request release of the eligible owner’s lot is being exercised;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the application is for a child’s lot, a copy of the birth certificate of the landowner’s child to prove that the landowner’s child is a minimum of 18 years old at the date of the issuance of the preliminary release;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A description of the land where the dwelling is to be located, along with proposed access to the dwelling;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A survey plat or tax map that shows the precise location of the proposed lot; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Signed statements indicating approval of the lot from both the local agricultural land preservation advisory board and the county planning and zoning department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Corporation or Similar Entity’s Request for Child’s Lot. The Foundation may not approve an application from a corporation, partnership, limited liability company, or other similar entity (“the entity”) for an owner’s or child’s lot unless:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At the time of the sale of the deed of easement, the entity is owned by family members who are actively engaged in the daily agricultural operations on the land (“the original family members”);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>At the time of the request for an owner’s lot or child’s lot, at least one of the original family members has retained an uninterrupted, continuous ownership interest in the entity or its successor since the sale of the deed of easement; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The entity is otherwise eligible to have a lot released.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Owner’s Lot. If an easement property has more than one landowner, only one lot may be released for the use and occupancy of an owner, regardless of how the land is titled (that is, as tenants in common, joint tenancy, tenancy by the entirety, or in an entity).</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Lot Release.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Two-Part Release.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>After Foundation approval, the release of the lot shall consist of two parts, a preliminary release and a final release, as specified in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-513">Agriculture Article, §2-513, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>After receiving payment for the lot, the Foundation will issue a preliminary release which conditionally releases the lot from the terms of the easement.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Foundation will issue a final release when the Foundation receives and certifies a nontransferable building permit in the name of the landowner or child for the construction of a dwelling house.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The preliminary release becomes void:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Upon the death of the person for whom the release was intended if the Foundation has not yet received a building permit; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the Foundation does not receive a nontransferable building permit in the name of the landowner or the child within 3 years of the date of recordation of the preliminary release, unless extended by a majority vote of the Foundation Board of Trustees.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the person for whom the release was intended occupies the dwelling before a final release is issued, the Foundation may give credit for the occupancy toward the 5-year period referred to in <cite path="|15|15|06|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Lot Transfer Restrictions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A landowner or child who has a lot released under the terms of the easement shall occupy the dwelling constructed on the lot and may not convey or lease the improved lot to any person until 5 years after the effective date of the final release. The Foundation may require evidence that the person for whom the lot was released occupies the dwelling for the 5-year period.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Before the expiration of the 5-year period, the Foundation may only approve a landowner’s or child’s request to convey a lot improved with a dwelling upon the occurrence of the following events:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notice to the Foundation of a transfer pursuant to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A bona fide foreclosure of a mortgage or deed of trust; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A deed in lieu of foreclosure;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The death of the landowner or the child for whom the lot was released;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A decree of divorce where the landowner or child is ordered to sell or convey the lot as part of a bona fide property settlement;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A change of employment location of the landowner or child for whom the lot was released if the Foundation determines that it would be impractical for the landowner or child to commute to the new work location; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Any other circumstance, as determined by the Foundation, where it would be impossible for the landowner or child to continue to occupy the dwelling.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>For purposes of illustration by way of example and not limitation, the Foundation may require the owner of the released lot to convey the lot to the current owner of the land encumbered by the easement from which it was released and subject the lot to the terms of the easement, if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A dwelling constructed upon the lot is conveyed or leased to a person other than the owner or child for whom the lot was released before the expiration of the 5-year period;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The lot is conveyed or leased to another person prior to the construction of a dwelling for the personal residential use of the landowner or child;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A dwelling is not constructed upon the lot during the lifetime of the landowner or child for whom the lot was released; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The landowner or child for whom the lot was released relinquishes the right to construct a dwelling on the lot.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Easement Violation.</heading>
    <text>A person who conveys, or receives, a lot in violation of this chapter is in violation of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag">Agriculture Article, Title 2, Subtitle 5, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the terms of the agricultural land preservation easement applicable to the farm, and the terms of the applicable release.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Agriculture Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-504">2-504</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-513">2-513</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-11-06">Regulations <cite path="|15|15|06|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|15|15|06|.06">.06</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective July 17, 2006 (33:17 Md. R. 1435); adopted permanently effective November 6, 2006 (33:22 Md. R. 1733)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-07-08" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective July 8, 2013 (40:13 Md. R. 1076)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
