<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>07</num>
  <heading>Approval for Uses of or Activities on Farmland Subject to an Agricultural Land Preservation District or Easement</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter establishes the criteria and eligibility for the approval of allowable uses or activities on a farm subject to an agricultural land preservation easement held by the Maryland Agricultural Land Preservation Foundation.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Eligibility.</heading>
    <text>The Maryland Agricultural Land Preservation Foundation may approve farm, forest, or home occupation related uses or activities of eligible landowners on a farm subject to easement restrictions even though the use or activity does not strictly fall within the definition of traditional agricultural use. Each request shall be reviewed by the Foundation based on the criteria provided by this chapter to determine if a landowner's requested use or activity conflicts with the overall purpose of the easement to preserve the farm for agricultural use and as open-space land.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Criteria to be Considered.</heading>
    <text>The Foundation shall consider the following criteria in determining whether to approve or disapprove any use or activity:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Proportion of size of use or activity to total farm operation;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Compatibility with farm or forest production;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Potential damage to soil productivity;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Extent of use of existing farm structures or buildings, and impact on the value of the existing structure for farm or forestry use;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Whether any new structure or parking to support the use meets Foundation guidelines for location, scale, and impervious surfaces;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Compatibility with the rural character of the farm and the surrounding area;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>County advisory board recommendation;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Compatibility with the implementation or maintenance of a best management practice provided in a soil conservation and water quality plan for the farm and, if applicable, a Forest Stewardship Plan or a nutrient management plan; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Impact on sensitive natural resources on the farm, such as steep slopes, highly erodible soils, wetlands, or stream buffers.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Application Procedure.</heading>
    <text>Before the Foundation may consider a request for approval of any use or activity provided by this chapter, all of the following information shall be submitted by the county on behalf of the landowner:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An application for approval that has been completed and signed by all titled landowners that fully and completely describes the proposed use or activity on the farm;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A letter of recommendation from the local agricultural land preservation advisory board or program administrator;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A written statement from the local planning and zoning office, or the county program administrator, indicating that the proposed use or activity is permitted as of right or by special exception under local zoning; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A written statement from the local soil conservation district that the use or activity does not:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Interfere in the implementation or maintenance of a best management practice for the farm provided in its soil conservation and water quality plan; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Adversely impact sensitive natural resources on the farm, if this statement is requested by the Foundation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Violation.</heading>
    <text>Any landowner who violates an approval by the Foundation for any use or activity may also be in violation of that landowner's district agreement or agricultural land preservation easement. This violation may result in the rejection of the landowner's offer to sell an easement or in the enforcement of easement restrictions.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Agriculture Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-504">2-504</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-513">2-513</cite>(b), Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-11-03">Effective date: November 3, 2008 (35:22 Md. R. 1959)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
