<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>08</num>
  <heading>Installment Purchase Agreement Grant Program</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>This chapter establishes the criteria for a program administered by the Maryland Agricultural Land Preservation Foundation to purchase easements under an installment purchase agreement for farmland selected by the Foundation, in cooperation with:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An eligible county, if a landowner chooses an eligible county's installment purchase agreement program; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Maryland Agricultural and Resource-Based Industry Development Corporation, if a landowner chooses the Foundation's installment purchase agreement program.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"County" means any county containing productive agricultural land that is actively farmed and that meets the criteria for land for easement purchase by the Maryland Agricultural Land Preservation Foundation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Easement" means an agricultural land preservation easement as defined by <cite path="15.15.01.01">COMAR 15.15.01.01</cite>-2.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Eligible county" means a county as provided in this chapter that has been approved by the Maryland Agricultural Land Preservation Foundation for a county IPA program, pursuant to <cite path="|15|15|08|.04|A.">Regulation .04A of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Escrow closing" means the date when all documents have been executed in connection with the sale of an easement.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Foundation" means the Maryland Agricultural Land Preservation Foundation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"IPA" means an installment purchase agreement between a landowner and an eligible county or the Maryland Agricultural and Resource-Based Industry Development Corporation to purchase an easement by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Payment of semiannual interest at a fixed interest rate on the outstanding balance of the easement purchase price; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Payment of the outstanding balance of the easement purchase price in one or more installments over a stated term of years.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Landowner" means the fee simple owner of land that is subject to easement restrictions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"MARBIDCO" means the Maryland Agricultural and Resource-Based Industry Development Corporation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"MOU" means a memorandum of understanding that states the duties and responsibilities between the Foundation and an eligible county as to grants to purchase an easement through an IPA program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Settlement" means the date established at escrow closing, when interest on any installment purchase agreement begins to accrue.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Landowner's Option for Installment Purchase Agreement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Foundation may offer to buy an easement from a landowner through an IPA either:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In an eligible county where the land will be subjected to easement restrictions; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Through MARBIDCO, if the offer is not for less than $100,000.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>At the time of escrow closing on an IPA, the landowner and the Foundation shall agree to the terms of an IPA, including the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Payment from MARBIDCO shall be made in cash for not less than:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The maximum value, based on the Foundation's per-acre purchase price, of any easements on an unrestricted lot or family lots reserved by the landowner at escrow closing for future purchase from the Foundation; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Any additional amounts, as required by the Foundation;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Payment from MARBIDCO shall be made in one or more IPAs, each in a principal amount not less than $100,000;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An IPA shall be with the appropriate eligible county or MARBIDCO; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the IPA is with MARBIDCO, the maturity date shall be at least 10 years from settlement for each IPA.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A landowner's designation of the appropriate eligible county for an IPA shall be approved by the eligible county before escrow closing.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="15|15|08|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Grant to Eligible County.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A county is an eligible county for purposes of this chapter upon the Foundation's approval and after submission by the county to the Foundation of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The IPA form to be used by the county to purchase easements pursuant to a Foundation offer, which installment purchase agreement shall meet the requirements of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-510">Agriculture Article, §2-510</cite>.1(b), Annotated Code of Maryland, and otherwise be acceptable to the Foundation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The opinion of bond counsel form that states that the IPA is legal, valid and binding, and that interest paid under the IPA is exempt from federal and Maryland state and local income taxes, in form and substance satisfactory to the Foundation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An ordinance, resolution, or other evidence of approval acceptable to the Foundation authorizing the issuance of the IPA by the county.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The terms of an eligible county's IPA program are governed by an MOU that states the duties and obligations between the Foundation and an eligible county and shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Require the county to make annual equal payments to the landowner of interest on the outstanding balance of the purchase price;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Require that the county pay the landowner the remainder of the purchase price at the end of the term;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>State the total amount of money the county will pay the landowner, the interest rate, and the terms of the agreement; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Require that the easement be recorded within 30 days of settlement.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If a landowner elects to sell an easement through an IPA with an eligible county, the Foundation shall, before escrow closing on the easement, ask the State Treasurer to provide funds for the Foundation's portion of the easement purchase price as a grant to the eligible county.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An easement acquired by an eligible county according to an IPA:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall be held jointly by the eligible county and the Foundation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>May not terminate.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An eligible county may use a Foundation grant described in <cite path="15|15|08|.04|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> to provide for the easement purchase price due under the IPA.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If the amount of the Foundation grant exceeds the amount needed by a county to settle the easement transaction, the remaining amount of the grant shall be used to extend offers to purchase additional easements within that county in ranking order as provided by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-510">Agriculture Article, §2-510, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>. However if there are no additional approved applicants within that county, the remaining IPA grant funds shall be retained, along with any future fund allocation by the Foundation, for up to two subsequent easement cycles for the purpose of making IPA easement offers to applicants in that county. IPA grant funds not used within those three consecutive easement cycles will revert to the Maryland Agricultural Land Preservation Fund.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>County IRA grant funds from the Foundation may only be used for farmland easement purchases, and may not be used to make offers through any local preservation program or to pay interest on an IPA.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>An eligible county may not use a Foundation grant for an IPA in the Foundation's matching grant program pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-512">Agriculture Article, §2-512, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Foundation IPA.</heading>
    <text>If a landowner elects to participate in the Foundation IPA program, and a county is paying a portion of the easement purchase price, the county shall provide its portion to the Foundation within 30 days of the Foundation's notice.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Agriculture Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-504">2-504</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-505">2-505</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-510">2-510</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-07-17">Effective date: July 17, 2008 (35:14 Md. R. 1247)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
