<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>09</num>
  <heading>Civil Penalty Standards</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Penalty in Violation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Foundation may impose a civil penalty on an owner of a property whose farm is subject to the terms of an easement granted under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag">Agriculture Article, Title 2, Subtitle 5, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, who violates that subtitle, any regulations adopted in accordance with the subtitle, or the terms of the easement.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A civil penalty may be imposed by the Foundation instead of, or in addition to, any remedies at law or in equity.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Violation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Property Use. Except as otherwise permitted by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-513">Agriculture Article, §2-513, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the deed of easement, or Foundation approval, the Foundation may impose a civil penalty on a property owner subject to this chapter who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Uses easement property for commercial, industrial, or residential use;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Grants an easement, right-of-way, oil, gas, or mineral lease, or similar servitude on land to any person or government agency;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Erects a sign, billboard, or outdoor advertising on easement property;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Dumps ashes, sawdust, bark, trash, or rubbish on easement property, except when used in normal agricultural practices; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Violates an approval by the Foundation for any use or activity under the deed of easement.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Property Management. Except as otherwise permitted by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-513">Agriculture Article, §2-513, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the deed of easement, or Foundation approval, the Foundation may impose a civil penalty on a property owner subject to this chapter who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Fails to manage easement property with sound agricultural soil and water conservation practices; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Fails to manage easement property with sound forest stewardship practices, if the land contains 25 acres or more of contiguous forest.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Subdivision or Conveyance. Except as otherwise permitted by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-513">Agriculture Article, §2-513, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the deed of easement, or Foundation approval, the Foundation may impose a civil penalty on a property owner subject to this chapter who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Divides, partitions, or subdivides the property, or otherwise creates a lot for any purpose, including off conveyance or boundary line adjustment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Sells, transfers, gives, bequeaths, donates, or otherwise divides, any pre-existing subdivided parcel separately from the total of the parts in an easement, whether voluntarily, involuntarily, or by reason of foreclosure or bankruptcy;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Transfers or sells any remaining developmental rights of the property; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Fails to comply with lot transfer restrictions.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Dwelling House. Except as otherwise permitted by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-513">Agriculture Article, §2-513, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the deed of easement, or Foundation approval, the Foundation may impose a civil penalty on a property owner subject to this chapter who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Constructs a dwelling on easement property;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Constructs a replacement dwelling house on easement property; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Permits any lot or dwelling house constructed on an owner's or child's lot to be used for the purposes of an individual other than a property owner or, in the case of a child's lot, the identified child.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Tenant House. Except as otherwise permitted by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-513">Agriculture Article, §2-513, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the deed of easement, or Foundation approval, the Foundation may impose a civil penalty on a property owner subject to this chapter who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Constructs a tenant house on easement property;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Allows a dwelling designated as a tenant house to be occupied entirely by individuals who are not fully engaged in the operation of the farm; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Subdivides and separately conveys a tenant house or the land where it is constructed, or both.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Foundation may impose a civil penalty on a property owner subject to this chapter who violates any other law or regulatory requirement governing the Maryland Agricultural Land Preservation Program, an individual deed of easement acquired by the Foundation, or Foundation approval or policy.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Violation Classification and Penalty.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Foundation may impose a penalty for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Up to $2,500 for each violation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Each day a violation occurs; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Up to $50,000 in penalties during one administrative hearing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Before imposing any civil penalty under this chapter, the Foundation shall consider the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The nature and gravity of each violation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The willfulness of the violation and the extent to which the existence of the violation was known to the violator but uncorrected by the violator; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A history of prior violations, if any.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Civil Penalty Procedure.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Foundation shall issue a written notice of violation to the property owner upon finding that a violation has occurred or is ongoing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A written notice of violation shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A statement of the statute, regulation, or deed of easement violated by the landowner;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A description of the evidence of a violation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A statement informing the property owner of the right to an informal meeting with the Foundation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The amount of the proposed civil penalty;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A statement of the remedial action necessary to bring the property owner into compliance; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A reasonable amount of time, as determined by the Foundation, to correct a violation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the alleged violation still exists after the property owner has had an opportunity for an informal meeting and a reasonable amount of time to correct the violation, the Foundation may issue a written notice of violation with a penalty.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Contested Case Hearing; Appeal.</heading>
    <text>A property owner may petition the Foundation for a contested case hearing on the violation and penalty within 30 calendar days of the issuance of the notice of violation by the Foundation. The Office of Administrative Hearings shall conduct a hearing and issue proposed findings of fact and conclusions of law pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 10, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>. The Foundation shall adopt or reject the proposed findings of fact and conclusions of law and issue a final decision. An owner may then appeal the Foundation's decision as provided by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-405">Agriculture Article, §2-405, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Penalty Payment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Unless a property owner requests a contested case hearing, the property owner shall promptly pay the penalty.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Payment of a penalty is not a substitute for compliance. If the property owner continues to violate this chapter, the Foundation may impose additional civil penalties or pursue other remedies at law or in equity.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Violation Date.</heading>
    <text>This chapter applies to any violation that occurs on or after October 1, 2009.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-519">Agriculture Article, §2-519, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-05-17">Effective date: May 17, 2010 (37:10 Md. R. 724)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
