<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>12</num>
  <heading>Agricultural Subdivision</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter explains the policy of the Maryland Agricultural Land Preservation Foundation to regulate the subdivision of land encumbered by an agricultural land preservation easement, including the criteria, eligibility, and procedure for the approval of an agricultural subdivision of a farm.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>All of the land subject to an agricultural land preservation easement acquired by the Foundation is considered to be one parcel of land even if the total acreage comprises separately described parcels or government-assigned tax parcels or accounts. Common ownership of parcels constituting the farm fulfills the legislative intent to protect the future productivity and profitability of Maryland farms. To preserve the integrity of easement land, agricultural land preservation easements generally preclude a landowner from dividing the farm into smaller parcels or conveying less than the whole farm subject to easement without Foundation approval.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Agricultural purpose” means the use of land to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Provide sources of food and fiber; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Produce, process, or store agricultural products.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Agricultural subdivision” means a division of land for an agricultural purpose.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Corrective easements" means a modification to an existing easement to create two or more separately enforceable easements.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Easement violation" means any action prohibited by, or a failure to act as required by, the agricultural land preservation easement, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-501">Agriculture Article, §2-501 </cite>et seq., Annotated Code of Maryland, or <cite path="|15.15">COMAR 15.15</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Land” means all that real property encumbered by the easement and intended to constitute one farm parcel, whether or not comprised of separately described parcels or government-assigned tax parcels or accounts.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Landowner” means the person or entity owning the land encumbered by the easement.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Subdivision” or “subdivide” means the division of land into two or more parts or parcels. Subdivision includes the lease of any part or parts less than 100 percent of the total parts of the land for a term in excess of 20 years.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="15|15|12|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Subdivision Prohibition.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Prohibition. Except as approved by the Foundation as provided by this chapter and in <cite path="15.15.01.17|C.">COMAR 15.15.01.17C</cite>. and <cite path="15.15.06.01">15.15.06.01</cite>—.06, a landowner may not subdivide land encumbered by an easement, including the movement of interior boundary lines, or transfer or cause to be transferred, any part or parts separately from the total acreage of the land, voluntarily, involuntarily, by testamentary disposition, or by reason of foreclosure or bankruptcy.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Exception for Agricultural Subdivision. The Foundation may give written approval to a landowner’s request for an agricultural subdivision of the land and separate ownership of the resulting divided parcels for reasons the Foundation considers sufficiently extraordinary to justify an exception to the prohibition against subdivision. The approval for an agricultural subdivision is not an absolute right of a landowner, and requests shall be reviewed by the Foundation on a case-by-case basis to determine if, in the Foundation’s opinion:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The proposed agricultural subdivision serves an agricultural purpose;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The proposed agricultural subdivision will enhance or have no effect upon the agricultural operations being conducted upon the land; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The resulting divided parcels from the agricultural subdivision are able to sustain long-term agricultural production, independent of each other.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Corrective Easements. If the Foundation approves an agricultural subdivision under this Chapter, approval shall be to accommodate a plan that the Foundation has determined will benefit the agricultural operation as required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-513">Agriculture Article, §2-513, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and <cite path="|15.15.11">COMAR 15.15.11</cite>. Corrective easements are required to formalize the Foundation’s approval. The corrective easements may include other additional terms, conditions, waivers, or restrictions that the Foundation considers appropriate to protect the agricultural purpose and the future profitability of resulting divided farm parcels. The landowner shall pay for the cost of all title work, title insurance premiums, surveys, and documentation necessary to complete the agricultural subdivision.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Waiver of Right to Request Termination. For easements approved for purchase by the Board of Public Works prior to October 1, 2004, the owners of all of the resulting divided parcels of an approved agricultural subdivision under this chapter shall waive the right to request termination under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-514">Agriculture Article, §2-514, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and shall agree to specify the waiver in the corrective easements.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Acreage and Soils Requirements for Agricultural Subdivision. The resulting divided parcels shall each be at least 50 acres, and each parcel shall meet the minimum soils requirement, as provided by <cite path="15.15.01.03|D.">COMAR 15.15.01.03D</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Exceptions to Acreage Requirement. The Foundation may permit resulting divided parcels of less than 50 acres of land if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The resulting parcel of less than 50 acres continues to meet minimum soil requirements as provided by <cite path="15.15.01.03|D.">COMAR 15.15.01.03D</cite> independently of the original farm and one of the following conditions exists for the resulting divided parcel comprised of less than 50 acres:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Foundation determines that there exists a physical separation of land, created by:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Bodies of water;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Public roads; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Features that significantly restrict the movement of agricultural equipment from one portion of the land to another;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The resulting divided parcel comprised of less than 50 acres is conveyed to owners of adjoining land encumbered by an easement in favor of the Foundation, and both of the following occur:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The owner amends the easement encumbering the adjoining land to encumber the resulting divided parcel, or an overlay easement in favor of the Foundation is placed over the entire acreage constituting the resulting divided parcel and the adjoining land; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The resulting divided parcel and the adjoining land together meet minimum soils requirements as provided by <cite path="15.15.01.03|D.">COMAR 15.15.01.03D</cite>; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The resulting divided parcel comprised of less than 50 acres:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Is conveyed to owners of adjoining land encumbered by an easement containing terms which are acceptable to the Foundation; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>An overlay easement in favor of the Foundation is placed over the entire acreage constituting the resulting divided parcel and the adjoining land.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The resulting divided parcel or parcels remaining after the subdivision of the smaller parcel are at least 50 acres and continue to meet the minimum soils criteria, as provided by <cite path="15.15.01.03|D.">COMAR 15.15.01.03D</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Tenant House. If a tenant house was previously approved by the Foundation under <cite path="|15.15.03">COMAR 15.15.03</cite> and it currently exists upon the land, an agricultural subdivision may be approved only if the following are met:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The resulting divided parcel on which the tenant house is situated is at least 100 acres, unless the Foundation approves otherwise according to <cite path="15.15.03.03">COMAR 15.15.03.03</cite> or <cite path="15|15|12|.04|F.">§F of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The corrective easement restricts the tenant house to the use of a tenant as that term is defined in <cite path="15.15.03.02">COMAR 15.15.03.02</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Existing Easement Violation. The Foundation may deny a request for an agricultural subdivision if an easement violation exists upon the land.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Previously Unapproved Subdivision.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Violation. The subdivision of land without Foundation approval is an easement violation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Procedure. Upon discovery of an unapproved subdivision, the Foundation may either require that the land be restored to its original configuration or it may consider accepting a subdivision request from the owners of all of the resulting divided parcels. In its consideration of whether to accept a request for agricultural subdivision, the Foundation may rely on the recommendation of Foundation staff and the county program administrator. If the Foundation decides to accept a request for an agricultural subdivision, the owners of all of the resulting divided parcels shall submit an application with the documentation required by this chapter. The Foundation shall then determine if the subdivision qualifies for the exception to the subdivision prohibition as provided in this chapter. If the Foundation does not approve the agricultural subdivision, the land shall be restored to its original configuration under the easement.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Requirements. An approval of the agricultural subdivision shall require that the owners comply with all of the requirements of this chapter, but, if any of the resulting divided parcels of the subdivision are less than 50 acres, the Foundation may waive the 50-acre requirement if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At the time of the subdivision:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Foundation’s regulations permitted the resulting divided parcels to be less than 50 acres; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The subdivision met the requirements of <cite path="|15|15|12|.04|F.">Regulation .04F of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The subdivision served an agricultural purpose;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The subdivision enhanced or had no effect upon the agricultural operations being conducted upon the land;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The resulting divided parcels have sustained agricultural production independent of each other from the time of the subdivision;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The resulting divided parcels still meet minimum soils requirements, as provided by <cite path="15.15.01.03|D.">COMAR 15.15.01.03D</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The landowners present evidence satisfactory to the Foundation to make a determination that the resulting divided parcels have sufficient potential to sustain agricultural production independent of each other in the future.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Agricultural Subdivision Application Procedure.</heading>
    <text>Before the Foundation may consider a request for an agricultural subdivision, a landowner shall submit the following:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An application, completed and signed by each titled landowner to all of the land encumbered by the easement, which addresses the criteria in <cite path="|15|15|12|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An unmarked copy of the tax map or boundary survey which outlines the entire easement land;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A second copy of the tax map which shall include the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Boundaries of the easement land;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The location of the proposed line or lines of subdivision, and the amount of acreage each resulting divided parcel is proposed to contain; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The location of, and access to, all preexisting dwellings, lot exclusions, tenant houses, and farm buildings;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A written statement from the landowner indicating:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The reason for the request, including an explanation of how the agricultural subdivision serves the agricultural purpose, how it will enhance or have no effect upon the agricultural operations, and how the resulting divided parcels will be able to sustain long-term agricultural production, independent of each other;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If any rights to a lot or lots have been reserved, but still unexercised, under the easement, a proposal detailing which resulting divided parcel or parcels are to be allocated those rights;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The name, address, email address, and telephone number of all landowners whose lands are involved in the request; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The name of the individual or entity who will pay for the costs of the corrective easement transactions;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A written statement from the county program administrator describing the current overall farm operation, whether the proposed agricultural subdivision serves an agricultural purpose, whether it will enhance or will have no effect upon the agricultural operations, and whether the resulting divided parcels will be able to sustain long-term agricultural production, independent of each other;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A letter of recommendation from the local agricultural land preservation advisory board addressing the potential for continued agricultural use of each of the resulting divided parcels;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Written verification from the local tax assessment office that each of the resulting divided parcels continue to qualify for agricultural use assessment under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtp">Tax-Property Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>A letter from the local planning and zoning office or the county program administrator that the requested subdivision is consistent with county planning and zoning regulations; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>If applicable, letters of support from organizations such as the Soil Conservation Service and Forest Service attesting to the long-term productive capabilities for each resulting divided parcel of less than 50 acres.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Requirements upon Approval.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A landowner may not proceed with plans pursuant to the approval until the corrective easements have been recorded among the land records in the county in which the land is situated, unless the Foundation issues a letter permitting the landowner to proceed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the Foundation approves the request, then the landowner:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall submit to the Foundation, 10 copies of a survey plat, signed and sealed by a surveyor registered in the State of Maryland depicting the resulting divided parcels of the land, along with separate written metes and bounds descriptions of those resulting divided parcels; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shall remit funds in the amount and manner directed by the Foundation to cover the costs of the transaction as specified in Regulation .04C and shall furnish such other documentation as directed by the Foundation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the funds and documentation required by this regulation are not provided by the landowner to the Foundation within 3 years of Foundation board approval, then, unless an extension request is submitted within 3 years and approved by Foundation staff, the approval is void.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Agriculture Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-504">2-504</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-509">2-509</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-513">2-513</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-08-08">Regulations <cite path="|15|15|12|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|15|15|12|.07">.07</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective June 8, 2011 (38:14 Md. R. 788); adopted permanently effective August 8, 2011 (38:16 Md. R. 945)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-09-01"><cite path="|15|15|12|.04|F.">Regulation .04F</cite> amended effective September 1, 2014 (41:17 Md. R. 971)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-09-01"><cite path="|15|15|12|.05|C.">Regulation .05C</cite> amended effective September 1, 2014 (41:17 Md. R. 971)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-09-01"><cite path="|15|15|12|.07|C.">Regulation .07C</cite> adopted effective September 1, 2014 (41:17 Md. R. 971)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
