<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>13</num>
  <heading>Guidelines for Forest Easement Overlays</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter establishes the criteria and eligibility standards for the approval of a forest easement overlay on land subject to an agricultural land preservation easement held by the Maryland Agricultural Land Preservation Foundation (the Foundation).</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Afforestation” means the establishment of tree cover on an area from which it has always or very long been absent, or the planting of open areas which are not presently in forest cover, as defined by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|5-1601">Natural Resources Article, §5-1601, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Forest.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Forest”, as defined by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|5-1601">Natural Resources Article, §5-1601, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, means a biological community dominated by trees and other woody plants covering a land area of 10,000 square feet or greater.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Forest” includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Areas that have at least 100 trees per acre with at least 50 percent of those trees having a 2-inch or greater diameter at 4.5 feet above the ground and larger; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Forest areas that have been cut but not cleared.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>“Forest” does not include orchards.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Forest easement overlay” means a perpetual restriction placed on an existing Foundation easement property to create, restore, or preserve forest, whether for current tax or other incentives, to bank credits under a forest mitigation banking plan, or to meet requirements prescribed by the State or local authority to mitigate activities elsewhere on the property consistent with the agricultural land preservation easement held by the Foundation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Forest mitigation” means the process by which the environmental impact of various development activities, from road construction to residential housing, is mitigated or offset by the restoration, enhancement, creation, or retention of forested land elsewhere, as required by the Maryland Forest Conservation Act of 1991, Natural Resources Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|5-1601">5-1601</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|5-1613">5-1613</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Forest mitigation banking” means the intentional restoration or creation of forests undertaken expressly for the purpose of providing credits for afforestation or reforestation requirements with enhanced environmental benefits from future activities, as defined by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|5-1601">Natural Resources Article, §5-1601, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Forest stewardship plan” or “forest management plan” means a plan prepared by a Maryland-licensed professional forester designed to manage land for productive, sustainable woodland purposes.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Resource conservation purpose” means to preserve soil and natural resources, reduce sediment and nutrient runoff, or improve air and water quality through the implementation of one or more best management practices.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="15|15|13|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Eligibility.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>To be eligible for consideration by the Foundation, a proposal for a forest easement overlay shall meet the requirements of a State or local forest conservation program, be approved by the applicable county’s planning authority, and be recommended by the county’s agricultural land preservation advisory board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>To be eligible for consideration by the Foundation, a proposal for a forest easement overlay shall be limited to 10 acres, or 10 percent of the total easement acreage, whichever is smaller, unless the Foundation determines otherwise.  To be eligible, a forest easement overlay shall allow prescribed harvests.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A forest easement overlay for mitigation purposes shall offset development inside a priority funding area only, with the exception of mitigation required by a Foundation-approved lot release on the same easement property as described in <cite path="15|15|13|.03|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>. Proposals for forest mitigation banking shall establish a reporting mechanism to the county and the Foundation for ensuring that credits, when taken, offset development in a priority funding area.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Resource Conservation.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A forest easement overlay shall serve a legitimate resource conservation purpose under a soil conservation and water quality plan or forest stewardship plan.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The proposed forest easement overlay shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Contribute substantially to good land and environmental resource stewardship on the farm;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Be an appropriate best management practice (BMP) to achieve the resource conservation objectives for the farm, based on Natural Resources Conservation Service (NRCS) standards and estimates;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Be included in the soil conservation and water quality plan and a forest stewardship or management plan for the farm; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Permit sustainable forest stewardship practices, including prescribed harvests.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Mitigation for Residential Development.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a county requires on-site forest mitigation because of on-site residential development, the landowner shall so inform the Foundation at the time of the lot release request. In this case, a separate forest mitigation proposal is not required.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the lot release request is approved, the forest mitigation easement overlay document shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be submitted to the Foundation for review in advance of recordation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Be subordinate to the agricultural land preservation easement unless otherwise required; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Allow prescribed harvests unless harvesting is restricted under the soil conservation and water quality plan.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>County Application Procedure.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Before the Foundation may consider a proposal for a forest easement overlay, applicants shall first submit the following information to their county program administrator:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A current soil conservation and water quality plan, developed by the local soil conservation district, that describes the resource conservation purpose served;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For properties with 25 acres or more in contiguous woodland or where required by an underlying easement, a forest stewardship plan or forest management plan, developed within the past 10 years by a Maryland-licensed forester, which provides for sustainable forest stewardship and management practices, including prescribed harvests;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If a soil conservation and water quality plan is not required because the property is 100 percent woodland, proof of a forest stewardship plan or forest management plan, developed within the last 10 years by a Maryland-licensed professional forester, describing the resource conservation purpose served; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A completed Foundation application, including an assessment of the following criteria:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The restrictions that would be imposed on the current and future production options for the land;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The potential effect of the forest easement on the ability of subsequent owners of the land to conduct profitable activities on the land;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The amount of land proposed for forest easement;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The productivity of the soil or soils; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The resource conservation purpose being served.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The county program administrator shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Review the application and supporting documentation for completeness;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Present the application and supporting documentation to the county agricultural land preservation advisory board for its recommendation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Present the application and supporting documentation to the applicable county’s planning authority for approval; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Send the proposal to the Foundation if the county agricultural land preservation advisory board recommends the proposal and the applicable county’s planning authority approves the proposal, with documentation verifying the recommendation and approval.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>When the county agricultural land preservation advisory board reviews a forest easement overlay proposal, it shall consider the Foundation’s criteria for review set forth in Regulation .05B and C of this chapter and convey the basis for its recommendation to the Foundation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>For forest mitigation proposals, the local government, whether it is the county program administrator or another responsible party chosen by the county, shall also identify in writing the type of development activity for which mitigation is required, locate the development activity on an appropriate map, inform the Foundation if the development activity is subject to the county’s approval and, if it is, verify that the county either has approved the project or believes that the development project is consistent with the plans, ordinances, and regulations governing its approval.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Foundation Application Procedure.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Upon receiving a completed proposal from the county program administrator, the Foundation staff shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Review the proposal for completeness;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Submit the proposal to the Maryland Department of Agriculture’s Office of Resource Conservation for a written opinion on the appropriateness of the forest easement overlay proposal;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Submit the proposal, if it involves mitigation, to the Maryland Department of Planning for a written statement indicating whether the development to be facilitated by the forest mitigation is in a priority funding area, is consistent with the local comprehensive plan and State planning policy, and is not likely to encourage or support substantial further development in areas the Foundation is attempting to preserve; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Submit the complete proposal and staff recommendation to the Foundation’s Board of Trustees.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>After receiving the proposal and recommendation from the Foundation staff, the Board shall determine if the forest easement overlay is consistent with the Foundation’s mission and is appropriate for the easement property. The approval for a forest easement overlay on a Foundation easement or district property is not an absolute right of a landowner, and requests shall be reviewed by the Foundation on a case-by-case basis.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Foundation shall also take into account the following criteria when reviewing a forest easement overlay proposal:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The restrictions that would be imposed on the current and future production options for the land;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The potential effect of the forest easement on the ability of subsequent owners of the land to conduct profitable activities on the land, compatible with the Foundation’s easement;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The amount of the land proposed for an easement overlay;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The productivity of the soil or soils;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The resource conservation purpose being served;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The recommendation of the county agricultural land preservation advisory board; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Any other considerations appropriate and necessary to determine the proposal’s compatibility with the Foundation’s goals and objectives.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the request is to establish a forest easement overlay for a forest mitigation bank, the Foundation shall approve or deny the request after considering the criteria set forth in this regulation. If the Board approves an overlay for forest mitigation banking, future mitigation credits may be approved by the Foundation staff but shall offset development in a priority funding area.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If the forest easement overlay request is for a property subject to an easement with a 25-year termination clause, the landowner shall amend the deed of easement to waive the right to request termination of the easement after 25 years and to clarify the perpetual nature of the easement. The waiver requirement of this section does not apply to a forest easement overlay request if local law requires the request be made to offset the development of an on-site residential lot authorized under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-513">Agriculture Article, §2-513, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The forest easement overlay document shall be submitted to the Foundation for review in advance of recordation and be subordinate to the agricultural land preservation easement unless the Foundation determines that the State’s interest in the land would be compromised by doing so.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Agriculture Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-504">2-504</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-513">2-513</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-06-27">Effective date: June 27, 2011 (38:13 Md. R. 757)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-06-04"><cite path="|15|15|13|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite> amended effective June 4, 2018 (45:11 Md. R. 579)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-06-04"><cite path="|15|15|13|.05|E.">Regulation .05E</cite> amended effective June 4, 2018 (45:11 Md. R. 579)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
