<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>16</num>
  <heading>Guidelines for Granting Overlay Easements and Rights-of-Way</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>This chapter establishes the criteria and eligibility standards for the approval of overlay easements and rights-of-way on land subject to an agricultural land preservation easement held by the Maryland Agricultural Land Preservation Foundation.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Eligibility.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definition.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In this regulation, the following term has the meaning indicated.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Term Defined. “Conservation values” means natural habitat for native plant and wildlife species, including, but not limited to, forests, riparian forested areas, wetlands, and greenways to buffer the Chesapeake Bay and its tributaries from pollution runoff.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>After a landowner has sold an agricultural preservation easement to the Foundation, the landowner and subsequent landowners may not grant or permit another to establish an easement, right-of-way, or other servitude in that land without the Foundation’s written permission. The Foundation may permit an easement, right-of-way, or other servitude to be granted in land encumbered by an agricultural preservation easement, subject to conditions it deems necessary to protect and maintain the agricultural integrity of the farm under the following circumstances:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If it is to service a lot released from the preservation easement restrictions under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-513">Agriculture Article, §2-513, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If it is to service a lot or land permitted to be withheld from the agricultural preservation easement at the time of sale of the agricultural preservation easement to the Foundation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If it is to service an adjacent farm, provided, however, that its use is restricted to the movement of farm equipment or other items associated with farming;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If it is a forest overlay easement that meets the criteria described in <cite path="15.15.13.01">COMAR 15.15.13.01</cite> et seq.;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If the overlay easement documents a use existing at the time the agricultural preservation easement was sold to the Foundation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>If the overlay easement serves telephone, television, gas, or other similar utility lines (but not access) to service the easement property or lots created under §A or B in this regulation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>If the overlay easement enhances a public road or bridge for the public health, safety, or welfare, where a minimal amount of land is required for such project, and the grantee of the proposed overlay easement has condemning authority;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>If the overlay easement is used to install a utility easement for electricity, telephone, cable, oil, gas, or similar utility and the grantee of the proposed overlay easement has condemning authority;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>If the overlay easement is used to create a septic area for an adjoining property which has a failed septic system and there is no other reasonable alternative site or method available;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>If failure to grant the overlay easement would result in significant detrimental impact to the conservation values on an adjacent property as determined by the Foundation; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>For any other lawful purpose not listed above, subject to any such further conditions or requirements deemed appropriate by the Foundation’s Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Conditions of Approval.</heading>
    <text>The following conditions apply to any overlay easement approved by the Foundation:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The proposed overlay easement may not prohibit any agricultural operation within the proposed overlay easement area, unless otherwise approved by the Board;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The proposed overlay easement shall have minimal interference on the overall farm operation;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the proposed overlay easement is a right-of-way, its width shall be the minimum required by law;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>When considering an overlay easement request, the Foundation shall consider the  legislative intent as provided in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-501">Agriculture Article, §2-501, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Foundation may require any other conditions it considers appropriate on a case-by-case basis when approving any particular overlay easement proposal, including other conditions required by law or regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Application Requirements.</heading>
    <text>An application to the Foundation for overlay easement approval shall provide the following information:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A location map outlining the entire property, the overlay easement area, and access to the overlay easement area;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A draft of the proposed overlay deed of easement (not a generic copy) that shall clearly list all activities that may or may not be permitted;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the Foundation requires, the proposed overlay easement form shall include language that would make the proposed overlay easement subordinate to the agricultural preservation easement;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the application is for a right-of-way easement, information shall be provided regarding the State’s or county’s minimum width requirements;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A statement of the purpose of the request, including alternatives available to the proposed overlay easement;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Confirmation from the county planning and zoning office that the proposed overlay easement complies with local zoning requirements;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A recommendation from the local Agricultural Land Preservation Advisory Board; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Any other information the Foundation considers necessary to consider the application.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Survey Requirement.</heading>
    <text>If the Foundation approves the proposed overlay easement, a survey of the overlay easement area, including access, shall be provided to the Foundation for approval before the overlay easement is signed and recorded.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Agriculture Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-504">2-504</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-513">2-513</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-06-04">Effective date: June 4, 2018 (45:11 Md. R. 580)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-07-26"><cite path="|15|15|16|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective July 26, 2021 (48:15 Md. R. 594)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
