<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>04</num>
  <heading>Emergency Use Auto-Injectable Epinephrine Program</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter applies to employees of food service, recreation, or wellness facilities on the premises of an institution of higher education as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|10-101">Education Article, §10-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and employees of food service facilities, as defined in <cite path="|10.15.03">COMAR 10.15.03</cite>, who voluntarily participate in the Program.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Affiliated individual” means an individual who is 18 years old or older who has been designated in writing by a participating facility to serve either as a health supervisor or as a certificate holder.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Agent” means an individual who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is 18 years old or older;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has successfully completed, at the expense of the participating facility, an emergency epinephrine educational training program approved by the Department; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Is designated in writing by a certificate holder to administer auto-injectable epinephrine in an emergency situation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Anaphylaxis” means a sudden, severe, and potentially life–threatening allergic reaction that occurs when an individual is exposed to an allergen.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Applicant” means an individual applying for a Certificate for Emergency Epinephrine.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Auto-injectable epinephrine” means a portable, disposable drug delivery device that contains a premeasured single dose of epinephrine that is used to treat anaphylaxis in an emergency situation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Certificate for emergency epinephrine” means a certificate issued by the Maryland Department of Health to an individual employed or designated by a participating facility to obtain, store, and administer auto-injectable epinephrine.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Certificate holder” means an individual who is authorized by the Maryland Department of Health to obtain, store, and administer auto-injectable epinephrine to be used in an emergency situation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Department” means the Maryland Department of Health.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“Eligible institution” means an institution of higher education that has a food service facility or a recreation and wellness facility on the premises and that otherwise meets the requirements of this chapter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>“Food service facility” has the meaning stated in <cite path="|10.15.03">COMAR 10.15.03</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>“Health supervisor” means an individual who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Provides health services for a participating facility; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is licensed by the State as a:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Physician;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Certified nurse practitioner; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Registered nurse.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>“Participating facility” means a recreation or wellness facility at an eligible institution or a food service facility, including a food service facility at an eligible institution, in the State that voluntarily participates in the Program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>“Successfully completed” means to pass a written examination with a grade of 75 percent or higher.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|13|04|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Emergency Epinephrine.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An individual may apply, on a form prescribed by the Department, for a certificate for emergency epinephrine, which shall be valid for up to 1 year if the applicant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is employed by a participating facility;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is 18 years old or older; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Has successfully completed, at the expense of the participating facility, an emergency epinephrine educational training program approved by the Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The applicant shall submit to the Department with the form required in <cite path="10|13|04|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> a written policy that includes:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Designation of agents and affiliated individuals;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The name of the approved emergency epinephrine educational training program; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Procedures to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Store emergency auto-injectable epinephrine;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Maintain the emergency auto-injectable epinephrine in a secure manner;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Report use of emergency auto-injectable epinephrine according to <cite path="10|13|04|.03|L.">§L of this regulation</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Train an emergency epinephrine certificate holder and agent annually; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Maintain documentation of an emergency epinephrine certificate holder and agent training for 3 years.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A provider of an emergency epinephrine educational training program shall meet the requirements of <cite path="10.16.07.15|C.">COMAR 10.16.07.15C</cite> and D.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An individual teaching an emergency epinephrine educational training program shall be licensed as a physician, a registered nurse, or a certified nurse practitioner.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Department shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Issue a certificate for emergency epinephrine to an applicant who meets the requirements in §§A and B of this regulation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Deny the issuance of a certificate for emergency epinephrine to an applicant who does not meet the requirements in §§A and B of this regulation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Revoke or suspend the certificate for emergency epinephrine of an individual who does not meet the requirements in §§A and B of this regulation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Approve an emergency epinephrine educational training program if the training program meets the requirements of <cite path="10|13|04|.03|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Disapprove an emergency epinephrine educational training program if the training program does not meet the requirement of <cite path="10|13|04|.03|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>On or before January 31 of each year, publish a report summarizing the information obtained from the reported uses of emergency auto-injectable epinephrine at participating facilities according to <cite path="10|13|04|.03|L.">§L of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A physician licensed to practice medicine in the State may prescribe auto-injectable epinephrine in the name of a certificate holder.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A pharmacist licensed to practice pharmacy in the State, or a physician, may dispense auto-injectable epinephrine under a prescription issued to a certificate holder.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>A certificate holder may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>On presentment of a certificate for emergency epinephrine, receive from any physician licensed to practice medicine in the State a prescription for auto-injectable epinephrine; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Possess and store prescribed auto-injectable epinephrine.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>A participating facility:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall ensure that there is a written plan for the emergency epinephrine program that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is approved annually, in writing, by a health supervisor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is on file at the participating facility and is available for inspection; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Includes at a minimum:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The name, title, and license number of the health supervisor;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Information on the emergency epinephrine educational training program used;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Procedures for disseminating information to staff on the emergency epinephrine program;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Procedures for the proper storage and handling of medication;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Procedures for the use of emergency services and 911 services; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Procedures for documenting incidents involving the administration of auto-injectable epinephrine by a certificate holder in accordance with <cite path="10|13|04|.03|L.">§L of this regulation</cite>;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shall ensure that a certificate holder who is employed by, or a designated affiliated individual of, the participating facility complies with all provisions of this chapter;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Shall provide the Department with access to records and documents required under this chapter;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Shall designate in writing the certificate holders who will be responsible for the storage, maintenance, and control of the supply of auto-injectable epinephrine;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>May not obtain or store auto-injectable epinephrine unless the participating facility has at least two certificate holders; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Shall maintain a copy of the certificate issued to a certificate holder under <cite path="10|13|04|.03|E.">§E of this regulation</cite> for at least 3 years.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Certificate Holders.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Subject to <cite path="10|13|04|.03|I.|(4)">§I(4) of this regulation</cite>, a certificate holder may obtain:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A prescription for a supply of auto-injectable epinephrine from a licensed physician as provided in <cite path="10|13|04|.03|F.">§F of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A supply of auto-injectable epinephrine from a licensed pharmacist or a licensed physician as provided in <cite path="10|13|04|.03|G.">§G of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A certificate holder shall store a supply of auto-injectable epinephrine obtained under <cite path="10|13|04|.03|J.|(1)">§J(1) of this regulation</cite>:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In accordance with the manufacturer’s instructions; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>In a location that is readily accessible to certificate holders and agents in an emergency situation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>In an emergency situation when physician or emergency medical services are not immediately available, a certificate holder or agent may administer auto-injectable epinephrine to an individual who is experiencing or believed in good faith by the certificate holder or agent to be experiencing anaphylaxis.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>A participating facility shall ensure that an incident that occurred on the premises of the facility that involved the administration of auto-injectable epinephrine by a certificate holder or agent is reported:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Immediately to the health supervisor and, in the case of a minor, to the minor’s parent or guardian; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>To the Department within 5 business days of the incident on a form prescribed by the Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health-General Article, §§2-104 and 13-7A-03, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-05-20">Effective date: May 20, 2019 (46:10 Md. R. 487)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-07-12"><cite path="|10|13|04|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective July 12, 2021 (48:14 Md. R. 538)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-07-12"><cite path="|10|13|04|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective July 12, 2021 (48:14 Md. R. 538)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-07-12"><cite path="|10|13|04|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective July 12, 2021 (48:14 Md. R. 538)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
