<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Individual Exchange Navigator Certification — Renewal, Reinstatement, Deactivation, and Suspension or Revocation of Certification</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Term.</heading>
    <text>An Individual Exchange navigator certification expires 2 years after the date it is issued unless it is renewed.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="14|35|03|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Renewal.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Notice.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At least 60 days before the expiration of an Individual Exchange navigator certification, the Exchange shall notify the Individual Exchange navigator, either directly at the address, including email address, on file with the Exchange, or by contacting the navigator entity by whom the Individual Exchange navigator is employed or engaged, of the expiration date of an Individual Exchange navigator certification.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The notification shall include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A renewal application;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The date by which the Exchange must receive the renewal application for the renewal to be issued before the certification expires; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The amount of the renewal fee, if any.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Eligibility for Renewal. An Individual Exchange navigator certification may be renewed for an additional 2-year term if the holder:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is otherwise entitled to receive Individual Exchange navigator certification, in accordance with the eligibility requirements set forth in <cite path="14.35.02.02">COMAR 14.35.02.02</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Files a renewal application on the form provided by the Exchange either by mail or electronically before expiration of the certification;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Pays to the Exchange a renewal fee if permitted by law and in the manner specified by the Exchange; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Has completed the Exchange annual training and the continuing education requirements under <cite path="14|35|03|.02|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Continuing Education. A certified Individual Exchange navigator shall complete at least 16 hours of Exchange-approved continuing education per renewal term.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Annual Training.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Exchange shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Schedule the Continuing Education Training on an annual basis; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Notify certified Individual Exchange navigators of the annual training.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A certified Individual Exchange navigator shall complete the annual training, including any examination, within 60 days before the open enrollment period during each year of the certification term, including any renewal term.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Reinstatement.</heading>
    <text>In order to obtain a reinstatement of an Individual Exchange navigator certification, the applicant shall submit to the Exchange an application as required under <cite path="14.35.02.03">COMAR 14.35.02.03</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="14|35|03|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Inactive Certification.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An Individual Exchange navigator shall provide evidence satisfactory to the Exchange of employment or engagement by a navigator entity before the navigator may become certified.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Exchange may deactivate an individual’s Individual Exchange navigator certification whenever the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Individual fails to complete the annual training;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Individual has not provided evidence satisfactory to the Exchange of employment or engagement by a navigator entity, as set forth under <cite path="14|35|03|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Exchange is informed, either by the individual or a navigator entity, that the individual is not employed or engaged by the navigator entity.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If certification is deactivated due to reasons listed under §B(2) or (3) of this regulation, the Exchange may waive the fees listed under <cite path="|14|35|03|.02|B.|(3)">Regulation .02B(3) of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Suspension or Revocation.</heading>
    <text>The Commissioner may suspend or revoke an Individual Exchange navigator certification for the reasons listed under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|31-113">Insurance Article, §31-113(l)(1), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Insurance Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|31-106">31-106</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|31-113">31-113</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-04-15">Effective date: April 15, 2013 (40:7 Md. R. 612)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-06-15"><cite path="|14|35|03|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite>, D amended effective June 15, 2020 (47:12 Md. R. 597)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-06-15"><cite path="|14|35|03|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective June 15, 2020 (47:12 Md. R. 597)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-06-15"><cite path="|14|35|03|.04|F.">Regulation .04F</cite> amended effective June 15, 2020 (47:12 Md. R. 597)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
