<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Insurance Producer Authorization — Renewal, Reinstatement, and Suspension or Revocation of Authorization</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Term.</heading>
    <text>An insurance producer authorization expires 2 years after the date it is issued unless it is renewed.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="14|35|05|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Renewal.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Notice.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At least 60 days before the expiration of an insurance producer authorization, the Exchange shall notify the authorized insurance producer of the expiration of the authorization.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The notification shall include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A renewal application;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The date by which the Exchange must receive the renewal application for the renewal to be issued before the authorization expires; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The amount of the renewal fee, if any.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Eligibility for Renewal. An insurance producer authorization may be renewed for an additional 2-year term if the holder:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is otherwise entitled to receive insurance producer authorization, in accordance with the eligibility requirements set forth in <cite path="14.35.04.02">COMAR 14.35.04.02</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Files a renewal application on the form provided by the Exchange before the expiration of the authorization;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Pays to the Exchange a renewal fee if permitted by law and in the manner specified by the Exchange;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Completes the annual training requirements set forth in <cite path="14.35.04.04">COMAR 14.35.04.04</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Is not denied by the Exchange for reasons set forth under <cite path="14|35|05|.02|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Exchange Annual Training.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Exchange shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Schedule the Exchange Annual Training; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Notify authorized insurance producers of the annual training.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Authorized insurance producers shall complete the annual training, including any examination, within 60 days before the open enrollment period.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Timely Receipt of Application:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Before the date of expiration of the authorization, a holder of an insurance producer authorization shall complete and return to the Exchange a renewal application and a renewal fee according to the renewal instructions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A holder of an expired insurance producer authorization may not sell qualified plans in the SHOP Exchange or Individual Exchange.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Denial.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Exchange may deny a renewal application if the insurance producer has:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Committed any act described in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|31-113">Insurance Article, §31-113(l)(1), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Had any professional license or certification suspended or revoked for a fraudulent or dishonest practice.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Denial of a renewal application is subject to the contested case hearing provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 10, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Reinstatement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>For up to 1 year after the expiration date, an individual whose insurance producer authorization has expired may apply to reinstate the expired authorization by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Filing a reinstatement application, either by mail or electronically, on the form approved by the Exchange;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Paying to the Exchange the renewal fee if permitted by law and in the manner specified by the Exchange;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Paying to the Exchange a reinstatement fee if permitted by law and in the manner specified by the Exchange; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Submitting evidence to the Exchange that the individual has successfully completed the Exchange annual training and the continuing education requirements under <cite path="|14|35|05|.02|C.">Regulation .02C of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An individual who does not file for reinstatement within 1 year after the expiration date of the insurance producer authorization shall apply for an authorization under the application procedures set forth in <cite path="14.35.04.03">COMAR 14.35.04.03</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Suspension or Revocation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Exchange may suspend or revoke an insurance producer authorization for a licensed producer authorized to sell qualified plans in the SHOP Exchange as set forth under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|31-112">Insurance Article, §31-112(f)(3)(i), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Exchange may suspend or revoke an insurance producer authorization for a licensed producer authorized to sell qualified plans in the Individual Exchange as set forth under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|31-113">Insurance Article, §31-113(m)(3)(i), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Insurance Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|31-106">31-106</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|31-112">31-112</cite>(f), (g), and (h), and 31-113(m), (n), and (o), Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-04-15">Effective date: April 15, 2013 (40:7 Md. R. 612)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-06-15"><cite path="|14|35|05|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective June 15, 2020 (47:12 Md. R. 597)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-08-18"><cite path="|14|35|05|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective August 18, 2025 (52:16 Md. R. 848)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-08-18"><cite path="|14|35|05|.02|E.">Regulation .02E</cite> adopted effective August 18, 2025 (52:16 Md. R. 848)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
