<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>14</num>
  <heading>Termination, Cancellation, and Rescission of Qualified Health Plan</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter describes the events that may result in the termination, cancellation, or rescission of the enrollment of an individual enrolled in a QHP through the Individual Exchange.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Cancellation” means an action that ends a qualified individual's enrollment through the Exchange on the date such enrollment became effective resulting in enrollment through the Exchange never having been effective.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Product” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-1309">Insurance Article, §15-1309(a)(3)(i), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Reinstatement” means a correction of an erroneous termination or cancellation action that results in restoration of an enrollment with no break in coverage.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Same QHP policy” means that one enrollee is enrolled under the same QHP contract as another enrollee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Termination” means an action taken after a coverage effective date that ends an enrollee's enrollment through the Exchange for a date after the original coverage effective date resulting in a period during which the individual was enrolled in coverage through the Exchange.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Terminations in General.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An enrollee who is the contract holder of a QHP who terminates enrollment in a QHP also terminates the enrollment of the other enrollees in the household.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Each enrollee, who is not the contract holder, may terminate enrollment in a QHP without affecting the enrollment status of the enrollee’s household or each individual member of the enrollee’s household other than the enrollee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A carrier shall process a request from the contract holder of a QHP to terminate coverage under <cite path="|14|35|14|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite> for all enrollees promptly and without undue delay.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A carrier shall process the Exchange’s termination determination under <cite path="|14|35|14|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite> promptly and without undue delay.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A carrier shall maintain records of termination of enrollment in a QHP in the format specified by the Exchange in an electronic data interchange format for a period of 10 years.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A carrier shall make reasonable accommodations for all individuals with disabilities (as defined by the Americans with Disabilities Act), including head-of-household and non-head-of-household enrollees, before terminating the individual's enrollment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A carrier shall send an electronic transaction to the Exchange documenting, or acknowledging, each termination of coverage carried out under this chapter, promptly and without undue delay.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>In cases of retroactive termination dates, the carrier shall accept the Exchange’s adjusted calculations of APTC, and premiums and changes to the plan variation of the QHP.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>A carrier shall confirm the termination of an enrollee’s coverage with a notice provided to the contract holder indicating the enrollees affected by the termination and the effective date of the termination.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Enrollee-Initiated Terminations — In General.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An enrollee may terminate the enrollee’s coverage in a QHP at any time within a month for a termination effective at the end of the month.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An enrollee may request a termination of the enrollee’s coverage in a QHP by providing notice to the Exchange or the enrollee’s QHP carrier as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Enrollees seeking to terminate coverage for an enrollee or enrollees on a QHP shall provide notice to the Exchange; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Enrollees seeking to terminate coverage for the enrollee’s household may notify either the Exchange or the QHP carrier.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Date of Terminations. If the enrollee provides notice to the Exchange or the carrier on any day within the month, the date of termination is the end of the month.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If an enrollee terminates coverage in one QHP because the enrollee elects enrollment in a different QHP, coverage in the original qualified health plan ends at midnight the day before the effective date of coverage in the enrollee’s new QHP.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Death.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In the case of a termination due to death, the last day of enrollment in a QHP through the Exchange is the date of death.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Any applicable premium refund, or premium due, shall be processed by the deceased enrollee's QHP in accordance with State law.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Notice of the enrollee’s death may be provided to the Exchange or the deceased enrollee’s QHP by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The policyholder under <cite path="31.10.01.02|B.|(7)">COMAR 31.10.01.02B(7)</cite>, or subscriber under <cite path="31.12.02.02|B.|(11)">COMAR 31.12.02.02B(11)</cite>, of the deceased enrollee’s QHP;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An enrollee who is 18 years or older and enrolled in the same QHP policy of the deceased enrollee; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The authorized representative of an enrollee under <cite path="14.35.11.14">COMAR 14.35.11.14</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Retroactive Terminations.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An enrollee may retroactively terminate or cancel the enrollee's coverage or enrollment in a QHP when the enrollee:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Demonstrates to the Exchange that the enrollee enrolled in Medicare Part A or B coverage with a retroactive effective date; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Requests retroactive termination of QHP coverage within 60 days of the enrollment.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The effective date of the retroactive termination must be no earlier than the later of the day before the first day of coverage under Medicare Part A or B, and the day that is 6 months before the retroactive termination in QHP coverage is requested.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A retroactive termination date as described in this section is not available for enrollments in stand-alone dental plans.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="14|35|14|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Enrollee-Initiated Terminations — Due to Error, Misconduct, or Enrollment without Knowledge or Consent.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An enrollee may retroactively terminate the enrollee’s coverage when:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The enrollee attempted to terminate the enrollee’s coverage and the enrollee experienced a technical error that did not allow the enrollee to terminate the enrollee’s coverage;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The enrollee’s enrollment in a QHP through the Exchange was unintentional, inadvertent, or erroneous and was the result of the error or misconduct of an officer, employee, or agent of the Exchange, its instrumentalities, or a non-Exchange entity providing enrollment assistance or conducting enrollment activities; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The enrollee was enrolled in a QHP without the enrollee’s knowledge or consent by any third party, including third parties who have no connection with the Exchange.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Misconduct under <cite path="14|35|14|.05|A.|(2)">§A(2) of this regulation</cite> means the failure of an officer, employee, or agent of the Exchange, its instrumentalities, or a non-Exchange entity providing enrollment assistance or conducting enrollment activities to comply with applicable standards under <cite path="|14.35.14">COMAR 14.35.14</cite> or other applicable State or federal laws as determined by the Exchange.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Except as specified in <cite path="14|35|14|.05|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>, the enrollee shall request termination under <cite path="14|35|14|.05|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> by notifying the Exchange of the request:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within 60 days of discovering the technical error under <cite path="14|35|14|.05|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Within 60 days of discovering the unintentional, inadvertent, or erroneous enrollment under <cite path="14|35|14|.05|A.|(2)">§A(2) of this regulation</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Within 60 days of discovering the enrollment under <cite path="14|35|14|.05|A.|(3)">§A(3) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the enrollee discovers an enrollment under <cite path="14|35|14|.05|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> in the previous calendar year, the enrollee shall request termination under <cite path="14|35|14|.05|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> by notifying the Exchange of the request by the end of March the calendar year immediately following the calendar year with the enrollment under <cite path="14|35|14|.05|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Notification to the Exchange under §§C and D of this regulation shall be satisfied if the enrollee provides notice:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To an Exchange-certified navigator, an Exchange-authorized broker, or an Exchange-certified consolidated service center representative; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Using any of the methods of communication listed under <cite path="14.35.07.03|B.">COMAR 14.35.07.03B</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The effective date of the termination under <cite path="14|35|14|.05|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For a retroactive termination under <cite path="14|35|14|.05|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite>, no later than the end of the month when the enrollee contacted the Exchange to request termination of the enrollee’s enrollment through the Exchange; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For a retroactive termination under §A(2) or (3) of this regulation:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The original coverage effective date; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A later date, as determined appropriate by the Exchange, based on the circumstances of the termination.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="14|35|14|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Termination by the Exchange.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A carrier shall terminate an enrollee’s coverage in a qualified health plan upon receiving an electronic data transaction from the Exchange directing that the enrollee’s coverage be terminated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Exchange shall direct the carrier to terminate an enrollee’s enrollment in a QHP if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The enrollee is no longer eligible for coverage in a QHP through the Exchange;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The enrollee requests termination under Regulations .04 and .05 of this chapter;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The enrollee’s coverage is rescinded under 45 CFR §147.128;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The QHP terminates or is decertified under 45 CFR §155.1080;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Exchange determines that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An enrollee was enrolled in a QHP without the enrollee’s knowledge or consent by a third party, including by a third party with no connection with the Exchange; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Where possible, the Exchange has provided reasonable notice to the enrollee of the Exchange’s determination;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The enrollee changes from one QHP to another QHP during an annual open enrollment period under <cite path="14.35.07.11|A.|(1)">COMAR 14.35.07.11A(1)</cite> or a special enrollment period under <cite path="14.35.07.12">COMAR 14.35.07.12</cite>—.19; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The enrollee moves outside of the service area under 45 CFR §155.430(b)(2)(vii) in reference to 45 CFR §147.106(b)(5).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the enrollee becomes eligible for other minimum essential coverage but does not request termination in accordance with <cite path="|14|35|14|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite> at the time of plan renewal, the enrollee may choose to remain enrolled in a QHP without the provision of financial assistance through APTC or CSR payments.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the enrollee does not choose to remain enrolled in the QHP through the Exchange when the enrollee becomes eligible for other minimum essential health coverage under <cite path="14|35|14|.06|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, the Exchange shall initiate termination of the enrollee’s coverage upon completion of the redetermination process specified in 45 CFR §155.330.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Upon termination by the Exchange, the last day of coverage by a QHP is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The last day of the enrollee’s eligibility, if the Exchange determines an enrollee to be no longer eligible for coverage in a QHP through the Individual Exchange;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The last day of the coverage month in which coverage is rescinded, if the enrollee’s coverage is rescinded in accordance with 45 CFR §147.128;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The last day of the coverage month in which the QHP is terminated or decertified, if the QHP terminates or, as described in 45 CFR §155.1080, is decertified;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The last day of the coverage month in which the enrollee is determined newly eligible for enrollment in Medicaid or MCHP, if the enrollee chooses to terminate the QHP;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The day before the first day of enrollment in the new QHP if an enrollee terminates coverage in a previous QHP and selects a new QHP during an annual open enrollment period under <cite path="14.35.07.11|A.|(1)">COMAR 14.35.07.11A(1)</cite> or a special enrollment period under <cite path="14.35.07.12">COMAR 14.35.07.12</cite>—.19;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The original coverage effective date for a cancellation under <cite path="14|35|14|.06|B.|(5)">§B(5) of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The date of death, if the enrollee is terminated because of the enrollee’s death; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The day before the change in the enrollee’s circumstance if the enrollee is terminated because of a circumstance where the enrollee could not have prevented the disruption of the QHP enrollment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>For an enrollee’s dependent turning age 26, the carrier may not terminate coverage of the dependent before the end of the coverage year in which the dependent reaches age 26.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="14|35|14|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Termination by Carrier.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A carrier may only terminate an individual’s coverage in a QHP before receiving an instruction from the Exchange to terminate coverage:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If the enrollee requests termination of the enrollee’s enrollment to the carrier, and the termination follows the procedures in <cite path="|14|35|14|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the enrollee’s coverage is rescinded under 45 CFR §147.128;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the carrier is decertified by the Exchange under <cite path="14.35.16.11">COMAR 14.35.16.11</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the carrier ceases to offer the QHP that an enrollee is enrolled in through the Exchange under 45 CFR §147.106(b)(4) and the carrier follows the requirements under 45 CFR §147.106(c);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If the carrier ceases to offer any QHPs through the Exchange under 45 CFR §147.106(b)(4) and the carrier follows the requirements under 45 CFR §147.106(d);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>If the enrollee has performed an act or practice that constitutes fraud or intentional misrepresentation of material fact in connection with the coverage under 45 CFR §147.106(b)(2); or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>For nonpayment of premiums as specified in <cite path="14|35|14|.07|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Termination for Nonpayment.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A carrier may terminate coverage for nonpayment of premium if the enrollee has not made applicable premium payments and at the time the enrollee first fails to pay premiums:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The enrollee is receiving APTC, and the 3-month grace period under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-1315">Insurance Article, §15-1315(c)</cite>—(e), Annotated Code of Maryland, has been exhausted; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The enrollee is not receiving APTC and all other applicable grace periods under State law have been exhausted.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A carrier may not terminate coverage for failure to make a premium payment if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Through a renewal of the plan under 45 CFR §155.335, the enrollee maintains coverage in the same QHP or same product that is a uniform modification of coverage under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-1309">Insurance Article, §15-1309(a)(4), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The applicable grace period has not been exhausted under:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-1315">Insurance Article, §15-1315(c)</cite>—(e), Annotated Code of Maryland; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Another applicable grace period under State law if the enrollee is not receiving APTC.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The last day of coverage is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The last day of the first month of the 3-month grace period when terminating an individual after exhaustion of the 3-month grace period for individuals receiving APTC; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>31 days after the missed premium payment was due when terminating an individual after the exhaustion of any other applicable grace period.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Notice of Non-Payment of Premiums. If an enrollee is delinquent on premium payment, the carrier shall provide the enrollee with notice of such payment delinquency. A carrier shall provide such notices promptly and without undue delay, within 10 business days of the date the issuer should have discovered the delinquency.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="14|35|14|.08">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Cancellation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An individual’s enrollment in a QHP may be canceled only if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The enrollee requests voluntary cancellation of the enrollee’s enrollment to the Exchange or the carrier under <cite path="14|35|14|.08|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The enrollee’s coverage is rescinded under 45 CFR §147.128; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The enrollee does not provide the first month’s premium required to effectuate an enrollment by the due dates set forth at <cite path="14.35.07.11|F.">COMAR 14.35.07.11F</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>To request cancellation of the individual’s enrollment under <cite path="14|35|14|.08|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, the individual shall notify the Exchange or the carrier of the request to cancel before or on the last day of the month prior to the date the coverage begins.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An enrollee may retroactively cancel the enrollee’s coverage if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The enrollee attempted to cancel the enrollee’s coverage and the enrollee experienced a technical error that did not allow the enrollee to cancel the enrollee’s coverage;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The enrollee’s enrollment in a QHP through the Exchange was unintentional, inadvertent, or erroneous and was the result of the error or misconduct of an officer, employee, or agent of the Exchange, its instrumentalities, or a non-Exchange entity providing enrollment assistance or conducting enrollment activities; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The enrollee was enrolled in a QHP without the enrollee’s knowledge or consent by any third party, including third parties who have no connection with the Exchange.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Misconduct under <cite path="14|35|14|.08|C.|(2)">§C(2) of this regulation</cite> means the failure of an officer, employee, or agent of the Exchange or HHS, its instrumentalities, or a non-Exchange entity providing enrollment assistance or conducting enrollment activities to comply with applicable standards under <cite path="|14.35.14">COMAR 14.35.14</cite> or other applicable State or federal laws as determined by the Exchange.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Except as specified in <cite path="14|35|14|.08|F.">§F of this regulation</cite>, the enrollee shall request cancellation under <cite path="14|35|14|.08|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> by notifying the Exchange of the request:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within 60 days after the enrollee discovered the technical error under <cite path="14|35|14|.08|C.|(1)">§C(1) of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Within 60 days of discovering the unintentional, inadvertent, or erroneous enrollment under <cite path="14|35|14|.08|C.|(2)">§C(2) of this regulation</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Within 60 days of discovering of the enrollment under <cite path="14|35|14|.08|C.|(2)">§C(2) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If the enrollee discovers an enrollment under <cite path="14|35|14|.08|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> in the previous calendar year, the enrollee shall request termination under <cite path="14|35|14|.08|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> by notifying the Exchange of the request by the end of March in the calendar year immediately following the calendar year with the enrollment under <cite path="14|35|14|.08|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Notification to the Exchange under §§E and F of this regulation shall be satisfied if the enrollee provides notice:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To an Exchange-certified navigator, an Exchange-authorized broker or an Exchange-certified consolidated service center representative; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Using any of the methods of communication listed under <cite path="14.35.07.03|B.">COMAR 14.35.07.03B</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The effective date of the cancellation under <cite path="14|35|14|.08|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For a retroactive cancellation under §C(1) or (2) of this regulation:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The day before the original coverage effective date; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A later date, as determined appropriate by the Exchange, based on the circumstances of the cancellation; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For a retroactive cancellation under <cite path="14|35|14|.08|C.|(3)">§C(3) of this regulation</cite>, the day before the original coverage effective date.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Reinstatement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An individual’s enrollment shall be reinstated:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If applicable, under QHP provisions required by <cite path="31.10.25.04">COMAR 31.10.25.04</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the Exchange determines an error was made by the Exchange that led to an improper termination or cancellation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the carrier determines an error was made by the carrier that led to an improper termination or cancellation; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the Exchange is ordered to reinstate the enrollee by the Maryland Insurance Administration, Office of Administrative Hearings, or a State or federal court.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the carrier erroneously terminates or cancels an enrollee’s coverage, including if the coverage was terminated or canceled for non-payment of premiums, a carrier shall process a reinstatement transaction from the Exchange.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Sanctions.</heading>
    <text>A carrier that fails to follow the requirements of this chapter may:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Be denied certification as an authorized carrier;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Be denied certification for a QHP offered for sale by the carrier on the Individual Exchange;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Have the carrier’s certification suspended or revoked;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Have the certification for a QHP offered for sale by the carrier on the Exchange suspended or revoked; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Be subject to other penalties under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|31-115">Insurance Article, §31-115(k), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and <cite path="14.35.16.11">COMAR 14.35.16.11</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Insurance Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|31-106">31-106</cite>(c)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|1">1</cite>)(iv) and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|31-108">31-108</cite>(b)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|1">1</cite>) and (6), Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-06-08">Effective date: June 8, 2015 (42:11 Md. R. 726)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-03-11" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|14|35|14|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|14|35|14|.07">.07</cite> repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|14|35|14|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|14|35|14|.10">.10</cite> adopted effective March 11, 2019 (46:5 Md. R. 308)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-02-17"><cite path="|14|35|14|.04|F.">Regulation .04F</cite> adopted effective February 17, 2025 (52:3 Md. R. 160)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-02-19"><cite path="|14|35|14|.06|F.">Regulation .06F</cite> adopted effective February 19, 2024 (51:3 Md. R.154)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-02-19"><cite path="|14|35|14|.07|C.">Regulation .07C</cite> adopted effective February 19, 2024 (51:3 Md. R.154)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
