<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Voter Registration Applications</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="33|05|02|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>State Board to Prescribe or Approve.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Board-Prescribed Forms. The following may be used for voter registration only in the form prescribed by the State Board:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Statewide voter registration application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Voter notification card;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Potential felony notice; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Confirmation notice.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Board-Approved Forms.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="33|05|02|.01|B.|(3)">§B(3) of this regulation</cite>, all forms must be approved by the State Board before they may be used for voter registration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>These forms include a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Motor vehicle voter registration application to be used by the MVA; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Declination form to be used by voter registration agencies.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>This section does not apply to federal voter registration applications.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="33|05|02|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Statewide VRA — Contents.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Required Contents. Every paper Statewide VRA shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Contain adequate spaces for entering the information required by <cite path="33.05.04.03|A.">COMAR 33.05.04.03A</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>State the penalties for the submission of a false application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Require the signature of the applicant, subject to the penalties of perjury, by which the applicant swears or affirms that the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Information contained in the registration application is true to the best of the applicant's knowledge, information, and belief; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Applicant meets all the qualifications to become a registered voter;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Include the following questions, with boxes for the applicant to check yes or no, and the following statement:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Are you a U.S. citizen?;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Are you at least 16 years old?; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If you checked "no" in response to either question, do not complete this form;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Contain a space for the applicant to designate party affiliation, together with information on the effect that a designation will have on the ability to vote in primary elections;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Contain a space for the applicant's personal identification number, which is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If the applicant has a current and valid Maryland driver's license or MVA identification card, the MVA identification number; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the applicant does not have a current and valid Maryland driver's license or MVA identification card, at least the last four digits of the applicant's Social Security number;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Contain a box for the applicant to check if the applicant does not have a personal identification number as specified in <cite path="33|05|02|.02|A.|(7)">§A(7) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Required Notification. The following information shall be made available to each applicant who is completing a paper Statewide VRA:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The qualifications to become a registered voter;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A statement that if an individual declines to register, this fact will remain confidential and be used only for voter registration purposes;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A statement that if an individual registers to vote, the office at which the application is submitted will remain confidential and will be used only for voter registration purposes;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A statement that providing the last 4 digits of the applicant’s Social Security number is required if the applicant does not have a driver’s license, a citation to the statutory authority permitting the State to ask for the last four digits of the Social Security number, and a statement that the last 4 digits of the Social Security number will be used only for registration and other administrative purposes and will otherwise be kept confidential;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A statement that, except for an applicant's full Social Security number or MVA identification number, voter registration records are generally available for public inspection and may be shared with jury commissioners, clerks, or other government agencies as provided by law, and that use of voter registration lists for commercial solicitation purposes is prohibited; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A statement that submitting the Statewide VRA to an individual other than an official, employee, or agent of a local board does not assure that the form will be filed or filed timely.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Prohibited Matters. A Statewide VRA may not require:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notarization or other formal authentication; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Any additional information, other than the information necessary to enable election officials to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Determine the eligibility of the applicant; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Administer voter registration and other parts of the election process.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="33|05|02|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Online Submission of the Statewide VRA — Contents.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Authentication.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The online voter registration system shall authenticate each applicant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="33|05|02|.03|A.|(3)">§A(3) of this regulation</cite>, each applicant shall enter:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The applicant’s Maryland driver’s license or MVA identification card number;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The date the applicant’s driver’s license or identification card was issued; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The last four digits of the applicant’s Social Security number.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If an applicant is an absent uniformed services voter or an overseas voter who does not have a Maryland driver’s license or MVA identification card number, the applicant shall enter the last four digits of the applicant’s Social Security number.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The online voter registration system shall immediately verify the information required in <cite path="33|05|02|.03|A.|(2)">§A(2) of this regulation</cite> with information on file with MVA.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If the MVA verifies the information, the applicant may submit the Statewide VRA via the online voter registration system.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the MVA cannot verify the information, the applicant shall submit the paper Statewide VRA.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Required Contents. The State Board’s online voter registration system shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Include fields for the applicant to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Enter the information required by <cite path="33.05.04.03|A.">COMAR 33.05.04.03A</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Designate a party affiliation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If the applicant has a current and valid Maryland driver's license or MVA identification card, provide the MVA identification number and the date MVA issued the current license or identification card; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Provide the last four digits of the applicant's Social Security number.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>State the effect that a party affiliation designation will have on the ability to vote in primary elections;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>State the penalties for the submission of a false application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Require the applicant to affirmatively consent to use, as the applicant’s signature for the Statewide VRA:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The electronic copy of the applicant’s signature that is on file with MVA; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the applicant is an absent uniformed services voter or an overseas voter who does not have a Maryland driver’s license or MVA identification card number, the applicant’s last four digits of the applicant’s Social Security number.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Require the applicant to swear or affirm, subject to the penalties of perjury, that the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Information entered by the applicant is true to the best of the applicant's knowledge, information, and belief; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Applicant meets all the qualifications to become a registered voter.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Required Notification. The online voter registration system shall include a link to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The qualifications to become a registered voter; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A statement that, except for an applicant's MVA identification number, the date the MVA identification number was issued, and Social Security number, voter registration records are generally available for public inspection and may be shared with jury commissioners, clerks, or other government agencies as provided by law, and that use of voter registration lists for commercial solicitation purposes is prohibited.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Prohibited Matters. The online submission of the Statewide VRA may not require:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notarization or other formal authentication; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Any additional information, other than the information necessary to enable election officials to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Determine the eligibility of the applicant; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Administer voter registration and other parts of the election process.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Paper Version of the Statewide VRA — Production and Cost.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In General. The State Board shall design and produce the paper Statewide VRA.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Costs. The State Board shall bear the expense of producing all Statewide VRA forms.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Translation. The State Board shall coordinate and bear the cost of translating the Statewide VRA into any non-English language, as required of the State Board or a local board under the Voting Rights Act.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>MVRA.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Contents. The MVRA shall contain:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Substantially the same information as the Statewide VRA; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A box stating "I do not wish to register to vote at this time."</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Production and Cost. The MVA shall bear the expense of producing the MVRA.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The State Board shall provide language for any application related to voter registration before MVA may use or distribute the application.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Disposition of VRAs and Related Information.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In General. All VRAs and all voter registration related documents, including duplicate applications, received by a local board shall be scanned into the Statewide voter registration system.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Personal Identification Information. If a copy of any personal identification information is submitted under <cite path="|33.07.06">COMAR 33.07.06</cite> or <cite path="33.11.02.07">COMAR 33.11.02.07</cite>, the copy shall be scanned into the Statewide voter registration system.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Document Retention. All documents scanned into the Statewide voter registration system shall be retained in accordance with the State Board's Record Retention and Disposal Schedule.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Ensuring Accuracy. To help ensure the accuracy and currency of the Statewide voter registration system, a local board shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Perform quality assurance audits and reviews as directed by the State Administrator;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Maintain conviction and sentencing information received with respect to disqualifying crimes committed by registered voters or voter registration applicants; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Maintain information received directly or indirectly from official death records.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Election Law Article, 2-102(b)(4), 2-202(b), 3-101, 3-102, 3-202, and 3-204.1, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-04-17">Regulations <cite path="|33|05|02|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|33|05|02|.05">.05</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective February 1, 2000 (27:6 Md. R. 635); adopted permanently effective April 17, 2000 (27:7 Md. R. 708)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-10-14">Regulations <cite path="|33|05|02|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|33|05|02|.05">.05</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 3, 2002 (29:18 Md. R. 1440); amended permanently effective October 14, 2002 (29:20 Md. R. 1595)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-11-24" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective November 24, 2003 (30:23 Md. R. 1654)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-05-31"><cite path="|33|05|02|.01|A.">Regulation .01A</cite> amended effective May 31, 2010 (37:11 Md. R. 767)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-05-31"><cite path="|33|05|02|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended effective May 31, 2010 (37:11 Md. R. 767)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-08-14"><cite path="|33|05|02|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite>, B amended as an emergency provision effective June 2, 2006 (33:13 Md. R. 1062); amended permanently effective August 14, 2006 (33:16 Md. R. 1366)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-05-31"><cite path="|33|05|02|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective May 31, 2010 (37:11 Md. R. 767)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-09-16" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective September 16, 2013 (40:18 Md. R. 1480)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-01-06"><cite path="|33|05|02|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended January 6, 2025 (51:26 Md. R. 1187)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-12-23"><cite path="|33|05|02|.03|C.">Regulation .03C</cite> amended effective December 23, 2013 (40:25 Md. R. 2073)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
