<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>08</num>
  <heading>Professional and Volunteer Firefighter Innovative Cancer Screening Technologies Program</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose and Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter sets forth the:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Responsibilities of the Maryland Department of Health for the Professional and Volunteer Firefighter Innovative Cancer Screening Technologies Program established by Health-General Article, §§13-4001—13-4007, Annotated Code of Maryland;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Responsibilities of a grantee that receives funds under the Professional and Volunteer Firefighter Innovative Cancer Screening Technologies Program;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Application process for a grant under the Professional and Volunteer Firefighter Innovative Cancer Screening Technologies Program; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Reporting requirements for the Professional and Volunteer Firefighter Innovative Cancer Screening Technologies Program.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Applicant” means an entity that applies to receive a grant under the Professional and Volunteer Firefighter Innovative Cancer Screening Technologies Program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Cancer Screening Test.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Cancer screening test” means a test that is designed to find cancer in an individual who does not present cancer signs or symptoms.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Cancer screening test” includes, but is not limited to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A laboratory test;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>An imaging procedure;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A medical procedure; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>A genetic test.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Cost effectiveness” means a comparison between cost and expected health outcomes of a cancer test or intervention.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Department” means the Maryland Department of Health.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Grant” means funds distributed to a grantee under the Professional and Volunteer Firefighter Innovative Cancer Screening Technologies Program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Grantee” means a local fire department, volunteer fire department, or volunteer fire company approved to receive funds under the Professional and Volunteer Firefighter Innovative Cancer Screening Technologies Program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Health care provider” means a doctor of medicine or osteopathy, dentist, nurse practitioner, or physician assistant who is authorized to practice by the state in which the individual practices.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Local fire department” means a fire department operating in a Maryland county or Baltimore City.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“Program” means the Professional and Volunteer Firefighter Innovative Cancer Screening Technologies Program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>“Qualifications” means the education, experience, skills, and licensing of an individual associated with a Program grant application.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>“Volunteer fire company” means a volunteer fire company operating in a Maryland county or Baltimore City.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>“Volunteer fire department” means a volunteer fire department operating in a Maryland county or Baltimore City.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Responsibilities of the Department.</heading>
    <text>The Department shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Administer the Program;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Provide one or more grants to local fire departments, volunteer fire companies, or volunteer fire departments to procure innovative cancer screening tests according to Health-General Article, §13-4003(a), Annotated Code of Maryland;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Develop and distribute an application for Program grants each fiscal year if funding is available;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Maintain a record of information submitted by a grantee to the Department; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Monitor the activities of a grantee to ensure compliance with the requirements of the Program.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Entities Eligible for Grants.</heading>
    <text>The following entities are eligible to apply for and receive a grant from the Department under the Program:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A local fire department;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A volunteer fire company;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A volunteer fire department; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If authorized by a local fire department, volunteer fire company, or volunteer fire department, a county.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Use of Grant Funds.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A grantee may use awarded funds to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Procure and administer innovative cancer screening tests that are not otherwise conducted during routine physical examinations or covered by insurance to professional firefighters employed by a local fire department and volunteer firefighters who serve in a volunteer fire company or department; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Pay for activities directly associated with the grant that are approved by the Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A grantee may not use awarded funds to pay for an activity that is not included in the approved grant application.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Application for Professional and Volunteer Firefighter Innovative Cancer Screening Technologies Program Grants.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall submit a completed application to the Department by the due date listed in the request for applications;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shall include in the application all required information listed in the request for applications, including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The names and qualifications of the health care providers that will advise the applicant on the selection and administration of cancer screening tests;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The number of firefighters to be screened;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The selection criteria the applicant used to identify firefighters at the highest cancer risk based on the latest scientific and medical research; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A description of each test to be procured by the applicant, including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The claimed accuracy and reliability of the test;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The scientific and clinical evidence supporting the claimed accuracy and reliability of the test;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Whether the test employs innovative or novel technologies, such as DNA sequencing, genomics, proteomics, metabolomics, machine learning, artificial intelligence, big data analytics, or other state-of-the-art technology;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Whether the test has the ability to simultaneously screen for two or more cancer types for which firefighters have a higher incidence or death rate;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>The cost of the test; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Whether the test is developed, manufactured, or commercialized by a business entity located in the State; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>May voluntarily withdraw an application at any time.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The county in which a volunteer fire company or department is located shall assist a volunteer fire company or a volunteer fire department in submitting an application.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Application Review, Selection of Grantees, and Grant Period.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Department shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Determine the amount of money available for grants under the Program in each fiscal year;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Develop a weighting formula to rate each application received by the Program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Make available the weighting formula on the Program website and include the weighting formula in the request for applications;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Request additional information or changes to the application if necessary; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Reject an application that does not meet the application requirements.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Department shall review and prioritize applications based on the quality of the application received and the degree to which the tests listed on the application meet the following criteria:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The scientific and clinical evidence supporting the claimed accuracy and reliability of test;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Whether the test employs innovative or novel technologies;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The ability of the test to simultaneously screen for two or more cancer types;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The cost effectiveness of the test; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Whether the test is developed, manufactured, or commercialized by a business entity located in the State.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Department may review an application in consultation with one or more experts in cancer screening.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the Department receives applications for grant funds totaling more than the amount of funds appropriated for the Program, the Department shall award the funds on a pro rata basis.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Funds shall be awarded under the Program for a maximum of 1 year..</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|14|08|.08">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Payments, Terms and Conditions of Grant Awards, and Terminations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Payments.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Department may approve an advance payment based on financial need.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a financial or progress report required by §B or C of this regulation is overdue, the Department may withhold payment of funds to a grantee until the financial or progress report is submitted.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Financial Reports and Records.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A grantee shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Establish a separate account to track expenditures under the grant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Maintain accurate records, including documentation of each transaction associated with the grant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Submit invoices for payment of grant funds to the Department within the deadline specified by the Department;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Submit a final report listing grant expenditures signed by the financial officer or designee of the grantee within the deadline specified by the Department;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Submit a final invoice for any unbilled expenditures within the deadline specified by the Department; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Submit a refund of any unexpended funds within the deadline specified by the Department.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Department may audit the accounts referenced in <cite path="10|14|08|.08|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite> at any time.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A grantee shall retain all records pertaining to a grant for 3 years from the date the final report is submitted under <cite path="10|14|08|.08|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>In the case of an audit or litigation, the Department may extend the time period under §B(1) or (3) of this regulation until the completion of the audit or litigation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Progress Reports. A grantee shall submit to the Program:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Interim reports describing the progress of the grant; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A comprehensive final report that provides a summary of all activities conducted under the grant no later than the deadline specified by the Department, including the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Number of individuals screened;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Tests used;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Cost of the tests; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Cancers detected by the tests.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Publications.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A grantee who publishes results from activities supported by a grant approved under this chapter shall include in the publication the following acknowledgement: “Supported in part with funds from the Professional and Volunteer Firefighter Innovative Cancer Screening Technologies Program of the Maryland Department of Health.”</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A grantee shall provide the Department with one electronic copy of any published article associated with an activity conducted under a grant.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Ownership of Cancer Screening Tests. A grantee:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall ensure that a cancer screening test purchased under a Program grant is used for the sole purpose of the grant;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shall keep an inventory of cancer screening tests purchased; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>May not transfer a cancer screening test to another entity without written permission from the Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Termination.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Department may terminate a grant:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If a grantee fails to comply with:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The requirements of this chapter; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>State, federal, and municipal laws applicable to the grant;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If a grantee fails to carry out the purposes for which the grant was awarded;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>In compliance with a court order; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>At the request of the grantee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Department may not be held responsible for any expenses incurred by a grantee after cancellation of a grant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The grantee shall return all unexpended funds to the Department within 30 days of termination of a grant.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Liability.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A grantee shall be solely responsible for its actions related to the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Program application process; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Activities conducted under a grant.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Department may not be held liable for any claims, losses, liabilities, expenses, or damages arising from activities related to the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Program application process; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Activities conducted under a grant.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health-General Article, §§13-4001—13-4007, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-11-13">Effective date: November 13, 2023 (50:22 Md. R. 975)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
