<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Medical Laboratories — General</heading>
  <text>.01	17-202, 17-207, 17-208, 17-217, 17-504, 17-507</text>
  <text>.02	17-202, 17-504</text>
  <text>.03	17-202, 17-504</text>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|10|02|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Responsibilities of the Department.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The OHCQ. The OHCQ shall conduct surveys, as set forth in this subtitle, of laboratories that obtain or retain a license.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Surveys. The OHCQ shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Conduct or oversee an announced or unannounced survey of a laboratory at any time during its hours of operation to assess compliance with applicable sections of Health-General Article, Title 17, Subtitles 2 and 5, Annotated Code of Maryland, and this chapter; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Examine, as part of a survey, a laboratory's facilities, equipment, quality assurance records and procedures, operating procedures, personnel and personnel records, proficiency testing, patient reports, and other records and files pertinent and subject to this subtitle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Issuance of Licensing Documents. The OHCQ shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>License a person to operate a laboratory by issuing a letter of exception or permit when the laboratory is in compliance with the applicable standards set forth in this subtitle;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Issue a license that includes the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Name of the laboratory;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Name of the licensee or laboratory director;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Name of the laboratory owner; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Expiration date of the license; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Issue a license that designates:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The classes of services, that is, disciplines, provided;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The tests or examinations offered; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Both §C(3)(a) and (b) of this regulation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Administration and Information Management. The OHCQ shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Maintain a list of licensed laboratories;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Document information regarding denial, suspension, or revocation of a license and submit this documentation to the Secretary;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Monitor the proficiency testing performance of a laboratory required to participate in proficiency testing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Conduct a cytology proficiency testing program for each cytotechnologist and pathologist who performs gynecological examinations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Set and collect fees as set forth in <cite path="|10.10.04">COMAR 10.10.04</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Impose alternative sanctions and initiate actions leading to imposition of principal sanctions against a laboratory under the appropriate provisions of this subtitle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Recommending Excepted Test Status.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Secretary shall maintain a Laboratory Advisory Committee to advise the Secretary on matters relating to medical laboratories as set forth in Health-General Article, Title 17, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Laboratory Advisory Committee's responsibilities shall include making a recommendation to the Secretary in favor of or against granting a test excepted status.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Laboratory Advisory Committee shall consider a test for excepted test status and make a recommendation to the Secretary if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Laboratory Advisory Committee is requested in writing by:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The Secretary;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A Maryland chapter of a specialty medical society; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The Medical and Chirurgical Faculty of Maryland;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The test on which the request is based is waived under CLIA, by the CDC, or by the federal Food and Drug Administration;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The test employs a directly collected specimen not subjected to post-collection manipulation or processing; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The test is a manual test or is a test system employing a single use test device for nonforensic testing that tests for one or more analytes in a single specimen.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Laboratory Advisory Committee shall make a recommendation to the Secretary concerning excepted test status based on:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Immediate patient need for the test in order to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Provide rapid patient follow-up;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Order additional tests; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Make an immediate diagnostic or therapeutic decision;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Whether the test is core to a physician's practice, based on:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Physician specialty;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Usefulness of the test in the specialty; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Who actually performs the test;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Access, applicability, and ease of performance by personnel in a POL and POC setting;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Whether all analytes testable on a multi-test, single-use test device are recommended for excepted status;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Consideration of the known benefits and risks of the test or test system, especially those involving an infectious disease; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The potential harm to a patient if the test:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Is performed incorrectly; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Produces a false positive or false negative test result.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>In recommending a test for excepted status, the Laboratory Advisory Committee may specify certain conditions to be met based on factors set forth in <cite path="10|10|02|.01|E.|(4)">§E(4) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Authorizing Excepted Test Status.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Secretary may authorize a test for excepted status if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The test is recommended for excepted test status by the Laboratory Advisory Committee; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Secretary:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Determines that the test meets the criteria of §E(3)(b)—(d) of this regulation; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Bases the authorization for excepted status on the factors set forth in <cite path="10|10|02|.01|E.|(4)">§E(4) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In authorizing a test for excepted status, the Secretary may specify certain requirements to be met based on factors set forth in <cite path="10|10|02|.01|E.|(4)">§E(4) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|10|02|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Accredited Laboratory and Accrediting Organization.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Accredited Laboratory — Determination. The Secretary shall accept as meeting the survey requirements of this chapter a laboratory accredited by an organization approved by the Secretary, as set forth in <cite path="10|10|02|.02|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, if the OHCQ determines that the standards of the laboratory's accrediting organization are equivalent to those under this subtitle.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Accredited Laboratory — Requirements. In addition to meeting the requirements for its certificate of accreditation, as set forth by its accrediting organization, an accredited laboratory shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Obtain and maintain a valid license issued by the Secretary; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Be subject to survey by the OHCQ for the purpose of investigating complaints or validating findings of the laboratory's accrediting organization.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Accrediting Organization.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A private, nonprofit laboratory accrediting organization may inspect and accredit laboratories in the State for the purpose of Maryland State licensure only after applying for and receiving approval of the OHCQ.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The OHCQ shall base approval of a laboratory accrediting organization on a review of that organization, when the review includes but is not limited to an evaluation of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Documentation of current accrediting status issued by CMS and of compliance with CMS reporting requirements;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Accreditation policies and standards;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Copies of survey forms and guidelines;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Surveying and deficiency writing policies;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Surveyor qualifications;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Complaint investigation policies;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Proficiency test monitoring policies;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Procedures the accrediting organization will follow when notifying the OHCQ that the organization:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Is denying, withdrawing, suspending, or revoking a laboratory's accreditation;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Finds serious patient jeopardy or identifies a hazard to public safety;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Accredits a new laboratory;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Imposes an adverse or corrective action on a laboratory; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Is initiating a complaint investigation; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>The accrediting organization's compliance with the requirements of <cite path="10|10|02|.02|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>In addition to requirements set forth elsewhere in this regulation, an accrediting organization shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Provide to the OHCQ:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Annually, an updated list containing the names, addresses, and accreditation expiration dates of all accredited laboratories in the State;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Within 30 days after conducting a survey, a certified written or electronic copy of each survey report covering each laboratory applying for or maintaining accreditation in the State;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Written notice of any proposed change to requirements for laboratory accreditation, at least 30 days before the effective date of the change;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Within 30 days after a laboratory's certificate of accreditation expires, written or electronic notice when the laboratory does not renew its certificate; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Within 24 hours after taking an action, telephonic or electronic notice whenever an accredited laboratory's certificate of accreditation is limited, suspended, revoked, or surrendered;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Evaluate compliance, when applicable, with State regulations pertaining to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Cholesterol testing;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Gynecological cytology;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Dermatopathology;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Forensic toxicology;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Laboratory reporting of test results covering contagious disease, blood lead, cancer, and other tests as required by law or regulation;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Proficiency testing;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Special medical waste disposal; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Testing performed at a temporary or mobile laboratory;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Evaluate compliance with State regulations by:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Employing a checklist provided by the Department;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Incorporating an evaluation of compliance with State regulatory requirements into its own survey process; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Demonstrating that its existing survey process adequately evaluates compliance with State regulations; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>On request, provide to OHCQ a copy of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A complaint investigation;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Surveyor qualifications;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A change in a laboratory's disciplines, subdisciplines, or specialties; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Other information the Secretary may require relating to approval of a laboratory accrediting organization.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|10|02|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Surveys.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A licensee shall allow an on-site survey by the OHCQ or, when applicable, by the laboratory's approved accrediting organization, at any time during the laboratory's normal hours of operation, to evaluate the laboratory's compliance with the applicable requirements, conditions, and standards of this subtitle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A survey may include but is not limited to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Observation and examination of laboratory facilities;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Equipment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Quality assurance and quality control program records;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Operating procedures;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Personnel;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Personnel records;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Proficiency testing;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Patient reports; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Other records and files pertinent to this subtitle.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Laboratory employees shall make data and records accessible within a reasonable time during the on-site survey.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Excepted Laboratory. A licensee operating a laboratory under a letter of exception, other than a mobile or temporary laboratory, is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Not subject to routine, on-site surveys;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Subject to surveys resulting from complaints or periodic validations, or both, conducted by the Secretary or CMS, or both, to determine regulatory compliance; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Required to make available, pursuant to a survey, records the Secretary may reasonably require to determine regulatory compliance.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Permitted Laboratory. A licensee operating a laboratory under a permit shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be subject to routine surveys conducted by OHCQ;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Undergo a routine annual survey for 2 consecutive years after the laboratory:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Begins operating;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Undergoes a change in ownership;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Fails to complete or submit to the Department an acceptable quality assurance self-assessment on forms provided by the OHCQ; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Has imposed on it a principal or alternative sanction; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Undergo a routine biennial survey when the laboratory:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Does not fall under one of the categories set forth in <cite path="10|10|02|.03|C.|(2)">§C(2) of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Completes and submits to the OHCQ an acceptable quality assurance self-assessment on forms provided by the OHCQ on the years when the OHCQ does not conduct an on-site survey, except as provided in <cite path="10|10|02|.03|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Accredited Laboratory. An accredited laboratory:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Undergoing routine on-site surveys conducted by an accrediting organization approved by the Secretary, except as provided in §D(2) and (3) of this regulation, is not subject to routine surveys conducted by the OHCQ;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is subject to surveys conducted by the OHCQ to investigate a complaint or to determine regulatory compliance; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Holding a permit in the discipline of forensic toxicology, subdiscipline of job-related testing, is subject to routine surveys of the laboratory's alcohol and controlled dangerous substances testing areas conducted by the OHCQ.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Temporary or Mobile Laboratory. The OHCQ may survey each testing event site when a temporary or mobile laboratory licensee offers to perform or performs testing services.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Excepted Laboratory — Limited Testing for Rare Diseases. A licensee operating a laboratory under a letter of exception — limited testing for rare diseases is subject to the survey requirements stated in <cite path="10|10|02|.03|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health-General Article, Annotated Code of Maryland<br/>Regulations	Sections</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-12-13">Effective date: December 13, 1999 (26:25 Md. R. 1897)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-06-01"><cite path="|10|10|02|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective June 1, 2009 (36:11 Md. R. 787)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-01-21"><cite path="|10|10|02|.01|E.">Regulation .01E</cite> adopted effective January 21, 2002 (29:1 Md. R. 23)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-04-16"><cite path="|10|10|02|.01|E.">Regulation .01E</cite> amended effective April 16, 2012 (39:7 Md. R. 492)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-08-29"><cite path="|10|10|02|.01|F.">Regulation .01F</cite> adopted effective August 29, 2005 (32:17 Md. R. 1438)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-04-16"><cite path="|10|10|02|.01|F.">Regulation .01F</cite> amended effective April 16, 2012 (39:7 Md. R. 492)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-06-01"><cite path="|10|10|02|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective June 1, 2009 (36:11 Md. R. 787)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-07-24"><cite path="|10|10|02|.02|C.">Regulation .02C</cite> amended effective July 24, 2000 (27:14 Md. R. 1340)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-06-01"><cite path="|10|10|02|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective June 1, 2009 (36:11 Md. R. 787)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
