<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Medical Laboratories — Licenses</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|10|03|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>General.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Requirement.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>General. A person shall possess a license before:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Offering to perform or performing a medical laboratory test or examination in this State;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Offering to perform or performing a medical laboratory test or examination on a specimen acquired from a health care provider in this State at a laboratory located outside this State; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Representing or servicing in this State a laboratory regardless of the laboratory's location.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Prohibited Tests. The Secretary may impose principal and alternative sanctions as set forth in <cite path="10.10.08.01|A.">COMAR 10.10.08.01A</cite> if a person offers to perform or performs a test or part of a test, including the use of a reagent, supply, procedure, technique, kit, or equipment, that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Does not produce accurate or reliable results as evidenced by documented, independent scientific testing and evaluation; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Lacks proof of efficacy substantiated by an independently conducted and documented scientifically based clinical trial.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Cholesterol Testing Plan for Health Departments.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A local or county health department intending to perform cholesterol testing outside a permanently located laboratory may submit to the Secretary a cholesterol testing plan instead of applying for a cholesterol testing permit.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the submitted plan meets applicable standards under this chapter, the Secretary may waive the permit requirement for a cholesterol testing permit.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If the plan does not meet the applicable standards of this chapter, the local or county health department shall apply for a permit as set forth in this chapter.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Limitation. A person may not operate a laboratory in a discipline other than what is listed on the license.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Eligibility. A person meeting the requirements and standards of this chapter may apply for one or more of the following licenses:</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>License:</td>
              <td>Laboratory that may apply for the license:</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Letter of exception</td>
              <td>POL<br/>POCL</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Permit (single-site)</td>
              <td>POL<br/>POCL<br/>State, county, or municipal hospital<br/>commercial</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Permit (multi-site)</td>
              <td>State, county, or municipal hospital<br/>private nonprofit<br/>mobile</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Issuance.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provisional Permit.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Secretary may issue a provisional permit before or after conducting an initial survey and pending determination of compliance with the standards in this chapter.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A provisional permit is valid for not more than 180 days and may not be renewed.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Letter of Exception and Permit. The Secretary may issue a letter of exception or permit that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is valid for not more than 2 years from the date of issue; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Shall be renewed before its date of expiration if a person intends to operate the laboratory in the succeeding permit period.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Single-Site and Multi-Site Licenses.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Except as set forth in <cite path="10|10|03|.01|D.|(3)|(b)">§D(3)(b) of this regulation</cite>, a person shall obtain a separate, single-site license for each location at which a laboratory performs a test.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Secretary may issue a multi-site license to a person operating:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A mobile laboratory using the address of its home base or main administrative office in the State;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A nonprofit laboratory or public health laboratory performing limited public health testing; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Hospital laboratories located at the same street address or within contiguous buildings and under common direction.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>In order to maintain a State license issued by the Department pursuant to this subtitle, a licensee shall be in compliance with all applicable federal, State, and local laboratory requirements.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|10|03|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Letters of Exception.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Eligibility.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An individual directing a POL or POCL who offers to perform or performs tests limited to one or more excepted tests may obtain a letter of exception instead of a permit to offer to perform or perform those tests.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An individual eligible for a letter of exception shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be qualified as a laboratory director as set forth in 42 CFR §493.1405, including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Being a doctor of medicine or doctor of osteopathy licensed in the State and having laboratory training or experience appropriate for the testing performed; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Holding an earned doctoral, master's, or bachelor's degree in a chemical, physical, biological, or clinical laboratory science or medical technology from an accredited institution;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Provide evidence of training in the performance and interpretation of excepted tests and be licensed in the State as a:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Nurse midwife;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Nurse practitioner;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Physician assistant;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Chiropractor;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Podiatrist;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Dentist; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Pharmacist; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Be clinical staff who:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Meets the qualifications set forth in <cite path="10.47.01.06|D.">COMAR 10.47.01.06D</cite>;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Is employed by a substance abuse treatment program that is certified or accredited in accordance with <cite path="10.47.04.03">COMAR 10.47.04.03</cite>; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Is authorized to order tests to detect the presence of controlled dangerous substances on patients enrolled in the substance abuse treatment program.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person operating a temporary medical laboratory to perform health awareness tests, regardless of testing site location, is not eligible for a letter of exception.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Excepted Tests. A POL or POCL operating under a letter of exception may perform one or more of the following excepted tests or types of tests:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Whole blood glucose by glucose monitoring devices cleared by the FDA for home use or a CLIA waived analyzer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Dermatophyte screen;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Dipstick glucose;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Dipstick urinalysis using reagent test pads affixed to plastic strips that detect one or a combination of any of the following urine characteristics or constituents:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Glucose;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Bilirubin;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Ketones detected in the form of acetoacetic acid;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Specific gravity;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Red blood cells or hemoglobin;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>pH;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Protein;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Urobilinogen;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Nitrites; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Leukocytes;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Gram stain;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Group A streptococcal screen;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Hematocrit;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Hemoglobin;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Infectious mononucleosis slide or card test;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Microscopic urinalysis;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Occult blood;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Pinworms;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Potassium hydroxide skin preparations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>Rheumatoid factor slide agglutination test;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>Sickle-cell screen;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>H. pylori test with a single-use test device for nonforensic testing, using a whole-blood specimen;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>Fructosamine test with a single-use test device for nonforensic testing, using a whole-blood specimen;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>Heterophile antibodies test with a single-use test device for nonforensic testing, using a whole-blood specimen;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>Urine bacteria colony count;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>Urine pregnancy test;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>Wet mounts;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>Influenza antigen test using a direct nasal or throat swab specimen;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>Hemoglobin A1c test using a whole blood specimen;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(24)</num>
        <text>Qualitative test for bladder cancer markers in voided urine including a test to detect:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Human complement factor H-related protein; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Nuclear mitotic apparatus protein (NMP);</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(25)</num>
        <text>Brain natriuretic peptide (BNP) test using a whole blood specimen to detect:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Heart disease; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The response of treatment for heart failure;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(26)</num>
        <text>Fern test for qualitative detection of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Amniotic fluid crystallization; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Estrogenic activity;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(27)</num>
        <text>Qualitative semen analysis, limited to detecting:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The presence or absence of sperm; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Sperm motility;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(28)</num>
        <text>Nitrazine vaginal pH test using phenaphthazine reagent paper strips;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(29)</num>
        <text>Qualitative immunochromatographic test to detect the presence of adenovirus antigens directly from eye fluid;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(30)</num>
        <text>Microalbumin-creatinine urinalysis test utilizing an instrument based dip-and-read reagent test strip for determining urine albumin and creatinine levels, including the urinary albumin-to-creatinine ratio (UACR) in a random urine specimen;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(31)</num>
        <text>Screening tests for urine or saliva performed on FDA-cleared for home use or FDA approved single-use test devices for the presence of alcohol and drugs of abuse solely for the purpose of directing patient counseling;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(32)</num>
        <text>Qualitative enzyme activity test using a chromogenic substrate of bacterial sialidase for use in the detection of bacterial vaginosis directly from vaginal fluid specimens;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(33)</num>
        <text>Qualitative immunochromatographic test to detect the presence of Trichomonas vaginalis antigens directly from a vaginal swab;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(34)</num>
        <text>CLIA-waived Prothrombin Time/International Normalized Ratio (PT/INR) with the additional requirements that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The licensee shall enroll into a Proficiency Testing program offered by an entity that has been approved by the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services (CMS) to ensure validation of all measurement capabilities for the instrument used to perform the test; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>When the numerical score is less than 80 percent, the licensee shall submit the official proficiency test results to the Office of Health Care Quality for review and monitoring with evidence of documented remedial actions taken;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(35)</num>
        <text>CLIA waived blood lipid analysis for cholesterol, HDL, LDL, and triglycerides;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(36)</num>
        <text>Whole blood lead testing on a CLIA waived analyzer with the additional requirements:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The licensee shall enroll into a Proficiency Testing program offered by an entity that has been approved by the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services to ensure validation of all measurement capabilities for the instrument used to perform the test;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>When the numerical score is less than 80 percent, the licensee shall submit the official proficiency test result to the Office of Health Care Quality for review and monitoring with evidence of documented remedial actions taken;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>All staff involved in testing shall undergo training on the testing device and testing techniques with annual competencies;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Records of training and competencies for staff shall be:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Maintained by the laboratory; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Made available for review by the Department; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Reporting requirements stated in <cite path="10|10|03|.02|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> shall be followed; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(37)</num>
        <text>CLIA Waived Urine Drug Screens with the following additional requirements:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The licensee shall enroll into a proficiency testing program offered by an entity that has been approved by the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>When the numerical score is less than 80 percent, the licensee shall submit the official proficiency test result to the Office of Health Care Quality for review and monitoring with evidence of documented remedial actions taken.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Reporting Requirements for Whole Blood Lead Testing on a CLIA Waived Analyzer.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The blood tests for lead shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be reported under this regulation in the format approved by the Maryland Department of the Environment; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Include the information required by this regulation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The blood tests for lead to be reported shall include the following information:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Demographic information including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Name, including first, last, middle initial;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Date of birth, sex, and race;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Complete home address at the time the blood specimen was drawn including house or apartment number, street, city, county or town, zip code, and state;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Telephone number; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Parent or guardian name;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Residential status, for example, whether parent or guardian owns their home or rents;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Type of specimen, either venous or capillary, and date the specimen was drawn;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Clinic or practice name, address, and telephone number;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Draw site name and address, if different from clinic or practice;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Blood lead level in micrograms per deciliter; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Any additional information as may be required by the Maryland Department of the Environment.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Regulatory Requirements. An individual required to obtain a license to operate a laboratory who chooses to operate under a letter of exception shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Obtain, complete, and file an application as prescribed in <cite path="|10|10|03|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Comply with good laboratory practices that include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Following the manufacturer's instructions for instrument or test system operation and test performance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Having a procedure manual describing the processes for performing tests and reporting patient test results;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Performing and documenting quality control procedures using applicable levels of control materials each day of testing;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Performing and documenting that remedial action has been taken when problems or errors are identified;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Documenting lot numbers of all quality control reagents used; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Performing and documenting test system function for instruments with internal quality controls on each day of testing.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Permits.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Requirement. A person operating a medical laboratory that performs one or more tests other than excepted tests shall obtain and renew a laboratory permit as required in this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Tests Other than Excepted Tests.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A test other than an excepted test is one not listed in <cite path="|10|10|03|.02|B.">Regulation .02B of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person holding a permit may perform both excepted tests and tests other than excepted tests.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Regulatory Requirements. A person operating a medical laboratory under a permit shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Obtain, complete, and submit permit applications as prescribed in this chapter and <cite path="|10.10.04">COMAR 10.10.04</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Comply with the survey requirements set forth in this subtitle;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Comply with the applicable quality assurance and quality control requirements required in <cite path="|10.10.06">COMAR 10.10.06</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Comply with the applicable proficiency testing requirements required in <cite path="|10.10.05">COMAR 10.10.05</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Comply with the applicable personnel requirements required in <cite path="10.10.06.15|B.">COMAR 10.10.06.15B</cite> and <cite path="|10.10.07">10.10.07</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|10|03|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Letter of Exception and Permit — Administrative Procedures.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Application — Filing.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except for a laboratory eligible for a multi-site license as set forth in <cite path="|10|10|03|.01|D.|(3)|(b)">Regulation .01D(3)(b) of this chapter</cite>, a person shall apply for a license for each laboratory location.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person holding a license to operate a laboratory in the discipline of chemistry or health awareness testing is not required to obtain a separate cholesterol testing permit to conduct cholesterol testing at a temporary laboratory site if the licensee complies with the requirements applicable to a temporary laboratory as set forth in this subtitle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person shall complete and file an application for a license using forms provided by the OHCQ.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A person shall complete on the application a description of laboratory services, which includes but is not limited to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Types of tests performed or to be performed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Total number of tests performed or to be performed annually, excluding tests for quality control and proficiency testing; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Qualifications of personnel who direct, supervise, and perform laboratory testing.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The laboratory director shall sign the application forms attesting that the information provided is accurate and that the laboratory is or will be operated in accordance with the requirements and standards required in this chapter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A person shall submit with the application the nonrefundable partial licensing fee set forth in <cite path="10.10.04.02|C.">COMAR 10.10.04.02C</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Application — Evaluation and Billing.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The OHCQ shall review and evaluate an application in accordance with the standards and requirements of this subtitle to determine if an application is complete.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The OHCQ shall review and evaluate an application in accordance with the standards and requirements of this subtitle to determine if the laboratory is eligible for a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Letter of exception;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Letter of exception — limited testing for rare diseases; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Permit.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Application — Denial of License. If the OHCQ determines that a laboratory is not in compliance with the requirements of this chapter and therefore cannot be issued a license, the OHCQ shall provide to the laboratory:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A written statement of the grounds on which the denial is based; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The opportunity to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Amend and resubmit the application; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Request, in writing, an opportunity for a hearing as provided in the Administrative Procedure Act, State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-201">10-201</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-226">10-226</cite>, and Health-General Article, §§17-210 and 17-509, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Notification Requirements. A licensee shall notify the OHCQ within 30 days of a change in laboratory:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Ownership;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Name;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Location; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Director.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Amending a Permit. Except as prescribed in <cite path="10|10|03|.04|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>, a licensee holding an unexpired permit who wishes to amend it shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Submit a written request for amendment to the Secretary; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Obtain written approval from the OHCQ before implementing the amendment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Expiration and Renewal.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A letter of exception or permit expires on the date shown on the license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The OHCQ shall mail a renewal application to a laboratory not less than 30 days before the expiration date shown on the license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A licensee shall file an application to renew a license using forms provided by the OHCQ and following the same procedures prescribed in §§A and B of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A licensee who fails to submit a completed renewal application before the expiration date may not operate the laboratory after its letter of exception or permit has expired.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Non-Transferability. A license is not transferable between laboratories, directors, or locations.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|10|03|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Letter of Exception — Limited Testing for Rare Diseases.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Secretary may waive the permit requirements under this subtitle for a laboratory that offers to perform or performs a rare disease test if the laboratory:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Meets the requirements of Regulations .05 and .06 of this chapter; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Obtains and maintains a letter of exception — limited testing for rare diseases.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Eligibility. A person operating a medical laboratory may be eligible for a letter of exception — limited testing for rare diseases if the laboratory:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is operated as:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A not-for-profit entity; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Part of an accredited educational institution;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Performs not more than a total of 50 tests per year for a specific rare disease on specimens from Maryland patients;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Offers to perform or performs only rare disease tests as defined in <cite path="10.10.01.03|B.">COMAR 10.10.01.03B</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Possesses a valid CLIA certificate for the complexity of the testing performed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Does not possess a Maryland permit for offering to perform or performing medical laboratory testing; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Meets the requirements for a laboratory to operate under a letter of exception — limited testing for rare diseases.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Research Laboratory. A research laboratory may obtain a letter of exception — limited testing for rare diseases if the laboratory meets the eligibility requirements of <cite path="10|10|03|.05|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Letter of Exception — Limited Testing for Rare Diseases; Standards and Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Application Requirements and Testing Approval. A person required to obtain a license to operate a laboratory that chooses to operate under a letter of exception — limited testing for rare diseases shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Submit:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A completed:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Application as prescribed in <cite path="|10|10|03|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Report or questionnaire as required by the Secretary to determine regulatory compliance;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A copy of the laboratory's:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Current CLIA certificate issued by CMS; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Most recent CLIA survey report;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Documentation of the rare disease testing offered or performed, including but not limited to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The test procedure, including instructions for quality control and quality assurance;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A description of the disease or condition;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>An explanation of the clinical validity of the test;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>The performance characteristics of the test;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>The expected turnaround time for patient test results; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Additional information necessary for determining eligibility and compliance with this subtitle; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Agree to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Make records and reports available to the Department as the Secretary may require;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Notify the Department when a change to a licensee's rare disease testing procedure occurs for the purpose of the Department's determining whether the change is in compliance with this subtitle;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Perform not more than 50 rare disease tests each year on specimens from Maryland patients; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Submit to the Department statistics that detail the number and types of rare disease tests performed each year on specimens from Maryland patients.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Standards. A person that wishes to obtain and maintain a letter of exception — limited testing for rare diseases shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Comply with good laboratory practices that include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Following the manufacturer's instructions for instrument or test system operation and test performance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Having and following a written procedure manual describing the processes for performing tests and reporting patient test results;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Performing applicable instrument calibration procedures at least once every 6 months;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Performing and documenting quality control procedures using applicable levels of control materials each day of testing; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Performing and documenting that remedial action has been taken when problems or errors are identified; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Meet the requirements and standards in this subtitle applicable to a permitted laboratory including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Proficiency testing under <cite path="|10.10.05">COMAR 10.10.05</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Quality assurance under <cite path="|10.10.06">COMAR 10.10.06</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Personnel under <cite path="|10.10.07">COMAR 10.10.07</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Sanctions under <cite path="|10.10.08">COMAR 10.10.08</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>CLIA regulations incorporated by reference at <cite path="10.10.01.04|B.|(3)">COMAR 10.10.01.04B(3)</cite> — (5).</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the submitted application and explanatory documentation do not meet the requirements of this regulation or if the information submitted for the plan is insufficient to make a determination of compliance with this subtitle, a person may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Submit amendments to the application and explanatory documentation; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Apply for a permit in accordance with this subtitle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The OHCQ may conduct on-site surveys of a laboratory operating under a letter of exception — limited testing for rare diseases to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Investigate a complaint; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Determine compliance with this subtitle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If a licensee wishes to perform more than 50 rare disease tests per year, the licensee shall submit an application for and obtain a permit as required under this subtitle.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|6-303">Environment Article, §6-303</cite>; Health-General Article, §§2-104(b), 17-202, 17-205—17-210, 17-212, 17-502, 17-503, 17-505, <br/>17-508, and 17-510; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-12-13">Effective date: December 13, 1999 (26:25 Md. R. 1897)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-07-23"><cite path="|10|10|03|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective July 24, 2000 (27:14 Md. R. 1340); July 23, 2001 (28:14 Md. R. 1321)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-06-01"><cite path="|10|10|03|.01|A.">Regulation .01A</cite> amended effective June 1, 2009 (36:11 Md. R. 787)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-06-01"><cite path="|10|10|03|.01|E.">Regulation .01E</cite> adopted effective June 1, 2009 (36:11 Md. R. 787)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-04-13"><cite path="|10|10|03|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective July 24, 2000 (27:14 Md. R. 1340); June 1, 2009 (36:11 Md. R. 787); April 13, 2015 (42:7 Md. R. 568)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-04-16"><cite path="|10|10|03|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended effective July 22, 2002 (29:14 Md. R. 1074); April 16, 2012 (39:7 Md. R. 492)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-01-06"><cite path="|10|10|03|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective November 1, 2004 (31:25 Md. R. 1789); amended permanently effective January 6, 2005 (31:26 Md. R. 1863)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-03-13"><cite path="|10|10|03|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective August 29, 2005 (32:17 Md. R. 1438); February 22, 2010 (37:4 Md. R. 341); April 16, 2012 (39:7 Md. R. 492); November 12, 2012 (39:22 Md. R. 1428); April 1, 2013 (40:6 Md. R. 473); March 13, 2017 (44:5 Md. R. 292)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-11-12"><cite path="|10|10|03|.02|C.">Regulation .02C</cite> amended effective November 12, 2012 (39:22 Md. R. 1428)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-08-29"><cite path="|10|10|03|.03|C.">Regulation .03C</cite> amended effective June 1, 2009 (36:11 Md. R. 787); August 29, 2016 (43:17 Md. R. 953)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-06-01"><cite path="|10|10|03|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective June 1, 2009 (36:11 Md. R. 787)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-08-29"><cite path="|10|10|03|.04|B.">Regulation .04B</cite>, E amended effective August 29, 2016 (43:17 Md. R. 953)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-06-01"><cite path="|10|10|03|.05">Regulation .05</cite> adopted effective June 1, 2009 (36:11 Md. R. 787)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-06-01"><cite path="|10|10|03|.06">Regulation .06</cite> adopted effective June 1, 2009 (36:11 Md. R. 787)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-08-29"><cite path="|10|10|03|.06|A.">Regulation .06A</cite> amended effective August 29, 2016 (43:17 Md. R. 953)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
