<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Medical Laboratories — Proficiency Testing</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|10|05|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Participation and Evaluation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Participation. A licensee operating under a permit shall ensure that the laboratory:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Enrolls in and participates satisfactorily in a PT program that meets the criteria set forth in this chapter for each of the tests that the laboratory offers to perform or performs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Tests PT samples in the same manner and number of times that it routinely tests patient specimens; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Complies with the applicable standards contained in 42 CFR §§493.801—493.807.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Evaluation — General. When a PT program does not evaluate a participating laboratory's PT results or the evaluated PT results are inconsistent with satisfactory performance, the participating laboratory and the OHCQ shall evaluate the PT results by comparing them to the all-method-results mean, all-instrument-results mean, or the all-participant-results mean found in the PT program's summaries of PT results.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Evaluation — Departmental.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Administrative Procedures.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Submission of Results. The OHCQ shall monitor for regulatory purposes only official results sent directly from the PT program.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Multiple Programs. If a licensee enrolls in more than one PT program and duplicate testing and reporting occurs, the licensee shall notify the OHCQ which PT program is to be scored for regulatory purposes.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Sample Testing. A licensee shall operate under the following PT procedures:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>PT samples shall be tested each time a shipment is received and for only those procedures offered or allowed under a laboratory's license;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>If a test is no longer offered or performed, the licensee shall inform the OHCQ in writing;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>PT samples shall be tested only in the laboratory for which they are intended;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>PT samples shall be handled, processed, and tested in the same manner as patient specimens; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Repeat testing may not be performed on PT samples unless it is the laboratory's policy to test patients in duplicate or if abnormal test results are routinely repeated to verify accuracy.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Testing and Reporting Deadlines.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A licensee shall test PT samples and report PT results within the time limits set by the PT program.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>PT results submitted late by a licensee are deemed unsatisfactory by the PT program and the OHCQ.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>PT Program Evaluation Errors. A licensee is responsible for seeing that an evaluation error on the PT report is corrected by the PT program and that the program sends a corrected PT report to the OHCQ.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Performance Records. A laboratory's marginal or unsatisfactory PT performance may not be changed to reflect satisfactory performance when:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>PT results are not submitted;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>PT results are submitted after the due date; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Transcription errors involving PT results went unnoticed until the evaluated results were scored.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Evaluation Procedures.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Grading Criteria.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The PT program shall score test results in terms of correlation with reference or referee laboratory test results, target values, or statistical methods based on means and standard deviations.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The OHCQ shall determine a laboratory's PT performance based on a PT program's numerical score for each specialty, subspecialty, constituent, analyte, and culture type.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Scores. Numerical PT scores required for satisfactory performance in each subdiscipline, specialty or subspecialty are as follows:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>AFP for NTD, equal to or greater than 80 percent;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Antibodies for HIV, equal to or greater than 80 percent;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Bacteriology, equal to or greater than 80 percent;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Blood gases, equal to or greater than 80 percent;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Blood lead, equal to or greater than 80 percent;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Chemistry, equal to or greater than 80 percent;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Coagulation, equal to or greater than 80 percent;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Cytogenetics, as set by PT program;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ix)</num>
            <text>Drugs of abuse, forensic, equal to or greater than 90 percent;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(x)</num>
            <text>Drugs of abuse, clinical or diagnostic, equal to or greater than 80 percent;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xi)</num>
            <text>Hematology, equal to or greater than 80 percent;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xii)</num>
            <text>Immunohematology, ABO and Rh typing, antibody screen, 100 percent;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xiii)</num>
            <text>Immunohematology, antibody identification, equal to or greater than 90 percent;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xiv)</num>
            <text>Mycology, equal to or greater than 80 percent;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xv)</num>
            <text>Mycobacteriology, equal to or greater than 80 percent;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xvi)</num>
            <text>Immunology, nonsyphilis serology, equal to or greater than 80 percent;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xvii)</num>
            <text>Parasitology, equal to or greater than 80 percent;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xviii)</num>
            <text>Syphilis serology, equal to or greater than 80 percent; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xix)</num>
            <text>Urinalysis, equal to or greater than 80 percent.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Scoring Criteria. A percent score is derived by dividing the number of satisfactory PT results by the total number of PT results for each subdiscipline, specialty, subspecialty, or individual constituent or analyte within a subspecialty.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>PT Failure. PT scores lower than the percent scores listed in <cite path="10|10|05|.01|C.|(2)|(b)">§C(2)(b) of this regulation</cite> are failing scores.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Evaluated PT Results. PT results evaluated in determining PT performance include PT results not evaluated by the PT program, code 10 results, for example, 10E, 10G, 10T, and codes of tests not performed.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Initial or Single PT Failure.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Licensee Action. A licensee shall investigate a single or initial PT failure and document the corrective action taken.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Departmental Procedures. The OHCQ shall document an initial or single PT failure and may request a licensee to submit a plan of correction and supporting documentation related to the failure.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Marginal PT Performance.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Test Scores. PT performance is marginal when a laboratory exhibits failing PT scores in two of three consecutive testing events in a subdiscipline, specialty, subspecialty, or individual constituent or analyte, for example, Na, RBC, cholesterol.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Departmental Procedures. The OHCQ shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Document the marginal PT;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Send written notice of the marginal PT to the licensee; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Request the licensee to submit a written plan of correction.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Laboratory Actions. A licensee shall submit to the OHCQ a written plan of correction that describes the investigation and steps taken to improve the applicable test performance.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Unsatisfactory PT Performance. PT performance is unsatisfactory when a laboratory exhibits:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Failing PT scores in three of four consecutive testing events in a subdiscipline, specialty, or individual constituent or analyte, for example, Na, RBC, cholesterol;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Failing PT scores in two of three consecutive testing events in a subdiscipline, specialty, subspecialty, or individual constituent or analyte, for example, Na, RBC, cholesterol, and the next PT report for the test states "test not performed"; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>An average PT score for a test over the last four consecutive testing events that falls below the minimum percent score set forth in <cite path="10|10|05|.01|C.|(2)|(b)">§C(2)(b) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Discipline, Specialty, and Subspecialty.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Primary Standard. A licensee operating under a permit shall ensure that the laboratory participates successfully in PT, when applicable, for each test or analyte in each of the following disciplines, subdisciplines, and specialties:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Microbiology, including the subdisciplines of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Bacteriology;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Mycobacteriology;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Mycology;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Parasitology; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Virology;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Immunology, including the subdisciplines of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>General immunology;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>General serology; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Syphilis serology;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Chemistry, including the subdisciplines of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Blood gas analysis;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Endocrinology;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Routine chemistry; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Toxicology;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Genetics, including the subdisciplines of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Biochemical genetics;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Cytogenetics; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Molecular genetics;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Hematology, including the subdisciplines of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Coagulation testing; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Routine hematology;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Pathology, including the subdiscipline of gynecologic cytology;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Immunohematology, including the specialties of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>ABO group and D(Rho) typing;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Unexpected antibody detection, that is, antibody screen;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Antibody identification; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Compatibility testing; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Forensic toxicology limited to job-related alcohol and controlled dangerous substances.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Discipline Standards.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>General. A licensee operating under a permit shall ensure that the laboratory meets the applicable PT standards set forth in this chapter and in 42 CFR §§493.821 — 493.865.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Gynecologic Cytology. A licensee operating under a permit to perform gynecologic cytology shall ensure that the laboratory enrolls and maintains successful participation in:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A cytology PT program operated by the Secretary if the laboratory is located inside this State; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A cytology PT program approved by CMS if the laboratory is located outside this State.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Job-Related Testing.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A licensee operating under a permit to perform job-related testing for alcohol or controlled dangerous substances shall ensure that the laboratory enrolls and continues to participate satisfactorily, when applicable, in one or more of the programs listed in §B(3)(b)—(e) of this regulation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Screening Tests. A licensee operating under a permit to perform screening tests for job-related alcohol and controlled dangerous substances shall ensure that the laboratory enrolls and participates satisfactorily in:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The American Association of Bioanalysts (AAB) Urine Toxicology Screening survey;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The American Association for Clinical Chemistry/College of American Pathologists (AACC/CAP) Forensic Urine Drug Testing Screening survey; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Another program approved by the Secretary as set forth in <cite path="|10|10|05|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Confirmation Tests. A licensee operating under a permit to perform confirmation tests for job-related alcohol and controlled dangerous substances shall ensure that the laboratory enrolls and participates satisfactorily in:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The AACC/CAP Forensic Urine Drug Testing Confirmatory survey;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The federal Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration's Federal Workplace Drug Testing Program; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Another program approved by the Secretary as set forth in <cite path="|10|10|05|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Blood Alcohol Tests. A licensee operating under a permit to perform tests for alcohol in blood shall ensure that the laboratory enrolls and participates satisfactorily in:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The AACC/CAP survey for whole blood alcohol or serum alcohol, or both; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Another program approved by the Secretary as set forth in <cite path="|10|10|05|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Hair Analysis. A licensee operating under a permit to perform tests for a controlled dangerous substance in hair shall ensure that the laboratory enrolls and participates satisfactorily in:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The State of Florida's P.T. program for drug testing in hair; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Another program that possesses standards set by the Secretary or that are equivalent to the State of Florida's PT program for drug testing in hair and is approved by the Secretary as set forth in <cite path="|10|10|05|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Program Approval.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Approval Required. A private, nonprofit, or commercial organization or government agency may not provide a PT program in this State without first obtaining program approval from CMS or the OHCQ.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Approval Granted Automatically. Except in the discipline of job-related alcohol and controlled dangerous substances, or other disciplines, subdisciplines, or specialties not covered by federal PT requirements, a PT program is approved when it is based on written evidence issued by CMS showing the program meets CMS's criteria for approval of PT programs as set forth in 42 CFR §§493.901—493.959.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Approval Granted by the Secretary. The OHCQ may approve a PT program for a laboratory discipline, subdiscipline, or specialty not approved by CMS, if the program:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provides reliable, documented evidence that the program is technically and administratively able to meet the applicable requirements of this chapter; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Uniformly and routinely prepares and submits directly to the OHCQ evaluations of all PT results from all laboratories enrolled in the program and holding a Maryland permit.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Cytology — Departmental Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Secretary may not issue a license to operate a laboratory that examines gynecologic cytology specimens if the laboratory does not enroll and participate satisfactorily in a cytology PT program operated or approved by the Secretary.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The OHCQ shall conduct annual PT for each pathologist and cytotechnologist who examines gynecological cytology slides acquired in the State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The OHCQ or an agent of the Department shall hand carry test materials for first-event testing in a PT cycle to a laboratory and shall conduct and supervise all testing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The OHCQ shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Conduct announced and unannounced on-site testing for individuals during an annual PT cycle; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Schedule and conduct a retesting event for an individual who has failed the annual PT testing event not more than 45 days after receipt of the notification of the PT testing event failure by the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Individual who failed the annual PT testing event; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Laboratory director of the individual who failed the annual PT testing event.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The OHCQ may conduct unannounced PT at any time during normal laboratory working hours when the testing is conducted as part of routine PT, a complaint investigation, a follow-up certification, or a regulatory compliance survey.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The OHCQ shall conduct announced retesting within an annual PT cycle at a site selected by the Department.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The OHCQ shall schedule an individual who misses a laboratory's annual PT event to make up the missed test.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The OHCQ shall evaluate an individual's PT performance as set forth in 42 CFR §493.945.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|10|05|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Cytology — Laboratory and Individual Standards.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Primary Standard. A pathologist or cytotechnologist who examines gynecological cytology specimens from individuals in this State shall participate satisfactorily in an annual cytology PT program approved by the Secretary.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Laboratory Standards.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A licensee operating under a permit to examine gynecologic cytology specimens shall ensure that each pathologist and cytotechnologist who examines gynecologic cytology specimens participates in a cytology PT program conducted by the Department or approved by the Secretary.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An in-State laboratory shall participate in the Department's PT program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An out-of-State laboratory shall participate in either the Department's PT program or another equivalently rigorous cytology PT program approved by the Secretary.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A licensee employing an individual who has failed a second testing event in an annual PT cycle shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Prohibit the individual from examining gynecologic specimens and provide or secure remedial training and education in gynecologic cytology for the individual, which training and education includes examination by the individual of gynecologic specimens in the individual's area of failure; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Document the individual's completion of education and training using a form provided by the OHCQ.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A licensee employing an individual who has failed a first or subsequent PT event and who does not obtain mandated retesting or retraining, or both, shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Immediately remove that individual from a position of examining gynecologic cytology specimens for the purpose of reporting diagnostic test results to a health care provider; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Provide written notice to the OHCQ within 30 days after being informed of the individual's last test failure that the individual is no longer examining gynecologic cytology specimens for the purpose of reporting diagnostic test results to a health care provider.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Individual Standards.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A cytotechnologist or pathologist who examines gynecological cytology specimens shall participate in an annual PT event that involves the examination of a 10-slide or 20-slide test set as set forth in 42 CFR §493.945.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An individual passes a testing event and performs satisfactorily in PT when the individual scores at least 90 percent on a 10-slide or 20-slide test set.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An individual fails a testing event and performs unsatisfactorily in PT if the individual:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Scores less than 90 percent on a 10-slide or 20-slide test set; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Fails to take a scheduled retest without prior Department approval.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>An individual who fails the annual testing event shall take a second test with another 10-slide test set:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Within 45 days after receiving notice of a test failure; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>At a later date with prior Department approval.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>An individual who fails a second test shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Cease examining gynecologic specimens immediately upon being notified of the second failure;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Complete at least 40 hours of remedial training and education in gynecologic cytology that includes examining gynecological specimens in the area of failure;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Complete the required training and education in a laboratory that operates under a:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>State permit for in-State laboratories; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Certificate issued by CMS in the subdiscipline of gynecologic cytology for out-of-State laboratories;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Document the required remedial training and education when completed, using a form provided by the OHCQ, and submit the completed form to the OHCQ;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Schedule and take a third test with a 20-slide test set within 30 days of completing the required remedial training and education; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Begin examining gynecologic cytology specimens only after the OHCQ informs the individual that the individual obtained a passing score on the third test.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>An individual who fails a third or subsequent test shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Complete at least 35 hours of documented, formally structured, continuing education in diagnostic cytopathology that focuses on the examination of gynecologic preparations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Document the education when completed, using a form provided by the OHCQ, and submit the completed form to the OHCQ;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Schedule and take a subsequent test with a 20-slide test set within 30 days of completing the required continuing education; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Begin examining gynecologic cytology specimens only after the OHCQ informs the individual that the individual obtained a passing score on the test required under <cite path="10|10|05|.05|C.|(6)|(c)">§C(6)(c) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>An individual who fails a first or subsequent testing event in an annual PT cycle and who chooses not to complete mandatory retesting or remedial training, or both, shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Immediately cease examining gynecologic cytology specimens and notify the OHCQ of this in writing; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Reenter the PT process at the point where the individual previously chose to withdraw from the testing process, if the individual decides at a later date to satisfy PT requirements.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health-General Article, §§17-202 and 17-211, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-10-05">Effective date: October 5, 1998 (25:20 Md. R. 1529)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-12-13" discontinuity="true">Chapter, Job-Related Alcohol and Controlled Dangerous Substances Testing, repealed and new chapter, Medical Laboratories—Proficiency Testing, adopted effective December 13, 1999 (26:25 Md. R. 1897)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-06-01"><cite path="|10|10|05|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective June 1, 2009 (36:11 Md. R. 787)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-06-01"><cite path="|10|10|05|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective June 1, 2009 (36:11 Md. R. 787)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-06-01"><cite path="|10|10|05|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective June 1, 2009 (36:11 Md. R. 787)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-06-01"><cite path="|10|10|05|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective June 1, 2009 (36:11 Md. R. 787)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-11-29"><cite path="|10|10|05|.04|D.">Regulation .04D</cite> amended effective November 29, 2010 (37:24 Md. R. 1658)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-06-01"><cite path="|10|10|05|.05|B.">Regulation .05B</cite>, C amended effective June 1, 2009 (36:11 Md. R. 787)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-11-29"><cite path="|10|10|05|.05|C.">Regulation .05C</cite> amended effective November 29, 2010 (37:24 Md. R. 1658)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
