<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>06</num>
  <heading>Medical Laboratories — Quality Assurance</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>General.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Primary Standards. To obtain or maintain a permit to operate a laboratory, a person or licensee shall ensure that the laboratory:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Establishes and follows written policies and procedures for a comprehensive quality assurance program designed to monitor and evaluate the ongoing and overall quality and safety of the total, that is, preanalytic, analytic, and postanalytic phases of the testing process;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Maintains a quality assurance program that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Continually evaluates the effectiveness of the laboratory's policies and procedures;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Routinely revises policies and procedures based on the results of on-going evaluation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Identifies and corrects problems;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Assures accurate, reliable, and prompt reporting of test results;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Assures adequate and competent personnel; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Documents all quality assurance activities; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Establishes and maintains a laboratory safety program.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Standards. A licensee shall ensure that the laboratory:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Meets the applicable:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Quality assurance standards set forth in this chapter and in 42 CFR §§493.1230 — 493.1299; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Quality testing standards for facility administration set forth in this chapter and in 42 CFR §§493.1100 — 493.1101;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Establishes, maintains, and enforces a laboratory safety program that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Provides all personnel with access to a safety manual covering the following topics, when applicable:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>General personnel safety;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Fire prevention and control;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Biological hazards;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Chemical hazards;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Radiological hazards;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Special medical waste disposal; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>The reporting of incidents and accidents; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Complies with the following applicable federal Occupational Safety and Health Administration standards:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>"Occupational Exposure to Hazardous Chemicals in Laboratories", contained in 29 CFR §1910.1450; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>"Bloodborne Pathogens," contained in 29 CFR §1910.1030; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Maintains a collection station:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>As part of and under the direction of the laboratory for which it collects specimens; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>With equipment and staff appropriate for the collection, preservation, storage, and maintenance of specimens in a manner suitable for later examination.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Authorization to Request Laboratory Tests.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Primary Standard. A laboratory may not perform a laboratory test, except under a health awareness permit or cholesterol permit, without obtaining written or electronic authorization from:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A court of law;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A doctor of medicine, osteopathy, podiatric medicine, or dentistry; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Another person authorized to order laboratory tests under the Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Other Authorized Persons. Other persons authorized to order laboratory tests include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A nurse midwife certified by the Maryland State Board of Nursing under <cite path="|10.27.05">COMAR 10.27.05</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A nurse practitioner certified by the Maryland State Board of Nursing under <cite path="|10.27.07">COMAR 10.27.07</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A physician's assistant, as authorized by the physician's assistant's supervising physician;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A chiropractor requesting a test on blood or urine;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>An employer requesting a job-related test for alcohol or controlled dangerous substances;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Clinical staff who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Meets the qualifications set forth in <cite path="10.47.01.06|D.">COMAR 10.47.01.06D</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is employed by a substance abuse treatment program that is certified or accredited in accordance with <cite path="10.47.04.03">COMAR 10.47.04.03</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Is authorized to order tests to detect the presence of controlled dangerous substances on patients enrolled in the substance abuse treatment program; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>A pharmacist, for tests that qualify for a letter of exception under <cite path="10.10.03.02|B.">COMAR 10.10.03.02B</cite> and for glucose, A1c, lipids (including total cholesterol, HDL, LDL, and triglycerides), AST, and ALT.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Standards. A licensee shall ensure that the laboratory meets the applicable standards concerning test requisition contained in 42 CFR §493.1241.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|10|06|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Patient Test Management.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Primary Standard. A licensee shall ensure that the laboratory:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provides patient manipulation by qualified personnel; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Employs and maintains a quality assurance program that provides for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Proper patient preparation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Proper specimen:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Collection;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Identification;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Preservation;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Transportation; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Processing;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Record maintenance; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Accurate reporting of results.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Standard — Patient Manipulation and Specimen Collection.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may not manipulate a patient, for example, to collect specimens unless the person is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A licensed:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Physician; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Nurse;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Authorized by law to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Collect a specimen from an individual for medical laboratory testing; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Manipulate a patient; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Employed by a licensee under this title.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A licensee shall ensure that specimens for laboratory testing are collected by individuals who are trained in and have documented experience in:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Preparing patients for specimen collection; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Collecting the appropriate specimen required for the requested test.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Qualified personnel authorized by the licensee may collect:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Blood specimens, including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Venipuncture; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Finger or heel stick whole-blood specimens;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Stomach contents; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Clinical materials for smears and culture, for example, throat and nasopharyngeal swabs, and other specimens required to perform a requested test under the direction or on the written request of a physician or other person authorized by law and identified in <cite path="|10|10|06|.02">Regulation .02 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>An employer may collect a specimen for job-related testing to determine use or abuse of a controlled dangerous substance or alcohol as set forth under <cite path="|10.10.10">COMAR 10.10.10</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A person collecting specimens for medical laboratory testing or examination shall follow the licensee's policies and procedures contained in the laboratory's quality assurance system as set forth in <cite path="10|10|06|.03|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>This section does not apply to the collection of a DNA specimen with a buccal swab used for determining paternity.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Standard — Quality Assurance. A licensee shall ensure that the laboratory's quality assurance system:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provides optimum patient test results by establishing and maintaining mechanisms to preserve specimen integrity and maintain positive specimen identification throughout the entire testing process, including the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Preanalytic phase;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Analytic phase; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Postanalytic phase; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Meets the applicable standards contained in 42 CFR §§493.1230 — 493.1234, 493.1240 — 493.1249, and 493.1281—493.1299.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Reporting and Releasing Test Results.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Primary Standard. A laboratory shall report or release test results, except results of a health awareness test, only to an authorized person.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Standards.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For all test results except those from a health awareness test performed at a temporary laboratory or from a job-related alcohol or controlled dangerous substance test, a licensee shall ensure that the laboratory:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Reports medical test results only to the physician, dentist, or other authorized person who requested the test, or to another laboratory that requested the test;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Sends a copy of a test result, other than a result for a health awareness or job-related alcohol or controlled dangerous substances test, directly to the individual tested only after the laboratory:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Receives a written request from the individual; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Notifies the authorized person who requested the test that the results will be released to the individual tested;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Meets the applicable standards concerning test reports contained in 42 CFR §§493.1234 and 493.1291; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Reports a test result on a form that identifies the name and address of the laboratory that performed the test.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For test results stemming from a health awareness test, set forth in <cite path="10.10.01.03|B.">COMAR 10.10.01.03B</cite>, and performed at a temporary laboratory, the laboratory may report those results directly to the individual tested.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the results of the tests listed in <cite path="|10|10|06|.02|B.|(7)">Regulation .02B(7) of this chapter</cite> are not within the desired range, the pharmacist shall provide:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The test results to the patient’s primary care practitioner for evaluation and treatment; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The patient with a referral to a licensed independent practitioner for evaluation and treatment.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Quality Control — General.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Primary Standard. A licensee operating under a permit shall ensure that the laboratory establishes and follows written quality control procedures for monitoring and evaluating the quality of the analytic phase of the testing process for each testing method and procedure to assure the accuracy and reliability of patient test results and reports.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Standard. A licensee shall ensure that the laboratory meets the applicable quality control standards as set forth in this chapter and in 42 CFR §§493.1200—493.1299.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05-1</num>
    <heading>Quality Control — Quality Control Program.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Primary Standard. A licensee shall develop, establish, implement, maintain, and follow quality control policies, procedures, and techniques that ensure accurate and reliable test results and patient test reports.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Standard — Quality Control Program. A licensee's quality control program shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Cover all tests and related examinations and procedures performed by the laboratory; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Meet the standards and requirements set forth in this chapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Standard — Quality Control Practices. A licensee's quality control practices shall include, but are not limited to, the use of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Analyses of reference materials to ensure that test results are:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Reproducible;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Accurate; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Reliable;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Systems to ensure proper functioning of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Instruments;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Equipment; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Reagents;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Validity, calibration, and systematic procedural checks for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Reagents;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Equipment; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Test systems; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Systems for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Review and reporting of test results that ensure timely error detection and correction; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Assessment of laboratory personnel:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Performance;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Proficiency; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Competency.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Standard — Adequacy of Methods and Equipment. A licensee shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Employ methods and equipment that provide accurate and reliable test results and reports;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Have sufficient and suitable equipment and instruments to perform the type of testing services and volume of tests offered by the laboratory;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Monitor all test methods, instruments, and test systems for the following performance characteristics, when applicable:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Detection limits for each:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Method;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Instrument; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Test system;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Precision;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Accuracy;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Specificity;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Sensitivity;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Test interferences; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Other related test variables that affect test results;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Have adequate systems in place to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Ensure that a statistically valid number of counts or measurement levels are obtained and verified to give accurate and reliable test results for systems each day instruments and equipment such as cell counters, radiation counters, and spectrophotometers are used; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Report results in an accurate and reliable manner and within the time frames established by the laboratory; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Perform test methods and use instrumentation in a manner that permits the laboratory to provide accurate and reliable test results within the laboratory's stated performance criteria.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Standard — Supplies, Reagents, and Materials. A licensee shall ensure that supplies, reagents, and other materials used in the collection, handling, testing, and storing of specimens in the laboratory are stored, labeled, checked for proper reactivity, and used according to §§F — I of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Storage. A licensee shall ensure that laboratory materials are stored in the manner stated by the manufacturer.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Labeling. A licensee shall ensure that laboratory testing materials, including reagents, solutions, culture media, controls, and calibrators are labeled to indicate the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Identity;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Concentration, strength, or titer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Storage requirements;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Preparation and expiration dates;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Identity of the preparer; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Other pertinent information that would affect test performance or outcome.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Reactivity Checks. A licensee shall ensure that representative samples of each lot of materials used for or in the process of testing specimens are tested on a regularly scheduled basis to determine each material's capacity to perform as required.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Use of Supplies and Other Materials. A licensee:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>May not use materials that have:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Exceeded the material's expiration date;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Substandard reactivity; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Deteriorated; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shall use supplies, reagents, kits, identification systems, and other materials in a manner consistent with the recommendations and instructions provided by the manufacturer.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Quality Control — Single-Use Test Devices.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Primary Standard. This regulation applies to test systems that use single-use test devices as defined in <cite path="10.10.01.03|B.">COMAR 10.10.01.03B</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Standards.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>General. A licensee shall ensure that the test system is validated on a continuing basis and that the ongoing validation includes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Calibration verification;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Parallel testing before or, when appropriate, instead of proficiency testing; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Proficiency testing.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Requirements of the Test System's Manufacturer. In addition to the standards set forth in this regulation, a licensee shall ensure that the laboratory meets the quality control and quality assurance requirements of the test system's manufacturer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Test System Validation.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Initial. Before implementing patient testing, a licensee shall ensure that the test system is validated to assure consistency with the test system manufacturer's performance attributes for acceptable accuracy, precision, and functions that affect test reliability and the competency of the testing personnel by:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Performing and documenting at least 20 quality control tests for a period of at least 5 days of test system use in the environment and under the conditions that the test system will be used; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Having all testing personnel participate in the validation process.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Prior Testing. A test system placed in service for patient testing before the effective date of this chapter does not require an initial validation if a licensee ensures that the laboratory has:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Maintained documented evidence of an established, comprehensive, and active quality assurance program; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Participated satisfactorily in and continues to participate satisfactorily in an approved proficiency testing program or, when appropriate, periodically has conducted documented, parallel testing with split samples and periodically continues to conduct documented parallel testing with split samples.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Validity Check. A licensee shall ensure that each time a test is performed the result of the validity check and any corrective action are documented when the result:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Shows a single-use test device or test system failure;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Indicates any substandard performance; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Requires operator intervention.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>System Check.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Quantitative Test System. A licensee shall ensure that a system check for a quantitative test system is performed and documented:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>As specified by the manufacturer or at least once each 8 hours of test system use; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>After a single-use test device is exposed to an environment or condition that could affect the accuracy or reliability of test results.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Qualitative Test System. A licensee shall ensure that a system check for a qualitative test system, if available, is performed and documented:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>As required by the manufacturer; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Each day the test system is used.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Quality Control Tests.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Quantitative Test Systems. A licensee shall ensure that quality control testing for a quantitative test system is performed and documented using at least two levels of control material before patient testing:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>On each lot of a single-use test device received in a shipment;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>At least weekly for each lot of a single-use test device used for patient testing;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>After the test system undergoes maintenance, repair, adjustment, or an environmental exposure that could affect the accuracy and reliability of test results; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Each day of use during the test system's validation.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Qualitative Test System. A licensee shall ensure that quality control testing for a qualitative test system is performed and documented using known positive and negative control materials before patient testing:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>On each lot of a single-use test device received in a shipment;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>At least weekly for each lot of a single-use test device used for patient testing;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>After a single-use test device is exposed to an environment or condition that could affect the accuracy or reliability of test results; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Each day of use during test system validation.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Calibration and Verifying Calibration.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Calibration. A licensee shall ensure that the test system is calibrated as directed by the manufacturer.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Verifying Calibration. A licensee shall ensure that calibration of the test system is verified as directed by the manufacturer or at least every 6 months.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Quality Assurance.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Activities and Documentation. In addition to following other appropriate quality assurance standards in this chapter, a licensee shall ensure that quality assurance activities and documentation include reviewing, monitoring, and evaluating:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Single-use test device lot number, expiration, and disposal; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Testing discrepancies, including failed or repeat quality control or patient tests, validity checks, and system checks.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Comparison of Test Results. When a facility performs a test using more than one method or test system, has multiple testing sites, or has multiple licensees performing the same test within a facility, the facility's primary or central testing site shall establish and maintain a quality assurance system that twice a year evaluates and defines the relationship of test results using the different methods, test systems, or testing sites.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Quality Control — Specialty and Subspecialty.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Primary Standard. A licensee operating under a permit shall ensure that the laboratory establishes and follows written policies and procedures for a comprehensive quality control program that includes verification and assessment of accuracy, measurement of precision, and detection of error for all analyses and procedures performed by the laboratory.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Standards.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>General. A licensee shall ensure that the laboratory meets the applicable quality control requirements for each specialty and subspecialty under:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>42 CFR §§493.1200—493.1299; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Regulations <cite path="|10|10|06|.07">.07</cite>—<cite path="|10|10|06|.16">.16</cite> of this chapter.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Cholesterol. A licensee or approved plan holder of a laboratory that performs cholesterol tests shall ensure that the laboratory obtains and maintains control samples at two levels, near or bracketing the 200 and 240 micrograms/deciliter decision levels.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|10|06|.08">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Quality Control — Job-Related Alcohol and Drug Testing.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Primary Standard. A licensee shall ensure that a laboratory has in place a quality assurance program designed to monitor and evaluate all phases of the testing process including but not limited to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Laboratory certification;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Specimens, specimen collection, chain of custody, and transport;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Security and controlled access;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Storage and specimen retention;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Analytical methods and procedures;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Accuracy, precision, and reliability;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Single-use test devices;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Reporting test results; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Proficiency testing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Standards.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Certification. A licensee of a laboratory that offers to perform or performs screening or confirmation tests for alcohol or controlled dangerous substances shall ensure that the laboratory is inspected and certified to perform tests for alcohol or controlled dangerous substances by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Secretary;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The College of American Pathologists;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The federal Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration (SAMHSA); or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A government agency, program, or accrediting organization approved by the Secretary as set forth in <cite path="10.10.02.02">COMAR 10.10.02.02</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Specimens, Specimen Collection, Chain of Custody, and Transport.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Permissible Specimens. A licensee shall ensure that job-related tests for alcohol or controlled dangerous substances are only performed using specimens derived from the human body as set forth in <cite path="10.10.10.06">COMAR 10.10.10.06</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A licensee shall ensure that a specimen is processed, handled, and transported in a manner that protects the identity and physical integrity of the specimen by:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Accepting a specimen in a sealed container that has a non-resealable closure or an evidentiary tape that assures detection of any tampering; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Implementing, maintaining, and employing chain of custody procedures, including documentation of specimen handling and access, that cover the life of a specimen from the time of collection through final disposal of the specimen.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Decontamination Requirement for Hair Specimens. A licensee shall ensure that the laboratory establishes, validates, and uses a procedure to remove possible external contamination from a hair specimen before a test is performed.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Security and Controlled Access. A licensee shall ensure that a specimen is collected and processed in a manner that protects the physical integrity of the specimen by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Collecting and processing a specimen under supervised conditions;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Securing the laboratory or any portion of the laboratory used for job-related alcohol or controlled dangerous substances testing;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Using and maintaining secure specimen storage areas that include, when applicable, locked freezers and refrigerators;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Limiting access to testing and specimen storage facilities to authorized personnel;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Exercising and maintaining control over a specimen storage area by documenting in an access log the identity, date, time of entry and exit, and the purpose for entry for each individual who enters the storage area; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Recording, reporting, and maintaining a test result in a manner that prevents alteration and breech of confidentiality by:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Limiting access to a test result to authorized personnel; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Preparing and storing a test result in a secured area.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Storage and Specimen Retention. A licensee shall ensure that a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Positive urine or hair specimen is retained in the original collection container for at least 6 months after a final test result is reported;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Positive urine or blood specimen is stored at less than or equal to -20° Centigrade; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Negative specimen is retained for at least 5 days at less than or equal to room temperature.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Analytical Methods and Procedures. A licensee shall ensure that tests are performed using proven and reliable methods and procedures that are approved by the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Secretary;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>College of American Pathologists (CAP);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The federal Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration (SAMHSA); or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>United States Food and Drug Administration (FDA).</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Approval of Methods and Procedures. The Secretary shall base approval or acceptability of any analytical method or procedure with questioned validity or reliability on evidence published in a peer-reviewed scientific journal and derived from independent:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Scientific testing and evaluation; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Scientifically based clinical trial.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Accuracy, Precision, and Reliability. The licensee shall ensure that the laboratory employs quality control mechanisms and practices, including but not limited to those assuring accuracy, precision, and reliability of test results by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Using a sufficient number of reference standard samples with each batch of test specimens to ensure accuracy of the assay or procedure's linearity over time;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Using reference standard samples that have values at or near the minimum drug detection levels or concentrations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Using results obtained from testing reference standard samples to document linearity and calculate test data obtained from test specimens;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Including in each analytical run quality control samples that are:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Certified to contain no alcohol or controlled dangerous substance;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Fortified with known reference standards;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Positive with the alcohol or controlled dangerous substance at or near the cutoff or minimum detection level; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Using a total number of quality control samples in an analytical run equal to at least 5 percent of the number of specimens being tested;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Verifying and documenting at least monthly the linearity and precision of each test method and procedure; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Using methods, procedures, and techniques that prevent samples and specimens from contaminating one another throughout the testing process.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Cutoff Levels.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A licensee that offers to perform or performs job-related alcohol or controlled dangerous substances testing shall use the established cutoff levels specified in §B(8)(b) and (c) of this regulation to distinguish a positive from a negative test specimen.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Urine. A laboratory testing urine shall use the cutoff levels set forth in 49 CFR §40.87.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Blood, Saliva, and Hair.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A licensee testing blood, saliva, or hair specimens shall use the cutoff levels established by an agency of the federal government for the purpose of determining whether a specimen is positive or negative for alcohol or a controlled dangerous substance.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>If cutoff levels in blood, saliva, or hair have not been established and accepted by an agency of the federal government, a licensee shall establish and use a cutoff level for each screening test and confirmatory test performed to determine whether a specimen is negative for each controlled dangerous substance that the licensee offers to detect by a screening or confirmatory procedure.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Validation. A licensee shall ensure that the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Laboratory maintains documented data validating each cutoff level; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Cutoff data is made available for review by the OHCQ.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Single-Use Test Devices. A laboratory that performs screening tests using single-use test devices, as defined in <cite path="10.10.01.03|B.">COMAR 10.10.01.03B</cite>, may meet the quality assurance and quality control standards set forth in <cite path="|10|10|06|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite> instead of the standards set forth at <cite path="10|10|06|.08|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Reporting Test Results. A licensee shall ensure that a job-related laboratory test report includes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A list of all the drug and alcohol tests that were performed on the specimen;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Positive test results only if the specimen was found positive by a confirmation test that employed a combination of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Gas chromatography and mass spectrometry (GC/MS);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Mass spectrometry and mass spectrometry (MS/MS);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Gas chromatography tandem mass spectrometry (GC/MS/MS); or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Other analytical methods that use mass spectrometry as the primary detection technique;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The value at the cutoff or detection level of each test, that is, screening test or confirmation test, or both, for alcohol or a controlled dangerous substance performed on the specimen;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The telephone number of the laboratory that may be used by an employer or individual who was tested to obtain technical assistance for the purpose of interpreting a positive test result; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Except as provided in Health-General Article, §17-214(i), Annotated Code of Maryland, no information to an employer or prospective employer on:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The use of a nonprescription drug, excluding alcohol, that is not prohibited under the laws of the State; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The use of a legally prescribed drug, unless the individual tested is unable to establish that the drug was prescribed in accordance with the laws of the State.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Proficiency Testing. A licensee shall ensure that the laboratory enrolls and continues to participate satisfactorily in a proficiency testing program that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Covers each type of job-related alcohol and controlled dangerous substance test specimen analyzed; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has the approval of the Secretary as set forth in <cite path="10.10.05.03">COMAR 10.10.05.03</cite> of this subtitle.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Repealed.</heading>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Quality Control — Cytology.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Primary Standard. A licensee of a laboratory offering to perform or performing tests in the subdiscipline of gynecologic cytology shall ensure that the laboratory:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Limits the number of slides an individual may examine as set forth in 42 CFR §493.1274;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Limits slide examination to the laboratory premises;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Establishes a quality assurance program and follows written quality control procedures to monitor and evaluate the quality of cytological procedures and testing processes;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Does not pay for the examination of cytology slides on a piecework basis;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Reviews not less than 10 percent of all negative gynecologic slides before reporting results on those slides;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Employs an individual who qualifies as a supervisory cytotechnologist or a technical supervisor in gynecologic cytology to review negative gynecologic slides;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Does not allow the evaluation of a slide that shows evidence of unsatisfactory preparation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Reports as to whether a slide is satisfactory or unsatisfactory for evaluation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Maintains records for 5 years of slides reported as unsatisfactory;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Maintains and stores for 5 years from the date of examination any slide that was examined;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Retains cytology reports for at least 10 years;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Does not send gynecologic cytology slides to a laboratory not holding a State license; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Requires cytotechnologists and pathologists to obtain continuing education.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Standards.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>General. A licensee shall ensure that the laboratory complies with the applicable requirements in 42 CFR §493.1221.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Continuing Education.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A cytotechnologist or pathologist who is employed by a laboratory and who performs primary gynecologic screening shall obtain at least 20 credit hours per calendar year of continuing education in cytology. A credit hour is 1 hour of active participation in the educational activity.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An individual may obtain cytological continuing education in a formal or informal educational activity, such as reading journal articles, reviewing case histories, and attending lectures or workshops. This activity provides the individual with increased medical or technical knowledge of cytopathology or exfoliative cytology.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A licensee shall ensure that the laboratory annually compiles records of the continuing education for each cytotechnologist and pathologist and retains them for at least 2 years.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Quality Control — Dermatopathology.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Primary Standard. In addition to meeting the requirements of other applicable regulations of this subtitle, a licensee of a laboratory performing tests in the subdiscipline of dermatopathology shall ensure that the laboratory:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Retains the services of either a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Laboratory director who meets the qualifications in <cite path="10.10.07.04|B.|(1)">COMAR 10.10.07.04B(1)</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Technical supervisor who meets the qualifications in <cite path="10.10.07.05|B.|(4)">COMAR 10.10.07.05B(4)</cite>;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Maintains applicable records and reports; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Effectively processes and stores specimens, slides, and tissue.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Standards.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Maintenance of Records, Reports, Tissue, and Slides.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A licensee shall ensure that the laboratory maintains a system of documentation to monitor the collection, receipt, handling, transport, processing, testing, and reporting of all specimens.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A system of documentation may include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A laboratory specimen log book; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Accession sheets or records.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A licensee shall ensure that the laboratory generates a written report for each patient specimen that is examined either microscopically or macroscopically. The report shall include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Patient name, age, and sex;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The dates of specimen collection and processing;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The source or anatomic site of a specimen;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>A gross description of the specimen;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>A description of the tissue, for example, bisected, submitted in total, number of blocks, or that only representative sections were submitted;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>The diagnosis or observed results of the test or examination;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>The examining physician's name, signature, and date of report;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>If appropriate, the clinical impression or differential diagnosis; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ix)</num>
            <text>Other pertinent or essential patient history that may affect the accuracy or reliability of the report.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A licensee shall ensure that a laboratory retains:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Records and reports for at least 10 years for final reports and 2 years for other laboratory records;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Wet tissue or tissue remnants for 2 weeks after a final report is issued;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A specimen or tissue in a paraffin block for 5 years from the date of examination; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Slides for 10 years from the date of examination.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>A licensee shall ensure that specimens, slides, and tissues are:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Processed in a facility licensed under this chapter;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Appropriately fixed for the tests performed;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Properly labeled with at least the patient's name or other cross-referenced identifier, such as a case or accession number; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Adequately stored and effectively filed to allow easy access and retrieval.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Quality Control. When a slide or specimen is processed or stained in the laboratory, the licensee shall ensure that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A staining container is labeled and covered when not in use;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A stain and a working solution are changed at appropriate intervals; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Routine employee access is provided to flowcharts and other written procedures that accurately reflect the procedures in use.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Quality Control — Temporary and Mobile Laboratories: General.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Primary Standard. The licensee shall ensure that a health awareness test or a job-related screening test for alcohol or controlled dangerous substances at a temporary or mobile laboratory is performed:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Under effective supervision, quality control, and safety procedures;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Using a previously evaluated analytical system; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>For a job-related screening test for alcohol or controlled dangerous substances, only at the request of an individual authorized in <cite path="10.10.06.02">COMAR 10.10.06.02</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Standards.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Limited Tests. A person may perform at a temporary or mobile laboratory only the health awareness tests defined in <cite path="10.10.01.03|B.">COMAR 10.10.01.03B</cite> and job-related screening tests for alcohol or controlled dangerous substances.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Health awareness and cholesterol testing may be performed at the request of the examinee. Staff who perform the tests shall have training and experience to perform testing that includes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Operation of the analyzers per manufacturer’s recommendations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Evaluation of the results of the quality controls;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Interpretation of the test results; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Counseling to the individual whose specimen is tested.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Supervision. A designated supervisor, knowledgeable in all aspects of the health awareness testing, shall be present at a temporary or mobile laboratory throughout a testing event to oversee testing, including compliance with all applicable requirements set forth in this chapter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Testing Sites.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A person may not perform a health awareness test in a restaurant where food or drink is prepared, served, or consumed.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A licensee shall ensure that a temporary laboratory:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Provides space, when applicable, for counseling examinees regarding test results;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Provides space appropriate for the number of staff, analytical systems, and examinees;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Provides work space adequate to minimize problems of transportation, communication, and safety;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Provides electricity of the type and in the amount needed to operate analytical systems properly;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Includes access to water and disinfectant supplies for routine cleaning and disinfection of the work area, equipment, and personnel;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Contains or is within 1 minute of a telephone with access to emergency assistance by calling 911;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Maintains levels of temperature, humidity, and ventilation to comply with manufacturer's specifications for effective operation of analytical systems;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Is situated a minimum of 12 feet from any produce, meat, or dairy department in a food market;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ix)</num>
            <text>Maintains partitions, such as ropes, on at least three sides of an area where blood is drawn or processed, to prevent unsupervised access to a blood-drawing or testing area;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(x)</num>
            <text>Employs separate receptacles for routine laboratory and special medical wastes within partitioned testing areas;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xi)</num>
            <text>Provides for the storage of reagents and other testing materials within temperatures recommended by the manufacturer; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xii)</num>
            <text>Complies with all pertinent State laws and local ordinances.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Pre-Field Evaluation of Analytical Systems. A licensee may not employ an analytical system in a mobile or temporary laboratory until the laboratory has documented the analytical system's levels of accuracy and precision in a permanent laboratory facility.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>In-Field Quality Control. A licensee operating a mobile or temporary laboratory shall establish and maintain a continuous quality control program for an analytical system operated in that mobile or temporary laboratory.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Phlebotomy Quality Control and Safety.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A licensee employing a phlebotomist at a temporary or mobile laboratory shall ensure that the phlebotomist is trained in proper techniques for:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Specimen collection; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Infection control.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A licensee shall provide appropriate protective clothing and disposable gloves and ensure that they are used appropriately by all personnel involved in drawing or handling blood.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A phlebotomist shall wear new gloves for each examinee.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A laboratory employee shall use and clean phlebotomy devices as prescribed by the manufacturer.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Testing Logs. A licensee shall maintain for 2 years a log identifying all:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Persons tested;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Test results; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Test dates.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Results Reporting. The licensee of a temporary or mobile laboratory:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>May give results of a health awareness test immediately following the testing directly to the individual who underwent the test; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Shall give the test results in writing stating the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Name of the individual tested,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Name of the laboratory performing the test,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Name of the test,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Date of the test, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Test result with appropriate interpretation or reference range consistent with current nationally recognized standards.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Disposal of Special Medical Waste. A licensee operating a temporary or mobile laboratory shall dispose of special medical waste as required in <cite path="|10.06.06">COMAR 10.06.06</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Quality Control — Temporary and Mobile Laboratories: Personnel Training.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Primary Standard. In addition to meeting other applicable requirements in this chapter, a licensee shall ensure that all laboratory personnel performing a health awareness test at a temporary or mobile laboratory are trained to perform all assigned duties.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Standards.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All Personnel. A licensee shall ensure that all personnel are trained to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Keep examinees' health information confidential;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Deal with emergency situations such as fainting and anxiety reactions;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Report and document information on testing services and activities; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Dispose of special medical waste as set forth in <cite path="|10.06.06">COMAR 10.06.06</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Phlebotomist. A licensee shall ensure that an individual who collects blood specimens is trained in:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Specimen collection methods; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Infection control and prevention techniques, including CDC recommendations for preventing the transmission of bloodborne pathogens in health care settings.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Operator of an Analytical System: General. A licensee shall ensure that an operator of an analytical system is trained in:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Infection control and prevention techniques, including CDC recommendations concerning the transmission of bloodborne pathogens in health care settings; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Proper use of the analytical system, including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Analytical system operation;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>System methods used to process the specimen; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Quality control techniques, procedures, and requirements.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Operator of an Analytical System: Competency.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Obtaining Personal Competency. Before an individual may operate an analytical system without direct supervision, the individual operator shall demonstrate competency in operating the analytical system by completing:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Pre-field supervised practice that includes performing under direct supervision a minimum of ten tests of each applicable type of health awareness test; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Field testing experience that includes individual performance of directly supervised testing in the field.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Documenting Training and Competency. The licensee shall document in writing that each analytical system operator has demonstrated competency as required under this regulation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Quality Control — Temporary and Mobile Laboratories: Event Registration.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Primary Standard. In addition to meeting other applicable requirements set forth in this chapter, a licensee intending to perform a health awareness test at a temporary or mobile laboratory shall register the testing event with the Department before the testing event may occur.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Standards.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A licensee shall inform the OHCQ by phone or in writing of the date, time, location, and on-site supervisor's name for a testing event at least 14 days before the event is to take place.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A licensee shall display in a public place at the testing site and throughout the testing event a copy of the laboratory's license.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|10|06|.15">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Quality Control — Temporary and Mobile Laboratories: Cholesterol and Health Awareness.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Primary Standard. In addition to meeting other applicable requirements in this chapter, a licensee offering to perform or performing cholesterol or health awareness testing at a temporary or mobile laboratory shall ensure that the laboratory:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Develops and maintains a written SOPM;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Validates the analyzer initially and utilizes the manufacturer’s reference range for the quality control with each new lot of quality control;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Employs and maintains an in-field quality control program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Reports test results as set forth in <cite path="10|10|06|.15|B.|(5)">§B(5) of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Informs examinees of test limitations based on current nationally recognized standards for each test performed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Standards.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Supervisor. A supervisor knowledgeable in all aspects of health awareness testing shall oversee all cholesterol or health awareness testing conducted at a temporary or mobile laboratory.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>SOPM.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A licensee shall develop and maintain a written SOPM covering all current procedures for:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Training personnel;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Analytical system maintenance;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Testing participants and quality control;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Retesting;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Documenting lot numbers and expiration dates of quality control materials and reagents (cassettes) used for participant testing;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Evaluation of quality controls on site and documentation of corrective actions when quality control results are unacceptable;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>An every 6 month evaluation of all analyzers used in Maryland using the worksheet provided by the Department; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Other aspects of the cholesterol and health awareness testing service's activities.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The general supervisor or director shall initially approve and when changes are made review, sign, and date the SOPM.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>All personnel shall have routine access to a copy of the SOPM at each testing site throughout each testing event.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Method Verification and Pre-Field Evaluation of an Analytical System. A licensee shall evaluate each analytical system by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Performing a method verification to demonstrate that the system produces test results within limits of accuracy and precision, as defined by either the licensee or the system's manufacturer, before the system may be used at a temporary or mobile laboratory; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Analyzing two levels of quality control materials.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>In-field Quality Control. At a temporary or mobile laboratory, a licensee shall maintain a continuous quality control program in which:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Each person who performs tests at a screening event shall test both levels of quality control samples identified in <cite path="10|10|06|.15|B.|(3)|(b)">§B(3)(b) of this regulation</cite> on one analyzer for each cholesterol and health awareness test performed at the screening event;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Quality control testing shall be performed on at least one analyzer, if more than one analyzer at a screening event is used;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Each testing person shall test two levels of quality control materials on another analyzer at the beginning of the cholesterol or health awareness event if more than one person is performing tests at an event; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The laboratory shall complete the comparison worksheet designated by the Department quarterly to ensure that all the analyzers used for reporting test results produce results within 15 percent to 20 percent of the other analyzers.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Examinee results shall be reported above the established reportable range of the instrument, that is, analytic range, as greater than the highest reference point, with the analytic range being determined by pre-field testing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Reporting and Releasing Test Results.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A licensee shall release cholesterol or health awareness test results only to the examinee or their physician in writing and in a manner to protect the confidentiality of the test results.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A licensee shall include the following on its reports:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The name, address, and phone number of the laboratory performing the test;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The date and location of the testing; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The signature, initials, or electronic authentication of a laboratory employee.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A laboratory shall provide to an examinee a written explanation of all cholesterol and health awareness test results and refer the examinee for medical care when indicated by the results.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health-General Article, §§17-202, 17-202.1, 17-214, and 17-504, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-11-18">Effective date: November 18, 1985 (12:23 Md. R. 2217)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-08-06">Regulations <cite path="|10|10|06|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|10|06|.06">.06</cite>, Physicians' Group Practice Laboratories in Maryland, repealed effective August 6, 1990 (17:15 Md. R. 1859)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-08-06" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|10|10|06|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|10|06|.28">.28</cite>, Physician Office and Other Point-of-Care Laboratories, adopted effective August 6, 1990 (17:15 Md. R. 1859)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1991-09-16"><cite path="|10|10|06|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite> amended effective September 16, 1991 (18:18 Md. R. 2005)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1991-09-16"><cite path="|10|10|06|.08|C.">Regulation .08C</cite> amended effective September 16, 1991 (18:18 Md. R. 2005)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1991-09-16"><cite path="|10|10|06|.09|B.">Regulation .09B</cite> amended effective September 16, 1991 (18:18 Md. R. 2005)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1991-09-16"><cite path="|10|10|06|.25">Regulation .25</cite> amended effective September 16, 1991 (18:18 Md. R. 2005)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-12-13" discontinuity="true">Chapter, Physician Office and Other Point-of-Care Laboratories, repealed and new chapter, Medical Laboratories—Quality Assurance, adopted effective December 13, 1999 (26:25 Md. R. 1897)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-06-01"><cite path="|10|10|06|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective June 1, 2009 (36:11 Md. R. 787)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-04-01"><cite path="|10|10|06|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended effective July 22, 2002 (29:14 Md. R. 1074); April 1, 2013 (40:6 Md. R. 473)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-04-16"><cite path="|10|10|06|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective April 16, 2012 (39:7 Md. R. 492)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-06-01"><cite path="|10|10|06|.02|C.">Regulation .02C</cite> amended effective June 1, 2009 (36:11 Md. R. 787)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-06-01"><cite path="|10|10|06|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective June 1, 2009 (36:11 Md. R. 787)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-01-13"><cite path="|10|10|06|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite> amended effective July 24, 2000 (27:14 Md. R. 1340); January 13, 2011 (38:1 Md. R. 11)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-06-01"><cite path="|10|10|06|.04|B.">Regulation .04B</cite> adopted effective June 1, 2009 (36:11 Md. R. 787)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-04-16"><cite path="|10|10|06|.04|B.">Regulation .04B</cite> amended effective April 16, 2012 (39:7 Md. R. 492)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-06-01"><cite path="|10|10|06|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective June 1, 2009 (36:11 Md. R. 787)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-06-01"><cite path="|10|10|06|.05-1">Regulation .05-1</cite> adopted effective June 1, 2009 (36:11 Md. R. 787)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-06-01"><cite path="|10|10|06|.07|B.">Regulation .07B</cite> amended effective June 1, 2009 (36:11 Md. R. 787)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-06-01"><cite path="|10|10|06|.08">Regulation .08</cite> amended effective June 1, 2009 (36:11 Md. R. 787)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-07-24"><cite path="|10|10|06|.08|B.">Regulation .08B</cite> amended effective July 24, 2000 (27:14 Md. R. 1340)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-06-01"><cite path="|10|10|06|.09">Regulation .09</cite> repealed effective June 1, 2009 (36:11 Md. R. 787)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-06-01"><cite path="|10|10|06|.10">Regulation .10</cite> amended effective June 1, 2009 (36:11 Md. R. 787)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-07-24"><cite path="|10|10|06|.10|B.">Regulation .10B</cite> amended effective July 24, 2000 (27:14 Md. R. 1340)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-04-01"><cite path="|10|10|06|.12">Regulation .12</cite> amended effective July 22, 2002 (29:14 Md. R. 1074); April 1, 2013 (40:6 Md. R. 473)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-04-16"><cite path="|10|10|06|.12|B.">Regulation .12B</cite> amended effective April 16, 2012 (39:7 Md. R. 492)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-06-01"><cite path="|10|10|06|.14|B.">Regulation .14B</cite> amended effective June 1, 2009 (36:11 Md. R. 787)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-04-01"><cite path="|10|10|06|.15">Regulation .15</cite> amended effective June 1, 2009 (36:11 Md. R. 787); April 1, 2013 (40:6 Md. R. 473)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-07-24"><cite path="|10|10|06|.15|B.">Regulation .15B</cite> amended effective July 24, 2000 (27:14 Md. R. 1340)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-04-01"><cite path="|10|10|06|.16">Regulation .16</cite> repealed effective April 1, 2013 (40:6 Md. R. 473)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-06-01"><cite path="|10|10|06|.16|A.">Regulation .16A</cite> amended effective June 1, 2009 (36:11 Md. R. 787)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
