<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>07</num>
  <heading>Medical Laboratories — Personnel</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|10|07|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Permitted POL and POCL — Director and Associate Director.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Primary Standard. The licensee of a permitted POL or POCL shall employ or otherwise engage the services of a qualified director or associate director and a laboratory supervisor or consulting supervisor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Standards.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Qualifications.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>POL. The director of a permitted POL shall be:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A physician licensed by the Board of Physicians to practice medicine in the State and a member or employee of the practice operating the laboratory; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>An employee or contractor of the practice who possesses the training and experience set forth in <cite path="|10|10|07|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>POCL. The director of a permitted POCL shall be:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A physician of the medical care facility who possesses the applicable training and experience set forth in <cite path="|10|10|07|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>An individual who qualifies as a director under 42 CFR §493.1443, and who possesses the applicable training and experience set forth in <cite path="|10|10|07|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>An individual who meets the definition of a technologist as set forth in <cite path="10.10.01.03|B.">COMAR 10.10.01.03B</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Duties and Responsibilities.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A director of a permitted POL or POCL shall participate in and actively oversee the planning, organization, direction, and review of all laboratory operations to the extent necessary to ensure compliance with this chapter.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A director's duties and responsibilities include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>When applicable, employing or otherwise engaging the services of a qualified general supervisor or consulting supervisor;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Ensuring that the general supervisor or consulting supervisor spends sufficient time performing the supervisory duties and responsibilities;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Completing and submitting to the OHCQ forms, supplied by the OHCQ, that document a general or consulting supervisor's education, training, and experience in laboratory practice;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Recruiting qualified and competent technical personnel;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Obtaining or providing and documenting initial training and continuing education for technical personnel;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Reviewing with the laboratory supervisor or consulting supervisor all laboratory procedures and policies and all evaluative material, including proficiency testing results, pertinent to the operation and performance of the laboratory;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Serving as a liaison between the physicians of the practice or medical care facility and the laboratory supervisor or consulting supervisor and other technical personnel to communicate situations such as test interpretations, timeliness of reports, reporting abnormal test results, and new or changing laboratory procedures and policies affecting patient care;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Ensuring that all application forms, documents, and other materials required under this chapter are submitted to the OHCQ within the appropriate time periods; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ix)</num>
            <text>Designating an associate director, when applicable.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Associate Director. An associate director shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Meet the same qualifications as set forth in <cite path="10|10|07|.01|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Act as laboratory director when the laboratory director is away from the laboratory for a period of more than 30 days.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Supervisory Consultation. A director of a permitted POL or POCL shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Consult with the laboratory supervisor in person, in writing, or by telephone at least once a month regarding the performance and operation of the laboratory; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Conduct an on-site visit to each directed laboratory at least once a month.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Director Limitation. A POL director may not serve as director or associate director, or both, of more than five medical laboratories at the same time.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Changes in Employment or Service. A director shall notify the OHCQ within 30 days of any change in the director's service or employment as a laboratory director.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Director Disqualification. A director or associate director may be disqualified to direct a permitted POL for failing to comply with the applicable standards and requirements of this chapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Permitted POL and POCL — General Supervisor and Consulting Supervisor.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Primary Standard. A licensee operating a POL or POCL under a permit shall employ or otherwise engage a qualified general supervisor or consulting supervisor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Standards.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Requirement. A laboratory shall employ or otherwise engage a qualified general supervisor or consulting supervisor who shall act in concert with the laboratory director to ensure that the laboratory complies with the standards and requirements of this chapter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Qualifications — POL and POCL General Supervisor. To qualify as a laboratory supervisor in a permitted POL or POCL, an individual shall be a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Physician who is board certified, or eligible to be certified in clinical pathology, and employed to perform or oversee testing on a full-time or part-time basis in the laboratory being supervised;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Technologist as defined in <cite path="10.10.01.03|B.">COMAR 10.10.01.03B</cite> and employed to perform tests at least 1 day a week in the lab being supervised; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Technician as defined in <cite path="10.10.01.03|B.">COMAR 10.10.01.03B</cite> and employed to perform tests on a full-time basis in the lab being supervised.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Qualifications — Consulting Supervisor. To qualify as a consulting supervisor of a POL or POCL, an individual shall be a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Technologist as defined in <cite path="10.10.01.03|B.">COMAR 10.10.01.03B</cite> who possesses at least 2 years of work experience in a laboratory that:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Operated under a permit; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Performed testing services related to those offered by the laboratory to be supervised; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Physician who is board certified, or eligible to be certified in clinical pathology, and employed to perform or oversee testing on a full-time or part-time basis in the laboratory being supervised.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Supervisory Duties and Responsibilities. A general supervisor or consulting supervisor shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Implement and maintain the applicable laboratory standards and requirements set forth in this chapter;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Ensure proper and reliable test performance, reporting, record keeping, and immediate general and technical supervision of testing personnel and laboratory services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Develop, implement, and oversee maintenance of an internal quality assurance program that includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A working quality control program or system that determines and documents accuracy and precision of all tests performed;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Selection and use of quality control and standard materials for analysis;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Recording and documenting quality control data;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Ongoing analysis of quality control data; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Implementation and maintenance of a specimen documentation and management system;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Prepare and maintain a SOPM;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Ensure full participation in an external proficiency testing program approved by the Secretary as set forth in <cite path="10.10.05.03">COMAR 10.10.05.03</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Teach proper laboratory techniques, including the importance of quality control, quality assurance, and proficiency testing;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Review proficiency testing results, determine sources of error, and work to correct any problems;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Review proficiency testing results, analytical studies and evaluations, and survey reports with technical personnel to improve test performance and laboratory services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Maintain, as part of laboratory records, a log or other suitable record documenting monthly consultations with the director and all supervisory activities provided to the laboratory;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Ensure that laboratory testing personnel:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Possess the education, training, and experience required to perform and report laboratory test results accurately and promptly;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Are sufficient in number for the scope and complexity of the services provided;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Receive regular in-service training and continuing education appropriate for the scope and complexity of the services provided; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Maintain competency in performing test procedures and reporting test results; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Perform other duties and responsibilities as delegated and authorized by the director that may include assisting in:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Developing cost benefit data;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Identifying and recommending adjustments to a laboratory's scope of services; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Recommending the purchase or replacement of test kits, reagents, and equipment.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Permitted POL and POCL — Consulting Supervisor Services.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A licensee operating a permitted POL or POCL who does not employ or otherwise engage technical personnel who qualify as a general supervisor shall arrange with a qualified consulting supervisor to provide technical and general supervisory consultation services in laboratory practice.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The licensee operating a POL or POCL under a permit shall use a consulting supervisor who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Makes and documents on-site visits to each laboratory facility at least twice each calendar year;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is available by telephone during the laboratory's regular operating hours; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Completes a laboratory inspection checklist, provided by the OHCQ, to be submitted to the OHCQ not more than once every 2 years.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Additional Visits. The OHCQ may require more than two on-site visits per year by a consulting supervisor when:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A laboratory exhibits unsatisfactory proficiency testing performance;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An on-site survey by the OHCQ shows that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A laboratory is not in substantial compliance with the applicable standards and requirements of this chapter;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A laboratory's written plan of correction in response to a Department survey does not ensure substantial compliance with the applicable standards and requirements of this chapter; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A laboratory's testing personnel require additional supervisory consultations to obtain or maintain proficiency in quality assurance, performing or reporting test results, or meeting other applicable standards of this chapter;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An inspection checklist submitted by the laboratory shows that the laboratory is operating in a manner that is not in compliance with applicable standards of this chapter; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The laboratory's general supervisor or consulting supervisor has been unable to perform the duties and responsibilities set forth in <cite path="|10|10|07|.02|B.|(4)">Regulation .02B(4) of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|10|07|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Permitted Laboratory Other than a POL or POCL — Director.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Primary Standard. A licensee operating a permitted laboratory other than a POL or POCL shall employ a director who meets the applicable qualifications, responsibilities, and standards set forth in this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Standards.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Qualifications. In addition to applicable personnel standards set forth in this chapter, a director shall meet the applicable standards set forth in 42 CFR §493.1443.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Responsibilities. A director shall carry out the applicable responsibilities set forth in 42 CFR §§493.1407 and 493.1445.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Associate Director. A director shall designate another individual who qualifies as a director under this chapter to serve as an associate or substitute director when the director:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Will be away from the laboratory for a period of more than 30 days; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is unable to carry out the responsibilities set forth in <cite path="10|10|07|.04|B.|(2)">§B(2) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Communications. A director shall communicate with the laboratory's supervisory personnel in person, in writing, or by telephone at least once a month regarding the performance and operation of the laboratory.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>On-site Visits. A director of a laboratory shall conduct an on-site visit of the laboratory at least once a month.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Limitation. The director of a permitted laboratory may not serve as director or associate director, or both, of more than five medical laboratories at the same time.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|10|07|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Permitted Laboratories — Technical Supervisors.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Primary Standards.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A laboratory director certified, or eligible for certification, in anatomic and clinical pathology by the American Board of Pathology qualifies as a technical supervisor in all disciplines and subdisciplines set forth in <cite path="10.10.01.03|B.">COMAR 10.10.01.03B</cite>, except:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Genetics; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Forensic toxicology.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A licensee who does not employ or otherwise engage a director certified in anatomic and clinical pathology by the American Board of Pathology, or a licensee operating a laboratory that performs testing in the discipline of genetics or forensic toxicology shall employ the services of a technical supervisor for each discipline set forth in <cite path="10.10.01.03|B.">COMAR 10.10.01.03B</cite> except the discipline of health awareness testing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A technical supervisor shall carry out the applicable responsibilities set forth in 42 CFR §493.1451.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Standards.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Requirement. A licensee operating a laboratory that performs testing in one or more disciplines shall employ a director or technical supervisor who meets the qualifications for a technical supervisor in the applicable disciplines or subdisciplines set forth in §B(2)—(13) of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Chemistry. A technical supervisor shall possess a bachelor's or higher degree including significant studies in chemistry and have at least 4 years post-baccalaureate or 2 years post-master's medical laboratory experience in clinical chemistry.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Gynecologic Cytology. A technical supervisor shall meet the requirements set forth in 42 CFR §493.1449.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Dermatopathology. A technical supervisor shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A physician licensed by the Board of Physicians to practice medicine in the State; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Either certified or eligible for certification in dermatopathology or anatomic pathology by the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>American Board of Dermatology;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>American Osteopathic Board of Dermatology;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>American Board of Pathology; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>American Osteopathic Board of Pathology.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Forensic Toxicology — General Qualifications. A technical supervisor shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be certified in toxicological chemistry by the American Board of Clinical Chemistry;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Be certified in forensic toxicology by the American Board of Forensic Toxicology;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Be certified in clinical pathology and chemistry by the American Board of Pathology; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Possess education and experience in toxicology equivalent to that required by one of these boards.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Forensic Toxicology — Alternative Qualifications. An individual who does not qualify as a technical supervisor under <cite path="10|10|07|.05|B.|(5)">§B(5) of this regulation</cite> may qualify as a technical supervisor if the individual:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Can document training or experience, or both, in the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Analysis of biological material for alcohol or controlled dangerous substances, or both; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Forensic applications of analytical toxicology, such as court testimony, use of chain of custody, and specimen security; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Possesses:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A degree in medicine or osteopathy acceptable for licensure as a physician by the Maryland State Board of Physicians, with certification in clinical pathology or forensic pathology, and have at least 2 years of laboratory experience in analytical toxicology;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A doctoral degree in a biological, chemical, pharmacological, or toxicological discipline and have at least 2 years of laboratory experience in analytical toxicology; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A master's degree in a biological, chemical, pharmacological, or toxicological discipline with at least 6 years of experience in analytical toxicology.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Genetics. A technical supervisor of biochemical genetics, cytogenetics, or molecular genetics shall possess:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A degree in medicine or osteopathy acceptable for licensure as a physician by the Maryland State Board of Physicians; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An earned doctorate in one of the biological or chemical sciences from an accredited institution with:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>4 years of laboratory experience in genetics; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Eligibility for certification by the American Board of Medical Genetics.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Hematology. A technical supervisor shall possess a baccalaureate or higher degree including studies in biology or general cytology and have at least 4 years post-baccalaureate or 2 years post-master's medical laboratory experience in hematology.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Immunology. A technical supervisor shall possess a baccalaureate or higher degree including studies in immunology, microbiology, or chemistry and have at least 4 years post-baccalaureate or 2 years post-master's experience in immunology-serology.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Microbiology. A technical supervisor shall possess a baccalaureate or higher degree including studies in microbiology or immunology and have at least 4 years post-baccalaureate or 2 years post-master's medical laboratory experience in clinical microbiology.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Molecular Biology. A technical supervisor shall possess a baccalaureate or higher degree including studies in molecular biology and have at least 4 years post-baccalaureate or 2 years post-master's experience in molecular biology, microbiology, immunology, or clinical chemistry.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Oral Pathology, Including Oral Cytopathology. A technical supervisor shall be a dentist or physician licensed to practice in Maryland and be certified or eligible for certification by the American Board of Oral Pathology, American Board of Pathology, or the American Osteopathic Board of Pathology.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Tissue Pathology. A technical supervisor shall be a physician licensed to practice medicine in Maryland and be certified or eligible for certification in anatomic pathology by the American Board of Pathology or the American Osteopathic Board of Pathology.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Permitted Laboratory Other than a POL or POCL — Supervisors.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Primary Standard. A licensee operating a laboratory other than a POL or POCL shall employ a qualified supervisory technologist or general supervisor, who in the absence of the director or technical supervisor is responsible for the proper performance of laboratory procedures and reporting of laboratory test results.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Standards: General Supervisor.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Personnel Qualifications. A general supervisor shall be a technologist who possesses at least 4 years technical experience in a licensed medical laboratory other than a laboratory operating under a letter of exception.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Responsibilities. A general supervisor shall carry out the responsibilities set forth in 42 CFR §493.1463.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Standards: Supervisory Cytotechnologist.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Personnel Qualifications. For the specialty of cytology, a laboratory shall employ the services of a supervisory cytotechnologist who meets the qualifications set forth in 42 CFR §493.1469.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Responsibilities. A supervisory cytotechnologist shall carry out the responsibilities set forth in 42 CFR §493.1471.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Standards: Supervisor of Blood Gas Analyses. An individual qualifies as a supervisor of blood gas analyses by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Possessing an earned doctoral, master's, or baccalaureate degree in respiratory care or cardiovascular technology; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Meeting the personnel qualifications set forth in 42 CFR §493.1449.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Permitted Laboratory Other than POL or POCL — Testing Personnel.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Primary Standard. A permitted laboratory other than a POL or POCL shall employ or engage testing personnel, sufficient in number to perform testing for the volume and complexity of testing performed, who meet the qualifications and carry out the responsibilities set forth in this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Standards — General.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Personnel Qualifications. An individual performing one or more laboratory tests shall meet the applicable qualifications set forth in 42 CFR §493.1489.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Responsibilities. Testing personnel shall carry out the responsibilities set forth in 42 CFR §493.1495.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Standards — Cytotechnologist.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Personnel Qualifications. For the specialty of cytology, a licensee shall employ the services of cytotechnologists who meet the qualifications set forth in 42 CFR §§493.1483.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Responsibilities. A cytotechnologist shall carry out the responsibilities set forth in 42 CFR §493.1485.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Standards — Blood Gas Analysis—Personnel Qualifications. Personnel performing blood gas analyses shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Meet the standards set forth in 42 CFR §493.1489; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Complete a 1-year certificate program in respiratory care.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health-General Article, §§17-202, 17-203, 17-206, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-12-13">Effective date: December 13, 1999 (26:25 Md. R. 1897)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-06-01"><cite path="|10|10|07|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective July 24, 2000 (27:14 Md. R. 1340); June 1, 2009 (36:11 Md. R. 787)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-06-01"><cite path="|10|10|07|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective June 1, 2009 (36:11 Md. R. 787)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-07-24"><cite path="|10|10|07|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective July 24, 2000 (27:14 Md. R. 1340)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-06-01"><cite path="|10|10|07|.05|B.">Regulation .05B</cite> amended effective June 1, 2009 (36:11 Md. R. 787)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
