<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>08</num>
  <heading>Medical Laboratories — Sanctions</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>General.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Authority and Types.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Secretary may impose one or more principal or alternative sanctions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Principal Sanctions. The Secretary may impose the following principal sanctions:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Denial of a license;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Suspension of a license; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Revocation of a license.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Alternative Sanctions. Instead of or in conjunction with lifting a principal sanction, the Secretary may impose one or more of the following alternative sanctions:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A directed plan of correction;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Limitation on testing; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Training and technical assistance.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Reasons for Imposition. A laboratory is subject to the imposition of one or more sanctions when the OHCQ finds:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A deficiency identified through an on-site survey or a review of materials submitted by a laboratory, such as applications data, personnel qualification materials, and self-inspection checklists;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Unsuccessful proficiency testing performance;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Demonstrated incompetence, such as showing consistent or repetitive errors in operating equipment or in performing a test or procedure;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>False statements made on an application, plan-of-correction, or other form submitted to the OHCQ;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Misrepresentation in obtaining a permit or letter of exception or in operating a laboratory;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Failure to comply with the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Cancer reporting requirements of Health-General Article, §18-204, Annotated Code of Maryland; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Infectious disease and submission of clinical material requirements of Health-General Article, §18-205, Annotated Code of Maryland, and <cite path="|10.06.01">COMAR 10.06.01</cite>;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Submission of a specimen by a laboratory inside the State to another laboratory that does not possess a license as set forth in <cite path="|10.10.03">COMAR 10.10.03</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Conviction by a court of a violation of the laws of the State pertaining to a medical laboratory; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Exceeding the 50 test per year limit when operating under a letter of exception—limited testing for rare diseases as set forth in <cite path="10.10.03.05|B.">COMAR 10.10.03.05B</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Factors Affecting Choice of Sanctions. The Secretary shall choose which sanctions to apply to a laboratory based on, but not limited to, the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Whether a deficiency poses immediate jeopardy to personal or public health or safety;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The nature, incidence, severity, and duration of the deficiency;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Whether a deficiency has been identified repeatedly;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The inaccuracy or extent of missing laboratory records, such as missing documentation of remedial action or failure to make records available to the OHCQ;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The relationship of one deficiency or group of deficiencies to another deficiency;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The overall compliance history of a laboratory, including but not limited to any period of noncompliance that occurred between determinations of compliance;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The corrective and long-term compliance outcomes the Secretary intends to effect through application of the sanction; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The progress a laboratory has made toward regulatory compliance following a reasonable opportunity to correct a deficiency.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Mandatory Revocation of a License. The Secretary shall revoke for 1 year the license of a laboratory that intentionally refers a proficiency test sample to another laboratory for analysis.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Owning and Operating Prohibition Following Revocation. A person who has owned, operated, or directed a laboratory that has had its license revoked may not, within 1 year of the revocation, apply for a license, or own or operate a laboratory for which a license has been issued under this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Departmental Actions — General.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Deficiency Posing Immediate Jeopardy.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a laboratory's deficiency poses immediate jeopardy to personal or public health or safety, the Secretary shall take one or more of the actions listed in §A(2) and(3) of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Initial Actions. When a deficiency involving immediate jeopardy is first identified, the Secretary shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Require the laboratory to take immediate action to remove the jeopardy; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Impose:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A principal sanction after giving the laboratory at least 24 hours notice; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>One or more alternative sanctions.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Follow-up Actions. If the OHCQ finds in a follow-up survey of a laboratory under an alternative sanction that the laboratory has not eliminated the immediate jeopardy, the Secretary shall impose a principal sanction after giving the laboratory at least 24 hours notice.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Deficiency Not Posing Immediate Jeopardy.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a laboratory's deficiency does not pose immediate jeopardy to personal or public health or safety, the Secretary may take one or more of the actions listed in §B(2)—(4) of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Initial Actions. When a deficiency is first identified, the Secretary may impose one or more alternative sanctions or a principal sanction.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Unsuccessful Proficiency Testing. If a laboratory exhibits unsuccessful proficiency testing, as set forth in <cite path="10.10.01.03|B.">COMAR 10.10.01.03B</cite>, the Secretary may impose the training and technical assistance requirements set forth in <cite path="|10|10|08|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite> as a directed plan of correction, as well as any other sanction.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Follow-up Actions. If the OHCQ finds in a follow-up survey that a laboratory has not corrected a deficiency within 30 days after it was identified, the Secretary may:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Impose, or continue if already imposed, one or more sanctions;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Conduct one or more on-site visits to evaluate progress in correcting a deficiency; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Conduct an additional follow-up survey to determine whether all corrections have been made.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Duration of a Sanction. A sanction shall remain in force until:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A laboratory corrects the deficiency; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A laboratory's license is revoked.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Lifting of a Sanction.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>General Rule. The Secretary may not lift a sanction until regulatory compliance is verified.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Credible Allegation of Compliance. When a sanctioned laboratory submits a credible allegation of compliance, the Secretary shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Determine compliance on the basis of the evidence submitted by the laboratory in its allegation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Conduct a follow-up survey to verify whether the laboratory has achieved compliance; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Both §D(2)(a) and (b) of this regulation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If a laboratory does not correct all deficiencies within 30 days after imposition of a sanction, the Secretary may initiate action to suspend or revoke the license.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Departmental Actions — Principal Sanctions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Hearing Requirement.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except when the Secretary finds that a danger to public health or safety imperatively requires that emergency action be taken to correct a deficiency, the Secretary shall inform the licensee in writing when a suspension or revocation of the licensee's license takes effect, the reason for the suspension or revocation, and that the licensee has an opportunity for a hearing on the matter before the suspension or revocation takes effect, as provided in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-226">State Government Article, §10-226, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When a finding is made that the public health or safety imperatively requires that emergency or immediate action be taken, the Secretary shall inform the licensee in writing of a suspension or revocation of the licensee's license, the reason for the suspension or revocation, and that the licensee has an opportunity for a hearing on the matter, as provided in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 10, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, after the suspension or revocation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Notice.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Contents. In cases involving a principal sanction, the Secretary shall give written notice to a licensee of the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Deficiency identified;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Sanction proposed for imposition;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Reason for the proposed sanction;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Projected effective date and duration of the proposed sanction;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Authority for the proposed sanction; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Time allowed for a laboratory to respond to the notice.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Opportunity to Respond. During the time allowed and stated in the written notice, a laboratory may submit to the Secretary written evidence or other information against imposition of the proposed sanction or sanctions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Notice Times.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If a deficiency is found imperatively to require emergency or immediate action, the Secretary shall provide notice at least 24 hours before the effective date of sanction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If a deficiency is found to warrant a principal sanction but does not imperatively require emergency or immediate action, the Secretary shall provide notice at least 10 days before the effective date of sanction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>To preserve its right to a hearing, a licensee shall request a hearing within 10 days of its receipt of the notice of the pending sanction.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Enforcement Procedures — Proficiency Testing.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Application. If a laboratory's performance in proficiency testing is unsuccessful or unsatisfactory, as set forth in <cite path="|10.10.05">COMAR 10.10.05</cite>, the Secretary may require the laboratory to undertake the directed plan of correction of the training of its personnel or the obtaining of necessary technical assistance, or both, in order to meet the proficiency testing requirements of this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Procedures. A laboratory required to undertake training of personnel or to obtain necessary technical assistance shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Document the training or assistance, or both, using forms provided by the OHCQ; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Submit the completed forms to the OHCQ.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|10|08|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Departmental Action — Reporting Erroneous or Questionable Patient Test Results.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If the Department determines that a licensee has reported an erroneous or questionable patient test result that threatens the health or safety of the patient, the Secretary may order the licensee, within a specified period of time, to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Give prompt notice of the erroneous or questionable patient test result to the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Person who requested that the test be performed; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Physician or other person to whom the laboratory has previously sent a report that contained the erroneous or questionable result;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide corrected reports to the persons notified in <cite path="10|10|08|.05|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Maintain duplicates of both the original report and the corrected report;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Conduct a quality assessment of all phases of the testing process to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Determine the cause of the erroneous or questionable test result; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Take the necessary remedial or corrective action to prevent recurrence of the problem; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Take any additional measures necessary to reduce or eliminate the threat to the health and safety of the patient including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Notifying the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Patient;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Community at large if the Secretary determines that the licensee's laboratory operation is a threat to patient health and safety; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>If the licensee is unable to notify a patient, the Department; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Retesting:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The same specimen;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A new specimen; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Both the same specimen and a new specimen.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Civil Penalty for Failure to Comply with Order.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A laboratory that fails to comply with an order issued by the Secretary under <cite path="10|10|08|.05|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> is subject to a civil penalty of up to $1,000 for each day of noncompliance, up to a maximum of $50,000.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Secretary may impose the civil penalty instead of or in addition to any other sanction imposed under this chapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Notice and Hearing.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notice. Before the Secretary imposes a civil penalty for noncompliance as provided in <cite path="10|10|08|.05|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, the Secretary shall give written notice to the licensee:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Of the intent to impose a civil money penalty; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>That the licensee has an opportunity for a hearing on the matter before the civil penalty is imposed.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Content. The Secretary shall give written notice to the licensee of the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Reason for the imposition of the civil penalty;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Amount of the civil penalty;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Effective date of the imposition of the civil penalty;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Time allowed for the licensee to respond to the notice; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Authority for imposing the civil penalty.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Opportunity to Respond. During the time allowed and stated in the written notice from the Secretary, the licensee may submit to the Secretary written evidence or other information to support the position that the licensee has not violated the requirements of this regulation or Health-General Article, §17-210, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>To preserve the right to a hearing, the licensee shall request a hearing within 10 days of receipt of the notice of the Secretary's intent to impose the civil penalty.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Factors to Be Considered in the Assessment of Penalties. In cases in which the Secretary determines that the imposition of a civil penalty is appropriate, the Secretary shall take into consideration the following factors in determining the amount of the penalty:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The extent to which the licensee derived any financial benefit from reporting erroneous or questionable patient test results;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The willfulness on the part of the licensee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The extent of actual or potential public harm caused by reporting erroneous or questionable patient test results;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The cost of investigating and prosecuting the case against the licensee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The licensee's history of previous failure to meet the standards of this subtitle; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The existence of mitigating factors.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Payment of Penalties.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At the Secretary's discretion, the Secretary may refer all cases of delinquent payment to the Central Collection Unit of the Department of Budget and Management to institute and maintain proceedings to ensure prompt payment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All monies collected by the Secretary pursuant to this regulation shall be paid into the General Fund of the State.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health-General Article, §§17-202, 17-206, 17-210, 17-211, and 17-509, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-12-13">Effective date: December 13, 1999 (26:25 Md. R. 1897)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-06-01"><cite path="|10|10|08|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective June 1, 2009 (36:11 Md. R. 787)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-06-01"><cite path="|10|10|08|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite>, B amended effective June 1, 2009 (36:11 Md. R. 787)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-06-01"><cite path="|10|10|08|.04|B.">Regulation .04B</cite> amended effective June 1, 2009 (36:11 Md. R. 787)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-03-27"><cite path="|10|10|08|.05">Regulation .05</cite> adopted effective March 27, 2006 (33:6 Md. R. 578)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
