<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>13</num>
  <heading>Medical Laboratories — Testing for Hereditary and Congenital Disorders in Newborn Infants</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter, together with <cite path="|10.52.12">COMAR 10.52.12</cite>, establishes a coordinated Statewide system for the screening of newborn infants in the State for certain hereditary and congenital disorders associated with severe problems of health or development.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This chapter also protects the public health by ensuring that accurate and reliable newborn screening and diagnostic test results are provided to a newborn infant's health care providers by requiring a medical laboratory performing screening tests, diagnostic tests, or both, on newborn infants for hereditary disorders, congenital disorders, or both, to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Operate under reliable procedures and test methods;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Employ qualified personnel;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Establish and maintain reliable quality control and quality assurance programs; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Interact effectively with components of the Department's coordinated Statewide Newborn Screening Program to identify newborn infants who may be at risk for a hereditary or congenital disorder.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Identifies standards and requirements for a medical laboratory performing screening tests, diagnostic tests, or both, for hereditary and congenital disorders on blood-spot specimens from newborn infants; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Addresses the following newborn screening and diagnostic tests:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Screening tests, which are:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>First-tier tests; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Supplemental tests; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Diagnostic tests, which are:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Second-tier tests; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Supplemental tests.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|10|13|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Abnormal test result" means a first-tier, supplemental, or second-tier test result that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Falls outside the normal range for the analyte measured; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Triggers a request for additional testing or is diagnostic for a disorder.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Allele.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Allele" means any one of a series of two or more different forms of a gene or DNA sequence that can exist at a single locus on a chromosome.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Allele" includes the gene or DNA sequence for hemoglobin traits and disease states, such as hemoglobin S (HbS) for sickle cell disease.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Analyte" means the substance or chemical constituent in blood being measured in a screening test used to detect the disorders listed in <cite path="|10|10|13|.12|C.">Regulation .12C of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Birthing Facility.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Birthing facility" means a facility that provides the antepartum, intrapartum, and postpartum management and care of women and their newborn infants.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Birthing facility" includes a:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Birthing service that is licensed or accredited as a unit of a hospital; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Freestanding birthing center as defined in <cite path="10.05.02.01|B.">COMAR 10.05.02.01B</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Blood-Spot Specimen.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Blood-spot specimen” means a whole-blood specimen collected from a newborn infant’s heel and applied to the designated area on a blood-spot collection test requisition card for the purpose of performing screening tests.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Blood-spot specimen” includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The first screening blood-spot specimen collected from a newborn infant, usually in the birthing facility or other place where the newborn infant was born, within 48 hours after the newborn infant’s birth;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The second screening blood-spot specimen collected from a newborn infant, usually collected when the newborn infant is between 10 and 14 days of age; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A blood-spot specimen collected subsequent to a blood-spot specimen specified in §B(5)(b)(i) and (ii) of this regulation as required to meet the medical needs and condition of the newborn infant and any additional specific screening blood-spot specimen collection and screening test requirements of this chapter and <cite path="|10.52.12">COMAR 10.52.12</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Borderline result" means a screening test result that is at or near the established cut-off level for a particular analyte.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"CLIA" means the federal Clinical Laboratory Improvement Amendments of 1988.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Congenital Disorder.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Congenital disorder" means a significant structural or functional abnormality of the body that is present at birth.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Congenital disorder" does not include a condition that results from:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>An intrauterine infection; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A birth injury.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Council" means the State Advisory Council on Hereditary and Congenital Disorders.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>“Courier” means an entity employed by a person to convey a blood-spot specimen from the site of blood-spot specimen collection to the laboratory where the blood-spot specimen will be tested.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Cut-off level" means a pre-determined, measurable value established for an analyte detected by a screening test, where that value is used to determine when a newborn infant's test result is normal, borderline, or abnormal.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>"Department" means the Maryland Department of Health.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>"Diagnostic test" means a test that is used to establish or confirm the presence of a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Specific disease; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Hereditary or congenital disorder.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>“First screening” means a screening performed on the first blood-spot specimen collected from a newborn infant after birth.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>“First–tier test” means a blood test performed on a newborn infant’s blood-spot specimen that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Indicates the probable presence or absence of a hereditary or congenital disorder; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Identifies a newborn infant who is at increased risk for a hereditary or congenital disorder.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>“Follow-Up Unit” means the follow-up component and staff of the Department’s Newborn Screening Program, which carries out the duties set forth in <cite path="10.52.12.12">COMAR 10.52.12.12</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>Hereditary Disorder.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Hereditary disorder" means a disorder that:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Is transmissible through the genetic material deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA); or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Arises through the improper processing of information in the genetic material.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Hereditary disorder" includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Hemoglobin disorders;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Metabolic disorders; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Endocrine disorders.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>“Home birth” means the birth of an infant which occurs intentionally outside of a birthing facility.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>“Home birth attendant” means a physician who is licensed to practice under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 14, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, a nurse midwife who is licensed and certified under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 8, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or a direct-entry midwife who is licensed under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 8, Subtitle 6C, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, who is caring for the mother and infant at delivery during a home birth as defined in <cite path="10|10|13|.03|B.|(18)">§B(18) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>"Metabolic Disorder" means a disorder caused by a genetic alteration that results in a defect in the function of a specific enzyme, hormone, or protein, which can be detected by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Direct analysis of the enzyme, hormone, or protein; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Testing for a substance whose metabolism is altered as a result of the defect.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>"Newborn" or "newborn infant" means an infant:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Born in Maryland;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Born on federal property within Maryland;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Born outside of Maryland to parents whose residence is in Maryland;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>From whom a blood-spot specimen was collected and submitted to the Department’s public health laboratory for newborn screening by a birthing facility or other health care provider located in Maryland, regardless of the infant’s place of birth;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Who has a screening test requested by the Follow-Up Unit:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>For first-tier screening follow-up;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>For confirmation of a previous screening test result; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>To assist with a newborn infant's diagnosis, therapy, or follow-up care; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Who is in Maryland.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>Newborn Screening or Screening.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Newborn screening" or "screening" means one or more first-tier tests.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Newborn screening" or "screening" includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>First-tier testing on a first, second, or subsequent blood-spot specimen; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Supplemental first-tier testing.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>Newborn Screening Program.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Newborn Screening Program" means the Department's screening program for hereditary and congenital disorders, which performs operations and activities necessary to ensure that:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Newborn infants are given the opportunity to be tested;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>At risk newborn infants who are tested are identified and located;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Newborn infants are given access to necessary follow-up testing;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Diagnostic tests are available and the diagnosis is made or ruled out; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Newborn infants diagnosed with a hereditary or congenital disorder are given access to treatment.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Newborn Screening Program" includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The Department's public health laboratory as the sole screening laboratory;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Another state's public health laboratory or a commercial laboratory that may serve the State as a screening laboratory during an emergency under a Departmental mutual aid agreement;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Supplemental and second-tier testing performed by a state public health laboratory or by a permitted commercial or research laboratory;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>The Follow-Up Unit; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>The State Advisory Council on Hereditary and Congenital Disorders.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(24)</num>
        <text>"Normal limit" means a measurable, numerical value or range that is considered not to indicate or establish the presence of a hereditary or congenital disorder.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(25)</num>
        <text>"Permittee" means a person issued a permit by the Secretary to operate a medical laboratory as defined in <cite path="10.10.01.03|B.">COMAR 10.10.01.03B</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(26)</num>
        <text>"Public health laboratory" means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Department's public health laboratory; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Another state's public health laboratory or a commercial laboratory permitted in Maryland that is approved under a Departmental emergency mutual aid agreement to perform newborn screening tests on Maryland newborns.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(27)</num>
        <text>Quality Assessment Plan.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Quality assessment plan" means a planned system of step-by-step activities to ensure that:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Testing is carried out according to the manufacturer's instructions;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Testing results are accurate and reliable;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Testing problems and errors are found and corrected to avoid adverse health outcomes for newborn infants; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Testing results are reported and communicated in a timely manner as required by this chapter.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Quality assessment plan" includes the ongoing activities that monitor, review, evaluate, and improve the overall quality of the procedures and processes before, during, and after a test is performed.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(28)</num>
        <text>"Quality control" has the meaning stated in <cite path="10.10.06.03|B.">COMAR 10.10.06.03B</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(29)</num>
        <text>Screening Test.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Screening test" means a first-tier test used to detect a hereditary or congenital disorder listed in <cite path="|10|10|13|.12">Regulation .12 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Screening test” includes a test performed on a:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>First screening blood-spot specimen;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Second screening blood-spot specimen; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Subsequent screening blood-spot specimen.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>"Screening test" does not include a:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Diagnostic test; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Second-tier test.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(30)</num>
        <text>“Second screening” means a test performed on a routine second blood-spot specimen collected when the newborn infant is between 10 and 14 days old even though the test results from the newborn’s first blood-spot specimen were normal.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(31)</num>
        <text>Second-Tier Test.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Second-tier test” means a test performed on a newborn screening blood-spot specimen when a first-tier test provides an abnormal screening test result or a borderline abnormal screening test result.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Second-tier test" includes a test that:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Establishes or confirms a newborn infant's risk for a hereditary or congenital disorder;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Separates a newborn infant into a lower or higher risk category for a hereditary or congenital disorder; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Is diagnostic because it confirms the presence of a hereditary or congenital disorder.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(32)</num>
        <text>"Secretary" means the Secretary of Health or the Secretary's designee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(33)</num>
        <text>“Supplemental test” means a test performed on a blood-spot specimen collected from a newborn infant that is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Used to detect a hereditary or congenital disorder not specified in <cite path="|10|10|13|.12|C.">Regulation .12C of this chapter</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Not required to be performed by the Department's public health laboratory under this chapter or <cite path="|10.52.12">COMAR 10.52.12</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(34)</num>
        <text>“Unsatisfactory blood-spot specimen” means a blood-spot specimen that may produce an inaccurate or unreliable test result because the blood-spot specimen exhibits one of the problems of collection as specified in Regulation .21B and C of this chapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Permit.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Eligibility.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as set forth in a Departmental mutual aid agreement, the Department's public health laboratory is the sole laboratory that may hold a State permit to perform and that may perform a first-tier newborn screening test on a newborn infant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A medical laboratory other than the State's public health laboratory may obtain a permit to perform:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A supplemental test;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A second-tier test; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Supplemental and second-tier tests.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Requirements. Before offering to perform or performing a first-tier, supplemental, or second-tier test on a blood-spot specimen collected from a newborn infant, a person shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Obtain and maintain a valid:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Permit issued by the Secretary to operate a medical laboratory; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>CLIA Certificate from the U.S. Health and Human Services' Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Meet applicable standards and requirements for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A medical laboratory, as set forth in <cite path="|10.10.01">COMAR 10.10.01</cite>—.08; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Testing for hereditary or congenital disorders in a newborn infant as set forth in this chapter.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Inspection Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Inspection Authority. The Department may conduct on-site inspections of a permittee or applicant for a permit to perform supplemental or second-tier tests to screen for or diagnose congenital and hereditary disorders in newborn infants.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Inspection Types. The Department may conduct the following types of inspections to assess compliance with the requirements of this subtitle and <cite path="|10.52.12">COMAR 10.52.12</cite>:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An initial inspection before issuing a permit;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A routine inspection during the permit period; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An inspection subsequent to a complaint.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Fees.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Permit Fees. A permittee or applicant for a permit that is not exempt under <cite path="10.10.04.01|C.">COMAR 10.10.04.01C</cite>, or that is not another state's public health laboratory approved to provide newborn screening tests under a Departmental mutual aid agreement, shall pay to the Department the applicable fees as required by <cite path="|10.10.04">COMAR 10.10.04</cite> and this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Screening and Follow-up Fee Requirement. A birthing center or person responsible for having newborn screening carried out for a newborn infant born outside a birthing facility shall pay a fee of $163.74 per newborn infant to the Department.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Screening and Follow-Up Fee Payment. A birthing center or person responsible for having newborn screening carried out for a newborn infant born outside a birthing facility shall pay to the Department the total fees owed:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>On a quarterly basis; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Within 30 days of receiving an invoice from the Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Director Requirement, Qualifications, and Responsibilities.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Director Requirement. A permittee that offers to perform or performs a first-tier, supplemental, or second-tier test shall employ a director.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Director Qualifications. The director shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Meet the qualifications for a medical laboratory director set forth at <cite path="10.10.07.04">COMAR 10.10.07.04</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Possess a current license as a laboratory director issued by the state in which the laboratory is located if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The laboratory is not located in Maryland; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Licensing is required by the state in which the laboratory is located.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Director Responsibilities. The director is responsible for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The overall operation and administration of the laboratory, including the employment of a sufficient number of competent personnel;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Ensuring that each first-tier, supplemental, or second-tier test conducted is performed accurately and reliably in all aspects of the testing process, including the preanalytic, analytic, and post-analytic phases of the total testing process; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Ensuring compliance with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>This chapter;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The applicable parts of <cite path="|10.10.01">COMAR 10.10.01</cite>— <cite path="|10.10.08">10.10.08</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text><cite path="|10.52.12">COMAR 10.52.12</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Technical Supervisor Requirement, Qualifications, and Responsibilities.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Technical Supervisor Requirement. A permittee that offers to perform or performs a first-tier, supplemental, or second-tier test shall employ a technical supervisor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Director as Technical Supervisor. The director may function as the technical supervisor if the director meets the technical supervisor qualifications specified in this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Technical Supervisor Qualifications. The technical supervisor shall meet the qualifications for a technical supervisor set forth at <cite path="10.10.07.05|A.|(1)">COMAR 10.10.07.05A(1)</cite> and B(7).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Technical Supervisor Responsibilities. A technical supervisor shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Responsible for the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Technical and scientific methods used in the laboratory; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Oversight of the laboratory;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Available to the laboratory personnel on an as-needed basis to provide supervision as specified in this chapter; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Accessible to the laboratory to provide on-site, telephonic, or electronic consultation to laboratory personnel and clients.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|10|13|.09">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Clinical Consultant Requirement, Qualifications, and Responsibilities.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Clinical Consultant Requirement. A permittee that offers to perform or performs first-tier, supplemental, or second-tier tests shall employ a clinical consultant.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Director as Clinical Consultant. The director may function as the clinical consultant if the director meets the qualifications set forth under <cite path="10|10|13|.09|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Clinical Consultant Qualifications. The clinical consultant shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A doctor of medicine or a doctor of osteopathy licensed to practice medicine or osteopathy; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Board certified by the American Board of Medical Genetics as a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Clinical geneticist;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Medical geneticist; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Biochemical geneticist.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Clinical Consultant Responsibilities. A clinical consultant shall provide clinical consultation related to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Inquiries concerning specific newborn screening tests;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Interpretation of specific test results;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Possible diagnostic or supplemental testing; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Assistance in ensuring that appropriate tests are ordered to meet clinical expectations.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>General Supervisor Requirement, Qualifications, and Responsibilities.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General Supervisor Requirement. A permittee that offers to perform or performs first-tier, supplemental, or second-tier tests shall employ a general supervisor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>General Supervisor Qualifications. The general supervisor shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Meet the qualifications for a general supervisor set forth at <cite path="10.10.07.06|B.|(1)">COMAR 10.10.07.06B(1)</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Have at least 6 months experience supervising the operation of applicable test systems, including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Tandem mass spectrophotometry (MS/MS);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Time-resolved immunofluorometry;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) systems; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Isoelectric focusing and high-performance liquid chromatography.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>General Supervisor Responsibilities. A general supervisor shall carry out the responsibilities set forth in 42 CFR §493.1463, including:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Supervising the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Day-to-day operation of the laboratory; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Personnel performing tests and reporting test results; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Being accessible to testing personnel at all times testing is performed to provide on-site, telephonic, or electronic consultation and resolve technical problems in accordance with policies and procedures established and approved by the director and technical supervisor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Testing Personnel Requirement and Qualifications.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Requirement. A permittee that offers to perform or performs first-tier, supplemental, or second-tier tests shall employ sufficient laboratory testing personnel to perform testing in accordance with the requirements of this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Qualifications. Testing personnel shall meet the qualifications set forth at <cite path="10.10.07.07">COMAR 10.10.07.07</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|10|13|.12">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>First-Tier, Supplemental, and Second-Tier Tests.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>First-Tier Tests; Requirement. The Department’s public health laboratory shall perform first-tier tests on all screening blood-spot specimens collected from a newborn infant.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>First-Tier Tests; Testing Limitations.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Only the Department's public health laboratory may screen for the disorders listed in <cite path="10|10|13|.12|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A permittee may perform a supplemental or a second-tier test only when the test is requested by an individual authorized to request a medical laboratory test as provided in <cite path="10.10.06.02">COMAR 10.10.06.02</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>First-Tier Tests. The Department’s public health laboratory shall perform a first-tier test on a newborn infant to screen for the following hereditary and congenital disorders, which are approved for screening by the Council and the Secretary:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Biotinidase deficiency;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Congenital adrenal hyperplasia (CAH);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Hypothyroidism;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Galactosemia, galactose-1-phosphate uridyl transferase deficiency (GALT);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Epimerase Galactosemia, uridine diphosphate-galactose-4-epimerase deficiency (GALE);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Galactokinase Galactosemia, galactokinase deficiency (GALK1);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Sickle cell disease;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Sickle cell disease: S beta-thalessemia;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Sickle C disease: SC disease;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Other hemoglobin variants;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Phenylketonuria (PKU);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Hyperphenylalaninemia (Hyper-PHE);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Biopterin cofactor biosynthesis defects (BIOPT-BS);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>Biopterin cofactor regeneration defects (BIOPT-REG);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>Tyrosinemia, type I;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>Tyrosinemia, type II;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>Tyrosinemia, type III;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>Homocystinuria;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>Hypermethioninemia;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>Branched chain ketoaciduria (BCK), also called maple syrup urine disease (MSUD);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>Citrullinemia, type I;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>Citrullinemia, type II;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>Arginosuccinic aciduria;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(24)</num>
        <text>Argininemia;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(25)</num>
        <text>Methylmalonic acidemia, mutase deficiency (MMA);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(26)</num>
        <text>Methylmalonic acidemia, adenosylcobalamin synthesis defects A and B (Cbl A, B);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(27)</num>
        <text>Methylmalonic acidemia, adenosylcobalamin synthesis defects C and D (Cbl C, D);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(28)</num>
        <text>Propionic acidemia (PA);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(29)</num>
        <text>Isovaleric acidemia (IVA);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(30)</num>
        <text>Glutaric aciduria type I (GA I);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(31)</num>
        <text>3-Hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl-CoA (HMG) lysase deficiency;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(32)</num>
        <text>Isobutryl-CoA dehydrogenase (IBCD) deficiency;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(33)</num>
        <text>2-Methylbutyryl-CoA dehydrogenase deficiency (2MBG);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(34)</num>
        <text>3-Methlycrotonyl-CoA carboxylase deficiency (3MCC);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(35)</num>
        <text>3-Methlyglutaconyl-CoA hydratase deficiency (3MGA);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(36)</num>
        <text>2-Methyl-3-hydroxybutyrl-CoA dehydrogenase deficiency (2M3HBA);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(37)</num>
        <text>Mitochondrial acetoacetyl-CoA thiolase (3-ketothiolase) deficiency (BKT);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(38)</num>
        <text>Multiple carboxylase deficiency (MCD);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(39)</num>
        <text>Malonic acidemia (MAL);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(40)</num>
        <text>Medium chain acyl-CoA dehydrogenase deficiency (MCAD);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(41)</num>
        <text>Medium chain ketoacyl-CoA thiolase deficiency (MCKAT);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(42)</num>
        <text>Short chain acyl-CoA dehydrogenase deficiency (SCAD);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(43)</num>
        <text>Short chain 3-hydroxy acyl Co-A dehydrogenase deficiency (SCHAD);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(44)</num>
        <text>Very long chain acyl-CoA dehydrogenase deficiency (VLCAD);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(45)</num>
        <text>3-hydroxy long chain acyl-CoA dehydrogenase deficiency (LCHAD);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(46)</num>
        <text>Multiple acyl-CoA dehydrogenase (MAD) or glutaric acidemia type II deficiency (GA II);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(47)</num>
        <text>Carnitine/acylcarnitine translocase deficiency (translocase deficiency);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(48)</num>
        <text>Carnitine palmitoyl transferase type I deficiency (CPT I);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(49)</num>
        <text>Carnitine palmitoyl transferase type II deficiency (CPT II);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(50)</num>
        <text>Carnitine uptake disorder;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(51)</num>
        <text>Trifunctional protein deficiency (TFP);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(52)</num>
        <text>2,4-dienoyl-CoA reductase deficiency (DE RED);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(53)</num>
        <text>Cystic fibrosis;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(54)</num>
        <text>Severe combined immunodeficiency (SCID);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(55)</num>
        <text>Pompe disease;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(56)</num>
        <text>Fabry disease;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(57)</num>
        <text>Spinal muscular atrophy (SMA);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(58)</num>
        <text>Mucopolysaccharidosis type I (MPS I);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(59)</num>
        <text>Mucopolysaccharidosis type II (MPS II);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(60)</num>
        <text>X-linked Adrenoleukodystrophy (X-ALD); and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(61)</num>
        <text>Guanidinoacetate Methyltransferase Deficiency (GAMT).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Approved Methods:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A permittee shall use:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A colorimetric method for testing for a biotinidase deficiency, which is the disorder listed at <cite path="10|10|13|.12|C.|(1)">§C(1) of this regulation</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A fluorometric method when testing for galactosemia, which is the disorder listed at §C(4)—(6) of this regulation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A fluorescent-linked immunoassay method when testing for the hereditary or congenital disorders listed in §C(2) and (3) of this regulation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Isoelectric focusing followed by high-performance liquid chromatography when testing for sickle cell disease, which is the disorder listed at §C(7)—(10) of this regulation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Tandem mass-spectrometry when testing for the metabolic disorders listed in §C(11)—(52) of this regulation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>IRT/IRT (immunoreactive trypsinogen/immuno-reactive trypsinogen) when testing for cystic fibrosis, which is the disorder listed in <cite path="10|10|13|.12|C.|(53)">§C(53) of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Real time polymerase chain reaction method when testing for severe combined immunodeficiency, which is listed in <cite path="10|10|13|.12|C.|(54)">§C(54) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A permittee shall have 60 days from the amendment's effective date to comply with any amendment made by the Secretary to <cite path="10|10|13|.12|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Screening Test Blood-Spot Specimens — Collection and Test Requisition.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Blood-Spot Specimen Collection.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person shall collect a newborn infant’s blood-spot specimen for testing under this chapter by using only the special blood-spot specimen collection test requisition card provided by the Department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Department shall provide the special blood-spot specimen collection test requisition card to the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Individual in charge of a birthing facility or the individual’s designated representative; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Home birth attendant.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The individual in charge of a birthing facility or the individual’s designated representative, or the home birth attendant shall collect a blood-spot specimen consisting of heel-stick whole blood obtained:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>When a newborn infant is 24 to 48 hours old;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>On a blood-spot specimen collection test requisition card provided by the Department; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>As set forth in <cite path="|10|10|13|.14">Regulation .14 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Blood-Spot Specimen Collection Test Requisition Card Information. An individual shall record the following information as specified on the Department-supplied blood-spot specimen collection test requisition card:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Newborn infant information, including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Name;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Date of birth;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Time of birth;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Current weight;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Gender;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Race;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Gestational age;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Birthing facility identification, including the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Facility name;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Facility street address, city, state, and zip code; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Newborn infant's medical record or chart number;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Date and time of first feeding;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Type of feeding, such as:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Breast;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Lactose-containing formula; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Formula containing no lactose;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Transfusion history, including transfusion date and time;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>General health status of the newborn infant; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>The total protein and calorie intake for any newborn infant in a neonatal intensive care setting;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Blood-spot specimen information, including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Date of collection;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Time of collection; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Initials or other identifier of the individual who collected the blood-spot specimen;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Mother or guardian information, including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Name;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Street address, city, state, and zip code; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Telephone number where the mother or guardian may be reached;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Information on the pediatrician or attending physician who will be following the newborn infant, including the physician's:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Name;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Street address, city, state, and zip code; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Telephone number; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Other information that can affect the test results or the interpretation of the test results when applicable, such as that antibiotics were administered to the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Mother; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Newborn infant.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Screening Test Blood-Spot Specimens — Procedures, Submission, and Delivery Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Standard Operating Procedure. The individual in charge of a birthing facility or the individual’s designated representative, or the home birth attendant shall maintain written standard operating procedures for the collection, handling, storage, and transport of newborn infant blood-spot specimen collection test requisition cards, including instructions for staff to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Ensure and maintain blood-spot specimen integrity, quality, and acceptability;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Ensure proper:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Site preparation and cleaning;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Performance of the heel stick puncture; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Application of whole blood to the collection test requisition card;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Identify precautions against:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Milking or squeezing the blood-spot specimen collection site;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Layering successive drops of blood on the same circle on the blood-spot specimen collection test requisition card;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Filling the circles on both sides of the filter paper;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Touching or smearing a blood-spot specimen before it is fully air-dried;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Scratching or abrading the blood-spot specimen;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Not allowing a blood-spot specimen to dry thoroughly before sending the blood-spot specimen collection test requisition card to a laboratory; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Damaging, stretching, or wrinkling the filter paper before, during or after blood-spot specimen collection;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Recognize unsatisfactory blood-spot specimens; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Handle and temporarily store a blood-spot specimen collection test requisition card, including the procedures and techniques for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Drying blood-spot specimens;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Stacking of blood-spot specimen collection test requisition cards; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Temporarily storing blood-spot specimen collection test requisition cards.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Submission and Delivery Requirements. The individual in charge of a birthing facility or the individual’s designated representative, or the home birth attendant shall transport and deliver to the Department’s public health laboratory a newborn infant blood-spot specimen collection test requisition card using:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An employee or private courier;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A commercial carrier providing:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Overnight express delivery; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Priority delivery;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A county or State operated courier system, where that service is available; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A combination of §B(1)—(3) of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Test Blood-Spot Specimens — Use, Research, Storage, and Retention.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Use. A permittee may use a newborn infant blood-spot specimen from a newborn infant to test for only the conditions listed in <cite path="|10|10|13|.12|C.">Regulation .12C of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Research. A researcher may not use a Maryland newborn infant’s blood spot specimen or test results for research purposes unless the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Research is approved in writing by the Department's:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Newborn Screening Program; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Institutional Review Board; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Researcher acknowledges in writing that the researcher will return all untested blood-spot specimens to the Department’s public health laboratory within 6 months of completing the approved research.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Storage. A permittee or researcher shall store a newborn infant blood-spot specimen in a sealed, moisture-proof container at between 2ºC and 6ºC.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Retention.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A permittee shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Retain a newborn infant’s gel, produced when testing for hemoglobin disorders, for at least 90 days after testing is complete; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Return to the State’s public health laboratory all untested blood-spot specimens received from the Department’s public health laboratory for supplemental or diagnostic testing within 90 days after testing is completed by the permittee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Department’s public health laboratory shall retain and maintain for 25 years a newborn infant’s blood-spot specimen after the blood-spot specimen is received for screening, supplemental testing, or diagnostic testing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Test Records — Retention.</heading>
    <text>The Department’s public health laboratory shall retain and maintain electronically or as a hard copy for 25 years the:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Top copy of the requisition portion of the blood-spot specimen collection test requisition card;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>All test results and reports;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Electronic data bases; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Supporting documents that show how a reported test result was obtained and verified, including but not limited to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Quality control records;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Instrument maintenance and repair records;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Test reagent records; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Instrument and test system data.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.17</num>
    <heading>Testing — First-Tier.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Department’s public health laboratory shall test, using first-tier tests, appropriately timed and collected blood-spot specimen of a newborn infant’s blood for the disorders listed in <cite path="|10|10|13|.12|C.">Regulation .12C of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Full-Term Healthy Newborn Infants.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a newborn infant is born at term and is healthy, the Department’s public health laboratory shall conduct a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>First screening using first-tier tests to detect the disorders listed in <cite path="|10|10|13|.12|C.">Regulation .12C of this chapter</cite> on a blood-spot specimen collected when the full-term healthy newborn infant is between 24 and 48 hours old; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Second screening using first-tier tests on a blood-spot specimen collected when the full-term healthy infant is between 10 and 14 days old.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the first blood-spot specimen is collected when a full term healthy newborn infant is younger than 24 hours old, the Department’s public health laboratory shall conduct a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Second screening using first-tier tests to detect the disorders listed in <cite path="|10|10|13|.12|C.">Regulation .12C of this chapter</cite> on a blood-spot specimen collected when the newborn infant is between 24 hours and 7 days old; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Third screening using first-tier tests on a blood-spot specimen collected when the full-term healthy infant is between 1 and 4 weeks old.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Premature or Ill Newborn Infant.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a newborn infant who is born prematurely or expected to be ill for more than 14 days was younger than 24 hours old when the blood-spot specimen was collected for a first screening, the Department’s public health laboratory shall conduct a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Second screening using first-tier tests to detect the disorders listed in <cite path="|10|10|13|.12|C.">Regulation .12C of this chapter</cite> when the newborn infant is between 24 hours and 3 days old; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Third screening using first-tier tests when the newborn infant is between 7 days and 14 days old to screen for:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Amino acid disorders as specified in Regulation .12C(11)—(24) of this chapter;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Acylcarnitine disorders as specified in Regulation .12C(25)—(52) of this chapter;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Congenital hypothyroidism as specified in <cite path="|10|10|13|.12|C.|(4)">Regulation .12C(4) of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Severe combined immunodeficiency, as specified in <cite path="|10|10|13|.12|C.|(54)">Regulation .12C(54) of this chapter</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a newborn infant who is born prematurely or expected to be ill for more than 14 days was 24 hours old or older at the time the newborn infant’s blood-spot specimen was collected for a first screening, the Department’s public health laboratory shall perform a second screening to screen for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Amino acid disorders as specified in Regulation .12C(11)—(24) of this chapter;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Acylcarnitine disorders as specified in Regulation .12C(25)—(52) of this chapter;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Congenital hypothyroidism as specified in <cite path="|10|10|13|.12|C.|(4)">Regulation .12C(4) of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Severe combined immunodeficiency, as specified in <cite path="|10|10|13|.12|C.|(54)">Regulation .12C(54) of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If a newborn infant was transfused before the blood-spot specimen was collected for a first screening, the Department’s public health laboratory shall conduct, in addition to any other screenings specified in §B(1) and (2) of this regulation, a fourth screening using first-tier tests on a blood-spot specimen collected 4 months after a newborn infant’s last transfusion to screen for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Hemoglobin as specified in Regulation .12C(7)—(10) of this chapter;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Biotinidase as specified in <cite path="|10|10|13|.12|C.|(1)">Regulation .12C(1) of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Galactose-1-P-uridyl-1-transferase as specified in <cite path="|10|10|13|.12|C.|(3)">Regulation .12C(3) of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.18</num>
    <heading>Testing — Second-Tier and Supplemental.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>When a test request is made by an individual authorized to request a laboratory test, as set out in <cite path="10.10.06.02">COMAR 10.10.06.02</cite>:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A permittee other than the Department's public health laboratory may perform a second-tier or supplemental test; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Department's public health laboratory may perform a second-tier test.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A permittee:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>May not contract out, subcontract, or otherwise transfer supplemental or second-tier testing to another laboratory that does not hold a Maryland permit in the discipline of diagnostic and supplemental testing for hereditary and congenital disorders in newborns;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shall complete a second-tier or supplemental test on a blood-spot specimen within 3 working days after the blood-spot specimen arrives at the laboratory; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Shall report the results of a second-tier or supplemental screening test as required in Regulations .23 and .24 of this chapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|10|13|.19">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.19</num>
    <heading>Proficiency and Competency Testing for Newborn Screening Tests.</heading>
    <text>A permittee shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Meet all requirements set forth in <cite path="|10.10.05">COMAR 10.10.05</cite>;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Successfully participate in one or more approved proficiency testing programs that cover all first-tier, second-tier, and supplementary tests offered or performed;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Evaluate and document performance, semiannually during the first year of testing and annually thereafter, of all individuals responsible for testing; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>In addition to the proficiency testing requirement in <cite path="10|10|13|.19|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, participate in the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention's Newborn Screening Quality Assurance Program.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.20</num>
    <heading>Quality Control.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Quality Control Program.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A permittee shall develop, establish, implement, maintain and follow written quality control policies, procedures, and techniques that provide and ensure accurate, reliable, and valid test results and reports.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A permittee's quality control program shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Cover all tests, methods, and procedures performed by the laboratory; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Meet the standards and requirements set forth in this chapter and <cite path="|10.10.06">COMAR 10.10.06</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A permittee's quality control procedures and practices shall include, but are not limited to, the use of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Analyses of reference materials to ensure the reproducibility and accuracy of test results;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Systems to ensure proper functioning of instruments, equipment, reagents, and performance of laboratory personnel;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Valid reagents, equipment, calibration, and systematic procedural checks;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A system that ensures timely and pertinent error detection and correction for the review and reporting of test results; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Quality control materials from the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention's Newborn Screening Quality Assurance Program.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Adequacy of Methods and Equipment. To ensure the adequacy of test methods, test systems, and equipment, a permittee shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Employ methods, test systems, and equipment that provide accurate and reliable test results and reports;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Have sufficient and suitable equipment and instruments to perform the type and volume of tests offered and performed by the laboratory;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Perform tests in a manner that provides accurate and reliable test results;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Monitor test methods, instruments, and testing systems, where applicable, for the following performance characteristics:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Method, instrument, and test system detection limits and cutoff levels;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Precision;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Accuracy;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Specificity;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Sensitivity;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Interferences; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Other related test variables that affect test results; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Have adequate quality control systems and procedures in place to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Obtain and verify a statistically valid number of counts or measurement levels to give accurate and reliable test results for an analytical instrument, each day an instrument is used for testing; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Report results:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>As set forth in <cite path="10.10.06.04">COMAR 10.10.06.04</cite>;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>As set forth in 42 CFR §493.1291; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Within the time frames required by this chapter.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Supplies, Reagents, and Materials.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A permittee shall ensure that supplies, reagents, and other materials used in the collected, handling, testing, and storing of newborn blood-spot specimens are stored, labeled, checked for proper reactivity, and used according to the provisions of this chapter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A permittee shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Label laboratory supplies and materials used in the testing process, including reagents, solutions, controls, and calibrators to indicate the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Identity of reagents, solutions, controls, and calibrators;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Strength or concentration;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Storage requirements;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Preparation and expiration date;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Identity of the preparer; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Other pertinent information that affects test performance;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Store laboratory materials in the manner recommended by the manufacturer;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Test representative samples of each lot of materials used for or in the process of testing blood-spot specimens on a regularly scheduled basis to determine that each lot of test material is capable of performing as required; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Use supplies, reagents, kits, test systems, and other materials in a manner consistent with the recommendations and instructions provided by the manufacturer.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A permittee may not use supplies, reagents, kits, test systems, or other materials in the testing process that have:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Exceeded the materials' established expiration dates;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Substandard reactivity; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Deteriorated.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|10|13|.21">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.21</num>
    <heading>Quality Assessment and Quality Assurance.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A permittee shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Establish and follow a written quality assessment plan that covers all phases of the testing process;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Meet the applicable quality assurance requirements of <cite path="|10.10.06">COMAR 10.10.06</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Have an accessioning mechanism or system that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Tracks blood-spot specimens and allows first and subsequent blood-spot specimens and test results from the same newborn infant to be linked for testing and analysis; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Identifies a specific analyte that requires retesting when a newborn infant's prior screening test results for that analyte are abnormal or border-line abnormal.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A permittee may not test a blood-spot specimen exhibiting:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Blood that did not saturate the filter paper;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A circle containing no blood;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A blood clot or tissue on the surface of the blood;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A circle over-saturated with blood showing dark areas in the circle or at the perimeter;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Blood that appears layered or clotted; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Serum rings or blood that appears diluted, discolored, or contaminated.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A permittee may not test a blood-spot specimen:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Collected more than 10 days before the screening test is to be started;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>That is unaccompanied by information necessary for the testing to be meaningful, including the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Age of the newborn infant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Identification of the newborn infant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Date and time of blood-spot specimen collection;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Date and time of birth;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Newborn infant's weight; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Date and time of a newborn infant's first feeding;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If an infant was transfused before the first screening and the repeat blood-spot specimen collected to test for hemoglobin was drawn earlier than 4 months after the last transfusion; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the newborn infant was younger than 24 hours old or the newborn's age was unknown at the time of collection and the requested screening test is for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Congenital adrenal hyperplasia as specified in <cite path="|10|10|13|.12|C.|(2)">Regulation .12C(2) of this chapter</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Thyroxine or thyroid stimulating hormone as specified in <cite path="|10|10|13|.12|C.|(4)">Regulation .12C(4) of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Within 24 hours of receipt of an unsatisfactory blood-spot specimen, the permittee shall notify the submitter of the unsatisfactory blood-spot specimen by telephone, facsimile, or electronic mail:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>That the blood-spot specimen cannot be tested; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>To submit another blood-spot specimen as soon as possible.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If a permittee reports a test result on a newborn infant and later discovers that the test result was erroneous or questionable, the permittee shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Give prompt notice of the erroneous or questionable patient test result to the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Person who requested that the test be performed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Physician or other person to whom the laboratory has previously sent a report that contained the erroneous or questionable result; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Follow-Up Unit;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide corrected reports to the persons notified in <cite path="10|10|13|.21|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Maintain duplicates of both the original report and the corrected report;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Conduct a quality assessment of all phases of the testing process to determine the cause of the erroneous or questionable test result;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Take the necessary remedial or corrective action to prevent recurrence of the problem; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Take any additional measures necessary to reduce or eliminate the threat to the health and safety of the patient including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Notifying a parent or guardian of the newborn infant of the erroneous or questionable result;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Retesting the same blood-spot specimen;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Testing a new blood-spot specimen; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Retesting the same blood-spot specimen and testing a new blood-spot specimen.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.22</num>
    <heading>Quality Assurance — Continuity of Operations and Disaster Recovery Plan.</heading>
    <text>A permittee shall develop, implement, and maintain written continuity of operations and disaster recovery plans that ensure the continuous performance of essential functions and operations:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>During an emergency; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>When the laboratory temporarily can no longer meet the requirements and standards set forth in this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|10|13|.23">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.23</num>
    <heading>Reporting Test Results.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>All Test Results. For a newborn infant, a permittee shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Report all first-tier, supplemental, and second-tier results to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The person who requested the test; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An individual who will use the test results in identifying, tracking, caring for, and treating the newborn infant, including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A physician specialist; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Personnel in the Follow-Up Unit;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Report to the persons listed in <cite path="10|10|13|.23|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite> within 3 working days after the laboratory obtains the blood-spot specimen, all test results that are within normal limits;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Report to a person requesting a second or subsequent screening the test results from the newborn infant's prior screening if not previously reported to the person;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Include with each report the following information:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Date the blood-spot specimen was received in the laboratory;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Date of the report; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Cut-off level for each reported analyte; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Report all abnormal test results to the Follow-Up Unit on the same day that a test result is obtained and reviewed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Specific Test results. A permittee may not report a test result as being within normal limits for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Amino acid levels for disorders specified in Regulation .12C(11)—(24) of this chapter and for a total galactose level for galactosemia as specified in <cite path="|10|10|13|.12|C.|(3)">Regulation .12C(3) of this chapter</cite> if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A newborn infant was not on milk or formula feeding at least 24 hours before the blood-spot specimen was collected; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The time of milk or formula feeding is unknown; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>17-hydroxy progesterone results for congenital adrenal hyperplasia as specified in <cite path="|10|10|13|.12|C.|(2)">Regulation .12C(2) of this chapter</cite> and thyroxine and thyroid stimulating hormone for hypothyroidism as specified in <cite path="|10|10|13|.12|C.|(4)">Regulation .12C(4) of this chapter</cite> if the blood-spot specimen was collected when the newborn infant was:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Younger than 24 hours old; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Of unknown age.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|10|13|.24">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.24</num>
    <heading>Reporting Abnormal Test Results to the Follow-Up Unit.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Reporting Requirements. A permittee shall immediately report an abnormal or diagnostic test result to the Follow-Up Unit by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Telephoning and personally speaking to an individual in the Follow-Up Unit;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Telephoning and personally speaking to a back-up individual representing the Follow-Up Unit, if an attempt to make in-person contact with an employee of the Follow-Up Unit fails; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Following up a telephonic report within 24 hours with a report by facsimile or electronic mail to the Follow-Up Unit.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Verification Requirement. A permittee shall contact the Follow-Up Unit by telephone at least once every 6 months to ensure that the permittee is able to meet the requirements in <cite path="10|10|13|.24|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Reporting Requirements; General. A permittee shall provide with each abnormal result, where applicable, the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Identity or name of each analyte measured;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Measured numerical concentration or range of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Each analyte measured; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>All related analytes measured;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Value of any relevant ratios used to determine abnormality;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Postnatal age of the newborn infant;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Appropriate gestational age/birth weight control range;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Cut-off level for the analyte of a hereditary or congenital disorder; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Measure of the degree of abnormality of the test result.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Reporting Requirements; Sickle Cell Disease Hemoglobin. A permittee shall report results for hemoglobin disorders as specified in Regulation .12C(7)—(10) of this chapter for sickle cell disease in terminology that includes:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The alleles present in decreasing quantitative order; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Specifying trait states and possible disease states for at least the following alleles:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Hemoglobin C;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Hemoglobin D;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Hemoglobin E;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Hemoglobin G;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Hemoglobin O; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Hemoglobin S.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.25</num>
    <heading>Reporting System and Communication Software.</heading>
    <text>A permittee shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Have available and use a reliable and accurate electronic information system that is capable of collecting, compiling, transferring, and communicating all normal and abnormal test results to the Follow-Up Unit; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Provide the Follow-Up Unit, where applicable, with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The necessary information system and electronic communications software or interface to be used by the Follow-Up Unit to receive from the permittee the newborn screening test results and reports required in this chapter; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Software programming assistance to ensure that the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Permittee's data transmitted to the Follow-Up Unit is accurate and timely; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Follow-Up Unit's information system maintains compatibility with the permittee's information system.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.26</num>
    <heading>Availability of Statistical and Scientific Data.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Statistical Reports. The State’s public health laboratory, the Follow-Up Unit, or both, on request, shall provide Newborn Screening Program statistical data for official State and national reports to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Council;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Department's Office of Genetics and Children with Special Healthcare Needs; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>State and federal agencies that use test results and statistics for the care and treatment of newborn infants.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Research Investigations. The Laboratories Administration, the Follow-Up Unit, or both, may participate in research investigations approved by the Department's Institutional Review Board.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|10|13|.27">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.27</num>
    <heading>Sanctions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Due to the life-threatening nature and effect of errors in newborn screening testing, the Secretary may order summarily the suspension of a permit if the Secretary finds that the public health, safety, or welfare imperatively requires emergency action, including but not limited to, if a permittee has:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Failed to report a newborn infant's abnormal test result as required in this chapter;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Falsified a document submitted to the Department, including but not limited to a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Newborn infant screening test report; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Quality control or quality assurance report; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Failed to provide a corrected or amended test report if the permittee has reported an erroneous or questionable test result.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the Secretary summarily suspends a permit as provided in <cite path="10|10|13|.27|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, the Secretary shall promptly give the permittee:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Written notice of the suspension, the finding, and the reasons that support the finding; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An opportunity to be heard.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Secretary may impose a directed plan of correction, limit testing, deny a permit renewal, or suspend or revoke a current permit if a permittee has:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Failed to meet the applicable standards and requirements set forth in:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Health-General Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text><cite path="|10.10.01">COMAR 10.10.01</cite>—.08 and this chapter;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Conducted research on newborn infant blood-spot specimens within the Newborn Screening Program’s approval as required in <cite path="|10|10|13|.15">Regulation .15 of this chapter</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Failed to pay the Department any fee required under this subtitle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>In addition to sanctions provided in §§A and C of this regulation, the Secretary may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Impose any sanction provided in <cite path="|10.10.08">COMAR 10.10.08</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Refer a person for criminal prosecution, as provided at Health-General Article, §17-216, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A person may have a hearing on the imposition of a sanction and an opportunity to respond to a sanction imposed by the Secretary under this regulation as set forth in <cite path="10.10.08.03">COMAR 10.10.08.03</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in §§A and B of this regulation, before the Secretary denies, suspends, or revokes a permit, the Secretary shall give the applicant or permittee notice of the action and an opportunity to be heard.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health-General Article, §§13-101—13-103, 13-108—13-112, 13-601—13-605, 17-201—17-206, 17-210,<br/>17-211, 17-215, and 17-216, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-03-23">Regulations <cite path="|10|10|13|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|10|13|.27">.27</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective January 1, 2009 (36:2 Md. R. 97); adopted permanently effective March 23, 2009 (36:6 Md. R. 490)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-04-24"><cite path="|10|10|13|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended effective April 24, 2017 (44:8 Md. R. 404)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-04-24"><cite path="|10|10|13|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite> amended effective April 24, 2017 (44:8 Md. R. 404)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-04-24"><cite path="|10|10|13|.04|B.">Regulation .04B</cite> amended effective April 24, 2017 (44:8 Md. R. 404)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-08-20"><cite path="|10|10|13|.06|B.">Regulation .06B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 1, 2012 (39:15 Md. R. 962); amended permanently effective August 20, 2012 (39:16 Md. R. 1080)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-04-14"><cite path="|10|10|13|.06|B.">Regulation .06B</cite> amended effective April 27, 2015 (42:8 Md. R. 608); April 14, 2025 (52:7 Md. R. 321)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-04-24"><cite path="|10|10|13|.12">Regulation .12</cite> amended effective April 24, 2017 (44:8 Md. R. 404)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-04-14"><cite path="|10|10|13|.12|C.">Regulation .12C</cite> amended effective August 23, 2021 (48:17 Md. R. 669); April 14, 2025 (52:7 Md. R. 321)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-04-24"><cite path="|10|10|13|.13">Regulation .13</cite> amended effective April 24, 2017 (44:8 Md. R. 404)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-04-24"><cite path="|10|10|13|.14">Regulation .14</cite> amended effective April 24, 2017 (44:8 Md. R. 404)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-04-24"><cite path="|10|10|13|.15">Regulation .15</cite> amended effective April 24, 2017 (44:8 Md. R. 404)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-04-24"><cite path="|10|10|13|.16">Regulation .16</cite> amended effective April 24, 2017 (44:8 Md. R. 404)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-04-24"><cite path="|10|10|13|.17">Regulation .17</cite> amended effective April 24, 2017 (44:8 Md. R. 404)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-04-24"><cite path="|10|10|13|.18|B.">Regulation .18B</cite> amended effective April 24, 2017 (44:8 Md. R. 404)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-04-24"><cite path="|10|10|13|.20|A.">Regulation .20A</cite>, C amended effective April 24, 2017 (44:8 Md. R. 404)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-04-24"><cite path="|10|10|13|.21">Regulation .21</cite> amended effective April 24, 2017 (44:8 Md. R. 404)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-04-24"><cite path="|10|10|13|.23">Regulation .23</cite> amended effective April 24, 2017 (44:8 Md. R. 404)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-04-24"><cite path="|10|10|13|.24|A.">Regulation .24A</cite>, D amended effective April 24, 2017 (44:8 Md. R. 404)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-04-24"><cite path="|10|10|13|.25">Regulation .25</cite> amended effective April 24, 2017 (44:8 Md. R. 404)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-04-24"><cite path="|10|10|13|.26|A.">Regulation .26A</cite> amended effective April 24, 2017 (44:8 Md. R. 404)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-04-24"><cite path="|10|10|13|.27|C.">Regulation .27C</cite> amended effective April 24, 2017 (44:8 Md. R. 404)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
