<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>09</num>
  <heading>Program Requirements</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|17|09|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Activities, Materials and Equipment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An operator shall provide to each group of children in care a sufficient quantity and variety of materials and equipment for indoor and outdoor activities according to the number and ages of the children.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Activity materials and equipment provided to a child shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Appropriate to the child's age and developmental status;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Safe;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>In good repair;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Clean;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Nontoxic; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Free from hazards, including lead paint.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Furnishings used by a child shall be scaled in proportion to the child's size.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The operator shall provide multipurpose tables and chairs.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Screen Time Activities.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Definitions. In this section, the following terms have the meanings indicated:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Interactive technology” means educational and age-appropriate technology, including programs, applications (apps), noncommercial television programming, videos, streaming media, and ebooks, that is designed to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Facilitate active and creative use of technology; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Encourage social engagement with other children and adults.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Passive technology” means noninteractive television, videos, and streaming media.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Limited use of appropriate interactive technology may support, but may not replace, creative play, physical activity, hands-on exploration, outdoor experiences, social interactions, and other developmentally appropriate learning activities for children.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Viewing Restrictions. Except as set forth in <cite path="13A|17|09|.01|E.|(4)">§E(4) of this regulation</cite>, a child in attendance may not be permitted to view more than 30 minutes of age-appropriate, educational passive technology per week.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Exceptions.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An occasional exception to the weekly passive technology viewing limit set forth in <cite path="13A|17|09|.01|E.|(3)">§E(3) of this regulation</cite> may be made for a special event or project, including a holiday or birthday celebration.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If an exception to the weekly passive technology viewing limit is made, a written record of the exception shall be made and retained on file that documents the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Nature and duration of the programming viewed; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Reason for the exception.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>No child may be permitted to view any:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Passive or interactive technology during a meal or a snack; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Media with brand placement or advertising for unhealthy or sugary food or beverages.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The operator shall give the parent of each enrolled child a written screen time policy that addresses the use of passive and interactive technology during child care hours.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Upon the request of a parent of a child in care, the operator shall assist the parent with scheduling a time and convenient location for the local lead agency responsible for administering the Maryland Infants and Toddlers Program to provide the appropriate screening for the child.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Rest Furnishings.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>There shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A suitable cot or mat for each child 2 to 5 years old present in the facility for more than 4 hours, and for children 5 years old or older who regularly take rest periods in the facility;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A suitable bed for each child who is present in the facility during those hours that are usual nighttime sleep hours for that child; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An adequate supply of clean bedding provided for each child who takes rest periods at the facility.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>When in use, all cots, mats, and beds shall be appropriately spaced to facilitate safe movement and evacuation of staff and children.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Storage.</heading>
    <text>There shall be appropriate storage for:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Materials and equipment;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Mats, cots, beds, and bedding;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Portable equipment intended for outdoor use;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Each child's clothing and possessions in an individual space; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Materials, equipment, furnishings, and supplies being held in reserve.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Education Article §§9.5-115, 9.5-401, 9.5-404, 9.5-405, 9.5-409, 905-411, and 9.5-413—9.5-418; Family Law Article §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|5-550">5-550</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|5-551">5-551</cite>;<br/><cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-333">General Provisions Article, §4-333</cite>; <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ghu|1-202">Human Services Article, §1-202</cite>; Annotated Code of Maryland<br/>Agency Note: Federal Statutory Reference—Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (42 U.S.C. §12101 et seq.);<br/>Pro-Children Act of 1994 (20 U.S.C. §6081 et seq.)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-10-20">Effective date: October 20, 2008 (35:21 Md. R. 1827)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-07-20"><cite path="|13A|17|09|.01|E.">Regulation .01E</cite> adopted effective July 20, 2015 (42:14 Md. R. 883)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-03-17"><cite path="|13A|17|09|.01|F.">Regulation .01F</cite> adopted effective March 17, 2025 (52:5 Md. R. 238)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
