<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Continuing Education</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This regulation governs a person practicing as a mortician, funeral director, or holder of a surviving spouse license in Maryland.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Board" means the Board of Morticians and Funeral Directors.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Continuing education unit (CEU)" means 50 clock minutes of educational instruction in a Board-approved continuing education program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Funeral director" means an individual who is licensed by the Board to practice all aspects of mortuary science except for embalming.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Mortician" means an individual who practices mortuary science.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Surviving spouse" means the legal widow or widower of a licensed funeral director or licensed mortician, whose license was in good standing at the time of death, and who, at the time of death, wholly or partly owned and operated a mortuary science business.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Standards of Continuing Education Preapproval.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Continuing education units are automatically approved and do not need to be submitted to the Board if the programs are:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Approved by the Academy of Funeral Service Practitioners;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Sponsored by national service organizations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Sponsored by State associations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Sponsored by local associations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Provided by suppliers; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Already approved by the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Licensed Maryland funeral establishments and other Maryland licensees may apply to the Board for CEU approval.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A continuing education course or workshop may be qualified for approval if the Board determines that it:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Constitutes an organized program of learning, including a symposium, which contributes directly to the professional competency of the licensee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is related to the practice of mortuary science;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Is conducted by individuals considered experts in the subject matter of the program by reason of education, training, or experience; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Is accompanied by a paper, manual, or written outline which substantially describes the subject matter of the program.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An individual seeking to conduct a seminar, workshop, or presentation shall submit for Board approval at least 6 weeks in advance of the proposed seminar, workshop, or presentation the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Documentation indicating the number of CEUs that will be proposed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A description of the course;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Qualifications of the presenter;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A course outline; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Any manuals or other documents to be distributed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Post-Approval and Review.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each licensee seeking credit for attendance and participation in an education program that is not preapproved shall submit to the Board, within 30 days after completion of the activity, the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Activity's dates;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Subjects covered;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Names of instructors and their qualifications; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Number of CEUs requested.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Within 90 days after receipt of the application, the licensee shall be advised by the board, in writing, as to whether the activity is approved and the number of CEUs allowed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A licensee may be denied credit if the licensee fails to comply with the requirements of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A continuing education course or workshop that is already approved may be monitored or reviewed by the Board, and, upon evidence of significant variation in the program presented from the program approved, all or any part of the approved hours granted the program may be disapproved.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Continuing Education Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The following licensees, except as otherwise stated, at the time of renewal, shall submit documentation of continuing education in the field of mortuary science to the Board:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Morticians;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Funeral directors; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Surviving spouses.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The morticians, funeral directors, and surviving spouses may begin to accumulate CEUs beginning May 1, 1994 for the renewal period of April 1996 for morticians and November 1997 for funeral directors and surviving spouses.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in this regulation, each licensee in the State shall submit, with the license renewal application, a list of a minimum of 12 CEUs each renewal period of continuing education course work approved by continuing education providers as set forth in <cite path="|10|29|05|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>, or the Board. The Board shall undertake a random audit of a certain percentage of licensees to determine CEU compliance.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>CEUs may be obtained by attending and participating in continuing education courses or workshops previously approved by the Board or otherwise meeting the requirements and approved by the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>During the time an organization, educational institution, or person is an approved sponsor, all continuing education programs of the organization, educational institution, or person may be approved by the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Board shall waive continuing education requirements for individuals newly licensed for the first-time renewal of a license.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Except as allowed by the Board, a licensee may not receive credit exceeding nine CEUs of the biennial total required:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For correspondence work;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For video, sound-recorded, or television programs; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>By information transmitted by other similar means as authorized by the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Service as a lecturer or discussion leader may be included to the extent that it contributes to the professional competency of the applicant, but repetitious presentations may not be counted and not more than 50 percent of the total required CEUs may be satisfied in this manner.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>The maximum number of CEUs which may be granted for any single continuing education course or workshop single topic is six.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>A licensee may not receive more than three CEUs within a renewal period for attending a Board of Morticians and Funeral Directors board meeting.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>A licensee may obtain three CEUs for any business courses completed and approved by continuing education providers set forth in <cite path="|10|29|05|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>, or the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>After the renewal period beginning May 1, 2008 for morticians, and December 1, 2008 for funeral directors and surviving spouse licensees, 3 carry-over credits may be granted per renewal cycle.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>A licensee shall earn a minimum of 1 CEU hour in an approved course on preneed law per renewal cycle.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Exemptions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board shall grant an exemption from meeting the continuing education requirements to a licensed mortician, funeral director, or surviving spouse license holder who has practiced mortuary science in the State for 40 years and has submitted a one-time request for an exemption to the Board at the time of license renewal.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board shall consider a waiver of all or part of the continuing education requirements on a case-by-case basis for a licensed mortician, funeral director, or surviving spouse license holder based on documentation of disability or unusual circumstances.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A mortician, funeral director, or surviving spouse licensee whose license is on an inactive status is not required to meet the continuing education requirements.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Upon reactivation of an inactive license, a mortician, funeral director, or surviving spouse shall submit documentation of CEUs for the current renewal period in which the license is reactivated.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|7-205">7-205</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|7-314">7-314</cite>(c)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|4">4</cite>), Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-12-05">Effective date: December 5, 1994 (21:24 Md. R. 1988)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-02-25"><cite path="|10|29|05|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective November 5, 2007 (34:24 Md. R. 2154); amended permanently effective February 25, 2008 (35:4 Md. R. 514)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-02-08"><cite path="|10|29|05|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective February 8, 2010 (37:3 Md. R. 176)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-02-08"><cite path="|10|29|05|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite>, D amended effective February 8, 2010 (37:3 Md. R. 176)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-02-08"><cite path="|10|29|05|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective January 7, 2002 (28:26 Md. R. 2273); September 7, 2009 (36:18 Md. R. 1380); February 8, 2010 (37:3 Md. R. 176)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-02-25"><cite path="|10|29|05|.05|J.">Regulation .05J</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective November 5, 2007 (34:24 Md. R. 2154);amended permanently effective February 25, 2008 (35:4 Md. R. 514)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-09-07"><cite path="|10|29|05|.06|A.">Regulation .06A</cite> amended effective September 7, 2009 (36:18 Md. R. 1380)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-03-27"><cite path="|10|29|05|.06|D.">Regulation .06D</cite> amended effective March 27, 1995 (22:6 Md. R. 474)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
