<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>08</num>
  <heading>Courtesy Card</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>These regulations govern courtesy cards for those licensed to practice mortuary science in other states or countries who wish to transport bodies from Maryland to their states or countries of licensure or from their states or countries of licensure to Maryland.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Board" means the Board of Morticians and Funeral Directors.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Committal service" means a ritual conducted at the graveside or crematory following a funeral held at a location other than a cemetery or crematory.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Courtesy card" means a license issued by the Board to licensed practitioners of mortuary science in other states or countries which allows these practitioners to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Remove a dead human body from this State and return the body to another state or country;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Return a dead human body from another state or country to this State for final disposition;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Fill out the family history portion of the death certificate;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Sign the death certificate in the holder's capacity as a licensed practitioner of mortuary science without the assistance of or being under the supervision of a Maryland licensed mortician or funeral director; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Participate in committal services in Maryland without the assistance of a Maryland mortician or funeral director.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Graveside funeral service" means a program or ritual conducted at the cemetery or crematory on behalf of a dead human body instead of one conducted at a funeral home or place of worship.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Requirements for Courtesy Card.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An individual already licensed in another state or country to practice mortuary science may apply to the Board for a courtesy card.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An individual licensed to practice mortuary science from another state or country, and who is seeking a courtesy card issued by the Board, shall fulfill the following requirements:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Complete an application on a form provided by the Board;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Have the state or country where the individual is licensed certify, by affixing the seal of that state or country on the completed application, that the applicant is a licensee in good standing in that state or country; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Submit the completed, certified application form along with the fee specified in <cite path="|10.29.04">COMAR 10.29.04</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Authority of Courtesy Card.</heading>
    <text>Upon issuance of a courtesy card by the Board, the courtesy cardholder is authorized to:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Complete the family history portion of the death certificate and file it with the local health department or Maryland Department of Health;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Complete any other forms, including the burial transit permit, incident to the disposition of a dead human body;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Transport an embalmed or unembalmed body from the state or country of licensure to Maryland for interment or cremation without the assistance of or under the direction of a Maryland mortician or funeral director;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Transport an embalmed or unembalmed body from Maryland to the state or country of licensure for interment or cremation without the assistance of or under the direction of a Maryland mortician or funeral director; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Conduct a committal service without the assistance of or under the direction of a Maryland mortician or funeral director.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Fee for Courtesy Card.</heading>
    <text>The fee for a courtesy card, as specified in <cite path="|10.29.04">COMAR 10.29.04</cite>, is nonrefundable and shall be prorated according to a schedule set by the Board.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Requirements for Renewal of Courtesy Card.</heading>
    <text>To renew a current courtesy card, the courtesy cardholder shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Complete a renewal application form provided by the Board;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Have the state or country where the individual is licensed certify, by affixing the seal of that state or country on the completed application, that the applicant is a licensee in good standing in that state or country; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Pay the renewal fee as specified in <cite path="|10.29.04">COMAR 10.29.04</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Prohibitions.</heading>
    <text>The holder of a courtesy card may not:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Transfer the card to another individual;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Own a funeral business in Maryland unless the courtesy cardholder is also an owner of or director in a corporation whose license is issued by the Board; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Except for the requirements listed in <cite path="|10|29|08|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>, perform any of the acts related to the practice of mortuary science in Maryland including, but not limited to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Arranging for funerals;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Conducting funerals in Maryland, including graveside services;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Advertising as a practitioner of mortuary science services in Maryland;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Signing contracts for funeral services in Maryland; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Preparing deceased human remains in Maryland for disposal.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|7-101">7-101</cite>(f) and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|7-311">7-311</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-12-19">Effective date: December 19, 1994 (21:25 Md. R. 2105)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-02-25"><cite path="|10|29|08|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective November 5, 2007 (34:24 Md. R. 2154); amended permanently effective February 25, 2008 (35:4 Md. R. 514)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
