<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Licensure of Graduates of Foreign Dental Schools</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Applicant" means any person applying for a license to practice dentistry pursuant to the provisions of these regulations and of Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|4-303">4-303</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|4-303">4-303</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Board" means the Maryland State Board of Dental Examiners.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Graduate of a foreign dental school" means any person who has graduated from a dental school located in any country outside the United States, its territories, districts, or possessions and the Dominion of Canada, and recognized by the country in which it is located.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|44|02|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Requirements for Limited License to Practice Dentistry; Exclusion.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This regulation does not apply to a pediatric dental fellow or an individual who has successfully completed a pediatric dental fellowship. The requirements for these individuals are contained in <cite path="|10|44|02|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In addition to meeting the requirements set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|4-302">Health Occupations Article, §4-302, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, with respect to moral character, and in addition to passing any required examination, to qualify for a limited license to practice dentistry, a graduate of a foreign dental school shall be 21 years old or older and shall submit the following credentials to the Board:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A completed application on a form the Board prescribes and furnishes to the applicant, accompanied by a 3 inch by 3 inch notarized photograph of the applicant;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Evidence satisfactory to the Board that the applicant has completed at least 24 months of formal general clinical training in a United States or Canadian accredited institution;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A copy of the degree or diploma issued to the applicant by the foreign dental school conferring it, properly authenticated by an official of that foreign dental school authorized to make the authentication;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A copy of the subjects taken and the credits earned by the applicant at the foreign dental school, duly authenticated by an official authorized to make the authentication;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A license to practice dentistry issued by the foreign country, or the proper subdivision of the country, in which the applicant has graduated, duly authenticated by the issuing authority;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A translation into English of a degree, diploma, or license required to be furnished to the Board, certified by an individual acceptable to the Board, if issued in a language other than English;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Two letters of recommendation written by persons acceptable to the Board, which shall certify to the Board the good moral character of the applicant and the applicant's age, qualifications, background, and experience, if any; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>A letter indicating that the applicant possesses sufficient comprehension and communication skills in written and spoken English to enable the applicant to adequately treat dental patients.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The letter required in <cite path="10|44|02|.02|B.|(8)">§B(8) of this regulation</cite> shall be received from:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The administrator of the hospital at which the license is limited;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The administrator of the sanitarium at which the license is limited;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The dean of the dental school at which the license is limited; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The administrator of the public health program at which the license is limited.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>In addition to the requirements of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|4-304">Health Occupations Article, §4-304, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, a graduate of a foreign dental school applying for a limited license to practice dentistry under these regulations shall submit to the Board with the application the credentials processing fee as specified in <cite path="|10.44.20">COMAR 10.44.20</cite>. This fee is not refundable in whole or in part.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A limited license to practice dentistry in this State is valid for 1 year from the date of issuance and is not renewable.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>An individual who has been in possession of a limited license may reapply for a limited license by submitting a new application to the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Requirements for Limited License to Practice Pediatric Dentistry for Certain Individuals.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In addition to meeting the requirements set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|4-303">Health Occupations Article, §4-303</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland, with respect to moral character, and in addition to passing any required examination, to qualify for a limited license to practice pediatric dentistry in a public health dental clinic, federally qualified health center, or Maryland qualified health center under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|4-303">Health Occupations Article, §4-303</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland, a graduate of a foreign dental school shall submit the following credentials to the Board:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A completed application on a form provided by the Board;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A photograph of the applicant 3 inches by 3 inches accompanied by a notarized statement stating that "the photograph is a true photograph of me";</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A copy of the degree or diploma issued to the applicant by the foreign dental school conferring it, properly authenticated by an official of that foreign dental school authorized to make the authentication;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A copy of the subjects taken and the credits earned by the applicant at the foreign dental school, duly authenticated by an official authorized to make the authentication;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A translation into English of a degree, diploma, or subjects taken which are required to be submitted to the Board, certified by an individual acceptable to the Board, if issued in a language other than English;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A certified letter with a raised embossed seal from the dental licensing authority of each state in which the applicant holds an active dental license or ever held an active dental license indicating that the license is or was in good standing and whether the applicant:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is being investigated;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has charges pending against the applicant's license;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Has been disciplined; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Has been convicted or disciplined by a court of any state or country for an act that would be grounds for disciplinary action under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|4-315">Health Occupations Article, §4-315, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>A copy of the applicant's National Practitioners Data Bank file;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Proof satisfactory to the Board that the applicant has passed parts one and two of the National Board Examinations conducted by the Council of National Boards of the American Dental Association;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Proof satisfactory to the Board that the applicant has successfully completed at least a 2-year pediatric dentistry residency program at a dental school or a hospital authorized by any state and which is recognized by the Board;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Proof satisfactory to the Board that the applicant is either a pediatric dental fellow, or has successfully completed a pediatric dental fellowship at the University of Maryland Dental School;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Proof satisfactory to the Board that the applicant is contractually obligated to provide pediatric dental services for at least 2 years in a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Public health dental clinic operated by the State or a county or municipality of the State;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Federally qualified health center; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Maryland qualified health center;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>A letter from the health officer of the public health program for which the applicant has contractually agreed to provide at least 2 years of pediatric dental services:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Requesting that the Board waive the education requirements of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|4-302">Health Occupations Article, §4-302, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, for the applicant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Stating that circumstances exist to justify granting the waiver; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Requesting that a limited license be issued to the applicant;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>A letter from the Dean of the University of Maryland Dental School:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Requesting that the Board waive the education requirements of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|4-302">Health Occupations Article, §4-302, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite> for the applicant; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Stating that circumstances exist to justify granting the waiver;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>Two letters of recommendation written by persons acceptable to the Board, which certify to the Board the applicant's:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Good moral character;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Age;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Qualifications;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Background; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Experience, if any;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>A letter from the dean of the dental school at which the license is limited indicating that the applicant possesses sufficient comprehension and communication skills in written and spoken English to enable the applicant to adequately treat dental patients;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>Documentation of change of name if the name on any of the documents submitted to the Board differs from the applicant's name; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>Any other documents or information pertinent to licensure required by the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A limited license to practice dentistry in this State is valid for 1 year from the date of issuance and is not renewable.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An individual who has been in possession of a limited license may reapply for a limited license by submitting a new application to the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Fees.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Fees as specified in <cite path="|10.44.20">COMAR 10.44.20</cite> shall accompany the application.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The credentials processing fee for limited licenses is not refundable in whole or in part.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Requirements — General License for a Limited Licensee Granted a Waiver.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A limited licensee granted a waiver under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|4-303">Health Occupations Article, §4-303</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland, may be granted a general license if the limited licensee fulfills the requirements of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|4-303">Health Occupations Article, §4-303</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland, and submits the following credentials to the Board:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A completed application on a form provided by the Board;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A photograph of the applicant 3 inches by 3 inches accompanied by a notarized statement stating that "the photograph is a true photograph of me";</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A copy of the degree or diploma issued to the applicant by the foreign dental school conferring it, properly authenticated by an official of that foreign dental school authorized to make the authentication;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A copy of the subjects taken and the credits earned by the applicant at the foreign dental school, properly authenticated by an official authorized to make the authentication;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If issued in a language other than English, a translation into English of a degree, diploma, or subjects taken which are required to be submitted to the Board, certified by an individual acceptable to the Board;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A certified letter with a raised embossed seal from the dental licensing authority of each state in which the applicant holds an active dental license or ever held an active dental license, indicating that the license is or was in good standing and whether the applicant:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is being investigated;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has charges pending against the applicant's license;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Has been disciplined;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Has been convicted or disciplined by a court of any state or country for an act that would be grounds for disciplinary action under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|4-315">Health Occupations Article, §4-315, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>A copy of the applicant's National Practitioners Data Bank file;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Proof satisfactory to the Board that the applicant has passed the written and clinical examinations of the North East Regional Board;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Proof satisfactory to the Board that the applicant has passed parts one and two of the National Board Examinations conducted by the Council of National Boards of the American Dental Association;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Proof satisfactory to the Board that the applicant has successfully completed at least a 2-year pediatric dentistry residency program at a dental school or a hospital authorized by any state and which is recognized by the Board;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Proof satisfactory to the Board that the applicant has successfully completed a pediatric dental fellowship at the University of Maryland Dental School;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Proof satisfactory to the Board that the applicant has successfully completed the applicant's contractual obligation to provide pediatric dental services for at least 2 years in a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Public health dental clinic operated by the State or a county or municipality of the State;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Federally qualified health center; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Maryland qualified health center;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Two letters of recommendation written by persons acceptable to the Board, which certify to the Board the applicant's:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Good moral character;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Age;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Qualifications;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Background; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Experience, if any;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>Proof of passing the Maryland Dental Jurisprudence Examination on the Maryland State Dental Law;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>Documentation of changes of name if the name on any of the documents submitted to the Board differs from the applicant's name; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>Any other documents or information pertinent to licensure required by the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The applicant shall be 18 years old or older.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|44|02|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Requirements for Teacher's License to Practice Dentistry.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In addition to meeting the requirements set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|4-302">Health Occupations Article, §4-302, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, with respect to moral character, to qualify for a teacher's license to practice dentistry, a graduate of a foreign dental school shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be 21 years old or older;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Hold a degree of Doctor of Dental Surgery, Doctor of Dental Medicine, or an equivalent degree from a school, college, or faculty of dentistry; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Submit the following credentials to the Board:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A completed application, on a form the Board prescribes and furnishes to the applicant, accompanied by a 3 inch by 3 inch notarized photograph of the applicant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A copy of the degree or diploma issued to the applicant by the foreign dental school conferring it, properly authenticated by an official of that foreign dental school authorized to make the authentication;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A copy of the subjects taken and the credits earned by the applicant at the foreign dental school, duly authenticated by an official of that foreign dental school authorized to make the authentication;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A translation into English of a degree or diploma required to be furnished to the Board, certified by an individual acceptable to the Board, if issued in a language other than English;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Two letters of recommendation, written by persons acceptable to the Board, which shall certify to the Board the good moral character of the applicant and the applicant's age, qualifications, background, and experience, if any;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>A letter from the dean of the dental school at which the license is limited indicating that the applicant possesses sufficient comprehension and communication skills in written and spoken English to enable the applicant to adequately treat dental patients;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Proof satisfactory to the Board that the applicant has at least 5 years of clinical dental experience; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Proof satisfactory to the Board that the applicant is professionally competent.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the applicant has been tested, licensed, or qualified in some other state of the United States, or its districts, territories, or possessions, the Board may accept the credentials submitted to the other state, district, territory, or possession, provided that the credentials meet the minimum standards of the Board as set forth in these regulations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In addition to the requirements of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|4-304">Health Occupations Article, §4-304, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, a graduate of a foreign dental school applying for a teacher's license to practice dentistry under this chapter shall submit to the Board with the application the credentials processing fee as specified in <cite path="|10.44.20">COMAR 10.44.20</cite>. This fee is not refundable in whole or in part.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The requirements of <cite path="10|44|02|.06|A.|(3)|(e)">§A(3)(e) of this regulation</cite> shall be waived if the applicant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is approved by the Dean of the University of Maryland Dental School;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Fulfills §A(1), (2), and (3)(a) — (d) and (g) — (h) of this regulation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Is appointed to a full-time faculty position at the University of Maryland Dental School.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A teacher's license to practice dentistry in the State is immediately void upon leaving the faculty position at the University of Maryland Dental School.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|4-303">4-303</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|4-303">4-303</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland; Ch. 131, Acts of 2003</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1973-06-07">Effective date: June 7, 1973</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1980-10-03"><cite path="|10|44|02|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite> amended effective November 17, 1978 (5:23 Md. R. 1740); October 3, 1980 (7:20 Md. R. 1880)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-07-29">Regulations <cite path="|10|44|02|.01">.01</cite> — <cite path="|10|44|02|.05">.05</cite> amended effective July 29, 1985 (12:15 Md. R. 1520)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-04-05" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective April 5, 1999 (26:7 Md. R. 544)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-02-19"><cite path="|10|44|02|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective February 19, 2001 (28:3 Md. R. 206)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-02-19"><cite path="|10|44|02|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective February 19, 2001 (28:3 Md. R. 206)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-12-11" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective December 11, 2003 (30:24 Md. R. 1743)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-01-02"><cite path="|10|44|02|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective January 2, 2006 (32:26 Md. R. 1997)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-01-02"><cite path="|10|44|02|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite> amended effective January 2, 2006 (32:26 Md. R. 1997)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-01-02"><cite path="|10|44|02|.06|A.">Regulation .06A</cite>, D amended effective January 2, 2006 (32:26 Md. R. 1997)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
