<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>The Conduct of Experimental Programs in Dental Schools or Colleges in the State, Which Use Dental Assistants, Dental Hygienists, or Both, in the Training of Students Enrolled in the Dental School or College</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>General Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Any experimental program shall be under the direct supervision of a full time faculty member of the dental school or college.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>All dental assistants utilized by or employed in connection with any program shall be "qualified dental assistants" as that term is defined in the regulations of the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>All dental hygienists utilized by or employed in connection with any program shall be duly licensed to practice dental hygiene in the State of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Specific Program Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If the conduct of an experimental program requires the delegation to a dental assistant or the hygienist would not otherwise be permitted to perform by law or regulation of the Board, the faculty supervisor of the experimental program shall notify in writing the assistant or hygienists, as well as students participating in the program, of the fact that this delegation of duty is for the purpose of the experimental program only and that the performance of the delegated duties by an assistant or hygienist, outside the experimental program, may be in violation of law or the regulations of the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>On and after June 1, 1973, all experimental programs proposed to be conducted in dental school or college, and not theretofore implemented which may involve dental procedures not otherwise approved by law or regulation of the Board, shall be submitted to the Board of Dental Examiners and the Maryland State Dental Association for review and comment at least 180 days in advance of the beginning of the experimental program.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|4-308">4-308</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|4-309">4-309</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1974-06-19">Effective date: June 19, 1974</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
