<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>11</num>
  <heading>Inactive Licenses</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Active Practice.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Active practice" with respect to dentistry means the practice of dentistry for at least 500 hours within the 36-month period preceding expiration of a license.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Active practice" with respect to dental hygiene means the practice of dental hygiene for at least 150 hours within the 36-month period preceding expiration of a license.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Approved school" means a school determined by the Commission on Dental Accreditation to have met minimum standards.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Board" means the Board of Dental Examiners.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Voluntary Change of License from Active to Inactive Status.</heading>
    <text>After receipt of a renewal application from the Board and before expiration of the current license, a dentist or dental hygienist who holds a general license may inform the Board on the renewal application of the licensee's intent to change the status of the license from active to inactive.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Terms and Conditions of an Inactive Status Certificate.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A licensee assigned inactive status shall submit to the Board the inactive status:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Application form provided by the Board; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Fee as specified in <cite path="|10.44.20">COMAR 10.44.20</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board shall issue an inactive status certificate to a licensee whose license is placed on inactive status.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An inactive status certificate expires on June 30 of the second year following the effective date of the certificate.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Before an inactive status certificate expires, the licensee may renew the certificate if the licensee:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Submits to the Board a renewal application on the form provided by the Board; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Pays to the Board the inactive status application fee as specified in <cite path="|10.44.20">COMAR 10.44.20</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A licensee whose license is on inactive status may not practice in Maryland unless otherwise authorized by law.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The practice of dentistry or dental hygiene in Maryland by a licensee whose license is on inactive status constitutes the unauthorized practice of dentistry or dental hygiene unless the practice is otherwise authorized by law.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|44|11|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Reactivating a Dental or Dental Hygiene Certificate on Inactive Status.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A licensee whose license to practice dentistry or dental hygiene is on inactive status may apply for reactivation of that license.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A licensee who applies for reactivation of a dental or dental hygienist license shall submit to the Board:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A completed application form provided by the Board;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Notarized affidavits or other evidence satisfactory to the Board that the applicant has actively practiced within the 36 months immediately preceding the application date;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Satisfactory proof of good standing from all states in which the applicant is currently licensed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Satisfactory evidence of completion, during the 2 years preceding application, of continuing education courses or programs equivalent in hours and type to those required of licensees by the Board; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Satisfactory evidence of passage, within 3 months of the application date, of the Board's jurisprudence examination.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In addition to submitting an application as required under <cite path="10|44|11|.04|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, an applicant for reactivation of a license shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be of good moral character;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Arrange for the National Practitioner's Data Bank to forward a report of the applicant's disciplinary activity to the Board; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Pay to the Board the difference between the license renewal fee and the inactive status application fee as specified in <cite path="|10.44.20">COMAR 10.44.20</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the applicant is unable to demonstrate active practice within the 36 months immediately preceding application for reactivation of a license, the applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Pass the North East Regional Board examination; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Have passed the North East Regional Board examination.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|4-310">Health Occupations Article, §4-310, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1983-08-01">Effective date: August 1, 1983 (10:15 Md. R. 1351)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-11-20"><cite path="|10|44|11|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective November 20, 1994 (21:23 Md. R. 1933)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-11-20"><cite path="|10|44|11|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective November 20, 1994 (21:23 Md. R. 1933)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-03-08" discontinuity="true">Chapter, Fee for Inactive Status, repealed and new chapter, Inactive Licenses, adopted effective March 8, 1999 (26:5 Md. R. 392)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-09-04">Chapter revised effective September 4, 2000 (27:17 Md. R. 1620)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-06-21" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective June 21, 2004 (31:12 Md. R. 913)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
