<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>15</num>
  <heading>Dentists and Dental Hygienists — Licensure by Examination</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter governs dentists and dental hygienists who seek a general license to practice dentistry or dental hygiene and who do not hold a license to practice dentistry or dental hygiene in another state.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Licensure for dentists licensed in another state is governed by <cite path="|10.44.05">COMAR 10.44.05</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Licensure for dental hygienists licensed in another state is governed by <cite path="|10.44.09">COMAR 10.44.09</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>General licensure for pediatric dental residents with a limited license at the University of Maryland Dental School who have successfully met all requirements for general licensure is governed by <cite path="|10.44.02">COMAR 10.44.02</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“ADEX” means the American Board of Dental Examiners, Inc., or its successor organization.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“ADHLEX” means the American Dental Hygiene Licensing Examination, which includes both a written component and a clinical component, designed and developed by ADEX, or its successor examination.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“ADLEX” means the American Dental Licensing Examination, which includes both a written component and a clinical component, designed and developed by ADEX, or its successor examination.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Board” means the Maryland State Board of Dental Examiners.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|44|15|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>General Qualification Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>To qualify for a general license to practice dentistry an applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be of good moral character;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Be at least 18 years old; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Hold a degree of Doctor of Dental Surgery, Doctor of Dental Medicine, or the equivalent from a college or university that is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Authorized by any state or any province of Canada to grant the degree; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Recognized by the Board as:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Requiring adequate preprofessional collegiate training; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Maintaining an acceptable course of dental instruction.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In addition to the requirements contained in <cite path="10|44|15|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, an applicant for a dental license shall meet all the requirements for licensure contained in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 4, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>To qualify for a general license to practice dental hygiene an applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be of good moral character; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Be a graduate of a school for dental hygienists that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Requires at least 2 years of education in an institution of higher education;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is accredited by the American Dental Association Commission on Dental Accreditation; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Is approved by the Board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>In addition to the requirements contained in <cite path="10|44|15|.03|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, an applicant for a dental hygiene license shall meet all of the requirements for licensure contained in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 4, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An applicant who otherwise qualifies for an initial dental license shall pass the written and clinical ADLEX examination with a score of 75 or greater in each required section.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>An applicant who otherwise qualifies for an initial dental hygiene license shall pass the written and clinical ADHLEX examination with a score of 75 or greater in each required section.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>An applicant for an initial dental or dental hygiene license shall pass the national boards examinations, also known as the National Boards, administered by the Council of National Boards of the American Dental Association.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>An applicant who fails the ADLEX or ADHLEX examinations four times may not be licensed.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Locations, Frequency, Content, and Grading of Examinations.</heading>
    <text>The ADEX has the authority to determine:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Examination sites;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Frequency of examinations;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Examination content; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Grading method, provided that the grading method is not arbitrary and capricious.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Completion of All Sections of Examinations Required.</heading>
    <text>Applicants may not be licensed until they have successfully passed:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>All required sections of the ADLEX or ADHLEX examination; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The national board examinations.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|44|15|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Maryland Law Examination.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In addition to passing the ADLEX or ADHLEX examination and national board examinations, an applicant shall pass a written examination on laws, regulations, and ethics given by the Board or its designee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The examination shall consist of the following two parts:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>General questions on:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Laws;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Regulations; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Ethics; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Questions on Maryland jurisprudence.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An applicant shall attain a score of 75 or greater on each section of the examination described in <cite path="10|44|15|.06|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Loss of Clinical Skills.</heading>
    <text>The Board may require that an applicant for licensure successfully pass each required section of the ADLEX or ADHLEX clinical examination if the Board determines that the applicant may have lost clinical skills because of an extended absence from clinical practice.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Application and Fee.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A candidate for licensure shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Fully complete the appropriate Board application; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Pay the required fee in accordance with <cite path="|10.44.20">COMAR 10.44.20</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An application shall be returned to the applicant and the applicant may not be licensed if the application:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is incomplete;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Does not contain all of the requested information or documentation; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Is not accompanied by the required fee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Board shall refund the application fee, less a $50 processing fee, to a dentist or a dental hygienist who does not qualify for licensure.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Application Procedures for Dentists and Dental Hygienists.</heading>
    <text>An applicant for a dental or a dental hygiene license shall submit the following to the Board:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A completed application on a form provided by the Board;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A recent photograph of the applicant not to exceed 3 inches by 3 inches accompanied by a notarized statement stating that "the photograph is a true photograph of me";</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An original National Board Score Card;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Certified proof of dental or dental hygiene education which contains the raised embossed school seal certifying its authenticity, except that letters from educational institutions on original letterhead, bearing an original signature, do not require a raised embossed seal;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A certified ADLEX or ADHLEX score;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Documentation of change of name if the name on any of the documents submitted to the Board differs from the applicant's name; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Any other documents or information pertinent to licensure required by the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|4-302">4-302</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|4-303">4-303</cite>.1(d), 4-305, and 4-306, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-02-19">Effective date: February 19, 1990 (17:3 Md. R. 300)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-07-05" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective July 5, 2004 (31:13 Md. R. 995)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-08-13"><cite path="|10|44|15|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective August 13, 2007 (34:16 Md. R. 1432)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-12-24" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|10|44|15|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|44|15|.08">.08</cite> repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|10|44|15|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|44|15|.09">.09</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective October 1, 2012 (39:22 Md. R. 1427); adopted permanently effective December 24, 2012 (39:25 Md. R. 1614)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
