<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>17</num>
  <heading>Temporary License to Practice Dental Hygiene</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>These regulations establish qualifications and requirements for applicants for a temporary license to practice dental hygiene in Maryland.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Eligibility.</heading>
    <text>An individual is eligible for a temporary license to practice dental hygiene if the individual:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Is a graduate of a school for dental hygienists that requires at least 2 years of education in an institution of higher learning that is accredited by the American Dental Association Commission on Dental Accreditation and is approved by the Board;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Is currently licensed to practice dental hygiene in any other state or any province of Canada; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Has practiced dental hygiene at least 800 hours per year for 2 years and has practiced dental hygiene during the past 2 years.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Application Procedures.</heading>
    <text>An applicant shall submit to the Board:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An application on the form that the Board requires for a temporary license;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Proof of current licensure in another state or province of Canada;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A statement from previous employers verifying the required practice experience;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An application fee as specified in <cite path="|10.44.20">COMAR 10.44.20</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Jurisprudence Examination.</heading>
    <text>Before a temporary license to practice dental hygiene is issued, the applicant shall pass a written examination administered by the Board, on the Maryland Dentistry Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 4, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and regulations adopted under that Act.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Term.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A temporary license expires on the date when licenses are issued to those who pass the first examination for a general license to practice dental hygiene given over 30 days after the effective date of the temporary license.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Notification that the temporary licensee has failed the first examination for a general license to practice dental hygiene given over 30 days after the effective date of the temporary license shall serve as notice of the expiration of that temporary license.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A temporary license to practice dental hygiene is not renewable.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|4-312">Health Occupations Article, §4-312, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-02-19">Effective date: February 19, 1990 (17:3 Md. R. 301)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-07-27"><cite path="|10|44|17|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended effective July 27, 1998 (25:15 Md. R. 1191)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-07-27"><cite path="|10|44|17|.03|D.">Regulation .03D</cite> amended effective July 27, 1998 (25:15 Md. R. 1191)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
