<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>28</num>
  <heading>Teachers' Licenses for Graduates of United States or Canadian Dental Schools and Schools of Dental Hygiene</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter establishes the requirements for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A teacher's license to practice dentistry for a graduate of a United States or Canadian dental school; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A teacher's license to practice dental hygiene for a graduate of a United States or Canadian school for dental hygienists.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The requirements for a teacher's license to practice dentistry for a graduate of a foreign dental school are set forth in <cite path="|10.44.02">COMAR 10.44.02</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Requirements for Teacher's License to Practice Dentistry.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>To qualify for a teacher's license to practice dentistry, an applicant shall meet the requirements set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|4-302">Health Occupations Article, §4-302, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An applicant for a teacher's license to practice dentistry shall submit the following to the Board:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A completed application on a form provided by the Board;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A photograph of the applicant not to exceed 3 inches by 3 inches accompanied by a notarized statement that "the photograph is a true photograph of me" ;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Certified proof of dental education with the raised embossed school seal certifying its authenticity, except that letters from educational institutions on original letterhead and bearing an original signature do not require a raised embossed seal;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A certified letter with a raised embossed seal from the dental licensing authority of each state in which the applicant holds an active dental license or ever held an active dental license, indicating that the license is or was in good standing, and that the applicant:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is not being investigated;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Does not have charges pending against the applicant's license;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Has not been disciplined; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Has not been convicted or disciplined by a court of any state or country for an act that would be grounds for disciplinary action under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|4-315">Health Occupations Article, §4-315, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Proof satisfactory to the Board that the applicant has at least 5 years of active dental experience;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A copy of the applicant's National Practitioner Data Bank file;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>A letter from the Dean of the college or university in which the applicant is to teach a subject required by the dental school of that college or university:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Requesting that the license be issued; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Indicating that the applicant is to be a full-time faculty member;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Documentation of a change of name if the name on any of the documents submitted to the Board differs from the applicant's name; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Any other documents or information pertinent to licensure required by the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The practice of dentistry in the armed forces, state and federal programs, and intern and residency programs within the 5 years preceding application shall count toward the required active dental experience.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Requirements for Teacher's License to Practice Dental Hygiene.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>To qualify for a teacher's license to practice dental hygiene, an applicant shall meet the requirements set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|4-302">Health Occupations Article, §4-302, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An applicant for a teacher's license to practice dental hygiene shall submit the following to the Board:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A completed application on a form provided by the Board;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A photograph of the applicant not to exceed 3 inches by 3 inches accompanied by a notarized statement that "the photograph is a true photograph of me" ;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Certified proof of dental hygiene education with the raised embossed school seal certifying its authenticity, except that letters from educational institutions on original letterhead and bearing an original signature do not require a raised embossed seal;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A certified letter with a raised embossed seal from the dental hygiene licensing authority of each state in which the applicant holds an active dental hygiene license or ever held an active dental hygiene license, indicating that the license is or was in good standing and that the applicant:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is not being investigated;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Does not have charges pending against the applicant's license;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Has not been disciplined; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Has not been convicted or disciplined by a court of any state or country for an act that would be grounds for disciplinary action under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|4-315">Health Occupations Article, §4-315, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Proof satisfactory to the Board that the applicant has at least 5 years of active dental hygiene experience;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A copy of the applicant's National Practitioner Data Bank file;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>A letter from the Dean of the college or university in which the applicant is to teach a subject required by the dental hygiene school or dental school of that college or university:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Requesting that the license be issued; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Indicating that the applicant is to be a full-time faculty member;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Documentation of change of name if the name on any of the documents submitted to the Board differs from the applicant's name; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Any other documents or information pertinent to licensure required by the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The practice of dental hygiene in the armed forces, state and federal programs, and intern and residency programs within the 5 years preceding application shall count toward the required active dental hygiene experience.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>License to Teach Dentistry at the University of Maryland Dental School.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A graduate of a United States or Canadian dental school who is not licensed to practice dentistry in another state and who wishes to obtain a teacher's license to teach dentistry at the University of Maryland Dental School, shall meet the requirements set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|4-303">Health Occupations Article, §4-303(c), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A graduate of a United States or Canadian dental school who is not licensed to practice dentistry in another state and who wishes to apply for a teacher's license to teach dentistry at the University of Maryland Dental School shall submit the following to the Board:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A completed application on a form provided by the Board;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A photograph of the applicant not to exceed 3 inches by 3 inches accompanied by a notarized statement that "the photograph is a true photograph of me" ;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Certified proof of dental education with the raised embossed school seal certifying its authenticity, except that letters from educational institutions on original letterhead and bearing an original signature do not require a raised embossed seal;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A certified letter with a raised embossed seal from the dental licensing authority of each state in which the applicant ever held an active dental license indicating that the license is or was in good standing and that the applicant:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is not being investigated;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Does not have charges pending against the applicant's license;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Has not been disciplined; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Has not been convicted or disciplined by a court of any state or country for an act that would be grounds for disciplinary action under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|4-315">Health Occupations Article, §4-315, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Proof satisfactory to the Board that the applicant has at least 5 years of clinical dental experience;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A copy of the applicant's National Practitioner Data Bank file;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>A letter from the Dean of the University of Maryland Dental School:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Providing the reasons why the Board should waive the requirement that the applicant be licensed in another state; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Indicating that the applicant is to be a full-time faculty member;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Documentation of a change of name if the name on any of the documents submitted to the Board differs from the applicant's name; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Any other documents or information pertinent to licensure required by the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Fees.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The applicant shall submit the fee specified in <cite path="|10.44.20">COMAR 10.44.20</cite> with the application for a teacher's license to practice:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Dentistry; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Dental hygiene.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The application fee is nonrefundable.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>License Void.</heading>
    <text>A teacher's license to practice dentistry and a teacher's license to practice dental hygiene in the State are immediately void upon leaving the faculty position.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|4-302">4-302</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|4-303">4-303</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-01-06">Effective date: January 6, 2005 (31:26 Md. R. 1863)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
