<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>35</num>
  <heading>Limited Dental Drug Dispensing Permits</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter covers the issuance by the State Board of Dental Examiners of a limited dental drug dispensing permit for dentists who wish to dispense only prescription strength:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Home fluoride products;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Dentin/enamel remineralizing products; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Antimicrobial rinses.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This chapter does not apply to a dentist who dispenses prescription drugs in the course of treating a patient at a:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Medical facility or clinic that is operated on a nonprofit basis;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Health center that operates on a campus of an institution of higher learning;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Public health facility;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Medical facility under contract with the State or local health department: or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Facility funded with public funds.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A dentist who dispenses a full course of antibiotics to a patient for infection control is not required to obtain a drug dispensing permit if the dispensing meets the requirements of <cite path="|10|44|35|.05|A.">Regulation .05A of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A dentist who wishes to dispense prescription drugs other than those covered in this chapter is required to obtain a drug dispensing permit as required by <cite path="|10.13.01">COMAR 10.13.01</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Administer” means the direct introduction of a single dosage of a drug at a given time, whether by injection or other means, and whether in liquid, tablet, capsule, or other form.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Board” means the Maryland State Board of Dental Examiners.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Dentist” means an individual who holds a current license to practice dentistry in Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Limited dental drug dispensing permit” means a drug dispensing permit for dentists who wish to dispense only prescription strength:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Home fluoride products;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Dentin/enamel remineralizing products; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Antimicrobial rinses.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Starter dosage” means an amount of a drug sufficient to begin therapy:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Of short duration of 72 hours or less; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Before obtaining a large quantity of the drug to complete the therapy.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Permit Required.</heading>
    <text>Subject to the exception contained in <cite path="|10|44|35|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>, a dentist may not dispense home fluoride products, dentin/remineralizing products or antimicrobial rinses unless the dentist holds a limited drug dispensing permit issued by the Board.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Issuance and Renewal of Permit.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A permit expires on October 1 of the 5th year following the effective date of the permit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>To obtain a permit, a dentist shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Submit to the Board an application on a form provided by the Board; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Pay the fee set by the Board in <cite path="|10.44.20">COMAR 10.44.20</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Board shall mail a renewal application to each dentist holding a limited dental drug dispensing permit at least 90 days before the expiration of the permit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Before the permit expires, an applicant may apply to renew the permit for an additional 5-year term if the applicant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Submits to the Board a renewal application on a form provided by the Board; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Pays the renewal fee set by the Board in <cite path="|10.44.20">COMAR 10.44.20</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Exceptions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Drug Samples. A dentist is not required to have a limited dental drug dispensing permit to dispense drug samples if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The sample complies with the labeling requirements contained in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|12-505">Health Occupations Article, §12-505, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, except that the labeling requirements may not apply if the dentist dispenses the drug:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In an emergency situation; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>As a sample dispensed in the regular course of the dentist’s practice;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>No charge is made for the sample; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The dentist enters an appropriate record in the patient’s chart.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Starter Dosages. A dentist is not required to have a limited dental drug dispensing permit to dispense starter dosages if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The starter dosage complies with the labeling requirements contained in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|12-505">Health Occupations Article, §12-505, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, except that the labeling requirements may not apply if the dentist dispenses the drug:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In an emergency situation; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>As a starter dosage dispensed in the regular course of the dentist’s practice;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>No charge is made for the starter dosage; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The dentist enters an appropriate record in the patient’s chart.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Course of Treating a Patient. A dentist is not required to have a limited drug dispensing permit to administer a prescription drug in the course of treating a patient.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Violations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>After an opportunity for a hearing, the Board may revoke or suspend a limited permit or take disciplinary action under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|4-315">Health Occupations Article, §4-315(a) </cite>or (b), Annotated Code of Maryland, if the Board finds that the holder of the permit violates any provision of this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Failure to comply with the provisions of this chapter constitutes unprofessional conduct and may constitute other violations of law.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|44|35|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Summary Suspension of a Permit.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board may order the summary suspension of a permit if the Board:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Finds that the public health, safety, or welfare imperatively requires emergency action; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Promptly gives the licensee:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Written notice of the suspension, the finding, and the reasons that support the finding; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An opportunity to be heard.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Service of the notice of the suspension, the finding, the reasons that support the finding, and the notice of the opportunity to be heard may be effected upon the holder of a permit by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Personal service; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Written notice sent by certified mail and regular mail to the permit holder’s address on file with the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Service made pursuant to <cite path="10|44|35|.07|B.|(2)">§B(2) of this regulation</cite> shall be effective upon mailing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The methods of service provided in this regulation are in addition to and not exclusive of any other means of service that are reasonably calculated to provide notice.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|4-207">Health Occupations Article, §4-207(b), </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-07-20">Effective date: July 20, 2015 (42:14 Md. R. 880)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
