<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Buffer Strip Uses</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>General Public Use of the Buffer Strip.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Applicability. The provisions of this regulation apply to the general public, including persons who own property adjacent to the buffer strip but who do not obtain a buffer strip use permit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Permissible Uses.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may walk along any portion of the buffer strip.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In an emergency a person may use any portion of the buffer strip for access to and from the lake.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person who holds a valid fishing license may fish from the buffer strip.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Prohibited Uses.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as authorized by permit issued by the lake manager, a person may not:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Construct, place, or maintain a dock, mooring buoy, or other facility or structure, or modify land or vegetation in or on the waters of the lake or on the buffer strip;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Camp, picnic, drive vehicles, bike, build fires, or beach boats on, or swim from the buffer strip, except in areas designated for those uses by the public.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not use, remove, deface, or damage a private dock, mooring buoy, navigational aid, launching ramp, fireplace, picnic table, pavilion, or other structure or facility placed on the buffer strip or in the lake by a commercial or adjacent landowner under permit from the Department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person may not deposit on the buffer strip or in the lake debris, garbage, sewage, waste, decaying or unused barrels, unused dock facilities, food stuff, paper, or other litter or obnoxious material, or solid waste.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A person may not attach a rope or cable to, or around, trees or shrubs on the buffer strip.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Adjacent Landowner Use of the Buffer Strip.</heading>
    <text>Permit Required. An adjacent landowner may make only such uses of the buffer strip as are authorized for the general public, unless the landowner obtains a buffer strip use permit from the lake manager, or is a member of an association, condominium, or group validly operating a common dock facility for residential purposes, which has obtained a valid buffer strip use permit.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Commercial Landowner Use of the Buffer Strip.</heading>
    <text>A commercial landowner shall be regulated in the same manner in which an adjacent landowner is regulated, and shall be subject to all the same provisions. In addition, a commercial landowner shall have his or her buffer strip use permit validated for commercial use.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Natural Resources Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|5-209">5-209</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|5-215">5-215</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|8-704">8-704</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-05-05">Effective date: May 5, 1986 (13:9 Md. R. 1024)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-07-10">Chapter revised effective July 10, 1989 (16:13 Md. R. 1419)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
