<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Permits</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|08|05|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>General Provisions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Scope of Permits.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A permit does not constitute an interest in property or a proprietary right in the buffer strip or the lake.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person acting under a permit may not engage in any activity which interferes with the operation of the lake as a hydroelectric project or with authorized public use of the buffer strip or lake.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Guests or tenants of a permittee may use the buffer strip in the same way as a permittee, unless restricted by the permittee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A buffer strip use permittee or guests or tenants may only use the buffer strip as authorized under <cite path="|08|08|05|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>. Other uses of the buffer strip by a buffer use permittee are prohibited unless authorized by a special permit, a development permit, or a nonconforming use permit.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Uses of the buffer strip not permitted for the general public are prohibited unless authorized by permit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Area of Use.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A permittee may use that area of the buffer strip located directly in front of the property through which the permittee claims access to the buffer strip as is determined by extending the permittee's property lines to the water's edge.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In coves or other areas where an extended property line intersects with the extended lines of other permittees, causing conflicts in the areas of the buffer strip to be used by each or resulting in the denial of an adjacent permittee's access to the lake, or producing a similar anomalous result, the lake manager shall determine the area which each permittee may use by taking the total area of buffer strip affected by the anomalous condition, and dividing it equitably among the permittees, based on the amount of buffer strip frontage of each.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>When an adjacent landowner claims access through deeded access or participates in a common dock facility, the lake manager shall consider the deed or other instrument through which the landowner claims access, or covenants pertaining to the common dock facility when the lake manager determines the landowner's area of use.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The lake manager shall designate on the permit the area of the buffer strip which the lake manager has determined may be used by a permittee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Authority of Lake Manager.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Permit Review.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The lake manager may deny a permit application, or limit the use, location, type, or position of a facility authorized under a permit, if the lake manager determines that this action is necessary to protect public safety or welfare or to carry out the policies set forth in <cite path="08.08.01.01">COMAR 08.08.01.01</cite>. In making a determination to grant or deny a permit, the lake manager shall consider:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Public safety;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The configuration of the lake frontage;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Fluctuation of the water line;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Depth of water at the proposed site;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Density of existing boat usage or other recreational uses;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Number of existing, permitted docks in the area;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Potential navigational problems;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Preservation of aquatic vegetation and wildlife in the area; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ix)</num>
            <text>Protection of the ecological balance of the lake.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the lake manager determines, based on the criteria stated in §C(1)(a), of this regulation, that a dock cannot be permitted under an individual buffer strip use permit, the lake manager may accept an application from adjoining landowners for a common dock facility that is consistent with the criteria stated in §C(1)(a), of this regulation. This paragraph applies only where the applicants meet all eligibility requirements under these regulations, including minimum frontage.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="08|08|05|.01|F.">§F of this regulation</cite>, within 30 days of receiving a complete application and any additional information required, the lake manager shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Approve or disapprove the application;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Notify the applicant in writing of the action taken; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>State the grounds for the decision.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The lake manager shall keep on file all applications received and copies of permits issued.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Allocations of New Slips after December 19, 1988. Except for permit applications for new transient slips assigned to restaurants and stores, all permit applications received after December 19, 1988 which request approval of new slips for new and existing facilities shall be reviewed by the lake manager in the following manner:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>From December 19, 1988 to August 31, 1990 the lake manager shall issue permits with not more than a total of 165 new slips. If requests for more than 165 new slips are received, the lake manager shall determine the priority of the applications in accordance with <cite path="08|08|05|.01|D.|(1)|(a)">§D(1)(a) of this regulation</cite>. Applications received between:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>December 19, 1988 and April 1, 1989 shall be reviewed as a group and the approved applications shall represent the slip allocation for 1989.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>April 2, 1989 and September 1, 1989 shall be reviewed as a group between September 2, 1989 and December 1, 1989. The lake manager shall issue all permits or denials by December 31, 1989. These permits shall be the total new slip allocation for 1990.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>After August 31, 1990 the lake manager shall issue permits for new slips in the following sequence:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Applications received between September 2, 1989 and September 1, 1990 shall be reviewed during the period of September 2, 1990 to December 1, 1990. The lake manager shall issue all permits or denials by December 31, 1990 which shall represent the 1991 new slip allocation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>New slip allocations for subsequent years shall be made in the same sequence as §E(2)(a), of this regulation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Permit Expiration. A permit issued under these regulations shall be valid for not longer than 1 year and shall expire:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>On March 31 of each year; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>At the end of the term specified in the permit.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|08|05|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Buffer Strip Use Permits.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An adjacent or commercial landowner who desires to use the lake or buffer strip other than as a member of the general public shall obtain a buffer strip use permit. Issuance of a buffer strip use permit entitles:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An adjacent landowner to use the lake and buffer strip as provided in <cite path="|08|08|05|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A commercial landowner to use the lake and buffer strip as provided in <cite path="|08|08|05|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Application.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An applicant for a buffer strip use permit shall apply to the lake manager on a form provided by the Department. The applicant shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Provide all additional relevant information requested by the lake manager;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Certify to the lake manager that the proposed use of the buffer strip conforms to existing zoning laws.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When more than one person is eligible, as a result of joint ownership or deeded access, to obtain a permit for use of the same portion of the buffer strip, the application shall be made by one eligible person on behalf of a minimum of two-thirds of the eligible persons.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Failure to meet any of the requirements of this section may result in denial of the application.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Eligibility.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="08|08|05|.02|C.|(2)">§C(2) of this regulation</cite>, the lake manager shall issue a buffer strip use permit to the following persons:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An adjacent or commercial landowner who owns property for which a valid dock permit was issued or was eligible to be issued, before imposition of the Department's moratorium on August 12, 1983;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A person who obtained a recreational permit from Penelec, holds a valid dock permit from the Department, and has continually maintained a dock in the lake, or shows good cause why these criteria are not met;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A person who owns property with at least 100 feet of land fronting on usable buffer strip or on a public right-of-way adjacent to the buffer strip, if the property was subdivided and recorded among the land records of Garrett County, either by deed or subdivision plan or plat, after imposition of the Department's moratorium on August 12, 1983, provided that the property meets local zoning requirements for the construction of a residential dwelling unit;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A person who owns property with less than 100 feet of land fronting on the buffer strip or on a public right-of-way adjacent to the buffer strip who desires to make only recreational use of the buffer strip and does not desire to install a dock or mooring buoy;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>A person who seeks a buffer strip use permit pursuant to a development permit issued by the lake manager;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>A person who has deeded access to the lake from a lot that meets local zoning requirements for the construction of a residential dwelling unit; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>A person who owns a parcel of land adjacent to the buffer strip that was conveyed to them by Penelec after January 1, 1994, and which has frontage that was issued or was eligible to be issued a buffer strip use permit before that date.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The lake manager may not issue a buffer strip use permit:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>To an applicant who has in the past 5 years had a buffer strip use permit revoked or is currently in violation of these regulations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If denial is required on the grounds stated in Regulation .01D;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>For property for which a development permit is required, but has not been obtained;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>To an applicant who does not have a minimum of 100 feet of usable buffer strip frontage, unless a permit was issued for the buffer strip before July 10, 1989.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Fee. Upon receipt of a buffer strip use permit, the permittee shall forward to the lake manager the fee specified in the permit. The permit shall be valid only after the lake manager receives the permit fee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Display of Permit Identification Numbers. Upon receipt of a buffer strip use permit, the permittee shall display the permit identification numbers on the permittee's dock, mooring buoy, and other structures so as to be visible from the lake and from land.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|08|05|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Uses Permitted with a Buffer Strip Use Permit.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An adjacent landowner who obtains a buffer strip use permit may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Make general recreational use of the buffer strip.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Fish from the buffer strip if the person has a valid fishing license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Maintain vegetation on the buffer strip by mowing grass and lawn care, including seeding, trimming, and such other activities as are necessary for maintenance of the grass only.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Unless otherwise authorized by a special permit, a development permit, or a nonconforming use permit, a buffer strip use permittee may install mooring buoys and a boating or swimming structure, or both, if the following requirements are met. The permittee may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Install not more than one dock for swimming or boating, or both, with slip space for not more than three boats regardless of the amount of land fronting on the buffer strip owned by the permittee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Keep up to four boats on the lake, including boats that are docked and those that are moored, not more than two of which may be power boats, or three which may be a combination of power boats and personal watercraft;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Keep not more than three powerboats on the lake; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Keep beach boats or vessels in addition to the four boats allowed under <cite path="08|08|05|.03|B.|(2)">§B(2) of this regulation</cite>, that individually have a total weight, including the power source, of not more than 500 pounds.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Docks, and boating and swimming structures shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be nonpermanent and easily removable from the lake.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Float or have wheels.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Have securely fastened flotation devices that are nontoxic, nonpermeable, and nonhazardous to aquatic life. Containers previously used for toxic material are prohibited.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A drum used as a flotation device shall contain sufficient positive flotation material to keep the drum visibly afloat if it detaches from the dock. E. Mooring buoys shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be nonpermanent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Be marked by polystyrene, plastic, or fiberglass flotation buoys not smaller than 500 cubic inches and not larger than 4,000 cubic inches;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Be white with a blue belly band;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Be marked with the owner's permit number; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Have no metallic portion within 2 feet of the water's surface, other than metal connecting rings or hardware.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Docks, and boating and swimming structures shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be nonpermanent and easily removable from the lake.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Float or have wheels.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Have securely fastened floatation devices that are nontoxic nonpermeable, and nonhazardous to aquatic life. Containers previously used for toxic material are prohibited.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Docks, boating and swimming structures, and mooring buoys shall be located within 100 feet of the shore, or within 1/3 of the distance to the opposite shore, whichever is less, unless otherwise approved by special permit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Removal of Docks, Boating and Swimming Structures, and Mooring Buoys.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="08|08|05|.03|G.|(2)">§G(2) of this regulation</cite>, from December 1 through April 1, all docks, boating and swimming structures, and mooring buoys shall be removed from the lake, and shall be secured to or removed from the buffer strip.  Vehicles may be driven on the buffer strip to comply with this section.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Lake Manager, in their discretion, may modify the April 1 deadline in <cite path="08|08|05|.03|G.|(1)">§G(1) of this regulation</cite> to allow docks, boating and swimming structures, and mooring buoys to be placed in the lake no earlier than March 15 of a given year.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>A buffer strip use permittee shall be responsible for the repair and upkeep of a dock, boating and swimming structure, or mooring buoy that the permittee installs.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Dock Slip Rental.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A buffer strip use permittee with at least one dock slip may rent, lease, or assign not more than one dock slip to another person.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Subject to the approval of the association, condominium, or common dock rental facility group, a member of an association, condominium, or group which has obtained a valid buffer strip use permit to operate a common dock facility for residential purposes and within which the member has at least one deeded dock slip may rent, lease, or assign not more than one deeded dock slip to another person.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Renting, leasing, or assigning a dock slip is subject to applicable State and local laws.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Uses Not Permitted within a Buffer Strip Use Permit.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A buffer strip use permittee may not:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Install a facility on, or use the buffer strip to interfere with operations of the Deep Creek hydroelectric project or with improvement to or installation of public works;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Discharge sewage or waste into the lake;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Install or expand septic systems, including tanks and drain fields, on the buffer strip or as prohibited by any law or regulation relating to septic systems;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Bury or dispose of garbage or trash in the lake or on the buffer strip;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Remove or plant trees or shrubbery on the buffer strip without written consent by the lake manager;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Alter or obstruct the natural flow of water in the lake;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Erect fences or other obstructions on the buffer strip;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Dredge or fill the lake except as authorized by a special permit;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Perform maintenance activities including the removal or pruning of live trees, the applying of fertilizers, weed control agents, or other chemicals, the cutting of undergrowth, or any other form of maintenance on the buffer strip, except by authorization of a special permit;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Remove water from the lake without the written consent of the lake manager;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Interfere with public uses of the lake authorized by these regulations or the lake manager; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>String a rope or cable across the water in a way that creates a safety hazard to lake users.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In addition to any other penalty required by law, failure to meet any of the requirements in this regulation may result in denial of the application for permit.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|08|05|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Special Permits.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Application.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The following persons shall be required to obtain a special permit:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A buffer strip use permittee who desires to use, alter, modify, or improve the lake or buffer strip other than as authorized under a buffer strip use permit;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A commercial landowner who desires to install more than one dock with three slip spaces or moorings, or who wishes to use a boat launch ramp for commercial purposes.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person who wishes to obtain a special permit shall apply to the lake manager on a form provided by the Department. When the special permit is requested:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>By a commercial landowner for the installation of more than one dock with three slip spaces, the applicant shall include a detailed plan for the proposed use of the buffer strip and the lake, including the proposed placement of docks, number of slips, and types of uses proposed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For alterations, modifications, or other uses of the buffer strip, the applicant shall include a detailed plan which describes materials to be used, construction methods, proposed timetables, location of modifications, and other relevant information.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The lake manager may request additional relevant information from the applicant. Failure to submit requested information shall result in denial of the application.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>After assessing the possible damage to the buffer strip and lake, or both, the lake manager may require the applicant to submit a bond in a reasonable amount to cover the possible damage to the lake or the buffer strip. If a bond is required, the lake manager shall state in writing to the applicant the amount of the bond and the reasons why a bond is required. Failure to submit the required bond shall result in denial of the application.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Issuance.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>When the applicant requests a special permit for installation of permanent structures, excavation or filling of the buffer strip or lake bottom, or removal of vegetation, other than maintenance authorized under <cite path="|08|08|05|.03|A.|(3)">Regulation .03A(3) of this chapter</cite>, the lake manager may issue the permit in accordance with this regulation, as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In reviewing an application for a special permit, the lake manager shall consider the criteria set out in <cite path="|08|08|05|.01|C.">Regulation .01C of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A special permit issued by the lake manager shall specify the use, modification, construction, alteration, or activity permitted. A permittee who exceeds the authority granted in a special permit shall be liable for damage resulting from the unauthorized action.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When the applicant requests the placement of a dock for a commercial landowner to accommodate greater than three slips or moorings, or the use of a boat launch ramp for commercial purposes, the lake manager may grant or deny the application as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If the lake manager determines that the plan for use of the lake and buffer strip is not consistent with these regulations, the application shall be denied.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The lake manager may approve or disapprove the proposed location, type, and position of dock facilities and mooring areas, or otherwise condition the special permit as necessary considering the criteria set out in <cite path="|08|08|05|.01|D.">Regulation .01D of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If the use of the boat slips or moorings includes the overnight storage of boats, not including rental boats, boats used by marina employees, or boats stored for service, or includes the leasing of boat slips to the public, the lake manager may approve not more than one slip space or mooring buoy for each 50 feet of usable buffer strip frontage to which the applicant has title, unless a permit had been issued before May 5, 1986 and the commercial use has not significantly changed. The following apply:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>If a property validated for commercial use significantly changes to a use other than that described in the permit and validation, then the lake manager shall restrict the number of slips or mooring buoys to one for each 50 feet of usable buffer strip.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The lake manager may assign to other commercial permittees slips in excess of the 50-foot limitation which have been eliminated from a special permittee's use permit due to a significant change in the nature of the permittee's operation.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The lake manager may approve less than one slip space or mooring buoy for each 50 feet of frontage as described in <cite path="08|08|05|.05|B.|(2)|(c)">§B(2)(c) of this regulation</cite>, if the lake manager determines that this action is necessary under the criteria set out in <cite path="|08|08|05|.01|D.">Regulation .01D of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>If the use of docks or mooring buoys does not include the overnight storage of boats at docking or mooring facilities, or involve ramping or dry storage to accomplish overnight storage of boats, the lake manager may approve more than one slip space or mooring buoy for each 50 feet of frontage, providing the approved level of use is consistent with the criteria set out in <cite path="|08|08|05|.01|D.">Regulation .01D of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Except for boats owned by a buffer strip use permit holder stored on ramps, when the special permit approves the use of a boat launch ramp, the lake manager shall specifically designate the number and types of launchings which are to be permitted. The lake manager may alter the permitted number of launchings at any time to protect public safety or welfare or to carry out the policies set forth in <cite path="08.08.01.01">COMAR 08.08.01.01</cite>. The commercial permittee shall limit the number of daily launchings to that stated in the permit.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A special permit holder who violates the terms of the permit or these regulations is liable for all damages to the buffer strip or lake resulting from the violation. Upon violation of the terms of the permit or regulations by a special permit holder, the lake manager may:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Revoke the bond, if any;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Recover from the special permit holder any additional damages not covered by the bond.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The forfeiture of the bond and any damages due are in addition to any other penalties provided in these regulations.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Fee. Upon receipt of a special permit, the permittee shall forward to the lake manager the fee specified in the permit. The permit shall be valid only after the lake manager receives the permit fee. This fee is in addition to any fee assessed for a buffer strip use permit.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|08|05|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Development Permits.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Permit Required. A person intending to develop property adjacent to the buffer strip, and who should reasonably anticipate future requests for one or more buffer strip use permits in connection with the development and use of the property, shall obtain a development permit, if the property or the buffer strip, or both, are to be used in any of the following ways:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>By constructing more than one residential unit which has or will have deeded access to the same area of buffer strip;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>By constructing multiple family dwellings with access to the buffer strip;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>By installing or expanding a common dock facility;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>By constructing or adding onto a hotel, motel, condominium, or convention center with access to the buffer strip.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Application. A person who wishes to obtain a development permit shall apply to the lake manager on a form provided by the Department. In addition, the application shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Include a plan and plat showing the lake frontage to be used and the property to be developed for which the development permit is requested;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>State the number of dwellings to be placed upon the property, the number of persons who will use the lake frontage, and other information relevant to use of the buffer strip by the occupiers of the property to be developed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Include a detailed plan for use of the buffer strip and the lake by persons using the area of the buffer strip to which the permit applies, including the proposed placement of a dock or docks, the number of slips, and any restrictions concerning number of boats and size of boats.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Request for Information. The lake manager may request information relevant to a decision as to the use of the buffer strip, and may request the applicant or parties who will use the buffer strip to prepare and execute appropriate covenants or contracts. Failure to comply with this section shall result in denial of the application.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Issuance.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>When a development permit is required for all or part of a property, the lake manager may not issue a buffer strip use permit in connection with the property unless the developer has obtained the development permit. The development permit is intended to facilitate a preliminary review process for development employing deeded access, common dock facilities, or multiple family dwellings, hotels, motels, and convention centers. After reviewing the application for a development permit, the lake manager may grant or deny the application as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If the lake manager determines that the plan for use of the lake and buffer strip is not consistent with these regulations, the lake manager shall deny the application for the development permit and for any associated applications for buffer strip use permits requested for the developer, the developer's successors in title, or the developer's lessees;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the lake manager approves the detailed plan for use of the lake and buffer strip that is submitted with the application, the lake manager may grant an application for a development permit and associated buffer strip use permits;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The lake manager may approve or disapprove the proposed location, type and position of dock facilities and mooring areas, or otherwise condition the development permit as necessary considering the criteria set out in <cite path="|08|08|05|.01|C.">Regulation .01C of this chapter</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The lake manager may not approve more than one slip space or mooring buoy for each 50 feet of usable buffer strip frontage adjacent to the buffer strip to which the applicant has title;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The lake manager may approve less than one slip space or mooring buoy for each 50 feet of frontage as described in <cite path="08|08|05|.06|D.|(1)|(d)">§D(1)(d) of this regulation</cite>, if the lake manager determines that this action is necessary under the criteria set out in <cite path="|08|08|05|.01|C.">Regulation .01C of this chapter</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The lake manager may approve the docking of personal watercraft at a common dock facility that originated with a development permit if:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The lake manager determines that this action is necessary under the criteria set out in <cite path="|08|08|05|.01|C.">Regulation .01C of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The number of personal watercraft does not exceed 1/3 the total slips allocated through the permit.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The lake manager may not issue a development permit to an applicant whose plan includes any of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The creation of a common area with less than 200 feet of usable buffer strip frontage;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The use of more than one area of usable buffer strip frontage, which does not have a continuous, uninterrupted common line shared by the applicant and the Department;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The placement of common dock facilities in an area not immediately next to the proposed common use area;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The intent to enter into long term lease agreements with a commercially designated facility for the purpose of obtaining additional boat slips, or short term ramping access for those not assigned boat slips in the common use area;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Separate docks for less than three boats in addition to a common dock;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The use of buffer strip frontage for which a previously issued buffer strip use permit exists for a single residence, unless adequate steps are taken to clearly designate a minimum of 100 feet of separate usable buffer strip frontage for that parcel;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>The creation of lots which do not meet local zoning requirements for the construction of a residential dwelling unit;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>The use of a boat ramp facility, when the ramp is intended to facilitate day use or dry storage of a number of boats which, when combined with boats stored at docking and mooring facilities, exceed the number of slips and moorings which could be permitted under the criteria described in <cite path="|08|08|05|.01|D.">Regulation .01D of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Before obtaining a development permit, a developer may not make any representation that a number or type of buffer strip facilities or use of the buffer strip or lake has been or will be approved by the lake manager in connection with the developed property.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The lake manager may not issue a development permit to an applicant who proposes a plan for use of the buffer strip which includes a boat ramp facility, when the ramp is intended to facilitate day use or dry storage of a number of boats which, combined with boats stored at the docking and mooring facilities, exceeds the number of slips and moorings which could be permitted under the criteria described in <cite path="|08|08|05|.01|D.">Regulation .01D of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Fees. Upon receipt of a development permit, the permittee shall forward to the lake manager the fee specified in the permit. The permit shall be valid only after the lake manager receives the fee. This fee is in addition to any fee assessed for a buffer strip use permit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Activity under a Development Permit. The development permit, including the approved lake and buffer strip use plan, shall control the use of the buffer strip for the property included under the permit, and buffer strip use permits shall be issued by the lake manager either to the developer, to his tenants, or to his successors in title, only in conformance with the development permit and plan.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The lake manager, after consulting with the applicant, shall set a termination date for the development permit. The lake manager may extend the termination date if the applicant submits to the lake manager evidence of substantial progress. The following shall be considered evidence of substantial progress:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Financing commitments which extend beyond the termination date of the permit;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The installation of footers for more than 60 percent of the project;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Contracts with subcontractors and material suppliers which extend beyond the termination date of the development permit;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Sales contracts with prospective purchasers for more than 5 percent of the development.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Notice of Application for Development Permit or Commercial Validation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Upon receipt of an application for a development permit, or an application for a special permit filed by a person who requests validation of his buffer strip use permit for commercial use and desires to install more than one dock with three slip spaces, the lake manager shall take the following actions:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Publish a notice of the filing and a summary of the application in a Garrett County newspaper of general circulation for at least 2 consecutive weeks, beginning not later than 10 days from the date of filing of the application.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Forward a copy of the application to each property owner whose property borders the application property and the buffer strip. Within 10 days of the filing:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Mail a copy of the application to the bordering property owner by Certified Mail — Return Receipt Requested, and regular mail;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Forward to each member of the Deep Creek Lake Advisory and Review Committee a copy of the application.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Applications on file with the lake manager are a matter of public record and shall be available to the public for inspection during the lake manager's regular weekly business hours.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Comments received on an application pending before the lake manager shall be considered in the lake manager's review of the application. A person who is, or may be, adversely affected by a decision of the lake manager may file an appeal in accordance with the appeals process under <cite path="|08.08.08">COMAR 08.08.08</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Nonconforming Use Permits.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Any use, structure, dock, or vessel which does not conform to these regulations is prohibited, unless the owner has obtained a nonconforming use permit by November 5, 1986, unless good cause for delay is shown.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A nonconforming use permit entitles the permittee to use the structure, dock, or vessel as provided in this regulation, and shall be obtained in addition to any other permits required under this subtitle.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Application. A person who desires to obtain a nonconforming use permit shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Have applied to the lake manager on a form provided by the Department not later than November 6, 1986, unless good cause for delay is shown; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Submit evidence to the lake manager that the structure, building, dock, or vessel for which a nonconforming use permit is sought was in existence lawfully and authorized by the Department before May 5, 1986.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Issuance.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>After reviewing the application under the criteria set out in <cite path="|08|08|05|.01|D.">Regulation .01D of this chapter</cite>, the lake manager may deny or approve all or any part of the application.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the lake manager approves all or part of the application, the lake manager shall issue a nonconforming use permit which specifies the use allowed and states the term of the permit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The lake manager may not issue a nonconforming use permit for use which:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is otherwise illegal under State or federal laws;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The lake manager finds represents a danger to the operation of the Deep Creek Lake Hydroelectric Project; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Existed before May 5, 1986, and which violated any previous regulations or permit governing the use of the buffer strip or Deep Creek Lake.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Fee. Upon receipt of a nonconforming use permit, the permittee shall forward to the lake manager the fee specified in the permit. This fee is in addition to any fee assessed for a buffer strip use permit. The permit shall be valid only after the lake manager receives the fee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Revocation. An alteration, expansion, or change in the character or size of the buildings, structures, docks, or boats or all of these, aside from ordinary maintenance, shall result in the revocation of the permit and of the nonconforming use status resulting in the right of the Department to take action as if the use were illegal under these regulations and in accordance with <cite path="|08.08.06">COMAR 08.08.06</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Natural Resources Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|5-209">5-209</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|5-215">5-215</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|8-704">8-704</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-05-05">Effective date: May 5, 1986 (13:9 Md. R. 1024)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1988-09-19"><cite path="|08|08|05|.02|C.">Regulation .02C</cite> amended effective September 19, 1988 (15:19 Md. R. 2245)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1988-09-19"><cite path="|08|08|05|.03|C.">Regulation .03C</cite> amended effective September 19, 1988 (15:19 Md. R. 2245)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1988-09-19"><cite path="|08|08|05|.04|D.">Regulation .04D</cite> amended effective September 19, 1988 (15:19 Md. R. 2245)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-07-10" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective July 10, 1989 (16:13 Md. R. 1419)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-05-29">Chapter revised as an emergency provision effective April 29, 2000 (27:10 Md. R. 962); revised permanently effective May 29, 2000 (27:10 Md. R. 965)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-06-09">Regulation 03A amended effective June 9, 2025 (52:11 Md. R. 532)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-10-04"><cite path="|08|08|05|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite> amended effective October 4, 2010 (37:20 Md. R. 1392)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-09-16"><cite path="|08|08|05|.03|G.">Regulation .03G</cite> amended effective September 16, 2024 (51:18 Md. R.808)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-06-09">Regulation 03I adopted effective June 9, 2025 (52:11 Md. R. 532)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-10-04"><cite path="|08|08|05|.06|D.">Regulation .06D</cite> amended effective October 4, 2010 (37:20 Md. R. 1393)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
