<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>07</num>
  <heading>Removal of Docks, Mooring Buoys, Structures, and Facilities</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Lapse, Revocation, or Other Termination of Permits.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Upon lapse, revocation, or other termination of a permit, a permanent structure or facility under the permit shall remain with the land unless the Department orders removal in writing for the following reasons:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Department determines that the structure or facility is or may become a safety hazard;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Department determines that the structure or facility is or may become an interference with the operation of the Deep Creek Lake hydroelectric project;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Department determines that the structure or facility is or may become an interference with public use of the buffer strip; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Department determines the structure or facility should be removed for aesthetic reasons due to dilapidation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Upon lapse, revocation, or other termination of a permit for a temporary structure or facility, the permittee shall remove, at the permittee's expense, the temporary structure or facility and restore the land to its natural condition.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Removal of Safety Hazards.</heading>
    <text>The Department may immediately remove, or the lake manager may order the immediate removal of, a safety hazard on the buffer strip or in the lake. The lake manager shall notify the permittee or other responsible person by certified mail. The person responsible for creating the safety hazard shall be liable to the Department for all costs of removal and damage to the lake or buffer strip, or both.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Removal by Department.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Upon failure of a person to remove a structure or facility within 30 days after notice to remove is sent by the lake manager, the Department may have the structure or facility removed. The person shall be liable to the Department for the cost of removal and storage.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A person who places or maintains a dock, mooring buoy, or other facility without first obtaining a permit from the lake manager, or after suspension or revocation of a permit, shall be subject to removal of the facility by the Department at the expense of that person.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Reclamation.</heading>
    <text>A person may reclaim a dock, mooring buoy or structure removed and stored by the Department by reimbursing the Department for the cost incurred. If a person fails to reclaim the property within 6 months of its removal, the Department may dispose of the property.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Failure to Comply.</heading>
    <text>If the lake manager orders removal of the structure, facility, safety hazard, dock, or mooring buoy and the permittee fails to comply within the time allowed, then the bond in <cite path="08.08.05.05|A.|(4)">COMAR 08.08.05.05A(4)</cite>, if required, shall be forfeited and the proceeds applied to:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Removal;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Damages to the lake or buffer strip, or both; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Storage.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Natural Resources Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|5-209">5-209</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|5-215">5-215</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-05-05">Effective date: May 5, 1986 (13:9 Md. R. 1024)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-05-29"><cite path="|08|08|07|.01|A.">Regulation .01A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective April 29, 2000 (27:10 Md. R. 963); amended permanently effective May 29, 2000 (27:10 Md. R. 965)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-07-10"><cite path="|08|08|07|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective July 10, 1989 (16:13 Md. R. 1419)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-07-10"><cite path="|08|08|07|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite> amended effective July 10, 1989 (16:13 Md. R. 1419)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-07-10"><cite path="|08|08|07|.05">Regulation .05</cite> adopted effective July 10, 1989 (16:13 Md. R. 1419)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
