<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Health Education — General Regulations</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Health Education Services Regulations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Type of Service to Be Provided. Services to be provided are health education services of a general nature for purposes of informing the public about various health issues, promoting health enhancing behaviors, and organizing groups to promote the health enhancing activities of others or to achieve societal and environmental changes conducive to health. These services include but are not limited to the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Planning, conducting, and evaluating a media campaign or a component of a media campaign;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Planning, conducting, and evaluating an employee or community intervention for a specified behavior change;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Training health professionals to provide effective education to their clients;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Distributing existing or newly developed health-related educational materials and resources;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Organizing and leading a group to find goals and strategies to achieve a health end;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Implementing population-based health education programs using evidence-based methods and strategies;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Assessing and analyzing community needs and assets;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Accessing, interpreting, and disseminating qualitative and quantitative data; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Planning, conducting, and evaluating health promotion and education interventions and initiatives.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Client Eligibility Standards. All permanent residents of Maryland are eligible to receive services subject to the funding available and limited by the jurisdiction or jurisdictions and target populations specified in a request for proposal.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Licensing or Certification Requirements of Professional Service Providers and Facilities as Applicable.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All organizations, public and private, which are permitted to engage in business in Maryland may be contractors for health education services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If candidates seeking health educator positions in State service have similar qualifications, the Maryland Department of Health shall give a hiring preference to those candidates who have Certified Health Education Specialist (CHES) credentials issued by the National Commission for Health Education Credentialing, Inc.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Vendor requirements for specific programs, if any, will be specified in a request for proposal.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health-General Article, §§2-104(b) and 2-105(b), Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-04-08">Effective date: April 8, 1985 (12:7 Md. R. 707)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-06-25"><cite path="|10|52|03|.01|A.">Regulation .01A</cite>, C amended effective June 25, 2012 (39:12 Md. R. 745)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
