<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>Fire Prevention Code</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Title.</heading>
    <text>This chapter shall be known and may be cited as the State Fire Prevention Code.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The purpose of this chapter is to establish minimum requirements that will provide a reasonable degree of fire prevention and control to safeguard life, property, or public welfare from:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The hazards of fire and explosion arising from the storage, handling, or use of substances, materials, or devices; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Conditions hazardous to life, property, or public welfare in the use or occupancy of buildings, structures, sheds, tents, lots, or premises.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This chapter incorporates by reference NFPA 1 Fire Code (2024 Edition), except as amended in Regulations .08 and .09 of this chapter, and NFPA 101 Life Safety Code (2024 Edition), except as amended in <cite path="|29|06|01|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The State Fire Prevention Commission recommends the use of the NFPA National Fire Codes or other nationally recognized standards in technical matters not specifically addressed by this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Application and Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter applies to both new and existing buildings and conditions. In various sections there are specific provisions for existing buildings that may differ from those for new buildings. Unless otherwise noted, this chapter does not apply to facilities, equipment, structures, or installations that were existing or approved for construction or installation before the effective date of this chapter, except in those cases in which it is determined by the authority having jurisdiction (AHJ) that the existing situation constitutes a hazard so inimical to the public welfare and safety as to require correction. The requirements for existing buildings and conditions may be modified if their application clearly would be impractical in the judgment of the AHJ, but only if it is clearly evident that a reasonable degree of safety is provided. The State Fire Marshal or the legally appointed designee has the authority to make a determination of the applicability of this chapter to any building or condition in it, subject to the right of appeal to the State Fire Prevention Commission as prescribed in <cite path="|29.06.02">COMAR 29.06.02</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Repealed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The provisions of this chapter do not apply in Baltimore City except to those buildings and conditions specifically prescribed in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps">Public Safety Article, Title 6, Subtitle 4, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The provisions of this chapter do not apply to buildings used solely as dwelling houses for not more than two families as prescribed in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps">Public Safety Article, Title 6, Subtitle 3, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Enforcement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Enforcement of this chapter is the responsibility of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The State Fire Marshal;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A legally designated fire official of a county or municipal corporation of the State; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Other persons legally appointed by the State Fire Marshal under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps">Public Safety Article, Title 6, Subtitle 3, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The State Fire Marshal or the legally appointed designee may accept alternate methods of satisfying the intent of this chapter if the material, method, or work is at least the equivalent of that required by this chapter in quality, effectiveness, durability, and safety, and meets or exceeds the intent of the chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If there are differing or conflicting requirements between this chapter and codes or standards adopted by incorporation by reference by this chapter, the State Fire Marshal or the legally appointed designee shall determine which requirements apply, subject to the right of appeal to the State Fire Prevention Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps">Public Safety Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or this chapter requires that a permit, license, or certificate of approval be obtained from the State Fire Marshal, it shall be obtained from the State Fire Marshal, or other appropriate authority, of the county, city, or incorporated town where the activity or equipment for which the permit, license, or certificate required is located.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A violation of this chapter is subject to the penalties set forth in the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps">Public Safety Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Authority having jurisdiction (AHJ)” means the State Fire Marshal or the legally appointed designee as prescribed in this chapter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“International Code Council (ICC)” means International Code Council, Inc., 200 Massachusetts Avenue N.W., Suite 250, Washington, DC 20001.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Legally appointed designee” means those local or county officials specifically authorized under the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps">Public Safety Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, to enforce the provisions of the State Fire Laws and State Fire Prevention Code.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“New building or condition” means a building, structure, installation, plant, equipment, renovation, or condition:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>For which a building permit is issued on or after the effective date of this chapter;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>On which actual construction is started on or after the effective date of this chapter in a jurisdiction where a building permit is not required;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Which represents a change from one occupancy classification to another on or after the effective date of this chapter; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Which represents a situation, circumstance, or physical makeup of any structure, premise, or process that was commenced on or after the effective date of this chapter.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“NFPA” means National Fire Protection Association, 1 Batterymarch Park, Quincy, MA 02169-7471.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="29|06|01|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Incorporation by Reference.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following documents are incorporated by reference, with the amendments specified in this chapter. Tentative interim amendments and supplements to these documents and to the codes and standards referenced in these documents are not included as part of this chapter unless specifically adopted by this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Documents Incorporated.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>NFPA 1 Fire Code (2024 Edition).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>NFPA 101 Life Safety Code (2024 Edition).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Incorporation by Reference Locations. The documents incorporated by reference in <cite path="29|06|01|.06|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> are available for inspection in State depository libraries.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>National Fire Protection Association 101 Life Safety Code.</heading>
    <text>The NFPA 101 Life Safety Code (2024 Edition) is incorporated by reference, except for the following amendments:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Amend Sections 2.2 and 2.4 to delete the referenced publications NFPA 150 Standard on Fire and Life Safety in Animal Housing Facilities, 2022 edition, and NFPA 5000 Building Construction and Safety Code, 2024 edition. Wherever NFPA 5000 is referenced, other than for extracted text, substitute the building code adopted by the AHJ.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Amend Subsection 3.3.66 to add the following Paragraph: 3.3.66.3 Bulkhead Door. A type of door assembly covering an opening in the ground providing direct access to a basement, the floor of which is not more than 8 feet below ground level. The door consists of a single rigid leaf or two overlapping rigid leaves or covers that need to be pushed or lifted upwards in order to be opened. A person, after opening the door, can walk up a series of steps to escape to the outside.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 3.3.70.1 to replace “three” with “five" and delete, “if any, accommodated in rented rooms”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 3.3.154.1 and Subparagraphs 16.6.1.1.2 and 17.6.1.1.2 to delete “more than 3, but”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraphs 3.3.205.4 and 6.1.4.1 to delete “four or more”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraphs 3.3.205.12 and 6.1.9.1 to replace “four” with “six”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Amend Subsection 4.5.8 and Paragraph 4.6.12.1 to delete “for compliance with the provisions of this Code”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 4.6.10.2 to replace “Where required by Chapters 11 through 43, construction” with “Construction”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 4.6.12.3 to delete “by the Code”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Amend Subsection 4.8.2 to add the following Paragraph: 4.8.2.4 Emergency action plans shall be maintained in a location approved by the AHJ.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Amend Subparagraph 6.1.8.1.1 to replace “three” with “five” and delete “, if any, accommodated in rented rooms”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Amend Subsection 7.1.10 to add the following Paragraph: 7.1.10.3 Trash or recyclable materials awaiting scheduled collection shall not be placed in exits, exit access corridors, or on egress balconies.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>Amend Sub-subparagraph 7.2.1.6.4.1 to replace “in Chapters 11 through 43” with "by the AHJ and Chapters 11 through 43".</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>Amend Subparagraph 7.2.1.7.1 to delete “required to be”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>Amend Subparagraph 7.2.1.7.4 to delete "Required".</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>P.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 7.2.1.12 to delete “7.2.1.12.1 or”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>Q.</num>
      <text>Delete Subparagraph 7.2.1.12.1.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>R.</num>
      <text>Amend Subparagraphs 7.2.1.14.1 and 7.2.1.15.1 to replace “Chapters 11 through 43” with “the AHJ or Chapters 11 through 43”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>S.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 7.9.1.2 to replace “only” in the first sentence with “, but not be limited to,”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>T.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 8.7.3.3 to replace “8.7.3.3.5” with “8.7.3.3.5, unless otherwise permitted by the AHJ:”</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>U.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 9.6.1.3 and Subsection 9.11.1 to delete “required by this Code”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>V.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 9.6.2.6 to add the following: This paragraph does not permit the omission of manual fire alarm boxes in accordance with other provisions of this Subsection unless specifically permitted by Chapters 11 through 43.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>W.</num>
      <text>Delete Subparagraph 9.6.2.10.7 and Sub-subparagraphs 9.6.2.10.7.1 and 9.6.2.10.7.2.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>X.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 9.7.1.1 to add the following Subparagraph: 9.7.1.1.1 For new ceiling installations, drop-out ceilings as referenced in NFPA 13 Subsection 9.3.11 and NFPA 13R Section 6.15 shall be prohibited.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>Y.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 9.11.4.1 and Subsection 9.14.1 to replace “Chapters 11 through 43” with “the AHJ and Chapters 11 through 43”</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>Z.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 9.11.4.2 to replace “by 9.3.5” with “by the AHJ, 9.3.5”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>AA.</num>
      <text>Amend Subsection 9.13.1 to replace “by another section of this Code” with “the AHJ and another section of this Code”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>BB.</num>
      <text>Amend Subsections 9.15.1 and 9.15.2 to insert the words “and the AHJ” after “NFPA 1225”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>CC.</num>
      <text>Amend Subsections 10.4.1 and 10.5.1 to add the following at the beginning of each sentence: “Unless otherwise permitted by the AHJ,”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>DD.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 10.7.1.1 to add “and be approved by the AHJ” after “10.7.5.2”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>EE.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 11.8.3.1 to add “High-rise buildings do not include a structure or building used exclusively for open-air parking.”</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>FF.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraphs 11.8.6.1 and 11.8.6.2 to replace “approved by the fire department” with “approved by the AHJ”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>GG.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph <cite path="|11.11">11.11</cite>.2.1 to add “or other approved testing standard approved by the State Fire Marshal”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>HH.</num>
      <text>Delete Section <cite path="|11.12">11.12</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>II.</num>
      <text>Delete Paragraphs 12.2.1.2, 14.2.1.5, 16.2.1.1, 28.2.1.4, 30.2.1.3, 32.2.2.7, 36.2.1.6, 38.2.1.5, 40.2.1.3, 42.2.1.3, Subparagraphs 16.6.2.1.2, 32.3.2.1.3, and Subsection 26.2.4.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>JJ.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraphs 12.2.4.1 and 13.2.4.1 to add the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Not less than two separate exits shall be provided on every story.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Not less than two separate exits shall be accessible from every part of every story.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>KK.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 12.3.5.1 to replace “The following assembly occupancies” with “The following assembly occupancies having an occupant load of 100 or more persons, or 5,000 or more square feet in area, or located on a floor other than the level of exit discharge”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>LL.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraphs 12.7.7.3 and 13.7.7.3 to replace “prior” with “within 10 minutes prior”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>MM.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraphs 14.7.2.3 and 15.7.2.3 to delete existing wording and replace with the following:</text>
      <text>Fire emergency egress drills shall be conducted as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Not less than one fire emergency egress drill shall be conducted every month the facility is in session, unless the following criteria are met:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In climates where the weather is severe, the monthly fire emergency egress drills shall be permitted to be deferred; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>In educational occupancies which are:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>fully protected by an automatic sprinkler system, the total number of annual fire emergency egress drills shall be five, with a least two of the required drills conducted in the first four months of the school year; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>not fully protected by an automatic sprinkler system, the total number of annual fire emergency egress drills shall be eight, with at least three of the required drills conducted in the first four months of the school year.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All occupants of the building shall participate in the fire emergency egress drill.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>One fire emergency egress drill, other than for educational occupancies that are open on a year-round basis, shall be required within the first 30 days of operation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>NN.</num>
      <text>Amend Sub-subparagraphs 15.2.2.2.4.1(3) and 17.2.2.2.6.1(3) to replace “operations,” with “operations, the locking device is of a type that is readily distinguishable as locked,”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>OO.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 15.2.4.2 to delete “unless otherwise permitted by 15.2.4.2(3)” from item (1) and delete item (3).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>PP.</num>
      <text>Amend Sub-subparagraph 15.3.4.3.1.2 to delete “control unit or”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>QQ.</num>
      <text>Amend Subsections 16.1.1 and 17.1.1 to add the following Paragraphs: 16.1.1.10 and 17.1.1.10 Day-care centers providing day care for school-age children before or after school hours in a building which is in use as a public or private school are not required to meet the provisions of this chapter, but shall meet the provisions for educational occupancies.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>RR.</num>
      <text>Amend Subparagraphs 16.2.11.1.1 to add the following item: (4) For grade floor windows the minimum net clear opening shall be permitted to be 5.0 square feet.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>SS.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 16.3.5.1 to add the following: Automatic sprinkler protection is not required if all of the following conditions are met:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The total number of occupants in the occupancy in which the day care center is located is not more than 300 persons.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All rooms used for day care are located on the level of exit discharge;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All rooms used for day care have at least one exterior exit door at grade level; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The occupancy in which the day care center is located does not exceed 12,000 square feet in area.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>TT.</num>
      <text>Amend Sub-subparagraphs 16.6.1.4.1.1 and 17.6.1.4.1.1 to delete “more than three, but” and replace “seven” with “nine”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>UU.</num>
      <text>Amend Sub-subparagraphs 16.6.1.4.1.2 and 17.6.1.4.1.2 to replace “7” with “9”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>VV.</num>
      <text>Amend Subparagraphs 16.6.1.7.1 and 17.6.1.7.1 to replace “both” with “all” and Items (1) and (2) with the following Items:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The minimum staff-to-client ratio shall be not less than one staff member for up to eight clients, including the caretaker's own children incapable of self-preservation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>There shall be not more than four clients incapable of self-preservation, including the caretaker's own children incapable of self-preservation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A staff-to-client ratio of at least one staff member to every two clients incapable of self-preservation shall be maintained at all times.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The staff-to-client ratio shall be permitted to be modified by the authority having jurisdiction where safeguards in addition to those specified in this section are provided.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>WW.</num>
      <text>Amend Subparagraph 16.6.2.1.1 and Paragraph 17.6.2.1 to add the following: Bulkhead doors may not serve as a primary means of escape.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>XX.</num>
      <text>Amend Subparagraphs 16.6.2.4.5 and 17.6.2.4.5 to delete item (3).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>YY.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraphs 16.6.2.2 (Reserved) and 17.6.2.2 (Reserved) to add the following: SLIDING DOOR: For family day-care homes, a sliding door used as a required means of escape shall comply with the following conditions:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The sliding door shall have not more than one, easily operated, locking device that does not require special knowledge, effort, or tools to operate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>There may not be draperies, screens, or storm doors that could impede egress;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The sill or track height may not exceed 1/2 inch above the interior finish floor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The surface onto which exit is made shall be an all weather surface such as a deck, patio, or sidewalk;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The floor level outside the door may be one step lower than the inside, but not more than 8 inches lower;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The sliding door shall open to a clear open width of at least 28 inches;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Before day-care use each day, the sliding door shall be unlocked and tested to the full required width to be sure it is operating properly, and the door shall be nonbinding and slide easily; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>During periods of snow or freezing rain, door tracks shall be cleared out and the door opened periodically throughout the day in order to ensure proper operation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>ZZ.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraphs 16.6.2.3 (Reserved) and 17.6.2.3 (Reserved) to add the following:</text>
      <text>SPECIAL MEANS OF ESCAPE REQUIREMENTS: For family day-care homes, deadbolt locks shall be provided with approved interior latches, or these locks shall be of a captured key design from which the key cannot be removed from the interior side of the lock when the lock is in the locked position.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>AAA.</num>
      <text>Amend Subparagraph 16.6.3.4.5 to replace the word “Reserved.” with the following: For compliance with Paragraph 43.7.2.1(2), approved battery-powered smoke alarms, rather than house electrical service-powered smoke alarms required by 16.6.3.4.4, shall be permitted where the facility has testing, maintenance, and smoke alarm replacement programs that ensure reliability of power to the smoke alarms.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>BBB.</num>
      <text>Amend Subparagraph 17.2.11.1.1 to add the following item:</text>
      <include>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>For grade floor windows the minimum net clear opening shall be permitted to be 5.0 feet.</text>
        </para>
      </include>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>CCC.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraphs 17.6.2.1, 28.2.1.2, 29.2.1.2, 30.2.1.2, 31.2.1.2 and Subparagraphs 16.6.2.1.1, 16.6.2.4.1, 16.6.2.4.2, 17.6.2.4.1, 17.6.2.4.2, and 33.3.2.1.2 to add the following sentence: The provisions of Subsection 24.2.8 shall not apply.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>DDD.</num>
      <text>Amend Subparagraph 17.6.3.4.5 to delete “existing” and replace “battery” with “smoke alarm”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>EEE.</num>
      <text>Amend Section 19.3 to add the following Paragraph and Subparagraphs:</text>
      <include>
        <para>
          <num>19.3.4.6</num>
          <text>Carbon Monoxide Detection.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>19.3.4.6.1</num>
          <text>Carbon monoxide detection, where required by 19.3.4.6.2, shall be in accordance with Section 9.12.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>19.3.4.6.2</num>
          <text>Carbon monoxide detection shall be provided in the following locations:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Carbon monoxide detectors shall be installed on the ceilings of rooms containing permanently installed fuel-burning appliances, including fireplaces.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Carbon monoxide detectors shall be installed within 36 inches (910 millimeters) of the first supply air register from a permanently installed, fuel-burning HVAC system.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </include>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>FFF.</num>
      <text>Amend Section 21.3 to add the following Paragraph and Subparagraphs:</text>
      <include>
        <para>
          <num>21.3.4.5</num>
          <text>Carbon Monoxide Detection.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>21.3.4.5.1</num>
          <text>Carbon monoxide detection, where required by 21.3.4.5.2, shall be in accordance with Section 9.12.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>21.3.4.5.2</num>
          <text>Carbon monoxide detection shall be provided in the following locations:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Carbon monoxide detectors shall be installed on the ceilings of rooms containing permanently installed fuel-burning appliances, including fireplaces.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Carbon monoxide detectors shall be installed within 36 inches (910 millimeters) of the first supply air register from a permanently installed, fuel-burning HVAC system.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </include>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>GGG.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 22.4.6.2 to add the following Subparagraph:</text>
      <include>
        <para>
          <num>22.4.6.2.5</num>
          <text>Automatic sprinkler protection shall be installed throughout the building in accordance with 9.7.1.1.</text>
        </para>
      </include>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>HHH.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 24.1.1.2 to replace “three” with “five” and delete “, if any, accommodated in rented rooms”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>III.</num>
      <text>Amend Subparagraphs 24.2.2.3.3, 32.2.2.3.1(3), and 33.2.2.3.1(3) to insert “, or not less than 5.0 square feet for grade floor windows” after “5.7 ft2”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>JJJ.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 26.1.1.1 to replace “buildings” with “buildings that do not qualify as one- and two-family dwellings”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>KKK.</num>
      <text>Delete Subsections 30.7.5 and 31.7.5.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>LLL.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 31.3.5.9.1 to replace “by January 1, 2033” with “within 12 years of the date of the original violation notice issued by the fire authority having jurisdiction.”</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>MMM.</num>
      <text>Amend Sub-subparagraph 33.3.3.4.8.1 to delete “33.3.3.4.8.2 and”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>NNN.</num>
      <text>Delete Sub-subparagraph 33.3.3.4.8.2.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>OOO.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraphs 36.3.5.3, 37.3.5.3, 38.3.5.2, and 39.3.5 to replace “portable” with “Unless otherwise permitted by the AHJ, portable”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>PPP.</num>
      <text>Amend Table 42.2.5 to replace “50” with “75” and “15” with “23” for common path of travel for ordinary hazard storage occupancy not protected throughout by an approved, supervised automatic sprinkler system in accordance with 9.7.1.1(1).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>QQQ.</num>
      <text>Amend Subparagraphs 42.3.4.1.2 and 42.3.4.1.3 to replace “Storage occupancies” with “Storage occupancies less than three stories”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>RRR.</num>
      <text>Amend Sub-subparagraphs 42.8.3.4.1.1 and 42.8.3.4.1.3 to replace “Parking structures” with “Parking structures less than three stories”.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>National Fire Protection Association 1 Fire Code.</heading>
    <text>The NFPA 1 Fire Code (2024 Edition) is incorporated by reference, except for the amendments in <cite path="|29|06|01|.09">Regulation .09 of this chapter</cite> and the following amendments:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Delete Section 1.11. (See <cite path="|29.06.02">COMAR 29.06.02</cite>)</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Delete Section 1.12.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Amend Subsection 1.13.1 to add the following Paragraph: 1.13.1.1 Permits, certificates, notices, approvals, or orders required by this code shall be governed by the policies and procedures of the AHJ.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 1.13.6.13 to replace “Permits shall” with “Permits may”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Amend Subsection 1.13.8 to replace “shall” with “may”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Amend Subsection 1.14.2 to delete “Mandatory.” and replace “shall” with “may”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Delete Paragraph 1.14.12.4.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Amend Subsection 2.1.1 and Paragraphs 2.1.1.1 and 2.1.1.2 to replace “Compliance” with “Where permitted by the AHJ, compliance”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Amend Section 2.2 to delete the referenced publication NFPA 5000 Building Construction and Safety Code, 2024 edition. Wherever NFPA 5000 is referenced, other than for extracted text, substitute the building code adopted by the AHJ. Delete the referenced publication NFPA 150 Standard on Fire and Life Safety in Animal Housing Facilities, 2022 edition.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Amend Section 2.4 to delete the publication NFPA 5000 Building Construction Safety Code, 2024 edition. Wherever NFPA 5000 is referenced, other than for extracted text, substitute the building code adopted by the AHJ.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Amend Subsection 3.3.17 to add the following Paragraph: 3.3.17.12 Consumer Fireworks Retail Sales Area. The portion of a consumer fireworks retail sales facility or store, including the immediately adjacent aisles, where consumer fireworks are located for the purpose of retail display and sale to the public.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Amend Subsection 3.3.136 and Paragraph 3.3.136.1 to add “and as referenced in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|10-101">Public Safety Article, §10-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>Delete Subsection 3.3.175.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 3.3.203.6 to delete “more than 3 but”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraphs 3.3.203.7 and 6.1.4.1 to delete “four or more”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>P.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 3.3.203.25 and Subparagraph 3.3.203.25.1 to replace “three” with “five” and delete “, if any, accommodated in rented rooms”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>Q.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraphs 3.3.203.28 and 6.1.9.1 to replace “four” with “six”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>R.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 4.5.8.1 to delete “for compliance with the provisions of this Code”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>S.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 4.5.8.3 to delete “by the Code”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>T.</num>
      <text>Amend Subparagraph 6.1.8.1.1 to replace “three” with “five” and delete “, if any, accommodated in rented rooms”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>U.</num>
      <text>Amend Subsection 10.1.2 to add “except as amended by <cite path="29.06.01.07">COMAR 29.06.01.07</cite>, <cite path="29.06.01.08">COMAR 29.06.01.08</cite>, and <cite path="29.06.01.09">COMAR 29.06.01.09</cite>”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>V.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 10.2.7.1 to replace “in Table 10.2.7.1” with “by the AHJ” and Table 10.2.7.1.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>W.</num>
      <text>Amend Annex A to add the following new Paragraph: A.10.2.7.1 The frequency of fire prevention inspections of existing buildings should be based upon a risk assessment of these properties completed by the responsible AHJ. Considerations for this assessment should include, but not be limited to, the occupancy classification of the building and hazards associated with that classification; the number, location, and physical and mental capabilities of potential building occupants (especially self-evacuation abilities); construction design and maintenance of the property; fire protection features of the building; special hazards associated with activities or operations conducted within the building; available fire department suppression resources with special consideration to necessary special suppression operations; and resources available for fire code inspections and enforcement actions<em>.</em></text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>X.</num>
      <text>Amend Subsections 10.5.1 and 10.5.2 to replace “AHJ” with “AHJ or incident commander”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>Y.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 10.2.7.1 to replace “in Table 10.2.7.1” with “by the AHJ” and Table 10.2.7.1.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>Z.</num>
      <text>Amend Subsection <cite path="|10.11">10.11</cite>.1 to add the following Subparagraph and Paragraph:</text>
      <include>
        <para>
          <num>10.11.1.1.1</num>
          <text>Subject to the approval of the AHJ, individual suites within structures and rear exterior entrances and/or access from service corridors shall be clearly identified.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num proof="done">10.11.1.9</num>
          <text>Where required by the AHJ, symbols in compliance with NFPA 170 Standard for Fire Safety and Emergency Symbols shall be used.</text>
        </para>
      </include>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>AA.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph <cite path="|10.11">10.11</cite>.1.1, <cite path="|10.11">10.11</cite>.1.2, <cite path="|10.11">10.11</cite>.1.3, <cite path="|10.11">10.11</cite>.1.4, and <cite path="|10.11">10.11</cite>.1.8 to replace “address numbers” with “premises identification”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>BB.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph <cite path="|10.11">10.11</cite>.1.6 to delete existing wording and replace with “Where required by the AHJ, the assignment of addresses to buildings shall be in accordance with an approved method.”</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>CC.</num>
      <text>Delete Paragraph <cite path="|10.11">10.11</cite>.1.7.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>DD.</num>
      <text>Amend Subparagraph <cite path="10.14.12.2">10.14.12.2</cite>.6 to replace “any vehicles” with “any vehicles, buildings,”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>EE.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph <cite path="|10.15">10.15</cite>.5.1 to replace “Portable” with “Unless otherwise approved by the AHJ, portable”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>FF.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph A.10.15.5.1 to add the following: For the purposes of reducing the distances between the operation and refueling of portable and vehicle-mounted generators and any building or enclosure opening, including windows, doors, and air intakes, one or more of the following conditions may be considered:</text>
      <include>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Nature of the occupancy of the building or enclosure.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Expected duration of generator use.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Use of certified low CO emission generators.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Actual available distance between the generator and building or enclosure openings.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Installation of approved CO detection within the building or enclosure.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>Openness of building or enclosure perimeter walls and ceiling.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>Physical barriers or other means to deflect generator exhaust from building or enclosure openings.</text>
        </para>
      </include>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>GG.</num>
      <text>Amend Section <cite path="|10.16">10.16</cite> to add the following Subsection: <cite path="|10.16">10.16</cite>.6 The AHJ shall have the authority to require that outdoor storage of any combustible material be enclosed by an approved fence or other protective enclosure to prevent unauthorized access.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>HH.</num>
      <text>Amend Subsection <cite path="|10.16">10.16</cite>.1 to replace “10 ft (3m)” with “15 feet (4.6 meters)” and “property line” with “property line, building, or adjacent pile of combustible material”; and add the following: The separation distance shall be allowed to be increased where the AHJ determines that a higher hazard to the adjoining property exists.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>II.</num>
      <text>Amend Subsection <cite path="|10.16">10.16</cite>.5 to add “and shall not exceed 10,000 square feet in area”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>JJ.</num>
      <text>Amend Subsection <cite path="|10.19">10.19</cite>.7 to replace “repaired” with “repaired on any balcony, under any overhanging portion, or”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>KK.</num>
      <text>Amend Subsection <cite path="|10.21">10.21</cite>.1 to replace “more than five” with “one or more” and replace “10 ft (3 m)” with “15 feet (4.6 meters)”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>LL.</num>
      <text>Amend Subsection <cite path="|10.21">10.21</cite>.4 Item (3) to replace “10 ft (3 m)” with “15 feet (4.6 meters)”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>MM.</num>
      <text>Amend Section <cite path="|10.22">10.22</cite> to replace “10.22.5” with “10.22.5, unless otherwise permitted by the AHJ”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>NN.</num>
      <text>Amend Section 11.1 to add the following Subsection:</text>
      <include>
        <para>
          <num>11.1.9</num>
          <text>Clearance. A clear space of not less than 30 inches (762 millimeters) in width, 36 inches (914 millimeters) in depth, and 78 inches (1981 millimeters) in height shall be provided in front of electrical service equipment. Where the electrical service equipment is wider than 30 inches (762 millimeters), the clear space shall not be less than the width of the equipment. No storage of any materials shall be located within the designated clear space. Exception: Where other specialized dimensions are required or permitted by NFPA 70.</text>
        </para>
      </include>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>OO.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 11.1.5.6 to delete existing wording and replace with the following: Extension cords shall not be used as a substitute for permanent wiring.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>PP.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 11.1.7.3 to add the following Subparagraph: 11.1.7.3.2 Doors to electrical control panel rooms shall be marked with a plainly visible and legible sign stating ELECTRICAL ROOM or similar approved wording in contrasting letters not less than one inch (25 millimeters) high and not less than ¼ inch (6.4 millimeters) in stroke width.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>QQ.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 11.3.6.1 to add the following sentence: Keys for new elevators shall be cut to a uniform key code to comply with the Maryland State Elevator Code.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>RR.</num>
      <text>Amend Subsection 11.9.1 to replace “approved by the fire department” with “approved by the AHJ”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>SS.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 12.6.9.1 to add the following new Subparagraph: 12.6.9.1.2 The AHJ shall be permitted to:</text>
      <include>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Approve the placement of a natural cut or balled tree;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Limit the number of natural cut or balled trees displayed; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Order the removal of any tree if the tree poses a hazard to life or safety.</text>
        </para>
      </include>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>TT.</num>
      <text>Amend Subparagraph 12.6.9.1.1 to replace “Christmas” with “Unless otherwise approved by the AHJ, Christmas”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>UU.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 12.6.9.5 to add the following Subparagraph: 12.6.9.5.3 Combustible artificial decorative vegetation shall be tested by a laboratory recognized by the Office of the State Fire Marshal.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>VV.</num>
      <text>Amend Subparagraph 12.6.9.6.1 to replace ½” (13 mm)” with “2 inches (50 millimeters)” and add the following sentence: “A natural cut tree shall not exceed 10 feet (3 meters) in height, excluding the tree stand.”</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>WW.</num>
      <text>Amend Section 13.1 to add the following Subsection: 13.1.14 Appearance of Equipment. The AHJ shall be permitted to prohibit any device that has the physical appearance of a life safety or fire protection function but does not perform that life safety or fire protection function.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>XX.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 13.1.3.1 to replace “by Chapters 11 through 43” with “by the AHJ and Chapters 11 through 43”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>YY.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 13.1.3.2 to replace “by 9.3.5” with “by the AHJ, 9.3.5”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>ZZ.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 13.3.1.2 to add the following Subparagraph: 13.3.1.2.1 For new ceiling installations, drop-out ceilings as referenced in NFPA 13, Subsection 9.3.11 and NFPA 13R, Section 6.15, shall be prohibited.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>AAA.</num>
      <text>Amend Subparagraph 13.3.2.5.1 replace “The following assembly occupancies” with “The following assembly occupancies having an occupant load of 100 or more persons, or 5,000 or more square feet in area, or located on a floor other than the level of exit discharge”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>BBB.</num>
      <text>Delete Subparagraph 13.3.2.24.2 and replace with the following:</text>
      <include>
        <text>13.3.2.24.2* Existing high-rise buildings, other than those meeting 13.3.2.24.2.1 or 13.3.2.24.2.2, shall be protected throughout by an approved automatic sprinkler system in accordance with this chapter and 13.3.2.24.2.3 through 13.3.2.24.2.5.</text>
        <para>
          <num>13.3.2.24.2.1</num>
          <text>An automatic sprinkler system shall not be required where every dwelling unit has exterior exit access in accordance with <cite path="|14.10">14.10</cite>.3.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>13.3.2.24.2.2</num>
          <text>An automatic sprinkler system shall not be required in buildings that have a previously approved and implemented engineered life safety system complying with 13.3.2.24.2.2.1 and 13.3.2.24.2.2.2.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>13.3.2.24.2.2.1</num>
          <text>The engineered life safety system shall have been developed by a registered professional engineer experienced in fire and life safety system design, approved by the authority having jurisdiction, and inspected for compliance by the authority having jurisdiction, and shall include any or all of the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Partial automatic sprinkler protection</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Smoke detection systems</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Smoke control systems</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Compartmentation</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Other approved systems</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>13.3.2.24.2.2.2</num>
          <text>The engineered life safety system shall be maintained in accordance with the approved design documents and applicable standard.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>13.3.2.24.2.3</num>
          <text>Each building owner shall, within 180 days of receiving notice, file an intent to comply with this regulation with the AHJ for approval.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>13.3.2.24.2.4</num>
          <text>The AHJ shall review and respond to the intent-to-comply submittal within 60 days of receipt.</text>
          <text>13.3.2.24.2.5* The entire building shall be required to be protected by an approved automatic sprinkler system within 12 years of the date of the original violation notice issued by the fire authority having jurisdiction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num proof="done">13.3.2.24.2.6</num>
          <text>Public Disclosure Signage. In high-rise buildings that are not protected throughout by an approved automatic sprinkler system, signage shall be posted complying with 13.3.2.24.2.6(A) through 13.3.2.24.2.6(D).</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>Signage shall be posted at all main building entrances as approved by the AHJ.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>The lettering on the sign shall be at least 1 inch (25 millimeters) high.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>The lettering shall be placed on a contrasting background.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(D)</num>
            <text>The wording shall state as follows: “WARNING: THIS HIGH-RISE BUILDING IS NOT PROTECTED THROUGHOUT WITH AN AUTOMATIC FIRE SPRINKLER SYSTEM”.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </include>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>CCC.</num>
      <text>Amend A.13.3.2.24.2.3 to replace “A.13.3.2.24.2.3” with “A.13.3.2.24.2.5”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>DDD.</num>
      <text>Amend Subparagraph 13.3.2.25.5 to delete existing wording and replace with the following: An automatic sprinkler system shall be installed throughout all mini-storage building fire areas greater than 2500 feet2(232 meters2) and where any of the individual storage units are separated by less than a 1-hour fire resistance-rated barrier. Fire areas shall be defined by approved fire barriers having a fire resistance rating of not less than 3-hours.[5000:30.3.5.4]</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>EEE.</num>
      <text>Amend Sub-subparagraph 13.3.2.27.1.1 to add the following:</text>
      <include>
        <text>Automatic sprinkler protection is not required if all of the following conditions are met:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The total number of occupants in the occupancy in which the day care center is located is not more than 300 persons.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>All rooms used for day care are located on the level of exit discharge;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>All rooms used for day care have at least one exterior exit door at grade level; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>The occupancy in which the day care center is located does not exceed 12,000 sq. feet in area.</text>
        </para>
      </include>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>FFF.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraphs 13.3.3.1 and 13.3.3.2 to delete “installed in accordance with this Code”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>GGG.</num>
      <text>Amend Subsection 13.4.1 to add the following Subparagraph: 13.4.1.1.1 No fire pump component, including the pump, driver, or controller, shall be permitted to be installed in below-ground vaults or pits unless otherwise approved by the AHJ.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>HHH.</num>
      <text>Amend Subsection 13.6.1.2 to add “, unless otherwise permitted by the AHJ.”</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>III.</num>
      <text>Amend Sub-subparagraph 13.6.4.1.2.1 to replace “certified” with “licensed as required by the AHJ”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>JJJ.</num>
      <text>Delete Sub-subparagraphs 13.6.4.1.2.1.1, 13.6.4.1.2.1.2, 13.6.4.1.2.1.3, 13.6.4.1.2.1.4, 13.6.4.1.2.1.5, 13.6.4.1.2.1.6.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>KKK.</num>
      <text>Amend Sub-subparagraph 13.6.4.1.2.3 to replace “certified” with “licensed”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>LLL.</num>
      <text>Amend Subparagraph 13.7.1.7.6 to add the following: This paragraph does not permit the omission of manual fire alarm boxes in accordance with other provisions of this Subsection unless specifically permitted by NFPA 101 Chapters 11 through 43.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>MMM.</num>
      <text>Amend Subparagraph 13.7.1.15.1 to replace “another section of this Code” with “the AHJ and another section of this Code”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>NNN.</num>
      <text>Amend Sub-subparagraph 13.7.2.5.6.4 to add the following: For compliance with NFPA 101, Paragraph 43.7.2.1(2), approved battery-powered smoke alarms, rather than house electrical service-powered smoke alarms shall be permitted where the facility has testing, maintenance, and smoke alarm replacement programs that ensure reliability of power to the smoke alarms.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>OOO.</num>
      <text>Amend Sub-subparagraph 13.7.2.6.6.5 to delete “existing” and replace “battery” with “smoke alarm”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>PPP.</num>
      <text>Amend Sub-subparagraph 13.7.2.22.8.1 to delete “13.7.2.22.8.2 and”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>QQQ.</num>
      <text>Delete Sub-subparagraph 13.7.2.22.8.2.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>RRR.</num>
      <text>Amend Sub-subparagraphs 13.7.2.28.1.2 and 13.7.2.28.1.3 to replace “Storage occupancies” with “Storage occupancies less than three stories”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>SSS.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 14.4.2.1 to add the following subparagraph:</text>
      <include>
        <para>
          <num>14.4.2.1.1</num>
          <text>Trash or recyclable materials awaiting scheduled collection shall not be placed in exits, exit access corridors, or on egress balconies.</text>
        </para>
      </include>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>TTT.</num>
      <text>Amend Subparagraphs 14.5.2.3.7 and 14.5.2.3.8 to add the following sentence: “The locking device shall be of a type that is readily distinguishable as locked.”</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>UUU.</num>
      <text>Amend Subparagraph 14.5.3.4.1 to replace “in Chapters 11 through 43” with “by the AHJ and in Chapters 11 through 43”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>VVV.</num>
      <text>Amend Subparagraph 14.5.3.5.1 to delete “required to be”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>WWW.</num>
      <text>Amend Subparagraph 14.5.3.5.4 to delete the word “Required”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>XXX.</num>
      <text>Amend Subsection 14.5.8 to delete “14.5.8.1 or”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>YYY.</num>
      <text>Delete Paragraph 14.5.8.1.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>ZZZ.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 14.5.10.1 to replace “by Chapters 11 through 43” with “by the AHJ or Chapters 11 through 43”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>AAAA.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph <cite path="|14.13">14.13</cite>.1.2 to replace “only” in the first sentence with “, but not be limited to,”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>BBBB.</num>
      <text>Amend Subparagraph 18.2.3.2.1 to replace “exterior door” with “exterior door acceptable to the AHJ”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>CCCC.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 18.2.3.4 to replace the word “shall” with “to” and replace the word “newly” with “the AHJ shall be permitted to require newly”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>DDDD.</num>
      <text>Amend Subparagraph 20.1.5.8.3 to replace “prior” to “within 10 minutes prior”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>EEEE.</num>
      <text>Amend Subparagraph 20.2.4.2.3 to delete existing wording and replace with the following: Fire emergency egress drills shall be conducted as follows:</text>
      <include>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Not less than one fire emergency egress drill shall be conducted every month the facility is in session, unless the following criteria are met:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>In climates where the weather is severe, the monthly fire emergency egress drills shall be permitted to be deferred; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>In educational occupancies which are:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(i)</num>
              <text>Fully protected by an automatic sprinkler system, the total number of annual fire emergency egress drills shall be five, with a least two of the required drills conducted in the first four months of the school year; or</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <text>Not fully protected by an automatic sprinkler system, the total number of annual fire emergency egress drills shall be eight, with at least three of the required drills conducted in the first four months of the school year.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>All occupants of the building shall participate in the fire emergency egress drill.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>One fire emergency egress drill, other than for educational occupancies that are open on a year-round basis, shall be required within the first 30 days of operation.</text>
        </para>
      </include>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>FFFF.</num>
      <text>Amend Subparagraph 20.3.4.1.1 and 20.3.4.1.2 to delete “more than 3, but” and the “,” after “12”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>GGGG.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 25.2.2.1 to add “or other approved testing standard approved by the State Fire Marshal”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>HHHH.</num>
      <text>Amend Subsection 26.1.6 to add the following Paragraphs:</text>
      <include>
        <para>
          <num>26.1.6.2</num>
          <text>When requested by the AHJ, a hazard assessment shall be conducted by a technically qualified person acceptable to the AHJ.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>26.1.6.3</num>
          <text>When requested by the AHJ, a list of hazardous materials used in each laboratory shall be provided. The list shall specify the chemical name, quantity and hazard class.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>26.1.6.4</num>
          <text>New laboratories or laboratories where the NFPA 45 laboratory hazard classification changes shall post an information placard near the main entrance to the laboratory. The placard shall state the building name or address, room number, NFPA 45 laboratory hazard classification, edition of NFPA 45, maximum allowable quantities of flammable liquids both inside a storage cabinet and open use, and maximum quantities of flammable gases permitted within the laboratory.</text>
        </para>
      </include>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>IIII.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 32.9.3.7 to replace “made” with “made within 10 minutes prior to the start of each program”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>JJJJ.</num>
      <text>Amend 34.1.3 to replace “An approved storage” with “Where required by the AHJ, an approved storage”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>KKKK.</num>
      <text>Amend Section 34.6 to add the following new Subsection and Paragraphs:</text>
      <include>
        <para>
          <num>34.6.7</num>
          <text>Standpipe systems shall be installed in all storage buildings having an area of 300,000 square feet or more.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>34.6.7.1</num>
          <text>Standpipe systems shall comply with Section 13.2 and NFPA 14.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>34.6.7.2</num>
          <text>Class I hose connections shall be provided at each of the following locations:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>In each exit passageway at the entrance from the storage area into the passageway;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Within every required exit stairwell;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>At other locations such that all points of the storage area floor are within 200 feet. of a hose connection, unless otherwise required by the AHJ.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </include>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>LLLL.</num>
      <text>Delete Chapter 35 Animal Housing Facilities.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>MMMM.</num>
      <text>Amend Subsection 42.7.5 to add the following Paragraphs:</text>
      <include>
        <para>
          <num>42.7.5.7</num>
          <text>Management/owner officials or employees shall conduct daily site visits to ensure that all equipment is operating properly.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>42.7.5.8</num>
          <text>Regular equipment inspection and maintenance at the unattended self-service facility shall be conducted.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>42.7.5.9</num>
          <text>Fuel dispensing equipment shall comply with one of the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The amount of fuel being dispensed is limited in quantity by preprogrammed card; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Dispensing devices shall be programmed or set to limit uninterrupted fuel delivery of not more than 25 gallons and shall require a manual action to resume continued delivery.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </include>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>NNNN.</num>
      <text>Amend Paragraph 42.7.5.5 to add the following: The following information shall be conspicuously posted in this area:</text>
      <include>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The exact address of the unattended self-service facility.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The telephone number of the owner or operator of the unattended self-service facility.</text>
        </para>
      </include>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>OOOO.</num>
      <text>Amend Subsection 50.8.1 to add the following Paragraphs, Subparagraphs, and Sub-subparagraphs:</text>
      <include>
        <para>
          <num>50.8.1.7</num>
          <text>Commercial Outdoor Cooking Operations. These requirements apply to commercial outdoor cooking operations such as those that typically take place under a canopy or tent-type structure at fairs, festivals, and carnivals. This includes, but is not limited to, deep frying, sauteing, and grilling operations.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>50.8.1.7.1</num>
          <text>LP Gas Fuel Requirements.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>50.8.1.7.1.1</num>
          <text>LP gas tank size shall be limited to 60 pounds. The total amount of LP gas on site shall not exceed 60 pounds for each appliance that is rated not more than 80,000 btu/hour and 120 pounds for each appliance rated more than 80,000 btu/hour.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>50.8.1.7.1.2</num>
          <text>Tanks shall be maintained in good physical condition and shall have a valid hydrostatic date stamp.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>50.8.1.7.1.3</num>
          <text>Tanks shall be secured in their upright position with a chain, strap, or other approved method that prevents the tank from tipping over.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>50.8.1.7.1.4</num>
          <text>Tanks shall be located so that they are not accessible to the public. LP gas tanks shall be located at least 5 feet from any cooking or heating equipment or any open flame device.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>50.8.1.7.1.5</num>
          <text>All LP gas equipment shall be properly maintained and comply with the requirements of NFPA 58.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>50.8.1.7.1.6</num>
          <text>Regulators. Single-stage regulators may not supply equipment that is rated more than 100,000 btu/hour rating. Two-stage regulators shall be used with equipment that is rated more than 100,000 btu/hour.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>50.8.1.7.2</num>
          <text>General Safety Requirements.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>50.8.1.7.2.1</num>
          <text>All electrical cords shall be maintained in a safe condition and shall be secured to prevent damage.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>50.8.1.7.2.2</num>
          <text>Movable cooking equipment shall have wheels removed or shall be placed on blocks or otherwise secured to prevent movement of the appliance during operation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>50.8.1.7.2.3</num>
          <text>Portable fire extinguishers shall be provided in accordance with Section 13.6, and shall be specifically listed for such use.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>50.8.1.8</num>
          <text>There shall be no obstructions or impediments to immediate escape from vehicles or other mobile units used for cooking operations.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>50.8.1.9</num>
          <text>Seating for the public shall not be located within any mobile or temporary cooking vehicle<em>.</em></text>
        </para>
      </include>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>PPPP.</num>
      <text>Delete Subsection 50.8.3 and replace with the following:</text>
      <include>
        <para>
          <num>50.8.3</num>
          <text>Tent and Canopy Requirements</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>50.8.3.1</num>
          <text>Temporary cooking operations conducted in tents and under canopies shall comply with NFPA 102 and Chapter 25.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>50.8.3.2</num>
          <text>All tent and canopy material shall comply with the flame resistance requirements of Section 25.2.2.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>50.8.3.3</num>
          <text>Tents or canopies where cooking equipment not protected in accordance with NFPA 96 is located shall not be occupied by the public.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>50.8.3.4</num>
          <text>Tents or canopies where cooking equipment not protected in accordance with NFPA 96 is located shall be separated from other tents, canopies, structures, or vehicles by a minimum of 10 feet (3050 millimeters) unless otherwise approved by the AHJ.</text>
        </para>
      </include>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>QQQQ.</num>
      <text>Amend Subparagraph 50.8.8.3.2 to replace “not be transported or stored inside the vehicle” with “be secured in an upright position during transport and storage”.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="29|06|01|.09">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Fireworks and Explosive Materials.</heading>
    <text>The NFPA 1 Fire Code (2024 Edition) is incorporated by reference, except for the amendments in <cite path="|29|06|01|.08">Regulation .08 of this chapter</cite> and the following amendments:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Permits shall be required for the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Fireworks displays;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Pyrotechnics before a proximate audience; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Flame effects before an audience.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Amend Sections 65.2, 65.3, and 65.4 to add the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All applications for permits for display shall be filed at least 10 business days before the display is to be held.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps">Public Safety Article, Title 10, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the following requirements apply to public liability and property damage insurance:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In order to meet the requirement of the statute, the State shall be named as an insured in the contract of insurance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Because the policy shall cover all damages to persons or property, a deductible form of coverage may not be accepted;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The minimum amount of coverage that the State can accept on any display is $25,000 for the injury of one person, $50,000 for more than one person, and $10,000 for property damage; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A duplicate policy of a certificate of insurance shall be attached to the application.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The policy or certificate shall provide that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The coverage may not be canceled without at least 30 days notice to the State Fire Marshal;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The duplicate policy or certificate shall set forth all of the terms, conditions, endorsements, and riders which are or which will become part of the policy when issued;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>It is understood and agreed that limitations cannot be included in the policy which are not set forth in the duplicate policy or certificate of insurance which has been filed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>If the policy is issued by an insurer authorized to do business in the State, it shall be validated by the signature of an agent licensed by the Maryland Insurance Administration to represent the insurer;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>If coverage is provided by an insurer who is not authorized to do business in the State, the duplicate policy or certificate of insurance shall be accompanied by a power of attorney or other satisfactory evidence that the person, firm, or corporation acting as agent in accepting the risk has authority to bind risks and issue policies for the insurer;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The State Fire Marshal's Office specifically reserves the right to disapprove contracts issued by any authorized insurer if the Fire Marshal's Office determines the insurer is unsatisfactory; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>If the policy issued by the unauthorized company is acceptable to the Fire Marshal's Office, it shall be registered and the registration fee and tax paid.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Amend Section 65.5 to add the following regarding the manufacture of fireworks:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A building containing hazardous mixes or items may not be located closer than 20 feet to the property line.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In <cite path="29|06|01|.09|C.|(3)">§C(3) of this regulation</cite>, the following terms have the meanings indicated:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Trainees" means employees undergoing initial training in a specific process for a period not to exceed 24 consecutive work hours.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Transients" means:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Supervisors not regularly assigned to the area;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Bona fide government agency personnel engaged in official business; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Material-handling personnel actively engaged in the transfer of materials into or out of the area.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The maximum number of workers, excluding one trainee and three transients, permitted in a building at one time shall be limited to one person per 100 square feet gross floor area or one person in buildings of less than 100 square feet gross floor area.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The total amount of explosives or pyrotechnic composition including raw materials, material being processed, and finished products, that may be safely permitted in any building at a given time, shall be determined by the enforcement agency based upon the American Table of Distances for Storage of Explosives, without recognition for barricades. However, distances may not be less than those required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|10-204">Public Safety Article, §10-204(a), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>. The amount of explosives or other pyrotechnic composition may not exceed the amount necessary for production for 4 hours.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Before beginning work, all fireworks plants shall submit for approval accurate scale plot plans of their premises to the State Fire Marshal of all proposed changes of location of any of the structures, fences, and gates.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Amend Section 65.5 to add the following Subsection:</text>
      <para>
        <num proof="done">65.5.3</num>
        <text>Sale or use of fireworks shall comply with the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Before the sale, offering for sale, or use within the State, of any sparkler, every manufacturer of sparklers shall submit sufficient samples for inspection to the State Fire Marshal, with a laboratory report from a certified testing laboratory affirming that the analysis of these sparklers showed that they contain no chlorates or perchlorates.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>All sparklers sold in the State shall be sold in boxes, and each box shall be clearly marked that the sparklers contain no chlorates or perchlorates.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The manufacturer shall furnish the State Fire Marshal with a current list of wholesalers, jobbers, retailers, or retail outlets, who handle or supply sparklers, or maintain a list of wholesalers, jobbers, retailers, or retail outlets, subject to inspection by the State Fire Marshal.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Amend Subsection 65.9.1 reference to NFPA 495 as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Amend Section 3.3 to add the following definition: Demolition. The explosive razing of any manmade structure or any part thereof that cannot be covered with overburden or blasting mats.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Amend Section 4.4 to add the following new Subsection: 4.4.7 Each applicant for a Demolition Class D permit shall possess 5 years of experience in the field of demolition and shall pass the demolition examination as approved by the Office of the State Fire Marshal.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>NOTE: The content of this regulation is extracted text from NFPA 1, 2012 edition, by permission. Copyright © 2012 NFPA.</text>
      <text>Amend Chapter 65 to add the following:</text>
      <include>
        <para>
          <num>65.10</num>
          <text>Sale, Handling, and Storage of Consumer Fireworks.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.1</num>
          <text>Applicability.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.1.1</num>
          <text>General Requirements. Retail sales of consumer fireworks in both new and existing buildings, structures, and facilities shall comply with the requirements of this section unless otherwise indicated.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.1.1.1</num>
          <text>New Facilities.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.1.1.1.1</num>
          <text>For the purpose of applying the requirements of this section, the following consumer fireworks retail sales (CFRS) facilities and stores shall be considered to be new:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Permanent CFRS facilities and stores that are not initially occupied until after the effective date of this Code, unless plans are submitted and accepted for review, plans have been approved for construction, or a building permit has been issued prior to the effective date of this Code;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Permanent CFRS facilities and stores constructed prior to the effective date of this Code and in which the retail sales of consumer fireworks have not been conducted either seasonally or year-round within one year prior to the effective date of this Code; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Temporary CFRS facilities and stores.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.1.1.1.2</num>
          <text>In a store where the area of the retail sales floor occupied by the retail displays of consumer fireworks is increased after the effective date of this Code, such that the area exceeds the limits specified in <cite path="|65.10">65.10</cite>.5.1.1(1), the building shall be considered to be a new CFRS facility.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.1.1.2</num>
          <text>Existing Facilities. For the purpose of applying the requirements of Section <cite path="|65.10">65.10</cite>, CFRS facilities and stores not considered to be new as specified in <cite path="|65.10">65.10</cite>.1.1.1 shall be considered to be existing.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.1.1.3</num>
          <text>Minimum Requirements. Existing life safety features that do not meet the requirements for new buildings but that exceed the requirements for existing buildings shall not be further diminished.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.1.1.4</num>
          <text>Modernization or Renovation. Any alteration or any installation of new equipment shall meet, as nearly as practicable, the requirements for new construction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.1.1.4.1</num>
          <text>Only the altered, renovated, or modernized portion of an existing building, system, or individual component shall be required to meet the provisions of this Code that are applicable to new construction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.1.1.4.2</num>
          <text>If the alteration, renovation, or modernization adversely impacts required life safety features, additional upgrading shall be required.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.1.1.4.3</num>
          <text>Except where another provision of this Code exempts a previously approved feature from a requirement, the resulting feature shall be not less than that required for existing buildings.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.1.2</num>
          <text>Facility Classification. The requirements of this section shall apply to the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Permanent buildings and structures, including the following:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>Stores; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>CFRS facilities.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Temporary facilities, including the following:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>CFRS stands;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>Tents;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(c)</num>
              <text>Canopies; or</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(d)</num>
              <text>Membrane structures.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.2</num>
          <text>Special Limits for Retail Sales of Consumer Fireworks.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.2.1</num>
          <text>Retail sales of consumer fireworks, including their related storage and display for sale of such fireworks, shall be in accordance with this Code.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.2.2</num>
          <text>Retail sales of consumer fireworks shall be limited to mercantile occupancies defined in 3.3.183.17 and NFPA 101.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.2.3</num>
          <text>Any building or structure used for the retail sales of consumer fireworks, including their related storage, shall comply with Section <cite path="|20.12">20.12</cite> and NFPA 101 for mercantile occupancies, except as provided in this Code.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.2.4</num>
          <text>Retail sales of display fireworks and pyrotechnic articles, including the related storage and display for sale of such fireworks and articles, shall be prohibited at a CFRS facility or store.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.2.5</num>
          <text>Retail sales of certain explosive devices prohibited by the Child Safety Act of 1966, including the related storage and display for sale of such devices, shall be prohibited at a CFRS facility or store.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.2.6</num>
          <text>The retail sales of pest control devices, including their related storage and display for sale, shall be prohibited at a CFRS facility or store.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.2.7</num>
          <text>The retail sales of fireworks that do not comply with the regulations of the U.S. Consumer Product Safety Commission as set forth in 16 CFR 1500 and 1507 and the regulations of the U.S. Department of Transportation as set forth in 49 CFR 100 to 178, including their related storage and display for sale, shall be prohibited.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3</num>
          <text>General Requirements for All Retail Sales.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.1</num>
          <text>Exempt Amounts.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.1.1</num>
          <text>The requirements of this section shall not apply to CFRS facilities or stores where the consumer fireworks are in packages and where the total quantity of consumer fireworks on hand does not exceed 125 pounds (net) (56.8 kilograms) of pyrotechnic composition or, in a building protected throughout with an approved automatic sprinkler system installed in accordance with Section 13.3 and NFPA 13, 250 pounds (net) (113.6 kilograms) of pyrotechnic composition.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.1.2</num>
          <text>Where the actual weight of the pyrotechnic composition of consumer fireworks is not known, 25 percent of the gross weight of the consumer fireworks, including packaging, shall be permitted to be used to determine the weight of the pyrotechnic composition.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.2</num>
          <text>Permits. Where required by state or local laws, ordinances, or regulations, a permit for the following shall be obtained:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Construction, erection, or operation of the following:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>Permanent building or structure; or</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>Temporary structure such as a stand, tent, or canopy used for the purpose of the retail display or sale of consumer fireworks to the public; and</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Storage of consumer fireworks in connection with the retail display or sale of consumer fireworks to the public.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.3</num>
          <text>Plans. Plans for facilities other than stands and tents shall include the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Minimum distances from the following:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>Public ways;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>Buildings;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(c)</num>
              <text>Other CFRS facilities;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(d)</num>
              <text>Motor vehicle fuel–dispensing station dispensers;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(e)</num>
              <text>Retail propane-dispensing station dispensers;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(f)</num>
              <text>Flammable and combustible liquid aboveground tank storage; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(g)</num>
              <text>Flammable gas and flammable liquefied gas bulk aboveground storage and dispensing areas within 300 feet (91.5 meters) of the facility used for the retail sales of consumer fireworks;</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Vehicle access and parking areas;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Location and type of portable fire extinguishers;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Floor plan and layout of storage and displays to indicate compliance with this chapter and applicable state or local laws, ordinances, or regulations;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Means of egress; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>Construction details.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.4</num>
          <text>Fire Department Access. Any portion of an exterior wall of a building, sidewall of a tent, or other defined perimeter of a CFRS facility or store shall be accessible within 150 feet (45.7 meters) of a public way or an approved fire apparatus access.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.5</num>
          <text>Construction of Buildings and Structures. Consumer fireworks shall only be permitted to be sold at retail in any of the following buildings or structures, provided that any new building or structure does not exceed one story in height:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Permanent buildings or structures constructed in accordance with the building code enforced by the AHJ;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Tents, canopies, or temporary membrane structures complying with NFPA 102, Standard for Grandstands, Folding and Telescopic Seating, Tents, and Membrane Structures;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Temporary structures constructed in accordance with this chapter;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Temporary CFRS stands greater than 800 square feet (74 square meters) in area that also meet the requirements for a permanent structure; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Vehicles, such as vans, buses, trailers, recreational vehicles, motor homes, travel trailers, trucks, and automobiles, complying with the applicable requirements for CFRS stands.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.6</num>
          <text>An automatic sprinkler system designed and installed in accordance with Section 13.3 and NFPA 13 shall be provided throughout permanent CFRS facilities and stores in which CFRS are conducted in the following buildings:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>New buildings greater than 6,000 square feet (557.2 square meters) in area; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Existing buildings greater than 7,500 square feet (694 square meters) in area.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.6.1</num>
          <text>Door and window openings in the fire barrier wall shall be protected by self-closing fire doors or fixed fire windows having a fire protection rating of not less than one hour and shall be installed in accordance with Section 12.4 and NFPA 80, Standard for Fire Doors and Other Opening Protectives.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.6.2</num>
          <text>Any other openings or penetrations in the fire barrier wall shall be protected in accordance with NFPA 101.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.6.3</num>
          <text>Every CFRS facility and store shall have no fewer than two portable fire extinguishers with a minimum rating of 2A, at least one of which shall be of the pressurized water type.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.7</num>
          <text>Storage Rooms. Storage rooms containing consumer fireworks in a new permanent CFRS facility or store shall be protected with an automatic sprinkler system installed in accordance with Section 13.3 and NFPA 13 or separated from the retail sales area by a fire barrier having a fire resistance rating of not less than one hour.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.8</num>
          <text>Portable Fire Extinguishers.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.8.1</num>
          <text>Specification. Portable fire extinguishers shall be provided as required for extra (high) hazard occupancy in accordance with Section 13.6 and NFPA 10.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.8.2</num>
          <text>Extinguisher Type. Where more than one portable fire extinguisher is required, at least one fire extinguisher shall be of the multipurpose dry chemical type if the facility is provided with electrical power.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.8.3</num>
          <text>Location. Portable fire extinguishers for permanent consumer fireworks retail sales facilities and stores shall be located so that the maximum distance of travel required to reach an extinguisher from any point does not exceed 75 feet (23 meters), as specified in NFPA 10.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.9</num>
          <text>Fire Alarms. A fire alarm system shall be provided as required by Section 13.7 and NFPA 101.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.10</num>
          <text>Smoke Control.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.10.1</num>
          <text>Smoke and heat vents designed and installed in accordance with NFPA 204, Standard for Smoke and Heat Venting, shall be provided in the CFRS area of new permanent CFRS facilities or stores where the ceiling height is less than 10 feet (3.05 meters) and the travel distance to reach an exit is greater than 25 feet (7.6 meters).</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.10.2</num>
          <text>The smoke and heat vents required by <cite path="|65.10">65.10</cite>.3.10.1 shall be automatically activated by a smoke detection system installed throughout the CFRS area in accordance with NFPA 72.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.11</num>
          <text>No Smoking Signs.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.11.1</num>
          <text>Smoking shall not be permitted inside or within 50 feet (15.5 meters) of the CFRS area.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.11.2</num>
          <text>At least one sign that reads as follows, in letters at least two inches (51 millimeters) high on a contrasting background, shall be conspicuously posted at each entrance or within 10 feet (3.05meters) of every aisle directly serving the CFRS area in a store: “FIREWORKS — NO SMOKING”</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.12</num>
          <text>Distance from Bulk Dispensing and Bulk Storage.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.12.1</num>
          <text>CFRS facilities and stores shall not be located within 50 feet (15.2 meters) of the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Retail propane-dispensing station dispensers;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Aboveground storage tanks for flammable or combustible liquid, flammable gas, or flammable liquefied gas; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Compressed natural gas–dispensing station dispensers.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.12.2</num>
          <text>New CFRS facilities and stores, existing CFRS stands and tents, and temporary CFRS facilities shall not be located within 50 feet (15.2 meters) of motor vehicle fuel–dispensing station dispensers.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.12.3</num>
          <text>Existing CFRS facilities, other than CFRS stands, tents, and temporary facilities, and existing stores shall not be located within 25 feet (7.6 meters) of motor vehicle fuel–dispensing station dispensers.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.12.4</num>
          <text>Fuel tanks on vehicles or other motorized equipment shall not be considered bulk storage.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.12.5</num>
          <text>Fuel storage for generators shall be in accordance with <cite path="|65.10">65.10</cite>.4.9.2.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.12.6</num>
          <text>CFRS areas and storage areas shall not be located within 300 feet (91.2 meters) of any aboveground bulk storage or bulk dispensing area for the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Flammable or combustible liquid;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Flammable gas; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Flammable liquefied gas.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.13</num>
          <text>Fire Safety and Evacuation Plan. For a CFRS facility or store, an approved fire safety and evacuation plan shall be prepared in writing and maintained current.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.14</num>
          <text>Means of Egress.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.14.1</num>
          <text>Number of Exits.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.14.1.1</num>
          <text>The minimum number of exits provided from the retail sales area shall be not less than three or as determined in accordance with Chapter 14 and NFPA 101, whichever number is greater.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.14.1.2</num>
          <text>Required means of egress from the retail sales area shall not be allowed to pass through storage rooms.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.14.2</num>
          <text>Egress Travel Distance. Exits provided for the retail sales area of tents, membrane structures, canopies, and permanent CFRS facilities, including Class C stores, shall be located so that the maximum egress travel distance, measured from the most remote point to an exit along the natural and unobstructed path of egress travel, does not exceed 75 feet (22.9 meters).</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.14.3</num>
          <text>Aisles. Aisles serving as a portion of the exit access in CFRS areas shall comply with this paragraph.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.14.3.1</num>
          <text>Aisle Width.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.14.3.1.1</num>
          <text>Aisles shall have a minimum clear width of 48 inches (1.2 meters).</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.14.3.1.2</num>
          <text>The required width of aisles shall be maintained unobstructed at all times the facility is occupied by the public.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.14.3.2</num>
          <text>Aisle Arrangements.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.14.3.2.1</num>
          <text>Not less than one aisle shall be provided and arranged so that travel along the aisle leads directly to an exit.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.14.3.2.2</num>
          <text>Other required exits shall be located at, or within 10 feet (3.05 meters) of, the end of an aisle or a cross-aisle.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.14.3.2.3</num>
          <text>Aisles shall terminate at an exit, another aisle, or a cross-aisle.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.14.3.2.4</num>
          <text>Dead-end aisles shall be prohibited.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.14.3.2.5</num>
          <text>Where more than one aisle is provided, not less than one cross-aisle shall have an unobstructed connection with every aisle, other than cross-aisles.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.14.3.2.6</num>
          <text>Cross-aisle connections shall be provided for each aisle at intervals not greater than 50 feet (15.2 meters) as measured along the aisle.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.14.3.2.7</num>
          <text>Where cross-aisles are required, not less than one cross-aisle shall have at least one end terminate at, or within 10 feet (3.05 meters) of, an exit.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.14.4</num>
          <text>Doors and Doorways. Doors and doorways used in the means of egress shall comply with this paragraph.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.14.4.1</num>
          <text>Egress doors shall be not less than 36 inches (910 millimeters) in width (providing a minimum of 32 inches (813 millimeters) clear width).</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.14.4.2</num>
          <text>Every egress door that has a latching device shall be provided with panic hardware complying with Chapter 14 and NFPA 101.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.14.4.3</num>
          <text>Means of egress doors shall be of the sidehinge swinging type and shall be arranged to swing in the direction of egress travel.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.14.5</num>
          <text>Exit Signs.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.14.5.1</num>
          <text>Exits shall be marked by an approved exit sign in accordance with Section <cite path="|14.14">14.14</cite> and NFPA 101.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.14.5.2</num>
          <text>Exit signs shall be required to be self-luminous or internally or externally illuminated.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.14.6</num>
          <text>Emergency Lighting.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.14.6.1</num>
          <text>The means of egress, including the exit discharge, shall be illuminated whenever the facility is occupied in accordance with Section <cite path="|14.12">14.12</cite> and NFPA 101.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.14.6.2</num>
          <text>Emergency lighting shall be provided for CFRS facilities and stores and shall comply with Section <cite path="|14.13">14.13</cite> and NFPA 101.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.15</num>
          <text>Retail Sales Displays.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.15.1</num>
          <text>General. The requirements of this section shall apply only to CFRS areas, unless otherwise specifically indicated.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.15.2</num>
          <text>Height of Sales Displays. To provide for visual access of the retail sales area by the employees and customers, partitions, counters, shelving, cases, and similar space dividers shall not exceed six feet (1.8 meters) in height above the floor surface inside the perimeter of the retail sales area.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.15.2.1</num>
          <text>Merchandise on display or located on shelves or counters or other fixtures shall not be displayed to a height greater than six feet (1.8 meters) above the floor surface within the CFRS area.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.15.2.2</num>
          <text>Where located along the perimeter of the consumer fireworks retail sales area, the maximum height of sales displays shall be limited to 12 feet (3.66 meters).</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.15.3</num>
          <text>Flame Breaks.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.15.3.1</num>
          <text>Where continuous displays of consumer fireworks are located on shelving, cases, counters, and similar display fixtures, a flame break shall be provided so that the maximum distance between flame breaks does not exceed 16 feet (4.9 meters) where measured along the length of the display.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.15.3.2</num>
          <text>The flame break shall extend as follows:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>From the display surface to not less than six inches (150 millimeters) above the full height of the displayed merchandise or to the underside of the display surface directly above; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>For the full depth of the displayed merchandise.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.15.3.3</num>
          <text>Where packaged fireworks merchandise is displayed on the same level as individual unpackaged fireworks devices, the flame break required in <cite path="|65.10">65.10</cite>.3.15.3.1 shall not be required where both of the following criteria are met:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The length of the display level containing individual unpackaged fireworks devices is interrupted by packaged fireworks merchandise, or open space, or any combination thereof, having a continuous length of not less than eight feet (2.4 meters); and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The distance between flame breaks does not exceed 32 feet (9.8 meters).</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.15.3.4</num>
          <text>Where a merchandise display level contains packaged fireworks merchandise, such merchandise shall be permitted to be displayed in a continuous length on the same level, where the display does not exceed 32 feet (9.8 meters) without the flame break required in <cite path="|65.10">65.10</cite>.3.15.3.1.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.15.3.5</num>
          <text>An aisle having a minimum width of 48 inches (1.2 meters) shall be permitted to substitute for the flame break required in <cite path="|65.10">65.10</cite>.3.15.3.1.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.15.3.6</num>
          <text>Where displays of merchandise face aisles that run along both long sides of the display fixtures or display surface, a flame break shall be installed lengthwise between the abutting display fixtures or along the approximate longitudinal centerline of the display surface so as to separate the merchandise facing one of the aisles from the merchandise that abuts it facing the other aisle.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.15.3.7</num>
          <text>Freestanding display racks, pallets, tables, or bins containing packaged fireworks merchandise shall be permitted without flame breaks, provided the dimensions of the area occupied by the fireworks merchandise do not exceed four feet (1.2 meters) in width, eight feet (2.4 meters) in length, and six feet (1.8 meters) in height, and the displayed fireworks merchandise is separated from other displays of merchandise by aisles having a minimum clear width of four feet (1.2 meters).</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.15.3.8</num>
          <text>Where both of the facing vertical surfaces of the abutting display fixtures are constructed of perforated hardboard panels not less than ¼ inch (6 millimeters) thick that are separated from each other by an open space not less than 1½ inches (38 millimeters) wide, a flame break specified in <cite path="|65.10">65.10</cite>.3.15.3.6 shall not be required.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.15.4</num>
          <text>Shelving.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.15.4.1</num>
          <text>Shelving or other surfaces used to support fireworks display merchandise shall be permitted to have not more than 10 percent of the area of the shelf contain holes or other openings.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.15.4.2</num>
          <text>The 10 percent limitation on the area of holes or other openings in the shelf used to support fireworks display merchandise shall not be applicable under the following conditions:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Where both of the facing vertical surfaces of the abutting display fixtures are constructed of perforated hardboard panels not less than ¼ inch (6 millimeters) thick and separated from each other by an open space not less than 1½ inches (38 millimeters) wide; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Where such merchandise is suspended from or fastened to the shelf or surface or is displayed as packaged merchandise on the surface or in bins.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.15.4.3</num>
          <text>Flame breaks and solid display surfaces shall not be required for packaged fireworks merchandise displayed in bins or display racks or on pallets or tables located at the end of a row of display fixtures where the following conditions are met:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Such end displays are separated from the ends of the display fixtures by an open space not less than three inches (76 millimeters) wide;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The fireworks merchandise occupies an area having dimensions not greater than the width of the end of the row of display fixtures and a depth not greater than 36 inches (910 millimeters); and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>The minimum required widths of the adjacent aisles are maintained, but in no case is the aisle width less than 48 inches (1.2 meters).</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.15.5</num>
          <text>Covered Fuses.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.15.5.1</num>
          <text>Only consumer fireworks meeting the criteria for covered fuses as described in <cite path="|65.10">65.10</cite>.3.15.5.2 shall be permitted where the retail sales of consumer fireworks are conducted.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.15.5.2</num>
          <text>A consumer fireworks device shall be considered as having a covered fuse if the fireworks device is contained within a packaged arrangement, container, or wrapper that is arranged and configured such that the fuse of the fireworks device cannot be touched directly by a person handling the fireworks without the person having to puncture or tear the packaging or wrapper, unseal or break open a package or container, or otherwise damage or destroy the packaging material, wrapping, or container within which the fireworks are contained.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.15.6</num>
          <text>Reserved.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.15.7</num>
          <text>Horizontal Barriers. Combustible materials and merchandise shall not be stored directly above the consumer fireworks in retail sales displays unless a horizontal barrier constructed of plywood at least 3/8 inch (9.5 millimeters) thick is installed directly above the consumer fireworks as follows:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Barriers shall extend from rack face to rack face and shall be tight to the vertical barriers;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Barriers shall be supported by horizontal rack members;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Transverse vertical barriers constructed of plywood at least 3/8 inch (9.5 millimeters) thick shall be provided at the rack uprights extending from rack face to rack face; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>For double-row racks, longitudinal vertical barriers constructed of plywood at least 3/8 inch (9.5 millimeters) thick shall be provided at the rack uprights in the center of the rack.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.16</num>
          <text>Electrical Equipment. All electrical wiring shall be in accordance with NFPA 70.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.17</num>
          <text>Heating Equipment.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.17.1</num>
          <text>Heating units shall be listed and shall be used in accordance with their listing.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.17.2</num>
          <text>Temporary heating sources shall have tip-over and temperature-overheat protection.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.17.3</num>
          <text>Open-flame and exposed-element heating devices shall be prohibited.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.18</num>
          <text>Portable Generators.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.18.1</num>
          <text>Class II and Class III combustible liquid generator fuel shall be limited to not more than five gallons (18.9 liters).</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.18.2</num>
          <text>Portable generators shall be permitted to use Class I flammable liquids as fuel, provided the quantity of such fuel is limited to two gallons (7.6 liters).</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.19</num>
          <text>Operations.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.19.1</num>
          <text>General. Means of egress, including but not limited to aisles, doors, and exit discharge, shall be clear at all times when the facility or the building is occupied.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.19.2</num>
          <text>Distances from Entrances and Exits.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.19.2.1</num>
          <text>No consumer fireworks shall be displayed for sale or stored within five feet (1.5 meters) of any public entrance in an enclosed building or structure.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.19.2.2</num>
          <text>No consumer fireworks shall be displayed for sale or stored within two feet (0.6 meters) of any exit or private entrance in an enclosed building or structure.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.19.3</num>
          <text>Security.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.19.3.1</num>
          <text>CFRS facilities and stores shall be secured when unoccupied and not open for business, unless fireworks are not kept in the facility during such times.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.19.3.2</num>
          <text>The fireworks displayed or stored in a CFRS facility or store shall be allowed to be removed and transferred to a temporary storage structure or location.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.19.4</num>
          <text>Fireworks shall not be ignited, discharged, or otherwise used within 300 feet (91.5 meters) of a CFRS facility or store.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.20</num>
          <text>Display and Handling. Not less than 50 percent of the available floor area within the retail sales area shall be open space that is unoccupied by retail displays and used only for aisles and cross-aisles.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.21</num>
          <text>Housekeeping.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.21.1</num>
          <text>CFRS areas and storage rooms shall be kept free of accumulations of debris and rubbish.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.21.2</num>
          <text>Any loose pyrotechnic composition shall be removed immediately.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.21.3</num>
          <text>Vacuum cleaners or other mechanical cleaning devices shall not be used. <cite path="|65.10">65.10</cite>.3.21.4 Brooms, brushes, and dustpans used to sweep up any loose powder or dust shall be made of nonsparking materials.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num proof="done">65.10.3.21.5</num>
          <text>Consumer fireworks devices that are damaged shall be removed and not offered for sale.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.21.6</num>
          <text>Damaged consumer fireworks shall be permitted to be returned to the dealer or shall be disposed of according to the manufacturer’s instructions.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.22</num>
          <text>Training. All personnel handling consumer fireworks shall receive safety training related to the performance of their duties.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.23</num>
          <text>Under the Influence. Any person selling consumer fireworks shall not knowingly sell consumer fireworks to any person who is obviously under the influence of alcohol or drugs.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.24</num>
          <text>Records.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.24.1</num>
          <text>Records shall be maintained on available inventory on the premise.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.3.24.2</num>
          <text>Records shall be made available to the AHJ upon request.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4</num>
          <text>Consumer Fireworks Retail Sales (CFRS) Facility Requirements.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.1</num>
          <text>Plan. Where required, plans for CFRS facilities shall be submitted to the AHJ with the permit application.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.2</num>
          <text>Site Plan. The site plan for tents shall show the location of the tent on the site and indicate the minimum separation distances required by <cite path="|65.10">65.10</cite>.4.7.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.3</num>
          <text>Construction Materials. The following construction materials requirements shall apply to new permanent CFRS facilities in jurisdictions that have not adopted a local building code:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Buildings having an area up to and including 8,000 square feet (743 square meters) shall be permitted to be constructed of any approved construction materials; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Buildings having an area greater than 8,000 square feet (743 square meters) shall be constructed in accordance with one of the following:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>Buildings shall be constructed of noncombustible or limited-combustible materials; or</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>Buildings with exterior walls having a fire resistance rating of not less than two hours shall be permitted to have the roof decking and its supporting structure and interior partitions constructed of combustible materials; and</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Roof coverings for any building shall have a minimum rating of Class C.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.4</num>
          <text>Multiple-Tenant Buildings.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.4.1</num>
          <text>Where new CFRS facilities are located in a building containing other tenants, the CFRS facility shall be separated from the other tenants by fire barriers having no openings and a fire resistance rating of not less than two hours.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.4.2</num>
          <text>Where the new CFRS facility is protected per Section 13.3 and NFPA 13, the fire resistance rating of the fire barrier required by <cite path="|65.10">65.10</cite>.4.4.1 shall be permitted to be not less than one hour.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.4.3</num>
          <text>Any penetrations of the fire barrier shall be protected in accordance with NFPA 101. <cite path="|65.10">65.10</cite>.4.5 Fire Protection.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num proof="done">65.10.4.5.1</num>
          <text>Automatic Sprinkler System Alarm. Any waterflow alarm device shall be arranged to activate audible and visual alarms throughout the CFRS facility in accordance with Section 13.7 and NFPA 72.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.5.2</num>
          <text>Portable Fire Extinguishers. Portable fire extinguishers for temporary CFRS facilities shall be installed and located so that the maximum distance of travel required to reach an extinguisher from any point does not exceed 35 feet (10.6 meters).</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.5.3</num>
          <text>Public Notification. In permanent CFRS facilities greater than 3,000 square feet (278.6 square meters) in area, a public address system or a means for manually activating audible and visible alarm indicating devices located throughout the facility in accordance with Section 13.7 and NFPA 72 shall be provided at a constantly attended location when the CFRS facility is occupied.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.6</num>
          <text>Site Requirements.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.6.1</num>
          <text>Clearance to Combustibles. The area located within 30 feet (9 meters) of a CFRS facility shall be kept free of accumulated dry grass, dry brush, and combustible debris.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.6.2</num>
          <text>Parking. No motor vehicle or trailer used for the storage of consumer fireworks shall be parked within 10 feet (3 meters) of a CFRS facility, except when delivering, loading, or unloading fireworks or other merchandise and materials used, stored, or displayed for sale in the facility.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.6.3</num>
          <text>Fireworks Discharge. At least one sign that reads as follows, in capital letters at least four inches (102 millimeters) high on a contrasting background, shall be conspicuously posted on the exterior of each side of the CFRS facility: “NO FIREWORKS DISCHARGE WITHIN 300 FEET”</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.7</num>
          <text>Separation Distances.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.7.1</num>
          <text>Permanent Facilities.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.7.1.1</num>
          <text>New Facilities. New permanent consumer fireworks retail sales facilities shall be separated from adjacent permanent buildings and structures in accordance with Table <cite path="|65.10">65.10</cite>.4.7.1.1.</text>
        </para>
        <aftertext>Table 65.10.4.7.1.1 Separation Distances Between New Permanent Buildings and Structures</aftertext>
        <aftertext>
          <table>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th colspan="2">Separation Distances</th>
                <th rowspan="2">Exterior Wall<br/>Fire Resistance<br/>Rating (hour)</th>
                <th rowspan="2">Exterior<br/>Wall Opening<br/>Protection<br/>rating (hour)</th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <th>Feet</th>
                <th>Meters</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">&lt;10</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">&lt;3.05</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">2</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">1 ½</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">≥10 to &lt;60</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">≥3.05 to &lt;18.3</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">1</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">¾</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">≥60</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">≥18.3</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">0</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">0</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </aftertext>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.7.1.2</num>
          <text>Existing Facilities. Existing permanent CFRS facilities shall be separated from adjacent permanent buildings and structures by not less than 10 feet (3.05 meters) or shall be separated by a wall with a one-hour fire resistance rating.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.7.2</num>
          <text>Temporary Facilities. Temporary CFRS facilities shall be located as specified in Table <cite path="|65.10">65.10</cite>.4.7.2.</text>
        </para>
        <aftertext>Table 65.10.4.7.2 Temporary CFRS Facilities — Minimum Separation Distances</aftertext>
        <aftertext>
          <table high-density="true">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th rowspan="2"/>
                <th colspan="2">Buildings</th>
                <th colspan="2">Combustibles<sup>a</sup></th>
                <th colspan="2">Tents<sup>b</sup></th>
                <th colspan="2">Vehicle Parking</th>
                <th colspan="2">Stands<sup>c</sup></th>
                <th colspan="2">Storage of<br/>Consumer<br/>Fireworks</th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <th>feet</th>
                <th>meters</th>
                <th>feet</th>
                <th>meters</th>
                <th>feet</th>
                <th>meters</th>
                <th>feet</th>
                <th>meters</th>
                <th>feet</th>
                <th>meters</th>
                <th>feet</th>
                <th>meters</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Tents<sup>b</sup></td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">20</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">6.1</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">20</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">6.1</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">20</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">6.1</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">10</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">3.05</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">20</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">6.1</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">20</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">6.1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Stands<sup>c</sup></td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">20</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">6.1</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">10</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">3.05</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">20</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">6.1</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">10</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">3.05</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">5<sup>d</sup></td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">1.5<sup>d</sup></td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">20</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">6.1</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </aftertext>
        <aftertext><sup>a</sup> The required clearances to combustibles shall also comply with 65.10.4.6.1.</aftertext>
        <aftertext><sup>b</sup> Tents refers to temporary retail sales of consumer fireworks in tents, canopies, and membrane structures.</aftertext>
        <aftertext><sup>c</sup> Stands refers to temporary CFRS stands.</aftertext>
        <aftertext><sup>d</sup> Where stands are separated from each other by less than 20 feet (6.1 meters), the aggregate area of such stands shall not exceed 800 square feet (74 square meters).</aftertext>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.8</num>
          <text>Means of Egress.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.8.1</num>
          <text>General.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.8.1.1</num>
          <text>Means of egress in CFRS facilities shall comply with the applicable requirements of Chapter 14 and NFPA 101, as modified by <cite path="|65.10">65.10</cite>.3.14 and <cite path="|65.10">65.10</cite>.4.8.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.8.1.2</num>
          <text>Means of egress in tents and membrane structures used for retail sales of consumer fireworks shall also comply with NFPA 102, as modified by <cite path="|65.10">65.10</cite>.3.14 and <cite path="|65.10">65.10</cite>.4.8.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.8.2</num>
          <text>The evacuation plan shall be posted in a conspicuous location that is accessible to the public as well as to persons employed or otherwise working in the CFRS facility.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.8.3</num>
          <text>Exit signs shall not be required to be illuminated in tents that are not open for business after dusk.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.8.4</num>
          <text>Emergency lighting shall not be required in tents that are not open for business after dusk.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.8.5</num>
          <text>Exit openings from tents shall have a clear opening width of not less than 44 inches (1100 millimeters).</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.9</num>
          <text>Source of Ignition.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.9.1</num>
          <text>Temporary Electrical Equipment. Battery powered equipment, electrical equipment, and electrical cords that are used in conjunction with a CFRS facility area shall be listed and shall be used in accordance with their listing.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.9.1.1</num>
          <text>Temporary wiring installed in a temporary structure, including tents and canopies, shall comply with NFPA 70.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.9.1.2</num>
          <text>Where temporary electrical conductors are placed on top of an outdoor surface to connect the permanent power source to the temporary CFRS facility’s temporary electrical system, the conductors shall be provided with physical protection against damage caused by pedestrian or vehicular traffic.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.9.2</num>
          <text>Portable Generators.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.9.2.1</num>
          <text>Portable generators supplying power to CFRS facilities shall use only Class II or Class III combustible liquid fuels.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.9.2.2</num>
          <text>Portable generators shall be located not less than 20 feet (6.1 meters) from the CFRS facility.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.9.2.3</num>
          <text>Generator fuels shall be stored not less than 20 feet (6.1 meters) from the CFRS facility.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.9.2.4</num>
          <text>Where the generator fuel storage is located not less than 50 feet (15.2 meters) from the CFRS facility, the quantity of such fuel shall not be limited by <cite path="|65.10">65.10</cite>.3.18.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.9.3</num>
          <text>Cooking Equipment.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.9.3.1</num>
          <text>Cooking equipment of any type shall not be permitted within 20 feet (6.1 meters) of tents, canopies, or membrane structures used for the storage or sale of consumer fireworks.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.9.3.2</num>
          <text>Open flame cooking equipment of any type shall not be allowed within 50 feet (15.2 meters) of tents, canopies, or membrane structures used for the storage or sale of consumer fireworks.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.10</num>
          <text>Quantity Limitations. The floor area occupied by the retail displays of consumer fireworks in permanent CFRS facilities shall not exceed 40 percent of the available floor area within the retail sales area.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.4.11</num>
          <text>Flame Breaks. In CFRS facilities the longitudinal flame break required in <cite path="|65.10">65.10</cite>.3.15.3.6 shall not be required where the display fixture or surface is adjacent to an aisle that is not used for public egress.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.5</num>
          <text>Stores.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.5.1</num>
          <text>General.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.5.1.1</num>
          <text>For the purpose of this chapter, stores in which retail sales of consumer fireworks are conducted shall not be considered CFRS facilities as defined in 3.3.72 where both of the following conditions exist:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The area of the retail sales floor occupied by the retail displays of consumer fireworks does not exceed 25 percent of the area of the retail sales floor in the building or 600 square feet (55.5 square meters), whichever is less; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The consumer fireworks are displayed and sold in a manner approved by the AHJ and comply with the applicable provisions of this code, federal and state law, and local ordinances.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.5.1.2</num>
          <text>Consumer fireworks displayed for sale in stores shall comply with the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Such fireworks shall be under the visual supervision of a store employee or other responsible party while the store is open to the public;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Such fireworks shall be packaged fireworks merchandise; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Such fireworks shall be packaged and displayed for sale in a manner that will limit travel distance of ejected pyrotechnical components if ignition of the fireworks occurs.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.5.2</num>
          <text>Egress. Means of egress in stores shall comply with Chapter 14 and NFPA 101, unless otherwise specified in <cite path="|65.10">65.10</cite>.3.14.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.5.3</num>
          <text>Storage Rooms. Storage rooms containing consumer fireworks in a new permanent store shall be protected with an automatic sprinkler system installed in accordance with Section 13.3 and NFPA 13 or separated from the retail sales area by a fire barrier having a fire resistance rating of not less than one hour.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.5.3.1</num>
          <text>Door and window openings in the fire barrier wall shall be protected by self-closing fire doors or fixed fire windows having a fire protection rating of not less than one hour and shall be installed in accordance with Section 12.4 and NFPA 80.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.5.3.2</num>
          <text>Any other openings or penetrations in the fire barrier wall shall be protected in accordance with NFPA 101.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.5.4</num>
          <text>Alarm Notification. In Class B stores, a public address system or a means for manually activating audible and visible alarm indicating devices located throughout the facility in accordance with Section 13.7 and NFPA 72 shall be provided at a constantly attended location when the store is occupied.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.5.5</num>
          <text>Flame breaks shall be allowed to be omitted in stores protected throughout with an automatic sprinkler system installed in accordance with Section 13.3 and NFPA 13.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.6</num>
          <text>Stands.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.6.1</num>
          <text>Site Plan. The site plan for stands shall show the location of the stand on the site and indicate the minimum separation distances required by <cite path="|65.10">65.10</cite>.4.7.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.6.2</num>
          <text>Temporary Stands.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.6.2.1</num>
          <text>Portable Fire Extinguisher. Temporary CFRS stands of less than 200 square feet (18.6 square meters) shall be required to have only one portable fire extinguisher.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.6.2.2</num>
          <text>Fire Safety and Evacuation Plan. An approved fire safety and evacuation plan shall not be required for temporary CFRS stands.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.6.2.3</num>
          <text>Means of Egress.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.6.2.3.1</num>
          <text>Retail sales areas within temporary CFRS stands shall have a minimum of two exits.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.6.2.3.2</num>
          <text>Exits provided for temporary fireworks retail sales stands shall be located such that the maximum egress travel distance as measured from the most remote point to an exit along the natural and unobstructed path of egress travel does not exceed 35 feet (10.6 meters).</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.6.2.3.3</num>
          <text>Customers shall not be permitted inside a temporary CFRS stand unless it complies with the means of egress requirements in <cite path="|65.10">65.10</cite>.3.14.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.6.2.3.4</num>
          <text>Exit signs shall not be required to be illuminated in stands that are not open for business after dusk, or in temporary CFRS stands where the interior is not accessible to the public.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.6.2.3.5</num>
          <text>Emergency lighting shall not be required in stands that are not open for business after dusk or for temporary CFRS stands where the interior is not accessible to the public.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.6.3</num>
          <text>Minimum Separation Distances. Temporary CFRS stands shall be separated from adjacent buildings and structures in accordance with Table <cite path="|65.10">65.10</cite>.4.7.2.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.6.4</num>
          <text>Stands Not Open to the Public.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.6.4.1</num>
          <text>Minimum Clear Width of Aisles. In temporary CFRS stands where the interior is not accessible to the public, the minimum clear width of the aisle shall be permitted to be not less than 28 inches (710 millimeters).</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.6.4.2</num>
          <text>Egress Doors.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.6.4.2.1</num>
          <text>Egress doors provided for temporary CFRS stands where the interior is not accessible to the public shall be permitted to be not less than 28 inches (710 millimeters) in width.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.6.4.2.2</num>
          <text>For temporary CFRS stands where the interior is not accessible to the public, latching devices on doors shall be permitted without panic hardware.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.6.4.3</num>
          <text>Storage. In temporary CFRS stands where the interior is not accessible to the public, the maximum height of sales displays shall be limited to eight feet (2.44 meters).</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.6.4.4</num>
          <text>Flame Breaks. Temporary CFRS stands where the interior is not accessible to the public shall not be required to comply with <cite path="|65.10">65.10</cite>.3.15.3.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.6.4.5</num>
          <text>Covered Fuses.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.6.4.5.1</num>
          <text>Only consumer fireworks meeting the criteria for covered fuses as described in <cite path="|65.10">65.10</cite>.3.15.5.2 shall be permitted where the retail sales of consumer fireworks are conducted.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>65.10.6.4.6</num>
          <text>Sales Display. The following shall apply to the sales display of consumer fireworks in temporary CFRS stands that do not allow access to the interior of the stand by the public:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Consumer fireworks shall be displayed in a manner that prevents the fireworks from being handled by persons other than those operating, supervising, or working in the temporary CFRS stand; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The handling requirements of <cite path="|65.10">65.10</cite>.6.4.6(1) shall not apply to packaged assortments, boxes, or similarly packaged containers of one or more items, regardless of type.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </include>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="29|06|01|.10">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Blasting Operations General Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Notifications. Written notification by email or facsimile shall be provided to the Office of the State Fire Marshal Bomb Squad at least 24 hours prior to each blast. The name of company or contractor performing the blasting and the location, date, and approximate time shall be identified. The geographical coordinates (longitude and latitude) shall be provided.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Complaints. If requested by a property owner registering a complaint and considered necessary by the State Fire Marshal, measurements on three consecutive blasts, using approved instrumentation, shall be made near to the structure in question.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Special Precautions. When blasting operations, other than those conducted at a fixed site such as a quarry, are to be conducted within 200 feet of a pipe line or high voltage transmission line, the contractor shall take additional precautionary measures and shall notify the owner of the line, or the owner’s agent, that blasting operations are intended.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Records.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A record of each blast shall be kept. All records, including seismograph reports, shall be retained for at least 3 years, be available for inspection, and include the following items:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Name of company or contractor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Location, date, and time of blast. The geographical coordinates (longitude and latitude) shall be identified;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Name, signature, and Social Security number of blaster in charge;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Type of material blasted;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Number of holes, burden, and spacing;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Diameter and depth of holes;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Type of explosives used;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Total amount of explosives used;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Maximum amount of explosives per delay period of 8 milliseconds or greater;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Method of firing and type of circuit;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Direction and distance in feet to nearest dwelling house, public building, school, church, and commercial or institutional building not owned or leased by the person conducting the blasting;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>Weather conditions including such factors as wind direction, etc.;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>Height or length of stemming;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(n)</num>
          <text>If mats or other protection to prevent fly rock were used;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(o)</num>
          <text>Type of detonators used and delay period used;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(p)</num>
          <text>Seismograph records including seismograph readings when required containing:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Name and signature of the individual operating the seismograph,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Name of the individual analyzing the seismograph records, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Seismograph reading; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(q)</num>
          <text>The maximum number of holes per delay period of 8 milliseconds or greater.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The person taking the seismograph reading shall accurately indicate the exact location of the seismograph, if used, and shall also show the distance of the seismograph from the blast.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Liability Insurance for Explosives Handlers.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>As provided in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps">Public Safety Article, Title 11, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, proof of liability insurance shall be provided by an applicant for a license to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Manufacture explosives;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Engage in the business of dealing in explosives; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Possess any explosives other than for use in firearms.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The minimum amount of liability insurance required for licensing for the activities specified in <cite path="29|06|01|.10|E.|(1)">§E(1) of this regulation</cite> is $1,000,000.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Portable Fire Extinguishers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>License to Service or Repair Portable Fire Extinguishers. A license shall be obtained from the State Fire Marshal's Office by every individual, firm, or corporation commercially servicing, repairing, filling, or refilling portable fire extinguishers, except fire departments.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Sale of Portable Fire Extinguishers.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>It is unlawful for a person, directly or through an agent, to sell or offer for sale in the State any make, type, or model of portable fire extinguisher, either new or used, unless the make, type, or model of extinguisher has been tested and listed by a testing laboratory accepted by the State Fire Marshal.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An extinguisher is not approved even if it bears the label of an accepted testing laboratory if it contains any of the following liquids:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Carbon tetrachloride, chlorobromomethane, azeotrophic chloromethane, dibromodifluoromethane, 1,2-dibromo-2-chloro-1,2-trifluoroethane;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>1,2-dibromo-2,2-difluoroethane, methyl bromide, ethylene dibromide;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>1,2-dibromotetrafluoroethane, hydrogen bromide, methylene bromide, bromodifluoromethane, dichlorodifluoromethane; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Any other toxic or poisonous liquid.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11-1</num>
    <heading>Nonwater-Based Fixed Fire Extinguishing Systems.</heading>
    <text>A license shall be obtained from the State Fire Marshal's Office by every individual, firm, or corporation commercially installing, servicing, or repairing nonwater-based fixed fire extinguishing systems.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Repealed.</heading>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Smoke Detectors for the Deaf or Hearing Impaired — Signs — Repealed.</heading>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Sale and Use of Heaters and Stoves.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Gasoline Stoves. The sale or use of gasoline stoves or other similar fuel-burning cooking or heating appliances using Class I flammable liquids as defined in NFPA 1 Fire Code (2024 Edition) and NFPA 30 Flammable and Combustible Liquids Code (2024 Edition), is prohibited unless the appliance has been tested and listed by a testing laboratory accepted by the State Fire Marshal. The appliance shall be installed, operated, and maintained in a safe manner in accordance with the prescribed recommendation of the manufacturer and the conditions stated in the listing by the respective testing laboratory.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Unvented Portable Kerosene-Fired Heaters.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The sale or use of unvented portable kerosene-fired heaters is permitted only if the heater or appliance meets the U.L. Subject 647 and bears the label of a testing laboratory accepted by the State Fire Marshal.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The heaters shall only be used as permitted under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcl|14-1310">Commercial Law Article, §14-1310, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Each heater shall contain a warning label stating: "This device must not be operated while unattended". In addition, the heater shall contain the manufacturer's warning label required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcl|14-1310">Commercial Law Article, §14-1310, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Sale or Use of Flame Retardant Chemicals.</heading>
    <text>An individual, firm, or corporation may not sell or offer for sale in the State any type of flame-retardant or flame-proofing compound, powder, or liquid, for fire-retardant purposes unless the product has been tested, listed, and bears the mark of a recognized testing laboratory accepted by the State Fire Marshal.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Visual Obscuration Systems.</heading>
    <text>Visual obscuration systems associated with security or burglar alarm systems may not be permitted.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Public Safety Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|6-206">6-206</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|6-501">6-501</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1972-07-21">Effective date: July 21, 1972</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1977-10-07">Regulations .01B, .13A, .15B, G, .16B, .18A, B, .22B, .23A—C, .26B, .29B—D, .33, .35B amended effective October 7, 1977 (4:21 Md. R. 1604)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1982-08-30">Regulations <cite path="|29|06|01|.04">.04</cite>—<cite path="|29|06|01|.14">.14</cite>, .16—.35, and .41 amended effective August 30, 1982 (9:17 Md. R. 1709)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1967-07-01"><cite path="|29|06|01|.14|D.">Regulation .14D</cite> adopted effective July 1, 1967</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1978-06-02">Regulations .15G, .16C, .18C, .22A, .29B, and .35B, E, F amended as an emergency provision effective February 23, 1978 (5:5 Md. R. 332); adopted permanently effective June 2, 1978 (5:11 Md. R. 885)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1984-04-09"><cite path="|29|06|01|.16|A.">Regulation .16A</cite> amended effective April 9, 1984 (11:7 Md. R. 628)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1975-05-14">Regulations .16B, .18A, E, .23, .26B, .29D amended effective May 14, 1975 (2:10 Md. R. 759)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1980-04-18"><cite path="|29|06|01|.16|B.">Regulation .16B</cite> amended effective April 18, 1980 (7:8 Md. R. 772)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1980-08-22"><cite path="|29|06|01|.23|B.">Regulation .23B</cite> amended effective August 22, 1980 (7:17 Md. R. 1672)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1981-12-07"><cite path="|29|06|01|.26">Regulation .26</cite> amended effective December 7, 1981 (8:24 Md. R. 1936)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1980-09-19"><cite path="|29|06|01|.30|E.">Regulation .30E</cite> adopted effective October 5, 1979 (6:20 Md. R. 1629); September 19, 1980 (7:19 Md. R. 1808)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1983-11-21"><cite path="|29|06|01|.33">Regulation .33</cite> amended effective November 21, 1983 (10:23 Md. R. 2064)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1977-11-04"><cite path="|29|06|01|.34">Regulation .34</cite> amended effective January 21, 1976 (3:2 Md. R. 87) and November 4, 1977 (4:23 Md. R. 1735)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1977-04-27"><cite path="|29|06|01|.36">Regulation .36</cite> adopted effective April 27, 1977 (4:9 Md. R. 1719)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1977-10-07"><cite path="|29|06|01|.36|A.">Regulation .36A</cite>, C amended effective October 7, 1977 (4:21 Md. R. 1604)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1979-10-05"><cite path="|29|06|01|.37">Regulation .37</cite> adopted effective February 26, 1979 (6:4 Md. R. 227); amended effective October 5, 1979 (6:20 Md. R. 1629)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1979-02-01"><cite path="|29|06|01|.37">Regulation .37</cite> (Cellulose and Foam Insulation) adopted as an emergency provision effective January 1, 1979 (6:1 Md. R. 15); emergency status withdrawn by AELR Committee for <cite path="|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> effective February 1, 1979 (6:4 Md. R. 275); emergency status expired May 12, 1979</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1979-10-05"><cite path="|29|06|01|.38">Regulation .38</cite> adopted effective October 5, 1979 (6:20 Md. R. 1629)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1980-10-31"><cite path="|29|06|01|.39">Regulation .39</cite> adopted effective October 31, 1980 (7:22 Md. R. 2074)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1981-07-20"><cite path="|29|06|01|.40">Regulation .40</cite> adopted effective July 20, 1981 (8:14 Md. R. 1228)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1981-10-12"><cite path="|29|06|01|.41">Regulation .41</cite> adopted effective October 12, 1981 (8:20 Md. R. 1636)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1983-01-17"><cite path="|29|06|01|.42">Regulation .42</cite> adopted effective January 17, 1983 (10:1 Md. R. 32)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-05-06" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective May 6, 1985 (12:9 Md. R. 812)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-07-24"><cite path="|29|06|01|.06|A.">Regulation .06A</cite> amended effective July 28, 1986 (13:15 Md. R. 1735); July 24, 1989 (16:14 Md. R. 1568)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1987-10-05"><cite path="|29|06|01|.06|O.">Regulation .06O</cite> amended effective October 5, 1987 (14:20 Md. R. 2143)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-10-01"><cite path="|29|06|01|.06|R.">Regulation .06R</cite> adopted effective October 1, 1985 (12:19 Md. R. 1849)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1988-03-07"><cite path="|29|06|01|.06|S.">Regulation .06S</cite> adopted effective March 7, 1988 (15:5 Md. R. 622)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-01-23"><cite path="|29|06|01|.07|B.">Regulation .07B</cite> amended effective January 23, 1989 (16:1 Md. R. 72)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-05-11" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective May 11, 1992 (19:9 Md. R. 879)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-11-22"><cite path="|29|06|01|.09|B.">Regulation .09B</cite> amended effective November 22, 1993 (20:23 Md. R. 1805)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-11-22"><cite path="|29|06|01|.10">Regulation .10</cite> adopted effective November 22, 1993 (20:23 Md. R. 1805)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-12-04" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective December 4, 1995 (22:24 Md. R. 1897)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-01-14"><cite path="|12.03.01">COMAR 12.03.01</cite> repealed effective January 14, 1999 (26:1 Md. R. 25)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-01-14" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|29|06|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|29|06|01|.22">.22</cite> adopted effective January 14, 1999 (26:1 Md. R. 25)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-08-06">Regulations <cite path="|29|06|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|29|06|01|.22">.22</cite> repealed effective August 6, 2001 (28:15 Md. R. 1400)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-08-06" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|29|06|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|29|06|01|.17">.17</cite> adopted effective August 6, 2001 (28:15 Md. R. 1400)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-08-01" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective August 1, 2004 (31:12 Md. R. 914)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-01-01" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective January 1, 2007 (33:24 Md. R. 1907)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-06-23"><cite path="|29|06|01|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective January 1, 2010 (36:25 Md. R. 1956); January 1, 2013 (39:23 Md. R. 1533); January 1, 2016 (42:23 Md. R. 1436); October 7, 2019 (46:20 Md. R. 847); June 23, 2025 (52:12 Md. R. 599)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-01-01"><cite path="|29|06|01|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite> repealed effective January 1, 2010 (36:25 Md. R. 1956)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-01-01"><cite path="|29|06|01|.04|D.">Regulation .04D</cite> amended effective January 1, 2010 (36:25 Md. R. 1956)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-06-23"><cite path="|29|06|01|.05|B.">Regulation .05B</cite> amended effective January 1, 2010 (36:25 Md. R. 1956); June 23, 2025 (52:12 Md. R. 599)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-01-01"><cite path="|29|06|01|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective January 1, 2016 (42:23 Md. R. 1436)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-06-23"><cite path="|29|06|01|.06|B.">Regulation .06B</cite> amended effective January 1, 2010 (36:25 Md. R. 1956); October 7, 2019 (46:20 Md. R. 847); June 23, 2025 (52:12 Md. R. 599)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-01-01"><cite path="|29|06|01|.06|C.">Regulation .06C</cite> amended effective January 1, 2010 (36:25 Md. R. 1956); January 1, 2013 (39:23 Md. R. 1533)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-06-23"><cite path="|29|06|01|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective January 1, 2010 (36:25 Md. R. 1956); January 1, 2013 (39:23 Md. R. 1533); January 1, 2016 (42:23 Md. R. 1436); October 7, 2019 (46:20 Md. R. 847); June 23, 2025 (52:12 Md. R. 599)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-06-23"><cite path="|29|06|01|.08">Regulation .08</cite> amended effective January 1, 2010 (36:25 Md. R. 1956); January 1, 2013 (39:23 Md. R. 533); January 1, 2016 (42:23 Md. R. 1436); October 7, 2019 (46:20 Md. R. 847); June 23, 2025 (52:12 Md. R. 599)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-06-23"><cite path="|29|06|01|.09">Regulation .09</cite> amended effective January 1, 2010 (36:25 Md. R. 1956); January 1, 2013 (39:23 Md. R. 533); January 1, 2016 (42:23 Md. R. 1436); October 7, 2019 (46:20 Md. R. 847); June 23, 2025 (52:12 Md. R. 599)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-08-03"><cite path="|29|06|01|.09|E.">Regulation .09E</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective February 7, 2020 (47:10 Md. R. 514); emergency provision expired effective August 3, 2020</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-08-10"><cite path="|29|06|01|.09|E.">Regulation .09E</cite> amended effective August 10, 2020 (47:16 Md. R. 738)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-10-07"><cite path="|29|06|01|.10">Regulation .10</cite> amended effective January 1, 2013 (39:23 1533); October 7, 2019 (46:20 Md. R. 847)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-01-01"><cite path="|29|06|01|.11">Regulation .11</cite> amended effective January 1, 2010 (36:25 Md. R. 1956)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-01-01"><cite path="|29|06|01|.11-1">Regulation .11-1</cite> adopted effective January 1, 2010 (36:25 Md. R. 1956)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-01-01"><cite path="|29|06|01|.13">Regulation .13</cite> repealed effective January 1, 2016 (42:23 Md. R. 1436)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-06-23"><cite path="|29|06|01|.14|A.">Regulation .14A</cite> amended effective January 1, 2010 (36:25 Md. R. 1956); January 1, 2013 (39:23 Md. R. 1533); January 1, 2016 (42:23 Md. R. 1436); October 7, 2019 (46:20 Md. R. 847); June 23, 2025 (52:12 Md. R. 599)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
