<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Acquisition of Real Property</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>General.</heading>
    <text>The Authority may acquire real property and interests in real property for any of the Authority's corporate purposes on the terms and conditions that it considers appropriate.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <text>In this chapter, terms appearing in the Act shall have the meanings defined there.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Authorization of the Executive Director Regarding Acquisitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>At the direction of the Board of Directors or on the Executive Director's own initiative the Executive Director may conduct preliminary negotiations or investigations relating to the acquisition of real property or interests in real property.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In connection with negotiations and acquisitions, the Executive Director, after consultation with the Board of Directors or at the direction of the Board of Directors, may obtain appraisals, surveys, engineering and architectural studies, title insurance, and any other items and services the Executive Director considers appropriate under the circumstances.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Upon approval of an acquisition as set forth in <cite path="|14|21|05|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>, the Executive Director shall have the power on behalf of the Authority to execute all documents and do all things necessary and convenient to accomplish the purposes of the approved transaction.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Executive Director is authorized to exercise remedies for default under agreements that have been approved in accordance with <cite path="|14|21|05|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Review.</heading>
    <text>Proposed construction of real estate development by the Authority shall be submitted for review to the Legislative Policy Committee of the General Assembly of Maryland and to the Maryland Department of Fiscal Services.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Approvals.</heading>
    <text>A proposed acquisition of real property or interest in real property shall be submitted for approval to the Board of Directors. If approved by the Board of Directors, the proposed acquisition shall be submitted for approval to the State Board of Public Works.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Article 41, §§13-101—13-121, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-03-16">Effective date: March 16, 1992 (19:5 Md. R. 578)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
