<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>07</num>
  <heading>Project Operations</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>General.</heading>
    <text>The Authority may manage directly or may engage the services of others to manage project facilities.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Terms appearing in the Act shall have the meanings defined there and, in addition, the meanings used in these regulations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Customer" means any purchaser of goods or services at the market, park, or other project.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Project" means the market, the park, and other food or agriculturally related real estate developments undertaken by the Authority to further the Authority's corporate purposes, including any ancillary facilities.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Supplier" means a wholesale distributor or other business which provides tenants with a commodity for resale.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Tenant" means any lessee of the Authority who operates a business in a market or other project facility.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Management Rules.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In accordance with the applicable laws and ordinances of the jurisdictions in which project facilities are located, the Authority may from time to time establish reasonable rules of operation for project facilities, giving reasonable notice of these rules, and posting them in a conspicuous location at the project facility.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The rules may concern:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Use of streets, driveways, docking slips, and parking areas;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Hours and days of operation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Reasonable fee schedules which describe fees or charges to be paid by suppliers, customers, tenants, and other users of project facilities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Safety and welfare of persons and protection of property; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Other matters which pertain to the management of project operations.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Sanctions. The rules established under this section may include reasonable sanctions. Sanctions may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Deny use of and access to project facilities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Impose fees or charges; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Impose other reasonable restrictions that the Authority may consider proper or necessary for the safe and efficient management of project operations.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Authorization of the Executive Director Regarding Project Operations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Executive Director has primary responsibility for management of project operations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Executive Director may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>With the approval of the Board of Directors, engage the services of others to manage one or more project facilities, or to perform particular services; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Exercise remedies for default under agreements relating to the provision of goods or services to the Authority.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Executive Director may delegate to other employees of the Authority duties relating to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Personnel management;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Procurement matters;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>On-site project management; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Such other duties as the Executive Director considers appropriate.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Article 41, §§13-101—13-121, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-03-16">Effective date: March 16, 1992 (19:5 Md. R. 578)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
