<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>06</num>
  <heading>Swine Herd Validation for Brucellosis and Validated-free Areas in Maryland</heading>
  <text>Preface</text>
  <text>These regulations are adopted to enable the Department, in cooperation with the U.S. Department of Agriculture, to be of greater assistance to Maryland swine producers in a program of brucellosis control and eradication. Testing and validation of an individual herd under this program will be undertaken only at the request of the herd owner. Area testing and validation will be undertaken only with the consent of a majority of the swine breeders within an area.</text>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>"Department" means Maryland Department of Agriculture.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>"Herd test" includes a test of all breeding swine 6 months old or older in a given herd.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>"Infected herd" means a herd that discloses one or more swine showing a complete agglutination reaction in the blood titer dilution of 1:100 or higher, or a positive reaction to the card test.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>"Negative herd" means a herd:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>That discloses no swine having agglutination reactions higher than incomplete at the 1:100 dilution, or any swine positive to the card test. All animals over 6 months old in the herd are to be included in the brucellosis test.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In which at least 10 percent of the breeding swine have been tested annually in a market swine testing program for 3 consecutive years with no positive test results.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>"Negative swine" means a swine from:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An infected herd or herd of unknown status that disclosed no reaction or less than complete agglutination in the blood titer dilution of 1:25, or a swine reported to be negative to the card test;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A validated or negative herd that discloses no reaction or less than complete agglutination in the blood titer dilution of 1:100, or that has no reaction to the card test.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>"Official test for brucellosis" means either:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The tube agglutination test;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The brucellosis card test; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any other test that may be recommended by the United States Animal Health Association and approved by the United States Department of Agriculture and the Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>"Reactor" or "positive swine" means swine:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Disclosing a complete agglutination reaction in the blood titer dilution of 1:100 or higher;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In an infected herd or herd of unknown status having a complete reaction in the 1:25 dilution or higher; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Disclosing a positive card test reaction.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>"Secretary" means Secretary of Agriculture or the Secretary’s designee.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Identification.</heading>
    <text>All swine tested shall be identified with an approved ear tag, tattoo, or other means as specified or approved by the Department.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Herd Validation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Negative Herds. A swine herd will be validated following two consecutive negative tests on the entire breeding herd 30 to 90 days apart. However, if all breeding swine tested on the first test can be accounted for on the validating test, an extension of time may be granted, but the extension will not be allowed to exceed 180 days. This includes all breeding animals 6 months old and older. Validation is effective for 12 months unless otherwise revoked. The validated status will apply to all offspring born since the last test. A swine of unknown brucellosis status or of a suspicious brucellosis status may not be added to or associated with a validated herd or a herd in the process of becoming validated. Herd validation will be voided under these circumstances.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Validated Herds.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Owners of herds that comply with validation requirements will be issued validation certificates by the Department and the Animal and Plant Health Inspection Service of the U.S. Department of Agriculture and may use them in advertising their breeding stock.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Upon expiration, validation certificates will not be renewed (or will be cancelled, whichever is appropriate) until such time as the herd again satisfies validation requirements.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Upon finding one or more reactors in a validated herd, the validation certificate will be immediately cancelled.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Infected Herds.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All infected herds shall be held in quarantine until free of brucellosis as determined by blood testing and until declared free of brucellosis by the Secretary.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In herds with reactors one of the following plans shall be selected by the herd owner in consultation with an agent of the Department, for eradicating the disease and qualifying the herd for validation:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Plan A. This plan is recommended for infected herds showing clinical symptoms of brucellosis.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The entire herd shall be sent to slaughter as soon as practicable.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Houses and equipment shall be cleaned and disinfected.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Restocking shall be done with swine from a negative herd.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Following two consecutive negative tests 30 to 90 days apart, the herd will be eligible for validation, and a certificate issued on proof of eligibility.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Plan B. This plan is useful in herds where only a few reactors are found and where no clinical symptoms of brucellosis have been noted.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>All reactors should be sent to slaughter.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The herd shall be retested at 30 day intervals, removing reactors for slaughter, until the entire herd is negative.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Two negative tests not less than 90 days apart, on all breeding animals 6 months old or older, will qualify the herd for validation.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>If the herd is not freed of infection within 180 days, Plan A will be recommended.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Herd Revalidation. Herds may be revalidated at the end of each 12-month period upon the basis of a negative test on all breeding animals 6 months old or older in the herd.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Cancellation of Herd Validation. If there are reactors revealed in the herd, or if the herd fails to requalify for validation renewal within 14 months, the validation certificate will be cancelled and the herd must requalify for validation in accordance with this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Area Plan.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Area Validation. Following a request from swine owners within a designated area, the Department and the U.S. Department of Agriculture, Animal and Plant Health Inspection Service, may declare that area validated-brucellosis-free provided it fulfills the following requirements:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All breeding herds in the designated area shall have attained negative status.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Not more than 3 percent of the herds, or one herd, whichever is greater, shall have been found to be infected during the 18-month qualification period.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Areas may qualify as validated-brucellosis-free for a period of 3 years provided all breeding herds in the designated area qualify under one of the two following procedures:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All herds of breeding swine in the designated area shall be validated or have a negative herd test, in which all breeding swine 6 months old or older are tested. All herds of breeding swine in the designated area qualifying under the procedure shall have been tested within 18 months before the date validation is requested.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>All herds of breeding swine in the designated area shall be validated or have established negative herd status under a market swine testing program (10 percent of the breeding swine to be tested annually for 3 consecutive years).</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Area Revalidation.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Areas which carry out one of the following provisions may be revalidated at the expiration of the 3 year period:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Negative herd test, in which all breeding swine 6 months old or older are tested and found negative within the last 18 months of the 3 year validation period.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Each herd of breeding swine shall blood test at least 10 percent of the breeding swine over 6 months old, or a minimum of one animal, whichever is greater, within the 3-year period. If one- half of the required tests are not reported by the end of the first 18 months of the 3 year validation period, it will be necessary to blood test all breeding swine in each herd in the area as under this subsection.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Infected Herds. Herds found infected during the validation period shall be placed under quarantine until freed of brucellosis.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Disposal of Reactors. Reactors shall be permanently identified by tag or brand, or both, and moved under permit within 10 days for immediate slaughter to an approved slaughtering establishment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Cleaning and Disinfection. Buildings, farrowing pens, and equipment shall be cleaned and disinfected following removal of the reactors.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Permissible Infection Rate for Revalidation. The accumulated number of infected herds in a validated-brucellosis-free area may not exceed 5 percent of the herds in the area, or one herd, whichever is greater, over the 3 year validation period.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Cancellation of Area Validation. Cancellation shall become effective at the end of a 36-month period if the designated area does not qualify for revalidation under §B, above.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Introduction of Swine into Validated-Free Areas and Movement of Swine Through Auction Markets and Livestock Sales.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Swine for immediate slaughter may move through regular marketing channels (approved livestock markets and approved slaughtering establishments) without brucellosis testing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Swine for feeding purposes may enter without a test, or may be held in validated areas without a test, provided the swine are maintained in isolation separate and apart from all breeding stock as approved by the Secretary.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Swine originating in validated-brucellosis-free herds, or negative non-validated herds in validated-brucellosis-free areas, may enter a non-validated herd without a test, provided the swine are moved directly and have not been in contact with infected swine or swine of an unknown brucellosis status, and have not been exposed to an infected premises.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Swine originating in herds not described in §C, above, shall have passed a negative test within 30 days before the date of entry, to be held in isolation, and pass one additional negative test within 30 to 60 days before being added to the herd.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Swine over 6 months old sold through auction markets or livestock sales, to be returned to farms for breeding purposes, shall originate directly from a validated herd, or be blood tested negative within 30 days before sale, or be blood tested negative before release.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>All swine consigned to farms in Maryland shall be transported in conveyances that have been properly cleaned and disinfected.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|3-101">Agriculture Article, §3-101, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-10-20">Effective date: June, 1968</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
