<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>07</num>
  <heading>Control, Eradication, or Both, of Infectious Diseases of Swine</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>"Department" means Maryland Department of Agriculture.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>"Secretary" means Secretary of Agriculture or the Secretary’s designee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>"Recognized slaughtering establishment" means a slaughtering establishment operating under supervision of municipal, State, or federal meat inspection or recognized by the Department.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>"Stockyard" or "livestock market" means a place in the State where swine are assembled for sale, either by private sale or public auction. All livestock markets in Maryland not under federal-State cooperative approval must receive approval from the Department before being permitted to handle swine. Approval will be based on the standards presently set forth and as may be amended by the U.S. Department of Agriculture governing interstate movement of swine with reference to hog cholera and other communicable diseases.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Movement of Swine.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Slaughter. Swine may be sold direct to recognized slaughtering establishments without restriction, if they are identified as provided under 9 CFR §71.19 and §§78.30—78.34 (1991), which are incorporated by reference with the following modifications:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Whenever "Administrator" appears, read "Secretary";</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Whenever "interstate" appears, read "intrastate"; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Whenever "authorized employee of the United States Department of Agriculture" appears, read "authorized employee of the Maryland Department of Agriculture".</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>For Other Than Slaughter.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All swine for sale or movement by any method shall meet the following conditions:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All are subject to veterinary inspection.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>All swine are restricted to one movement. One movement is defined as from farm to farm, from farm to auction market to farm, or from farm to dealer to farm. The entire movement shall be completed within 72 hours.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Swine sold for return to farms may not show evidence of any infectious or contagious disease.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>All purchased swine shall be quarantined to the premises of destination for 30 days regardless of origin.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Swine consigned to Maryland from other states are subject to State and federal interstate regulations.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In addition to those above, swine for sale or movement through dealers, auction markets, and public stockyards shall meet the following conditions:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All public stockyards and livestock markets where swine are sold for purposes other than immediate slaughter and all trucks transporting the swine shall be thoroughly cleaned and disinfected before each use for swine. Each market or truck operator shall be responsible for the proper cleaning of his market or vehicle to the satisfaction of the Department.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>All swine at public stockyards and auction markets shall be individually identified by eartag or other method approved by the Secretary.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>All swine for return to farms shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Originate from either pseudorabies monitored or qualified pseudorabies negative herds unless they have been tested and found negative for pseudorabies within 30 days before sale;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Be kept completely segregated and isolated from swine consigned for sale as slaughter swine; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>At public sales and auctions, be sold before the sales ring and alleyways are used for slaughter swine.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>At public sales and auctions, cull swine (those which do not pass veterinary inspection for health reasons) shall be penned separate and apart from feeder or breeder swine. They may be released for slaughter. If, in the opinion of the inspecting veterinarian, they are unfit for slaughter, they may be released to a rendering plant or direct to a farm in Maryland to be held separate and apart from other swine under permanent quarantine until they are suitable for slaughter and then released by written permission.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The name and address of the consignor of any swine showing evidence of infectious or contagious disease shall be reported without delay to the Department.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>All swine leaving auction markets and public stockyards shall be accompanied by a certificate of release.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Auction markets, public stockyards, and dealers shall maintain records of origin and destination of all swine movements and shall grant federal and State inspectors access to those records.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|3-101">Agriculture Article, §3-101, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date: November, 1971</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-07-06"><cite path="|15|11|07|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective July 6, 1992 (19:13 Md. R. 1203)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
