<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>09</num>
  <heading>Eradication of Tuberculosis in Swine</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>"Department" means Maryland Department of Agriculture.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>"Reactor" means the same as the definition of a reactor in "Uniform Methods and Rules." There is no suspect category in swine tuberculin testing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>"Secretary" means Secretary of Agriculture or the Secretary’s designee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>"Tuberculin test" means the intradermal test as described in the Uniform Methods and Rules for Tuberculosis Eradication.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>"Uniform Methods and Rules" means the latest edition of Uniform Methods and Rules for Tuberculosis Eradication as published by the U.S. Department of Agriculture.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Reporting Tuberculosis.</heading>
    <text>All persons having knowledge of the existence of or suspicion of the existence of tuberculosis in swine or poultry shall report it to the Department.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Quarantine.</heading>
    <text>Any premises upon which swine tuberculosis reactors are disclosed, or any premises to which slaughter swine with confirmed lesions of tuberculosis have been traced, or any premises where the Secretary has reason to suspect tuberculosis infection may exist or exposure to tuberculosis has taken place, shall be subject to immediate quarantine. Once quarantine is imposed, movement of swine on or off the premises shall be prohibited, except for slaughter purposes under written permit issued by the Secretary. This quarantine shall include any other species of animal or fowl that the Secretary determines is infected with or has been exposed to tuberculosis. The quarantine shall be released after it has been determined, by testing or other means, that tuberculosis no longer exists on the premises and any cleaning and disinfecting required by the Secretary has been completed.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Herd Test.</heading>
    <text>Tuberculin tests of any or all swine in a herd will be carried out whenever the Secretary has reason to suspect that tuberculosis exists in the herd or that it has been exposed to this infection. Further testing, or other appropriate procedures, shall be conducted on the farm in order to find and remove sources of infection in any species of animal or poultry on the premises. All tests for tuberculosis shall be reported promptly.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Epidemiology.</heading>
    <text>When an infected herd has been found, a complete epidemiological investigation shall be made. This should cover all species of animals and fowl on the premises.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Reactors.</heading>
    <text>Tuberculin test reactors shall be identified with a reactor tag and sent to slaughter under permit or disposed of in other manner approved by the Secretary within 30 days of the test date.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Indemnity.</heading>
    <text>Indemnity by the State shall be paid in accord with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|3-107">Agriculture Article, § 3-107, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and the following requirements:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Indemnities will be paid to owners of tuberculosis reactors and to owners of herds depopulated because of the existence of tuberculosis.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Swine of feeder, slaughter, or both types shall be appraised using the prevailing market quotation price per pound as a guide. This will vary with age, size, and quality of the animal.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Breeding swine shall be appraised using the price of similar animals in recent sales as a guide.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Maximum indemnity from State sources may not exceed $175 per animal. Maximum indemnity payments shall be reserved for breeding swine.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If indemnity from other sources is paid to owners of swine destroyed because of the existence of tuberculosis, indemnity from State sources will be paid only to the extent that total indemnity payments plus net salvage received does not exceed 90 percent of the appraised value of the animal.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Cleaning and Disinfecting.</heading>
    <text>Infected premises and all vehicles and equipment used in connection with the infected premises shall be thoroughly cleaned and disinfected in a manner approved by the Secretary.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Department Cooperation with U.S.D.A.</heading>
    <text>When the U. S.D.A. has approved and put into effect a program for the control and eradication of tuberculosis in swine, the Department intends to cooperate with U.S.D.A. in carrying out the program.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Other Procedures and Policies.</heading>
    <text>In all procedures and policies relating to the eradication of tuberculosis in swine not covered above, the latest published edition of "Uniform Methods and Rules for Tuberculosis Eradication" shall apply.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|3-101">Agriculture Article, §3-101, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1972-10-16">Effective date: October 16, 1972</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
