<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>14</num>
  <heading>Requirements for Livestock or Animal Exhibitions</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter describes the animal health requirements for any livestock or animal exhibition for the purpose of preventing the spread of a contagious or infectious disease.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This chapter also includes requirements concerning the proper care and treatment of animals at exhibitions.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter does not apply to livestock exhibition activities regulated by the Maryland Racing Commission.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meaning indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Accredited herd" means a livestock herd meeting the U.S. Department of Agriculture testing requirements for tuberculosis under 9 CFR §77.1.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Accredited veterinarian" means a veterinarian approved to participate in a federal—state animal health program by the U.S. Department of Agriculture and by the Department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Department" means Maryland Department of Agriculture.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Exhibition" means any livestock show, except a show conducted for the sole purpose of selling the livestock exhibited.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Exhibitor.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Exhibitor" means a person 18 years old or older who owns or presents livestock for exhibition.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Exhibitor" includes a parent or guardian of a minor child exhibiting livestock.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Interstate certificate of veterinary inspection" means a form provided by the U.S. Department of Agriculture that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is issued by an accredited veterinarian in the state where the livestock originated;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is valid for 30 days from the date of issue; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Documents a veterinary inspection which certifies that livestock is fit for transport and for exhibition.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Intrastate certificate of veterinary inspection" means a form provided by the Department that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is issued by an accredited veterinarian in Maryland;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is valid for the exhibition season in the calendar year it is issued unless otherwise directed by the Department; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Documents a veterinary inspection which certifies that livestock originating in Maryland is fit for exhibition in this State.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Livestock" includes the following animal species:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Bovine (cattle);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Camelid (llama, alpaca, vicuna and guanaco);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Caprine (goat);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Cervid (deer);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Equine (horse, donkey, and mule);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Ovine (sheep);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Porcine (pig); and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Lagomorpha (rabbit and hare).</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Person" includes the State, any county, municipal corporation, an individual, receiver, trustee, guardian, executor, administrator, fiduciary, or representative of any kind, or any partnership, firm, association, public or private corporation, or any other entity.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Petting zoo" means an exhibition where the public is encouraged to touch any livestock or other animal.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Sponsor" means the person responsible for organizing the livestock exhibition.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>"Veterinarian" means an individual who is licensed, registered or otherwise permitted to lawfully practice veterinary medicine in Maryland, any of the several states, U.S. territories, the District of Columbia, or any appropriate political entity as determined by the Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>General Exhibition Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General Prohibition.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may not conduct a livestock exhibition or exhibit livestock without first complying with the requirements of this chapter for the prevention of contagious or infectious disease.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not enter or show livestock at any exhibition if the livestock has a contagious or infectious disease.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Ringworm. A person may exhibit livestock showing signs of ringworm only if the exhibitor possesses a certificate from a veterinarian stating that the affected livestock:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Has been under appropriate ringworm treatment by that veterinarian for at least 21 days before entering the exhibition site; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is no longer contagious to other animals.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Rabies Vaccination. A person may not show livestock at any petting zoo unless all exhibited animals in the petting zoo, 105 days or older, are vaccinated against rabies as provided in <cite path="|10.06.02">COMAR 10.06.02</cite>, unless there is no rabies vaccine licensed and approved by the U.S. Department of Agriculture for that animal species.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="15|11|14|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Sponsor Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each livestock exhibition sponsor shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provide the Department at least 60 days advanced written notice of the date, time, and location of any livestock exhibition, unless:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The exhibition is a Maryland fair and show board funded event; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The exhibition sponsor is exempt from this requirement as determined by the Department; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Do one of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Report to the Department any animal from the exhibition suspected of having or showing obvious, apparent, or known signs of a contagious or infectious disease; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Exclude from the exhibition premises any animal having obvious, apparent, or known signs of a contagious or infectious disease.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Exemptions under <cite path="15|11|14|.05|A.|(1)|(b)">§A(1)(b) of this regulation</cite> may be granted if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The exhibition is sponsored, sanctioned, or otherwise approved by an association, coalition, or other entity which serves as an umbrella organization for multiple livestock exhibitions in a calendar year; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>That organization provides adequate and timely notice of subordinate exhibitions to the Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="15|11|14|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Exhibitor Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General Requirements. Each livestock exhibitor shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Have all livestock examined by an accredited veterinarian before the exhibition as prescribed by the Department;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="15|11|14|.06|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, keep a copy of a valid interstate or intrastate certificate of veterinary inspection with each animal at all times during the exhibition;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Do all of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Personally examine all livestock for any signs of contagious or infectious disease prior to entry to the exhibition site but not more than 24 hours before entry to the exhibition site;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Document the examination with a properly completed Departmental livestock exhibition self-certification form for animal health;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Present for exhibition only animals that:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Have not been exposed to contagious or infectious diseases; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Appear by the pre-exhibition examination conducted by the exhibitor to be free from infectious or contagious disease; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Maintain a copy of the completed self-certification form with the livestock during the exhibition;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Individually identify each animal by ear tag, tattoo, registration number, national animal identification system device, or other means approved by the Department;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Make all records required by this chapter available to the Department or sponsor upon request;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Report animals suspected of having a contagious or infectious disease to the sponsor; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Allow the Department to examine or test any livestock for a contagious or infectious disease.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Required vaccinations and testing shall be documented by the accredited veterinarian on the certificate of veterinary inspection or other required health documents when appropriate.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Exhibitors of horses shall substitute a valid official report documenting freedom from equine infectious anemia.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Special Exhibitor Requirements for Certain Livestock. Each livestock exhibitor shall ensure that the health requirements in §§E—K of this regulation are met before any exhibition.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Bovine (Cattle).</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All cattle 6 months or older, including castrates, shall meet:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The tuberculosis control requirements under both <cite path="15.11.01.04">COMAR 15.11.01.04</cite> and 9 CFR 77; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Brucellosis control requirements under both <cite path="|15.11.02">COMAR 15.11.02</cite> and 9 CFR 78.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All cattle shall be vaccinated in a manner prescribed by the Department against bovine respiratory disease complex. The vaccine shall be administered in a manner adequate to confer protective immunity against these diseases for the duration of the exhibition.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Porcine (Pigs). All pigs, except castrates, 6 months old or older, shall meet the Brucellosis control requirements of <cite path="|15.11.06">COMAR 15.11.06</cite> and 9 CFR 78.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Ovine (Sheep).</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All sheep shall meet the scrapie in sheep requirements under <cite path="|15.11.18">COMAR 15.11.18</cite> and 9 CFR 79.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The exhibitor shall have a certificate of veterinary inspection for all sheep, including lambs, clearly stating that the entire flock has been inspected and found free of evidence of all contagious or infectious diseases.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Each certificate shall include the scrapie premise identification number and each individual scrapie identification number.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Caprine (Goat).</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All goats 6 months or older shall meet the tuberculosis and brucellosis control requirements of <cite path="15.11.01.06">COMAR 15.11.01.06</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All goats shall meet the scrapie in goat requirements under both <cite path="|15.11.18">COMAR 15.11.18</cite> and 9 CFR 79. The exhibitor shall have a certificate of veterinary inspection for all goats, indicating that the entire flock has been inspected and found to be free of evidence of all contagious or infectious diseases. Each certificate shall include the scrapie premise identification number and the individual scrapie identification number as required by both <cite path="15.11.18.03">COMAR 15.11.18.03</cite> and 9 CFR §79.5.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Equine (Horse).</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The exhibitor shall ensure that each horse exhibited meets all requirements including testing for equine infectious anemia under <cite path="|15.11.12">COMAR 15.11.12</cite>. Horses originating in Maryland are exempt from requirements pertaining to a certificate of veterinary inspection.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The exhibitor shall keep a copy of a valid official result for the test (Coggins) to determine the horse is free from equine infectious anemia with each animal at all times during the exhibition.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The exhibitor shall comply with horse transport requirements under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|3-902">Agriculture Article, §3-902, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Camelids (Llama, Alpaca, Vicuna, and Guanaco). All Camelids, including castrates, 6 months or older, shall meet at least one of the following requirements to be eligible for exhibition:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Originate directly from a herd in Maryland not under restriction or quarantine for tuberculosis and from which all animals have tested negative for tuberculosis within the past 12 months; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Have a negative individual Tuberculin test documented within 60 days of exhibition.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Lagomorpha (Rabbits, Hares). All rabbits presented for exhibition shall meet the conditions described under general requirements for exhibitors.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Prohibited Conduct.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A person may not knowingly expose livestock to an animal with a contagious or infectious disease, or expose a healthy animal to a contagious or infectious disease in violation of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|3-110">Agriculture Article, §3-110, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A person may not willfully make false statements, provide false information, alter or possess an altered animal health certificate or report, or alter, damage, use, or attempt to use any animal or premise identification device or document in violation of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|3-118">Agriculture Article, §3-118, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A person may not knowingly conceal the fact that a contagious or infectious disease exists on his premises in violation of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|3-113">Agriculture Article, §3-113 </cite>(b), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A person may not knowingly conceal signs of a contagious or infectious disease, to include giving anti-inflammatory drugs to mask fever and discharges, appling coloring or creams to lesions, or employ any other method that may be used to alter or disguise signs of contagious or infectious disease.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A person may not give away a live animal as a prize for, or inducement to enter, a contest, game, or other competition except as an agricultural project, conservation purpose, or for slaughter, without the approval of the Secretary of Agriculture in violation of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|10-610">Criminal Law Article, §10-610, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Penalties.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Criminal Penalties.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>General. A person who violates the provisions of this chapter, except regarding animals given as a prize, is guilty of a misdemeanor and is subject to the penalties provided in Agriculture Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|12-101">12-101</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|12-102">12-102</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Animal Given as a Prize. A person who violates the provisions of <cite path="|15|11|14|.07|E.">Regulation .07E of this chapter</cite> is guilty of a misdemeanor and upon conviction is subject to a fine not exceeding $500 as provided in the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|10-610">Criminal Law Article, §10-610, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Administrative Penalties.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>General. In lieu of or in addition to being subject to criminal sanctions, a person who violates the provisions of this chapter, except regarding animals given as a prize and unlawful horse transport, is subject to administrative penalties up to $10,000, as provided in <cite path="|15.11.19">COMAR 15.11.19</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Unlawful Horse Transport. In lieu of or in addition to being subject to criminal sanctions, a person who violates the provisions of <cite path="|15|11|14|.06|B.|(5)|(c)">Regulation .06B(5)(c) of this chapter</cite> is subject to administrative penalties up to $1,000 per horse as provided in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|3-903">Agriculture Article, §3-903, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Agriculture Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-103">2-103</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|3-101">3-101</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1975-07-09">Effective date: July 9, 1975 (2:5 Md. R. 1078)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-07-17" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|15|11|14|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|15|11|14|.05">.05</cite> repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|15|11|14|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|15|11|14|.08">.08</cite> adopted effective July 17, 2008 (35:14 Md. R. 1246)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
