<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>15</num>
  <heading>The Control and Eradication of Pseudorabies in Swine and Other Livestock Within Maryland</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>"Department" means Maryland Department of Agriculture.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>"Pseudorabies", also known as "mad itch" or Aujeszky's Disease, is an infectious disease caused by a herpes virus to which several species of mammals and birds are susceptible, the clinical signs and symptoms of which are characterized by central nervous system disturbance.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>"Secretary" means Secretary of Agriculture or the Secretary’s designee.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Reporting Pseudorabies Outbreaks.</heading>
    <text>Any person having knowledge or suspicion of the existence of pseudorabies shall report this to the Department within 48 hours.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Quarantine of Infected Herds.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Any herd which the Secretary has reason to believe is infected with or has been exposed to pseudorabies shall be quarantined and no livestock may be moved from or to a quarantined herd without written permission of the Secretary. The quarantine will be lifted when tests and examinations, as the Secretary may require, indicate that the herd is not infected.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the Secretary permits swine to be moved from a quarantined herd to a quarantined feedlot, those swine shall be identified individually by a method approved by the Secretary.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Pseudorabies Vaccines.</heading>
    <text>The use of pseudorabies vaccine in swine is subject to the following restrictions:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The vaccine shall be a USDA licensed vaccine or vaccine that is authorized for field trials by federal and State officials.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Prior approval for use or possession of the vaccine shall be obtained in writing from the Department. This approval will be granted only for use in swine herds determined to be infected or threatened with infection by pseudorabies.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>At the time of vaccination, all swine shall be individually identified by a method approved by the Secretary.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Disinfection of Infected Premises.</heading>
    <text>Infected premises and all vehicles and equipment used in connection with an infected premises shall be thoroughly cleaned and disinfected in a manner approved by the Department.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|3-101">Agriculture Article, §3-101, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1978-10-06">Effective date: October 6, 1978 (5:20 Md. R. 1500)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
