<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Interagency Discharge Planning for Hospitalized Children and Adolescents</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>The following regulations govern procedures for the development of interagency plans for the provision of services to hospitalized children.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Case service coordinator" means a State employee, assigned to the Office for Children, who is responsible for tracking the status of hospitalized children and coordinating interagency efforts to secure the timely and appropriate placement of these children.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Departments" means the Maryland Departments of Health, Human Services, Education, and Juvenile Services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Discharge plan" means the written plan, developed by the hospital treatment team and qualified professionals from the Departments providing services to the child, which describes the services, treatment, and training appropriate for the child outside the hospital setting.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Hospitalized child" means both State-hospitalized children and privately hospitalized children.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Lead agency" means the Department designated by the multi-agency review team to implement the hospitalized child's discharge plan.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Multi-agency review team" means a committee of senior officials from the Departments and the Office for Children.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Private psychiatric hospital" means Brooklane Hospital, Gundry Glass Hospital, Sheppard and Enoch Pratt Hospital, and Taylor Manor Hospital.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Privately hospitalized child" means an individual under 18 years old, committed by juvenile court order to State custody and who is admitted to a private psychiatric hospital.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"State-hospitalized child" means an individual 18 years old admitted to the Mental Hygiene Administration's inpatient hospital-level care.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Procedures for Identification and Tracking of Hospitalized Children.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each State hospital and each private psychiatric hospital, when possible, shall complete an inpatient tracking form for each hospitalized child and report to a designated Department as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within 24 hours after the first business day following the admission of a hospitalized child, the hospital staff shall complete and transmit the inpatient tracking form to the designated Department; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The hospital staff shall update the inpatient tracking forms every 2 weeks and transmit the forms to the designated Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The case service coordinator shall maintain the tracking forms and any data reports generated from the forms. The case service coordinator shall forward data reports generated from the forms to all Departments.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Procedures for Development of Interagency Plans.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Within 10 working days after a child is hospitalized, the lead agency shall provide case management services to each hospitalized child, in the manner considered appropriate by the lead agency, to assist in securing and maintaining appropriate discharge services and placement.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The hospital treatment team and lead agency shall jointly develop for each hospitalized child a discharge plan that includes recommendations for the services needed to maintain the child outside the inpatient setting and provide appropriate treatment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The recommendations in the discharge plan may include the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Therapy;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Education;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Residential arrangement;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Medications and medical needs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Physical needs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Social and recreational needs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Family involvement in therapy; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Family visitation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The case manager from the lead agency shall attend the discharge planning meeting with the hospital treatment team, or be available by telephone to discuss the discharge plan. The lead agency shall be responsible for implementing the discharge plan.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The multi-agency review team shall meet every 2 weeks to review the discharge plan and the tracking forms of each hospitalized child who is ready for discharge or whose tracking forms indicate possible difficulty in obtaining timely and appropriate discharge to assist in resolving problems that might require interagency action or planning.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Transitional Services.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Transitional services include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Therapeutic;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Educational;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Interim residential;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Social; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Recreational.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The lead agency shall provide transitional services when the treating physician, in consultation with the hospital treatment team and the lead agency, determines that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The hospitalized child is ready for discharge and remains in the hospital; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Transitional services are necessary to prevent specific clinical deterioration of the hospitalized child.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The lead agency, in consultation with the treating physician and the hospital treatment team, other departments, the child, and the child's parents if the parents are available, shall determine the specific transitional services provided to the child.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The lead agency may provide transitional services if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The lead agency determines that transitional services are necessary to assist with a hospitalized child's adjustment to an aftercare placement; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Resources are available.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Article 41, §§6-101 and 6-104; Article 83C, §§2-102, 2-104, and 2-113; Article 88A, §3; Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-301">8-301</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-303">8-303</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-401">8-401</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-417">8-417</cite>; Health-General Article, §§2-102, 2-104, 2-105, 4-305, 4-307, 7-401, 7-1007, 10-204, 10-207, 10-712, 10-1203, and 15-102.1; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-07-31">Effective date: July 31, 1995 (22:15 Md. R. 1117)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-11-28" discontinuity="true"><cite path="|01.04.03">COMAR 01.04.03</cite> revised and recodified to <cite path="|14.31.03">COMAR 14.31.03</cite> as an emergency provision effective June 30, 2005 (32:15 Md. R. 1314); recodified permanently effective November 28, 2005 (32:23 Md. R. 1828)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-11-24"><cite path="|14|31|03|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective June 30, 2005 (32:15 Md. R. 1314); amended permanently effective November 24, 2005 (32:23 Md. R. 1828)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
