<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Transfers Of Service</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Customer Changes of Service Providers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A customer may move between SOS or HPS and competitive electricity supply service.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A customer may not be charged a fee for switching between SOS or HPS and competitive electricity supply.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Except as provided by an order of the Commission, a utility may not impose a minimum contract term for the provision of electricity supply service under this subtitle.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|52|03|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Notice of Transfer to Standard Offer Service.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Existing Customers. If an existing utility customer does not select a competitive electricity supplier to provide electricity supply service, the customer shall receive standard offer service under this subtitle until that choice is made in accordance with <cite path="20|52|03|.02|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>New Customer. A customer establishing a new service, after the service periods specified in <cite path="|20.52.02">COMAR 20.52.02</cite>, shall receive SOS until the customer affirmatively selects a competitive electricity supplier.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Transfer Rules.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a customer or the customer’s competitive supplier requests SOS, 12 or more days before the customer's next regularly scheduled meter read date, the utility shall place the customer on SOS on the customer's next regularly scheduled meter read date.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a customer or the customer’s competitive supplier requests SOS, less than 12 days before the customer’s next regularly scheduled meter read date, the utility shall transfer the customer to SOS on the subsequent scheduled meter read date after the date of the request.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If a customer is subject to an involuntary transfer to SOS, the customer shall receive SOS effective on the date on which PJM transfers responsibility for supplying that customer's electricity to the utility.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|52|03|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Notice of Transfer From Standard Offer Service.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>When a customer receiving SOS chooses electricity from a competitive electricity supplier, the competitive electricity supplier shall notify the utility.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The notice required under <cite path="20|52|03|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall comply with the requirements of <cite path="|20.53">COMAR 20.53</cite> and the utility's approved supplier coordination tariffs.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Transfer Rules.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>When a competitive electricity supplier provides the transfer notice required under <cite path="20|52|03|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, 12 or more days before a customer's next regularly scheduled meter read date, the utility shall transfer the customer to the competitive electricity supplier on the next regularly scheduled meter read date after the notice.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When a competitive electricity supplier provides the transfer notice, required under <cite path="20|52|03|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, less than 12 days before a customer's next regularly scheduled meter read date, the utility shall transfer the customer to the competitive electricity supplier on the subsequent scheduled meter read date after the notice.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|52|03|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Hourly Priced or Competitive Service — Selection or Transfer.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Utility Fixed Price or Variable Price Service Customers.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a customer eligible for does not select or have a competitive electricity supplier, a utility shall provide HPS service to the customer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a customer eligible for HPS selects a competitive electricity supplier, the competitive electricity supplier shall provide the utility notice of the selection in a manner conforming to the requirements of the applicable utility’s supplier coordination tariff and <cite path="20.53.06.05">COMAR 20.53.06.05</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Failure of Competitive Electricity Supplier to Deliver.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a competitive electricity service customer is eligible for HPS and the competitive electricity service supplier fails to deliver power as defined by PJM due to default, bankruptcy, or Commission action, the customer shall receive HPS.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A customer eligible for HPS and affected by <cite path="20|52|03|.04|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite> may elect at any time to switch to another competitive electricity supplier.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Denial or Termination of SOS.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A utility or other Commission-authorized entity providing SOS may terminate SOS only if the termination process complies with <cite path="|20.31">COMAR 20.31</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A utility or other Commission-authorized entity providing SOS may deny SOS only if the denial complies with <cite path="|20.50.04">COMAR 20.50.04</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Public Utilities Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-113">2-113</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-121">2-121</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|5-101">5-101</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-510">7-510</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-06-07">Effective date: June 7, 2004 (31:11 Md. R. 857)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-02-04"><cite path="|20|52|03|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective February 4, 2013 (40:2 Md. R. 73)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-02-04"><cite path="|20|52|03|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective February 4, 2013 (40:2 Md. R. 73)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-02-04"><cite path="|20|52|03|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite>, C amended effective February 4, 2013 (40:2 Md. R. 73)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-02-04"><cite path="|20|52|03|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective February 4, 2013 (40:2 Md. R. 73)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
