<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Price</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Public Notice of Price.</heading>
    <text>Upon completion of the electric supply procurement process under <cite path="|20.52.04">COMAR 20.52.04</cite>, a utility shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Explain the methodology used to calculate the price for electric service under this subtitle;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Calculate the price for each type of electric service offered to a customer under this subtitle;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>File tariffs with the Commission containing the methods of calculating the price for each service authorized by this subtitle at least 30 days, and if possible 2 months, before the effective date of the tariffs;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Provide affected customers at least 30 days notice, and if possible 2 months notice, of new prices for electric service under this subtitle; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Post on the utility's internet website, the actual price payable each month for each service offered under this subtitle.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|52|05|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Calculation of Prices.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>For service periods stated in <cite path="|20.52.02">COMAR 20.52.02</cite>, retail prices for each service other than HPS under this subtitle shall consist of the sum of the following components:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The seasonally differentiated and, if applicable, the time-of-use differentiated load weighted average of all awarded electric supply prices for specific services in each year;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Retail charges designed to recover, on an aggregate basis, FERC-approved transmission charges and any other PJM charges and costs incurred by the utility;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An administrative charge, including other costs and return or profit; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Applicable taxes.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Commission may approve adjustments or reconciliation of a price component under <cite path="20|52|05|.02|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Public Utilities Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-113">2-113</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-121">2-121</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|5-101">5-101</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-510">7-510</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-06-07">Effective date: June 7, 2004 (31:11 Md. R. 857)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
