<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>04</num>
  <heading>Election Day Page Program</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this subtitle, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Page” means a student selected by a local board participating in the program to assist the local board and election judges in performing duties in a polling place on election day.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Program” means the election day page program.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>The purpose of the program is to provide assistance to election judges in the polling places on election day.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Administrator to Develop and Issue.</heading>
    <text>The State Administrator shall develop and issue for local boards:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A page’s training manual;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Instruction sheets summarizing certain procedures relating to the program;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The curriculum for training pages; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A combined oath and commission.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="33|02|04|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Local Board Participation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Participation. A local board is not required to participate in the program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Notice of Participation. If a local board decides to participate in the program, the local board shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At least four months prior to election day, notify the State Administrator of its participation in the program; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="33|02|04|.04|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, implement the page training program developed by the State Administrator under <cite path="33.02.04.03">COMAR 33.02.04.03</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Waiver. A local board may request from the State Administrator a waiver of a program requirement. The State Administrator shall respond to a request for a waiver within 5 days of receipt of the waiver.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Program Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Local Board Requirement. A local board participating in the program shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Ensure each page received the required training before election day;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Encourage individuals at least 16 years old who apply to the program to serve as an election judge in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|10-202">Election Law Article, §10-202, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Certify community service hours for those participants that complete their service;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Use the combined oath and commission required by <cite path="|33|02|04|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Remove any individual who is unfit or incompetent for the program, at the discretion of the local board, and the individual may not receive community service hours.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Collaboration with School Boards. The local board:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall work with the local board of education to obtain appropriate access to the local schools and home-schooled programs to present the program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shall inform the local board of education that a student may obtain community service hours for participating in the program, and that any form used by the local board of education or local schools to certify community service hours should include space for the collection of the following information:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Name of page;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Signature of page’s parent or guardian;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Signature of local school administrator;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Number of hours worked;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Signature of a chief judge assigned to the same polling place as the page; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Signature of Election Director or designee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Allow the State Administrator or designee and/or a representative from the local school system to observe the training program.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Qualifications.</heading>
    <text>To qualify as a page, an individual shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Apply to the local board in the individual’s county of residence;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Be at least 14 years old by election day;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Be able to speak, read, and write the English language;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Be available to work at least one full 4-hour shift on election day;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Complete the required training provided by the local board before election day;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Take and subscribe to a written oath; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Be enrolled in a public, private, independent, or religious school or be home-schooled.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Responsibilities.</heading>
    <text>A page:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>May work up to two 4-hour shifts at a polling place on election day;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Shall serve under the direct supervision of the chief election judges for the assigned polling place; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Shall assist election judges with election day duties as directed.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Prohibitions.</heading>
    <text>During service on election day, a page may not:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Engage in any partisan activity while serving as a page at a polling place;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Handle or touch a marked ballot or voting equipment at any time;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Use electronic devices inside the polling room; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Work on election day unless the individual has completed the training provided by the local board.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Election Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|2-102">2-102</cite>(b)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|4">4</cite>), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|2-202">2-202</cite>(b), and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|10-402">10-402</cite>(c), Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-01-13">Effective date: January 13, 2020 (47:1 Md. R. 19)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
