<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>General Regulations</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>These regulations apply to LPG systems located in Maryland and to owners of these systems.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definition of Terms.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this subtitle, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Accident" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code">Public Utility Companies Article, §5-304, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Accuracy" means the degree of conformity of a measure to a standard or true value.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Associated metering device" means an instrument used to adjust the quantity of gas measured by a meter, based on the measurement of the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Temperature of the gas passing through the meter;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Pressure of the gas passing through the meter; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Temperature and pressure of the gas passing through the meter.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Check flow" means a flow of gas at 20—50 percent of the rated capacity of a meter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Commission" means the Public Service Commission of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Full rated flow" means a flow of gas at approximately 100 percent of the rated capacity of a meter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Gas" means LPG in the vapor state.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"LPG" means liquified petroleum gas which includes propane, or butane, or other combustible gases, or mixtures thereof.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"LPG system" means an LPG service installation located in Maryland that provides service to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Ten or more customers by underground pipes from a LPG storage tank; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>At least two but fewer than ten customers by underground pipes from a LPG storage tank, if a portion of the LPG system is located in a public place.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Meter" means a device used by an owner to measure a quantity of gas.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Owner" means the person, as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|1-101">Public Utilities Article, §1-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, owning the LPG system.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|56|01|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>General Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each owner shall provide the Commission with the following information in writing:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The location of each LPG system;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The number of customers or dwelling units provided service by each LPG system; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The name, address, and telephone number of the office of the person responsible for each LPG system.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The information required by <cite path="20|56|01|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall be filed with the Public Service Commission under <cite path="20.07.01.01">COMAR 20.07.01.01</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|56|01|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Incorporation by Reference.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following documents are incorporated by reference:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>49 CFR Part 191 Transportation of Natural Gas and Other Gas by Pipeline; Annual Reports, Incident Reports, and Safety Related Condition Reports, as amended;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>49 CFR Part 192 Transportation of Natural and Other Gas by Pipeline: Minimum Federal Safety Standards, as amended; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The applicable provisions in the GPTC Guide for Gas Transmission and Distribution Piping Systems, which is incorporated by reference under <cite path="20.55.02.02">COMAR 20.55.02.02</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Each owner shall use as acceptable good engineering practice applicable provisions under <cite path="20|56|01|.04|A.|(3)">§A(3) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Enforcement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Public Utilities Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-117">2-117</cite>(a), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|5-101">5-101</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|5-304">5-304</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|12-101">12-101</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|12-113">12-113</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|13-203">13-203</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland, shall apply to the owners of LPG systems to the extent ordered by the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Commission is an authorized agent of the United States Department of Transportation for the administration and enforcement of these regulations and those federal regulations that apply to LPG systems in this State.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Inspections and Tests.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Upon reasonable notice, a representative of the Commission shall be given access to each LPG system in order to conduct tests or inspections to assure compliance with these regulations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Routine inspections of the LPG systems shall be made during regular business hours and may be inspected at any time in the event of an emergency or incident.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|56|01|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Gas Leak Surveys.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Frequency of Leak Surveys. Each owner shall conduct a gas leak survey of a LPG pipeline system in accordance with the following schedule:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At least once each calendar year, at intervals not exceeding 15 months, for a pipeline located in a business district or place of public assembly;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>At least once every 3 calendar years, at intervals not exceeding 39 months, for a pipeline made of cast iron, ductile iron, and cathodically unprotected steel; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>At least once every 5 calendar years, at intervals not exceeding 63 months, for all other types of pipelines.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Testing Methods.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each owner shall establish written procedures for conducting gas leak surveys as specified in this chapter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Acceptable methods for owners conducting gas leak surveys, as described in the GPTC Guide for Gas Transmission and Distribution Piping Systems, include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Subsurface gas detector survey, including bar hole surveys;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Bubble leakage test for pipelines exposed to the atmosphere; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Pressure drop test.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>In addition to the acceptable methods listed in <cite path="20|56|01|.07|B.|(2)">§B(2) of this regulation</cite>, other survey and test methods that have been tested and proven to be at least equal to the methods listed in <cite path="20|56|01|.07|B.|(2)">§B(2) of this regulation</cite> and approved by the Commission may be used to meet the requirements of <cite path="20|56|01|.07|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A leak or leaks discovered by a gas leak survey conducted pursuant to this regulation shall be classified, and the appropriate action taken as described in the GPTC Guide For Gas Transmission and Distribution Piping Systems.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Field Operations.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An owner shall conduct a leakage survey on each new or replaced service line before the line is placed in service, but after backfilling and a reasonable period of gas pressurizing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>After a leak repair, an owner shall conduct a gas leakage survey in accordance with <cite path="20|56|01|.07|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Records of Leak Surveys.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An owner shall maintain a record of each leak survey listing by location and date for the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Number of leaks detected;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Severity of each leak; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Action taken to repair each leak.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An owner shall maintain the records required under <cite path="20|56|01|.07|E.|(1)">§E(1) of this regulation</cite> as long as the segment of pipeline involved remains in service.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Pipeline Location.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Identification.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An owner shall install tracer wire on all newly installed plastic pipes.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When the open trenching method of pipeline construction is used, an owner shall install suitable identification tape at least 12 inches above the top of the pipe.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Location of Residential Service Lines and Meters.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Residential customer meters shall be placed as close to the exterior building wall as possible.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Gas service may not be provided to new or renewed service lines if there is any underground pipeline after the meter, unless the pipeline carries gas only to gas utilization equipment located outdoors.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If it is not possible to comply with §B(1) or (2) of this regulation, written permission shall be obtained from the Commission before placing the meter and activating the service.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If a residential service line is replaced, the new service line shall be installed as provided in §B(1)—(3) of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|56|01|.09">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Records and Reports.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each owner of a LPG system shall maintain records and provide reports to the Commission as required by this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Fatal Accidents.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In the event of a fatal accident, an owner shall promptly notify the Commission of the fatal accident by telephone.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A written report shall be submitted to the Commission within 20 days of the date of the incident resulting in the fatal accident reported under <cite path="20|56|01|.09|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Leaks in pipes or tanks that are hazardous to the public shall be reported immediately to the local central fire department communications center and to the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Each owner shall submit to the Commission, on a quarterly basis, reports summarizing the leaks discovered, leak calls made pursuant to <cite path="20|56|01|.09|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, and the owner's responses to these events.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>All reports required to be filed with the United States Department of Transportation by 49 CFR 191 and 192 shall also be filed with the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Commission may require additional reports to be submitted to it by owners of LPG systems.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Construction Notices.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An owner shall notify the Commission in writing at least 10 days before the estimated start date of a major construction project.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A major construction project includes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A new pressure-regulating station;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A significant modification to gas supply equipment at an existing pressure-regulating station;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A new propane plant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A significant modification to process equipment at an existing propane plant; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>A new pipeline installation of 500 or more feet.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The notification required by this regulation shall be on a form provided by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Public Utilities Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-113">2-113</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-117">2-117</cite>(a), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-121">2-121</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|5-101">5-101</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|5-304">5-304</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-301">7-301</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-302">7-302</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|11-102">11-102</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|12-101">12-101</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|12-113">12-113</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|13-203">13-203</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1982-09-13">Effective date: September 13, 1982 (9:18 Md. R. 1801)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-03-31"><cite path="|20|56|01|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective March 31, 2003 (30:6 Md. R. 422)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1987-11-02"><cite path="|20|56|01|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective November 2, 1987 (14:22 Md. R. 2340)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1982-10-11">Regulations .07 and .08 adopted effective October 11, 1982 (9:20 Md. R. 1982)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1996-01-15"><cite path="|20|56|01|.07|C.">Regulation .07C</cite> amended effective January 15, 1996 (23:1 Md. R. 36)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1987-11-02"><cite path="|20|56|01|.08|E.">Regulation .08E</cite> amended effective November 2, 1987 (14:22 Md. R. 2340)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-04-21" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective April 21, 2008 (35:8 Md. R. 809)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
