<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Mandatory Construction Contract Clauses</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Application.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In addition to the clauses required by this chapter, each construction contract shall include the clauses required by <cite path="|21.07.01">COMAR 21.07.01</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If clauses covering the same subject matter are required by <cite path="|21.07.01">COMAR 21.07.01</cite> and this chapter, the clauses set forth in this chapter shall be used in each construction contract.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The language of the clauses set forth in this chapter may not be varied.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Changes.</heading>
    <text>Mandatory provision for all construction contracts:</text>
    <include>
      <text>"Changes</text>
      <text>"(1) The procurement officer unilaterally may, at any time, without notice to the sureties, if any, by written order designated or indicated to be a change order, make any change in the work within the general scope of the contract, including but not limited to changes:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>In the specifications (including drawings and designs);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>In the method or manner of performance of the work;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>In the State-furnished facilities, equipment, materials, services, or site; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Directing acceleration in the performance of the work.</text>
      </para>
      <aftertext>"(2) Any other written order or an oral order, including a direction, instruction, interpretation or determination, from the procurement officer that causes any such change, shall be treated as a change order under this clause, provided that the Contractor gives the procurement officer written notice stating the date, circumstances, and source of the order and that the Contractor regards the order as a change order.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>"(3) Except as herein provided, no order, statement, or conduct of the procurement officer shall be treated as a change under this clause or entitle the Contractor to an equitable adjustment hereunder.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>"(4) Subject to paragraph (6)of this clause, if any change under this clause causes an increase or decrease in the Contractor's cost of, or the time required for, the performance of any part of the work under this contract, whether or not changed by any order, an equitable adjustment shall be made and the contract modified in writing accordingly; provided, however, that except for claims based on defective specifications, no claim for any change under paragraph (2) of this clause, shall be allowed for any costs incurred more than 20 days before the Contractor gives written notice as therein required; and provided further, that in the case of defective specifications for which the State is responsible, the equitable adjustment shall include any increased cost reasonably incurred by the Contractor in attempting to comply with such defective specifications.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>"(5) If the Contractor intends to assert a claim for an equitable adjustment under this clause, the Contractor shall, within 30 days after receipt of a written change order under paragraph(1) of this clause, or the furnishing of written notice under paragraph (2) of this clause, submit to the procurement officer a written statement setting forth the general nature and monetary extent of such claim, unless this period is extended by the State. The statement of claim hereunder may be included in the notice under paragraph (2) of this clause.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>"(6) Each contract modification or change order that affects contract price shall be subject to the prior written approval of the procurement officer and other appropriate authorities and to prior certification of the appropriate fiscal authority of fund availability and the effect of the modification or change order on the project budget or the total construction cost. If, according to the certification of the fiscal authority, the contract modification or change order will cause an increase in cost that will exceed budgeted and available funds, the modification or change order may not be made unless sufficient additional funds are made available or the scope of the project is adjusted to permit its completion within the project budget.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>"(7) No claim by the Contractor for an equitable adjustment hereunder shall be allowed if asserted after final payment under this contract."</aftertext>
    </include>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Variations in Estimated Quantities.</heading>
    <text>Mandatory provision for only those construction contracts that contain estimated quantity items:</text>
    <include>
      <text>"Variations in Estimated Quantities</text>
      <text>"Where the quantity of a pay item in this contract is an estimated quantity and where the actual quantity of such pay item varies more than twenty-five percent (25%) above or below the estimated quantity stated in this contract, an equitable adjustment in the contract price shall be made upon demand of either party. The equitable adjustment shall be based upon any increase or decrease in costs due solely to the variation above one hundred twenty-five percent (125%) or below seventy-five percent (75%) of the estimated quantity. If the quantity variation is such as to cause an increase in the time necessary for completion, the procurement officer shall, upon receipt of a written request for an extension of time within ten (10) days from the beginning of the delay, or within a further period of time which may be granted by the procurement officer before the date of final settlement of the contract, ascertain the facts and make the adjustment for extending the completion date as in the procurement officer’s judgment the findings justify."</text>
    </include>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Suspension of Work.</heading>
    <text>Mandatory provision for all construction contracts:</text>
    <include>
      <text>"Suspension of Work</text>
      <text>"(1) The procurement officer unilaterally may order the Contractor in writing to suspend, delay, or interrupt all or any part of the work for a period of time as the procurement officer may determine to be appropriate for the convenience of the State.</text>
      <text>"(2) If the performance of all or any part of the work is for an unreasonable period of time, suspended, delayed, or interrupted by an act of the procurement officer in the administration of this contract, or by the procurement officer’s failure to act within the time specified in this contract (or if no time is specified, within a reasonable time), an adjustment shall be made for any increase in the cost of performance of this contract (excluding profit) necessarily caused by an unreasonable suspension, delay, or interruption and the contract modified in writing accordingly. However, no adjustment shall be made under this clause for any suspension, delay, or interruption to the extent(1) that performance would have been so suspended, delayed, or interrupted by any other cause, including the fault or negligence of the Contractor or (2) for which an equitable adjustment is provided for or excluded under any provision of this contract.</text>
      <text>"(3) No claim under this clause shall be allowed(1) for any costs incurred more than 20 days before the Contractor shall have notified the procurement officer in writing of the act or failure to act involved (but this requirement shall not apply as to a claim resulting from a suspension order), and (2) unless the claim, in an amount stated, is asserted in writing as soon as practicable after the termination of a suspension, delay, or interruption, but not later than the date of final payment under the contract."</text>
    </include>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Differing Site Conditions.</heading>
    <text>Mandatory provision for all construction contracts:</text>
    <include>
      <text>"Differing Site Conditions</text>
      <text>"(1) The Contractor shall promptly, and before such conditions are disturbed, notify the procurement officer in writing of:(1) subsurface or latent physical conditions at the site differing materially from those indicated in this contract, or (2) unknown physical conditions at the site of an unusual nature, differing materially from those ordinarily encountered and generally recognized as inhering in work of the character provided for in this contract. The procurement officer shall promptly investigate the conditions, and if the procurement officer finds that such conditions do materially so differ and cause an increase or decrease in the Contractor’s cost of, or the time required for, performance of any part of the work under this contract, whether or not changed as a result of such conditions, an equitable adjustment shall be made and the contract modified in writing accordingly.</text>
      <text>"(2) No claim of the Contractor under this clause shall be allowed unless the Contractor has given the notice required in paragraph(1) of this clause; provided, however, the time prescribed therefor may be extended by the State.</text>
      <text>"(3) No claim by the Contractor for an equitable adjustment hereunder shall be allowed if asserted after final payment under this contract."</text>
    </include>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05-1</num>
    <heading>Disputes.</heading>
    <text>Mandatory provision for all construction contracts:</text>
    <include>
      <text>"A. This contract is subject to the provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf">State Finance and Procurement Article, Title 15, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and <cite path="|21.10">COMAR 21.10</cite>.</text>
      <text>"B. Except as otherwise provided in this contract or by law, all disputes arising under or as a result of a breach of this contract that are not disposed of by mutual agreement shall be resolved in accordance with this clause.</text>
      <text>"C. As used herein, claim means a written demand or assertion by one of the parties seeking, as a legal right, the payment of money, adjustment or interpretation of contract terms, or other relief, arising under or relating to this contract. A voucher, invoice, or request for payment that is not in dispute when submitted is not a claim under this clause. However, if the submission subsequently is not acted upon in a reasonable time, or is disputed as to liability or amount, it may be converted to a claim for the purpose of this clause.</text>
      <text>"D. Within 30 days after contractor knows or should have known of the basis for a claim relating to this contract, contractor shall file a written notice of claim with the procurement officer.</text>
      <text>"E. Contemporaneously with, or within 90 days after, the filing of a notice of claim, contractor shall submit the written claim to the procurement officer. If contractor so requests, the procurement officer, on conditions the procurement officer deems satisfactory to the unit, may extend the time in which contractor must submit the claim. An example of when a procurement officer may grant an extension includes situations in which the procurement officer finds that a contemporaneous or timely cost quantification following the filing of the notice of claim is impossible or impractical.</text>
      <text>"F. The claim shall set forth all the facts surrounding the controversy. Contractor, at the discretion of the procurement officer, may be afforded an opportunity to be heard and to offer evidence in support of the claim.</text>
      <text>"G. The procurement officer shall mail or deliver written notification of the final decision within:</text>
      <text>"(1) 90 days after the procurement officer receives the claim if the claim is an amount for which the Appeals Board accelerated procedure, set forth in <cite path="21.10.06.12">COMAR 21.10.06.12</cite>, may be used;</text>
      <text>"(2) 180 days after the procurement officer receives the claim for a claim not covered under G(1) of this clause; or</text>
      <text>"(3) A longer period that the procurement officer and contractor agree to in writing.</text>
      <text>"H. The final decision may award a contract claim only for those expenses incurred not more than 30 days before contractor was initially required to have filed the notice of claim.</text>
      <text>"I. The procurement officer's decision is the final action of the agency. If the procurement officer fails to render a final decision within the time required, contractor may deem the failure to be a final decision not to pay the claim.</text>
      <text>"J. If the final decision grants the claim in part and denies the claim in part, the agency shall pay contractor the undisputed amount. Payment of the partial claim is not an admission of liability by the agency and does not preclude the agency from recovering the amount paid if a subsequent determination modifies the final decision.</text>
      <text>"K. Contractor may file a written appeal with the Maryland State Board of Contract Appeals within 30 days of receipt of notice of the decision.</text>
      <text>"L. Pending resolution of a claim, contractor shall proceed diligently with the performance of the contract in accordance with the procurement officer's decision."</text>
    </include>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="21|07|02|.05-2">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05-2</num>
    <heading>Prompt Payment of Subcontractors.</heading>
    <text>Mandatory provisions for all construction contracts:</text>
    <include>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>This contract and all subcontracts issued under this contract at any tier are subject to the provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|15-226">State Finance and Procurement Article, §15-226, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and <cite path="|21.10.08">COMAR 21.10.08</cite>. In §§A—D of this regulation, the terms “undisputed amount”, “prime contractor”, “contractor”, “subcontractor”, and “supplier” have the meanings stated in <cite path="21.10.08.01">COMAR 21.10.08.01</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>A contractor shall promptly pay its subcontractors or suppliers an undisputed amount to which a subcontractor or supplier is entitled for work performed under this contract within 10 days after the contractor receives a progress payment or final payment for work under this contract.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>If a contractor fails to make payment within the period prescribed in <cite path="21|07|02|.05-2|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, a subcontractor or supplier may request a remedy in accordance with <cite path="|21.10.08">COMAR 21.10.08</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>D.</num>
        <text>A contractor shall include in its subcontracts at any tier for work under this contract wording that incorporates the provisions, duties, and obligations of §§A—D of this regulation, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|15-226">State Finance and Procurement Article, §15-226, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and <cite path="|21.10.08">COMAR 21.10.08</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </include>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05-3</num>
    <heading>Retainage.</heading>
    <text>Mandatory provisions for all construction contracts:</text>
    <include>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Sections A—E apply if the contractor has furnished 100 percent payment security and 100 percent performance security.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>The contractor may not retain from any payment due a subcontractor a percent of the payment greater than the percent for retainage specified in the contract.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>A subcontractor at any tier may not retain from any payment due a lower tier subcontractor a percent of the payment greater than the percent of payments retained from the subcontractor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>D.</num>
        <text>A contractor and a subcontractor are not prohibited, by §§A and B, from withholding an amount in addition to retainage if the contractor or subcontractor determines that a subcontractor's performance under the subcontract provides reasonable grounds for withholding the additional amount.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>E.</num>
        <text>The contractor and each subcontractor at any tier shall include, in all of their subcontracts for work called for by this contract, wording that incorporates the provisions of §§B—E.</text>
      </para>
    </include>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Site Investigation.</heading>
    <text>Mandatory provision for all construction contracts:</text>
    <include>
      <text>"Site Investigation</text>
      <text>"The Contractor acknowledges that the Contractor has investigated and satisfied itself as to the conditions affecting the work, including but not restricted to those bearing upon transportation, disposal, handling and storage of materials, availability of labor, water, electric power, roads and uncertainties of weather, river stages, tides or similar physical conditions at the site, the conformation and conditions of the ground, the character of equipment and facilities needed preliminary to and during prosecution of the work. The Contractor further acknowledges that the Contractor has satisfieditself as to the character, quality and quantity of surface and subsurface materials or obstacles to be encountered insofar as this information is reasonably ascertainable from an inspection of the site, including all exploratory work done by the State, as well as from information presented by the drawings and specifications made a part of this contract. Any failure by the Contractor to acquaint itself with the available information may not relieve the Contractor from responsibility for estimating properly the difficulty or cost of successfully performing the work. The State assumes no responsibility for any conclusions or interpretations made by the Contractor on the basis of the information made available by the State."</text>
    </include>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Default, Delay and Time Extensions.</heading>
    <text>Mandatory provision for all construction contracts:</text>
    <include>
      <text>“Termination for Default — Damages for Delay — Time Extensions</text>
      <text>“(1) If the Contractor refuses or fails to prosecute the work, or any separable part thereof, with such diligence as shall insure its completion within the time specified in this contract, or any extension thereof, fails to complete said work within this time, or fails to provide any required annual and renewable bond 30 days prior to expiration of the current bond then in effect, the State may, by written notice to the Contractor, terminate the Contractor’s right to proceed with the work or the part of the work as to which there has been delay. In this event the State may take over the work and prosecute the same to completion, by contract or otherwise, and may take possession of and utilize in completing the work the materials, appliances, and plant as may be on the site of the work and necessary therefor. Whether or not the Contractor’s right to proceed with the work is terminated, the Contractor and its sureties shall be liable for any damage to the State resulting from the Contractor’s refusal or failure to complete the work within the specified time.</text>
      <text>“(2) If fixed and agreed liquidated damages are provided in the contract and if the State so terminates the Contractor's right to proceed, the resulting damage shall consist of such liquidated damages until a reasonable time as may be required for final completion of the work together with any increased costs occasioned the State in completing the work.</text>
      <text>“(3) If fixed and agreed liquidated damages are provided in the contract and if the State does not so terminate the Contractor's right to proceed, the resulting damage shall consist of these liquidated damages until the work is completed or accepted.</text>
      <text>“(4) The Contractor's right to proceed may not be so terminated nor the contractor charged with resulting damages if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The delay in the completion of the work arises from unforeseeable causes beyond the control and without the fault or negligence of the Contractor, including but not restricted to, acts of God, acts of the public enemy, acts of the State in either its sovereign or contractual capacity, acts of another Contractor in the performance of a contract with the State, fires, floods, epidemics, quarantine restrictions, strikes, freight embargoes, unusually severe weather, or delays of subcontractors or suppliers arising from unforeseeable causes beyond the control and without the fault or negligence of either the Contractor or the subcontractors or suppliers; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The Contractor, within 10 days from the beginning of any such delay (unless the procurement officer grants a further period of time before the date of final payment under the contract), notifies the procurement officer in writing of the causes of delay. The procurement officer shall ascertain the facts and the extent of the delay and extend the time for completing the work when, in the procurement officer’s judgement, the findings of fact justify such an extension, and the procurement officer’s findings of fact shall be final and conclusive on the parties, subject only to appeal as provided in the “Disputes” clause of this contract.</text>
      </para>
      <aftertext>“(5) If, after notice of termination of the Contractor's right to proceed under the provisions of this clause, it is determined for any reason that the Contractor was not in default under the provisions of this clause, or that the delay was excusable under the provisions of this clause, the rights and obligations of the parties shall, if the contract contains a clause providing for termination for convenience of the State, be the same as if the notice of termination had been issued pursuant to the clause. If, in the foregoing circumstances, this contract does not contain a clause providing for termination for convenience of the State, the contract shall be equitably adjusted to compensate for the termination and the contract modified accordingly; failure to agree to any such adjustment shall be a dispute concerning a question of fact within the meaning of the clause of this contract entitled “Disputes”.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>“(6) The rights and remedies of the State provided in this clause are in addition to any other rights and remedies provided by law or under this contract.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>“(7) As used in paragraph (4)(a) of this clause, the term “subcontractors or suppliers” means subcontractors or suppliers at any tier.”</aftertext>
    </include>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Liquidated Damages.</heading>
    <text>Mandatory provision for:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>All contracts with certified MBE participation goals, in accordance with <cite path="21.11.03.10|E.">COMAR 21.11.03.10E</cite>; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>All construction contracts unless the agency head determines that the exclusion of the clause is in the best interest of the State:</text>
      <include>
        <text>"Liquidated Damages</text>
        <text>"Time is an essential element of the contract and it is important that the work be vigorously prosecuted until completion.</text>
        <text>"For each day that any work shall remain uncompleted beyond the time(s) specified elsewhere in the contract, the Contractor shall be liable for liquidated damages in the amount(s) provided for in the solicitation, provided, however, that due account shall be taken of any adjustment of specified completion time(s) for completion of work as granted by approved change orders."</text>
      </include>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Termination for Convenience.</heading>
    <text>Mandatory provision for all construction contracts:</text>
    <include>
      <text>"Termination for Convenience of the State</text>
      <text>"(1) The performance of work under this contract may be terminated by the State in accordance with this clause in whole, or from time to time in part, whenever the procurement officer shall determine that such termination is in the best interest of the State. Any such termination shall be effected by delivery to the Contractor of a Notice of Termination specifying the extent to which performance of work under the contract is terminated, and the date upon which such termination becomes effective.</text>
      <text>"(2) After receipt of a Notice of Termination, and except as otherwise directed by the procurement officer, the Contractor shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Stop work under the contract on the date and to the extent specified in the Notice of Termination;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Place no further orders or subcontracts for materials, services or facilities, except as may be necessary for completion of the portion of the work under the contract as is not terminated;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Terminate all orders and subcontracts to the extent that they relate to the performance of work terminated by Notice of Termination;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Assign to the State in the manner, at the times, and to the extent directed by the procurement officer, all of the right, title, and interest of the Contractor under the orders and subcontracts so terminated, in which case the State shall have the right, in its discretion, to settle or pay any or all claims arising out of the termination of such orders and subcontracts;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>Settle all outstanding liabilities and all claims arising out of the termination of orders and subcontracts, with the approval or ratification of the procurement officer, to the extent the procurement officer may require, which approval or ratification shall be final for all the purposes of this clause;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>Transfer title and deliver to the State, in the manner, at the times and to the extent, if any, directed by the procurement officer,(i) the fabricated or unfabricated parts, work in process, completed work, supplies, and other material produced as a part of, or acquired in connection with the performance of, the work terminated by the Notice of Termination, and (ii) the completed or partially completed plans, drawings, information, and other property which, if the contract had been completed, would have been required to be furnished to the State;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>Use the Contractor’s best effort to sell, in the manner, at the times, to the extent, and at the price or prices directed or authorized by the procurement officer, any property of the types referred to in (f) of this clause; provided, however, that the Contractor(i) shall not be required to extend credit to any purchaser, and (ii) may acquire any such property under the conditions prescribed by and at a price or prices approved by the procurement officer; and provided further that the proceeds of any such transfer or disposition shall be applied in reduction of any payments to be made by the State to the Contractor under this contract or shall otherwise be credited to the price or cost of the work covered by this contract or paid in such other manner as the procurement officer may direct;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>Complete performance of such part of the work as may not have been terminated by the Notice of Termination; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(i)</num>
        <text>Take such action as may be necessary, or as the procurement officer may direct, for the protection and preservation of the property related to this contract which is in the possession of the Contractor and in which the State has or may acquire an interest. The Contractor may submit to the procurement officer a list, certified as to quantity and quality, of any or all items of termination inventory not previously disposed of, exclusive of items the disposition of which has been directed or authorized by the procurement officer, and may request the State to remove such items or enter into a storage agreement covering them. Not later than 15 days thereafter, the State shall accept title to such items and remove them or enter into a storage agreement covering the same; provided, that the list submitted shall be subject to verification by the procurement officer upon removal of the items, or if the items are stored, within 45 days from the date of submission of the list, and any necessary adjustment to correct the list as submitted shall be made prior to final settlement.</text>
      </para>
      <aftertext>"(3) After receipt of a Notice of Termination, the Contractor shall submit to the procurement officer the Contractor’s termination claim, in the form and with certification prescribed by the procurement officer. Such claim shall be submitted promptly but in no event later than one year from the effective date of termination, unless one or more extensions in writing are granted by the procurement officer, upon request of the Contractor made in writing within such one year period or authorized extension thereof. However, if the procurement officer determines that the facts justify such action, the procurement officer may receive and act upon any such termination claim at any time after such one year period or any extension thereof. Upon failure of the Contractor to submit its termination claim within the time allowed, the procurement officer may determine, on the basis of information available to the procurement officer, the amount, if any, due to the Contractor by reason of the termination and shall thereupon pay to the Contractor the amount so determined.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>"(4) Subject to the provisions of paragraph (3) of this clause, the contractor and the procurement officer may agree upon the whole or any part of the amount or amounts to be paid to the Contractor by reason of the total or partial termination of work pursuant to this clause, which amount or amounts may include a reasonable allowance for profit on work done; provided, that such agreed amount or amounts, exclusive of settlement costs, shall not exceed the total contract price as reduced by the amount of payments otherwise made and as further reduced by the contract price of work not terminated. The contract shall be amended accordingly, and the Contractor shall be paid the agreed amount. Nothing in paragraph (5) of this clause, prescribing the amount to be paid to the Contractor in the event of failure of the Contractor and the procurement officer to agree upon the whole amount to be paid to the Contractor by reason of the termination of work pursuant to this clause, shall be deemed to limit, restrict, or otherwise determine or affect the amount or amounts which may be agreed upon to be paid to the contractor pursuant to this paragraph.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>"(5) In the event of the failure of the Contractor and the procurement officer to agree, as provided in paragraph (4) of this clause, upon the whole amount to be paid to the Contractor by reason of the termination of work pursuant to this clause, the procurement officer shall pay to the Contractor the amounts determined by the procurement officer as follows, but without duplication of any amounts agreed upon in accordance with paragraph (4) of this clause.</aftertext>
      <para>
        <num proof="done">(a)</num>
        <text>With respect to all contract work performed before the effective date of the Notice of Termination, the total (without duplication of any items) of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>The cost of the work;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(ii)</num>
          <text>The cost of settling and paying claims arising out of the termination of work under subcontracts or orders as provided in paragraph (2)(e) of this clause, exclusive of the amounts paid or payable on account of supplies or materials delivered or services furnished by the subcontractor before the effective date of the Notice of Termination of Work under this contract, which amounts shall be included in the cost on account of which payment is made under subdivision(i) above; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(iii)</num>
          <text>A sum, as profit on subdivision(i) above, determined by the procurement officer, to be fair and reasonable; provided, however, that if it appears that the contractor would have sustained a loss on the entire contract had it been completed, no profit shall be included or allowed under this subdivision (iii) above and an appropriate adjustment shall be made reducing the amount of the settlement to reflect the indicated rate of loss; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The reasonable cost of the preservation and protection of property, incurred pursuant to paragraph (2)(i) of this clause; and any other reasonable cost incidental to termination of work under this contract, including expense incidental to the determination of the amount due to the Contractor as the result of the termination of work under this contract.</text>
      </para>
      <aftertext>The total sum to be paid to the Contractor under paragraph(a) of this clause, shall not exceed the total contract price as reduced by the amount of payments otherwise made and as further reduced by the contract price of work not terminated. Except for normal spoilage, and except to the extent that the State shall have otherwise expressly assumed the risk of loss, there shall be excluded from the amounts payable to the Contractor under paragraph(a) of this clause, the fair value, as determined by the procurement officer, of property which is destroyed, lost, stolen, or damaged so as to become undeliverable to the State, or to a buyer pursuant to paragraph (2)(g) of this clause.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>"(6) Costs claimed, agreed to, or determined pursuant to paragraphs (3), (4), (5), and (9) hereof shall be in accordance with COMAR 21.09 as in effect on the date of this contract.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>"(7) The Contractor shall have the right of appeal, under the clause of this contract entitled "Disputes", from any determination made by the procurement officer under paragraphs (2), (5), or (9) hereof, except that if the Contractor has failed to submit its claim within the time provided in paragraph (3) or (9) hereof, and has failed to request extension of such time, the Contractor shall have no such right of appeal. In any case where the procurement officer has made a determination of the amount due under paragraphs (3), (5), or (9) hereof, the State shall pay to the Contractor the following:(a) if there is no right of appeal hereunder or if no timely appeal has been taken, the amount so determined by the procurement officer, or (b) if an appeal has been taken, the amount finally determined on such appeal.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>"(8) In arriving at the amount due the Contractor under this clause there shall be deducted(a) all unliquidated advance or other payments or account theretofore made to the Contractor, applicable to the terminated portion of this contract, (b) any claim which the State may have against the Contractor in connection with this contract, and (c) the agreed price for, or the proceeds of sale of any materials, supplies, or other things acquired by the Contractor or sold, pursuant to the provisions of this clause, and not otherwise recovered by or credited to the State.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>"(9) If the termination hereunder be partial, the Contractor may file with the procurement officer a claim for an equitable adjustment of the price or prices specified in the contract relating to the continued portion of the contract (the portion not terminated by the Notice of Termination), and such equitable adjustment as may be agreed upon shall be made in such price or prices. Any claim by the Contractor for an equitable adjustment under this clause shall be asserted within ninety (90) days from the effective date of the termination notice, unless an extension is granted in writing by the procurement officer.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>"(10) The State may from time to time, under such terms and conditions as it may prescribe, make partial payments and payments on account against costs incurred by the Contractor in connection with the terminated portion of this contract whenever in the opinion of the procurement officer the aggregate of such payments shall be within the amount to which the Contractor shall be entitled hereunder. If the total of such payments is in excess of the amount finally agreed or determined to be due under this clause, such excess shall be payable by the Contractor to the State upon demand, together with interest computed at the legal rate for the period from the date such excess payment is received by the contractor to the date on which the excess is repaid to the State; provided, however, that no interest shall be charged with respect to any such excess payment attributable to a reduction in the Contractor's claim by reason of retention or other disposition of termination inventory until ten days after the date of the retention or disposition, or a later date as determined by the procurement officer by reason of the circumstances.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>"(11) Unless otherwise provided for in this contract, or by applicable statute, the Contractor shall, from the effective date of termination until the expiration of three years after final settlement under this contract, preserve and make available to the State at all reasonable times at the office of the Contractor but without direct charge to the State, all its books, records, documents and other evidence bearing on the costs and expenses of the contractor under this contract and relating to the work terminated hereunder, or, to the extent approved by the procurement officer, photographs, microphotographs, or other authentic reproductions thereof."</aftertext>
    </include>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Performance and Payment Bonds.</heading>
    <text>Mandatory provision for all construction contracts exceeding $100,000:</text>
    <include>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Performance Bond. The required performance bond shall be in the form specified as follows:</text>
        <text>
          <table class="layout-table">
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="2" data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">PERFORMANCE BOND</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="2"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Principal</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Business Address of Principal</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="2"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Surety</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Obligee</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">a corporation of the State of _____________________</td>
                <td data-text-align="right" data-vertical-align="middle">STATE OF MARYLAND</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">and authorized to do business in the State of Maryland</td>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="2"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Penal Sum of Bond (express in words and figures)<br/>_________________________________________</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Date of Contract<br/>_____________________, 20_____</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Description of Contract<br/><br/>Contract Number: _________________________</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Date Bond Executed<br/>_____________________, 20_____</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="2"/>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
        <text>KNOW ALL BY THESE PRESENTS, That we, the Principal named above and Surety named above, are held and firmly bound unto the Obligee named above in the Penal Sum of this Performance Bond stated above, for the payment of which Penal Sum we bind ourselves, our heirs, executors, administrators, personal representatives, successors, and assigns, jointly and severally, firmly by these presents. However, where Surety is composed of corporations acting as co-sureties, we the co-sureties, bind ourselves, our successors and assigns, in such Penal Sum jointly and severally as well as severally only for the purpose of allowing a joint action or actions against any or all of us, and for all other purposes each co-surety binds itself, jointly and severally with the Principal, for the payment of such sum as appears above its name below, but if no limit of liability is indicated, the limit of such liability shall be the full amount of the Penal Sum.</text>
        <text>WHEREAS, Principal has entered into or will enter into a contract with the State of Maryland, by and through the Administration named above acting for the State of Maryland, which contract is described and dated as shown above, and incorporated herein by reference. The contract and all items incorporated into the contract, together with any and all changes, extensions of time, alterations, modifications, or additions to the contract or to the work to be performed thereunder or to the Plans, Specifications, and Special Provisions, or any of them, or to any other items incorporated into the contract shall hereinafter be referred as "the Contract."</text>
        <text>WHEREAS, it is one of the conditions precedent to the final award of the Contract that these presents be executed.</text>
        <text>NOW, THEREFORE, during the original term of said Contract, during any extensions thereto that may be granted by the Administration, and during the guarantee and warranty period, if any, required under the Contract, unless otherwise stated therein, this Performance Bond shall remain in full force and effect unless and until the following terms and conditions are met:</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>Principal shall well and truly perform the Contract; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>Principal and Surety shall comply with the terms and conditions in this Performance Bond.</text>
        </para>
        <aftertext>Whenever Principal shall be declared by the Administration to be in default under the Contract, the Surety may, within 15 days after notice of default from the Administration, notify the Administration of its election to either promptly proceed to remedy the default or promptly proceed to complete the contract in accordance with and subject to its terms and conditions. In the event the Surety does not elect to exercise either of the above stated options, then the Administration thereupon shall have the remaining contract work completed, Surety to remain liable hereunder for all expenses of completion up to but not exceeding the penal sum stated above.</aftertext>
        <aftertext>The Surety hereby stipulates and agrees that no change, extension of time, alteration or addition to the terms of the Contract or to the work to be performed thereunder or the Specifications accompanying the same shall in any way affect its obligation on this Performance Bond, and it does hereby waive notice of any such change, extension of time, alteration or addition to the terms of the Contract or to the work or to the Specifications.</aftertext>
        <aftertext>This Performance Bond shall be governed by and construed in accordance with the laws of the State of Maryland and any reference herein to Principal or Surety in the singular shall include all entities in the plural who or which are signatories under the Principal or Surety heading below.</aftertext>
        <aftertext>IN WITNESS WHEREOF, Principal and Surety have set their hands and seals to this Performance Bond. If any individual is a signatory under the Principal heading below, then each such individual has signed below on his or her own behalf, has set forth below the name of the firm, if any, in whose name he or she is doing business, and has set forth below his or her title as a sole proprietor. If any partnership or joint venture is a signatory under the Principal heading below, then all members of each such partnership or joint venture have signed below, each member has set forth below the name of the partnership or joint venture, and each member has set forth below his or her title as a general partner, limited partner, or member of joint venture, whichever is applicable. If any corporation is a signatory under the Principal or Surety heading below, then each such corporation has caused the following: the corporation's name to be set forth below, a duly authorized representative of the corporation to affix below the corporation's seal and to attach hereto a notarized corporate resolution of power of attorney authorizing such action, and each such duly authorized representative to sign below and set forth below his or her title as a representative of the corporation. If any individual acts as a witness to any signature below, then each such individual has signed below and has set forth below his or her title as a witness. All of the above has been done as of the Date of Bond shown above.</aftertext>
        <aftertext>
          <table class="layout-table">
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="2"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">In Presence of:</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Individual Principal</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Witness:<br/>__________________________________ as to</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">_____________________________________(SEAL)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="2"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">In Presence of:</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Co-Partnership Principal</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Witness: <br/>______________________________________</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">_____________________________________(SEAL)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(Name of Co-Partnership)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">__________________________________ as to</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">By:__________________________________(SEAL)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">__________________________________ as to</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">_____________________________________(SEAL)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">__________________________________ as to</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">_____________________________________(SEAL)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="2"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Corporate Principal</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">______________________________________</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Attest:</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(Name of Corporation)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <td data-text-align="right" data-vertical-align="middle">AFFIX</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">__________________________________ as to</td>
                <td data-text-align="right" data-vertical-align="middle">By: _____________________________ CORPORATE</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Corporate Secretary</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">President                                                                       SEAL</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="2"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">______________________________________</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(Corporate Surety)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Attest:                                                                (SEAL)</td>
                <td data-text-align="right" data-vertical-align="middle">By: _____________________________ SEAL</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">______________________________________</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Title ______________________________________</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Signature</td>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Bonding Agent's Name: ____________________</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">______________________________________</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(Business Address of Surety)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Agent's Address __________________________</td>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="2"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Approved as to legal form and sufficiency this</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">______ day of _____________ 20 __</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">______________________________________</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Asst. Attorney General</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </aftertext>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Payment Bond. The required payment bond shall be in the form specified as follows:</text>
        <text>
          <table class="layout-table">
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="2" data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">PAYMENT BOND</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="2"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Principal</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Business Address of Principal</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="2"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Surety</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Obligee</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">a corporation of the State of _____________________</td>
                <td data-text-align="right" data-vertical-align="middle">STATE OF MARYLAND</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">and authorized to do business in the State of Maryland</td>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Penal Sum of Bond (express in words and figures)<br/>_________________________________________</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Date of Contract<br/>_____________________, 20_____</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Description of Contract<br/><br/>Contract Number: _________________________</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Date Bond Executed<br/>_____________________, 20_____</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="2"/>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
        <text>KNOW ALL MEN BY THESE PRESENTS, That we, the Principal named above and Surety named above, being authorized to do business in Maryland, and having business address as shown above, are held and firmly bound unto the Obligee named above, for the use and benefit of claimants as hereinafter defined, in the Penal Sum of this Payment Bond stated above, for the payment of which Penal Sum we bind ourselves, our heirs, executors, administrators, personal representatives, successors, and assigns, jointly and severally, firmly by these co-sureties, bind ourselves, our successors and assigns, in such Penal Sum jointly and severally as well as severally only for the purpose of allowing a joint action or actions against any or all of us, and for all other purposes each co-surety binds itself, jointly and severally with the Principal, for the payment of such sum as appears above its name below, but if no limit of liability is indicated, the limit of such liability shall be the full amount of the Penal Sum.</text>
        <text>WHEREAS, Principal has entered into or will enter into a contract with the State, by and through the Administration named above acting for the State of Maryland, which contract is described and dated as shown above, and incorporated herein by reference. The contract and all items incorporated into the contract, together with any and all changes, extensions of time, alterations, modifications, or additions to the contract or to the work to be performed thereunder or to the Plans, Specifications, and Special Provisions, or any of them, or to any other items incorporated into the contract shall hereinafter be referred to as the "Contract".</text>
        <text>WHEREAS, it is one of the conditions precedent to the final award of the Contract that these presents be executed.</text>
        <text>NOW THEREFORE, the condition of this obligation is such that if the Principal shall promptly make payment to all claimants as hereinafter defined, for all labor and materials furnished, supplied and reasonably required for use in the performance of the Contract, then this obligation shall be null and void; otherwise it shall remain in full force and effect, subject to the following conditions:</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>A claimant is defined to be any and all of those persons supplying labor and materials (including lessors of the equipment to the extent of the fair market value thereof) to the Principal or its subcontractors and subcontractors in the prosecution of the work provided for in the Contract, entitled to the protection provided by Section 9-113 of the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="grp">Real Property Article of the Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, as from time to time amended.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>The above named Principal and Surety hereby jointly and severally agree with the Obligee that every claimant as herein defined, who has not been paid in full may, pursuant to and when in compliance with the provisions of the aforesaid Section 9-113, sue on this Bond for the use of such claimant, prosecute the suit to final judgment for such sum or sums as may be justly due claimant and have execution thereon. The Obligee shall not be liable for the payment of any costs or expenses of any such suit.</text>
        </para>
        <aftertext>The Surety hereby stipulates and agrees that no change, extension of time, alteration or addition to the terms of the Contract or to the work to be performed thereunder or the Specifications accompanying the same shall in any way affect its obligation on this Payment Bond, and it does hereby waive notice of any such change, extension of time, alteration or addition to the terms of the Contract or to the work or to the Specifications.</aftertext>
        <aftertext>This Payment Bond shall be governed by and construed in accordance with the laws of the State of Maryland and any reference herein to Principal or Surety in the singular shall include all entities in the plural who or which are signatories under the Principal or Surety heading below.</aftertext>
        <aftertext>IN WITNESS WHEREOF, Principal and Surety have set their hands and seals to this Payment Bond. If any individual is a signatory under the Principal heading below, then each such individual has signed below on his or her own behalf, has set forth below the name of the firm, if any, in whose name he or she is doing business, and has set forth below his or her title as a sole proprietor. If any partnership or joint venture is a signatory under the Principal heading below, then all members of each such partnership or joint venture have signed below, each member has set forth below the name of the partnership or joint venture, and each member has set forth below his or her title as a general partner, limited partner, or member of joint venture, whichever is applicable. If any corporation is a signatory under the Principal or Surety heading below, then each such corporation has caused the following: the corporation's name to be set forth below, a duly authorized representative of the corporation to affix below the corporation's seal and to attach hereto a notarized corporate resolution of power of attorney authorizing such action, and each such duly authorized representative to sign below and set forth below his or her title as a representative of the corporation. If any individual acts as a witness to any signature below, then each such individual has signed below and has set forth below his or her title as a witness. All of the above has been done as of the Date of Bond shown above.</aftertext>
        <aftertext>
          <table class="layout-table">
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="2"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">In Presence of:</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Individual Principal</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Witness:<br/>__________________________________ as to</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">_____________________________________(SEAL)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="2"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">In Presence of:</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Co-Partnership Principal</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Witness:</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">_____________________________________(SEAL)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(Name of Co-Partnership)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">__________________________________ as to</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">By:__________________________________(SEAL)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">__________________________________ as to</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">_____________________________________(SEAL)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">__________________________________ as to</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">_____________________________________(SEAL)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="2"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Corporate Principal</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">______________________________________</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Attest:</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(Name of Corporation)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <td data-text-align="right" data-vertical-align="middle">AFFIX</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">__________________________________</td>
                <td data-text-align="right" data-vertical-align="middle">By: _____________________________ CORPORATE</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Corporate Secretary</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">President                                                                       SEAL</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="2"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">______________________________________</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(Corporate Surety)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Attest:                                                                (SEAL)</td>
                <td data-text-align="right" data-vertical-align="middle">By: _____________________________ SEAL</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">______________________________________</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Title ______________________________________</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Signature</td>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Bonding Agent's Name: ____________________</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">______________________________________</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(Business Address of Surety)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Agent's Address __________________________</td>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="2"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Approved as to legal form and sufficiency this</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">______ day of _____________ 20 __</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">______________________________________</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Asst. Attorney General</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </aftertext>
      </para>
    </include>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Performance and Payment Bonds — Multiyear Annual and Renewable.</heading>
    <text>
      <cite path="21|07|02|attachments|21.07.02.11">For full text of Regulation 21.07.02.11, at end of chapter (FORM AT END OF CHAPTER)</cite>
    </text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Payment of Employee Health Care Expenses.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The following is a mandatory provision for all State-funded construction contracts awarded after a competitive sealed bid:</text>
      <include>
        <text>“Payment of Employee Health Care Expenses</text>
        <text>The contractor and each subcontractor shall pay employee health care expenses as required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf">State Finance and Procurement Article, Title 17, Subtitle 8, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>. If the contractor fails to submit records required under this section within a reasonable period of time, the procurement officer may void the contract.”</text>
      </include>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">State Finance and Procurement Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|12-101">12-101</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|13-216">13-216</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|13-218">13-218</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|13-225">13-225</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|15-226">15-226</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|17-801">17-801</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|17-804">17-804</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1981-07-01">Effective date: July 1, 1981 (8:13 Md. R. II-5)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-05-06"><cite path="|21|07|02|.09">Regulation .09</cite> amended effective May 6, 1985 (12:9 Md. R. 816)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-01-09" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective January 9, 1989 (15:27 Md. R. 3138)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-07-15"><cite path="|21|07|02|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective July 15, 2019 (46:14 Md. R. 623)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-07-15"><cite path="|21|07|02|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective July 15, 2019 (46:14 Md. R. 623)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-07-15"><cite path="|21|07|02|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective January 2, 2017 (43:26 Md. R. 1449); July 15, 2019 (46:14 Md. R. 623)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-07-15"><cite path="|21|07|02|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective July 15, 2019 (46:14 Md. R. 623)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1997-10-06"><cite path="|21|07|02|.05-1">Regulation .05-1</cite> adopted effective October 6, 1997 (24:20 Md. R. 1405)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-01-24"><cite path="|21|07|02|.05-1E">Regulation .05-1E</cite> amended effective January 24, 2000 (27:1 Md. R. 78)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-10-02"><cite path="|21|07|02|.05-2">Regulation .05-2</cite> adopted effective October 2, 2000 (27:19 Md. R. 1730)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-03-03"><cite path="|21|07|02|.05-2">Regulation .05-2</cite> amended effective July 9, 2001 (28:13 Md. R. 1216); September 18, 2023 (50:18 Md. R. 800); March 3, 2025 (52:4 Md. R. 221)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-07-09"><cite path="|21|07|02|.05-3">Regulation .05-3</cite> adopted effective July 9, 2001 (28:13 Md. R. 1216)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-07-15"><cite path="|21|07|02|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective July 15, 2019 (46:14 Md. R. 623)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-06-29"><cite path="|21|07|02|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective July 15, 2019 (46:14 Md. R. 623); June 29, 2020 (47:13 Md. R. 643)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-07-15"><cite path="|21|07|02|.08">Regulation .08</cite> amended effective July 15, 2019 (46:14 Md. R. 623)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-07-15"><cite path="|21|07|02|.09">Regulation .09</cite> amended effective July 15, 2019 (46:14 Md. R. 623)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-03-16"><cite path="|21|07|02|.10">Regulation .10</cite> amended effective May 20, 1996 (23:10 Md. R. 733); February 23, 2009 (36:4 Md. R. 355); March 16, 2015 (42:5 Md. R. 488)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-03-03"><cite path="|21|07|02|.10|A.">Regulation .10A</cite> amended effective March 11, 2019 (46:5 Md. R. 310); March 3, 2025 (52:4 Md. R. 221)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-07-15"><cite path="|21|07|02|.11">Regulation .11</cite> adopted effective July 15, 2019 (46:14 Md. R. 623)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-05-17"><cite path="|21|07|02|.12">Regulation .12</cite> adopted effective May 17, 2021 (48:10 Md. R. 401)</annotation>
  </annotations>
  <attachments>
    <attachment name="21.07.02.11" url="/us/md/exec/comar/initial-attachments/21.07.02.11.pdf"/>
  </attachments>
</container>
