<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Beer Franchises and Local Alcoholic Beverage Reporting</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="14|23|03|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Beer Franchises.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A beer franchise filing is required to be filed with the Executive Director on the form prescribed by the Executive Director. A beer franchise form shall be filed periodically by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A beer nonresident dealer who sells beer to a Maryland wholesaler or county dispensary for distribution in the State;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A Maryland brewery or microbrewery who sells beer to a Maryland wholesaler for distribution in the State; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A Maryland beer wholesaler who self-imports beer for sale in Maryland or subdistributes beer to another Maryland beer wholesaler for sale in Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>When a franchise status changes, a person required to file a beer franchise form under <cite path="14|23|03|.01|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall report the change promptly to the Executive Director by filing a replacement beer franchise form or submitting an explanatory letter, or both.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Reports of Boards of License Commissioners and County Dispensaries.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Report of Retail License Activity.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each retail alcoholic beverages license-issuing authority shall file on a monthly basis a report with the Executive Director, on forms provided or approved by the Executive Director, listing all retail alcoholic beverages license activity, including issuances, cancellations, transfers, revocations, etc., for the report month. Each issuing authority shall file the monthly report with the Executive Director by the 15th of the month following the report month. Reports are due even if there is no activity.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Each alcoholic beverages license-issuing authority shall file annually a complete report of all retail alcoholic beverages licenses renewed for the year on forms provided or approved by the Executive Director. This annual report shall be filed by the 15th of the month following the month the licenses are renewed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Reports filed by the alcoholic beverages license-issuing authority shall include the names of licensees, entity name and trade name, address, and any other information the Executive Director may require. The Executive Director may adopt a Statewide control number to be used by the alcoholic beverages license-issuing authority when filing reports.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Each alcoholic beverages license-issuing authority shall file annually a complete report of all revenue derived for the year preceding from retail alcoholic beverages licenses, on forms provided or approved by the Executive Director. This annual report shall be filed by August 15 annually.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Report of Dispensary Activities. Each county dispensary shall file annually a complete report summarizing all dispensary activities for the year on forms provided or approved by the Executive Director. This report shall be filed by August 15 annually and shall include gross profits, expenses, net profits of the dispensary, and any other information relating to the sale of alcoholic beverages that the Executive Director may require.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Alcoholic Beverages Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gab|1-311">1-311</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gab|5-103">5-103</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gab|5-104">5-104</cite>; <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtg|2-103">Tax-General Article, §2-103</cite>; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-12-26">Effective date:  December 26, 2022 (49:26 Md. R. 1080)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
