<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Insurance Producers — Continuing Education Requirements</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter applies to an individual licensed resident or nonresident insurance producer who seeks to renew a license under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin">Insurance Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, but does not apply to an individual holding the type of license described in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|10-116">Insurance Article, §10-116(b), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The following types of courses are not considered to be continuing education courses and are outside the scope of this chapter:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A course that is designed for preparing an applicant for the examination given to obtain an initial license as an insurance producer; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A course designed to prepare a person for an examination in a kind or subdivision of insurance that the insurance producer seeks to add to the insurance producer's existing license.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Advisory board” means a group of individuals appointed by the Insurance Commissioner pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|10-110">Insurance Article, §10-110, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, to review continuing education courses for insurance producers and to make recommendations regarding the courses.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Bail bondsman services” means any conduct relating to the sale, solicitation, negotiation, or procurement of a bail bond, and includes the posting of a bail bond.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Commissioner" means the Insurance Commissioner of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Course” means a presentation of information delivered in person, in print, electronically, or via teleconference, the successful completion of which is measured by verifiable attendance or by examination, or both.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Course completion date” means the date when a student has submitted all necessary information to the education provider and, when applicable, successfully met the course attendance requirements or passed the final examination, or both.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Course completion roster” means a listing of candidates who have completed a continuing education course, provided in a format determined by the Commissioner, which includes the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The course name, the designated course number, and the course completion date;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The provider’s identification number;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The instructor’s license number, if applicable; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>For each student who completes the course:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The student’s name;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The student’s national producer number or the student’s license number, or both; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The number of hours of continuing education earned by the student.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Course coordinator" means an individual who is responsible for organizing a continuing education course, getting it approved by the Insurance Commissioner, and supervising the administration of the course after its approval.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Expiration date” means the date the license expires as stated on the license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“Hour of continuing education” means 50 minutes of work in a course that has been approved by the Commissioner to receive continuing education credit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>“Instructor” means a subject matter expert, approved by the Commissioner, presenting course activities or information in a course approved by the Commissioner.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>“License” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|10-101">Insurance Article, §10-101(d), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>“Licensed insurance producer” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|1-101">Insurance Article, §1-101(w), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>“National examination” means an examination given as part of a nationally recognized designation awarded by a national insurance organization, including the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Life Underwriter Training Council (LUTC) course curricula;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>American College diploma curriculum for Chartered Life Underwriter (CLU), Chartered Financial Consultant (ChFC), Certified Employee Benefits Specialist (CEBS) or Registered Health Underwriter (RHU);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>College of Financial Planning diploma curriculum for Chartered Financial Planning (CFP) program;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Insurance Institute of America curriculum for:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Program in General Insurance (INS);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Associate in Claims Program (AIC);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Associate in Risk Management Program (ARM);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Associate in Underwriting Program (AIU);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Associate in Loss Control Management Program (ALCM);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Accredited Advisor in Insurance Program (AAI);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Associate Premium Auditing Program (APA); and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Associate in Research and Planning Program (ARP);</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>American Institute for Property and Liability Underwriters Chartered Property and Casualty Underwriter (CPCU) program;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Health Insurance Association of America Program (HIAA);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Academy of Life Underwriting Education Council curriculum for LUEC program; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Certified Insurance Counselor program (CIC).</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>“Preneed insurance contract” has the meaning stated in <cite path="31.05.03.03|B.">COMAR 31.05.03.03B</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>“Provider” means an entity that has been approved by the Commissioner to offer continuing education courses to licensed insurance producers in the State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>“Renewal period” means the period from the issuance or renewal of a license until the day before the expiration date of the license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>“Renewal year” means the 12-month period from January 1 until December 31 in which a license renewal occurs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>“Self-study course” means a course that is not presented in a classroom, is not delivered in person, and does not require interaction with an instructor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>“Successfully complete” means to complete and meet all requirements of an approved course for which a valid certificate of course completion has been issued.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>“Teleconference” means the live exchange of information among several persons who are separately located but linked by audio or video, or both, that provides for opportunities for interactions between student and instructor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>“Viatical settlement broker” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|8-601">Insurance Article, §8-601(k), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|03|02|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>General Continuing Education Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as set forth in this regulation, in order to renew a license, a licensed insurance producer shall successfully complete in each renewal period at least 24 hours of continuing education.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A licensed insurance producer who, as of October 1, 2008, has held a license for 25 or more consecutive years shall successfully complete 8 hours of continuing education in each renewal period in order to renew the license.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A licensed insurance producer shall obtain at least 3 hours of continuing education in Ethics.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A licensed insurance producer shall obtain hours of continuing education in the kind or subdivision of insurance for which they hold a license, as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except for the required hours of continuing education in Ethics, if the licensed insurance producer has only a license for property insurance, casualty insurance, or any of the subdivisions of property or casualty insurance, the licensed insurance producer shall obtain all necessary hours of continuing education in courses designated by the Commissioner as "Property/Casualty" or "PC";</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Except for the required hours of continuing education in Ethics, if the licensed insurance producer has only a license for life insurance, health insurance, or any of the subdivisions of life or health insurance, the licensed insurance producer shall obtain all necessary hours of continuing education in courses designated by the Commissioner as "Life/Health" or "LH";</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the licensed insurance producer has a license for property or casualty, or any subdivision of property or casualty, and life or health, or any subdivision of life or health, then the licensed insurance producer shall complete:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>24 hours of continuing education with a minimum of 6 hours of continuing education in one or more courses designated by the Commissioner as “Property/Casualty” and a minimum of 6 hours of continuing education in one or more courses designated by the Commissioner as “Life/Health”; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For licensed insurance producers who meet the requirements of <cite path="31|03|02|.03|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>,8 hours of continuing education with a minimum of 2 hours of continuing education in one or more courses designated by the Commissioner as “Property/Casualty” and a minimum of 2 hours of continuing education in one or more courses designated by the Commissioner as “Life/Health”;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>In addition to the required hours of continuing education in Ethics, if the licensed insurance producer holds a title insurance producer license only, the licensed insurance producer shall obtain 13 hours of continuing education in one or more courses designated by the Commissioner as “Title” in each renewal period in order to renew the license;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If the licensed insurance producer has a license for title and property or casualty, or any subdivision of property or casualty, then the licensed insurance producer shall complete:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>24 hours of continuing education with a minimum of 6 hours of continuing education in one or more courses designated by the Commissioner as “Title” and a minimum of 6 hours of continuing education in one or more courses designated by the Commissioner as “Property/Casualty”; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For licensed insurance producers who meet the requirements of <cite path="31|03|02|.03|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, 8 hours of continuing education with a minimum of 2 hours of continuing education in one or more courses designated by the Commissioner as “Title” and a minimum of 2 hours of continuing education in one or more courses designated by the Commissioner as “Property/Casualty”;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>If the licensed insurance producer has a license for title and life or health, or any subdivision of life or health, then the licensed insurance producer shall complete:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>24 hours of continuing education with a minimum of 6 hours of continuing education in one or more courses designated by the Commissioner as “Title” and a minimum of 6 hours of continuing education in one or more courses designated by the Commissioner as “Life/Health”; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For licensed insurance producers who meet the requirements of <cite path="31|03|02|.03|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, 8 hours of continuing education with a minimum of 2 hours of continuing education in one or more courses designated by the Commissioner as “Title” and a minimum of 2 hours of continuing education in one or more courses designated by the Commissioner as “Life/Health”;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>If the licensed insurance producer has a license for title, property, or casualty, or any subdivision of property or casualty, and life or health, or any subdivision of life or health, then the licensed insurance producers shall complete:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>24 hours of continuing education with a minimum of 6 hours of continuing education in one or more courses designated by the Commissioner as “Title”, a minimum of 6 hours of continuing education in one or more courses designated by the Commissioner as “Property/Casualty”, and a minimum of 6 hours of continuing education in one or more courses designated by the Commissioner as “Life/Health”; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For licensed insurance producers who meet the requirements of <cite path="31|03|02|.03|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, 8 hours of continuing education with a minimum of 1 hour of continuing education in a course designated by the Commissioner as “Title”, a minimum of 2 hours of continuing education in one or more courses designated by the Commissioner as “Property/Casualty”, and a minimum of 2 hours of continuing education in one or more courses designated by the Commissioner as “Life/Health”; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>A licensed insurance producer who has only a license for life insurance and also is a licensed funeral director or a licensed mortician and sells only life insurance policies or annuity contracts that fund preneed insurance contracts and is not a viatical settlement broker shall complete at least 16 hours of continuing education courses designated by the Commissioner as “Life/Health” in each renewal period in order to renew the license.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Sales of Long-Term Care Insurance.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A licensed insurance producer with authority to sell health insurance who also sells long-term care insurance shall obtain at least 2 hours of continuing education in a course designated "Long Term Care" or "LH-LTC" in order to renew the license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>These hours of continuing education may be considered a part of the required hours of continuing education under §A or B of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A licensed insurance producer who possesses a license to sell property and casualty insurance and who sells flood insurance, homeowners insurance, or commercial property insurance shall obtain at least 2 hours of continuing education that directly relates to flood insurance as part of the required hours of continuing education.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A licensed insurance producer who possesses a license to sell property and casualty insurance and provides bail bondsman services shall obtain at least 4 hours of continuing education that directly relates to bail bond insurance.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Hours of Continuing Education — Passing Scores.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A licensee who receives a passing score on a national examination and has been awarded a nationally recognized designation as listed in Regulation .02B(13)of this chapter may request that the Commissioner apply towards the requirement stated in <cite path="31|03|02|.03|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Up to 24 hours of continuing education credits approved by the Commissioner towards the hours of continuing education required for the next renewal period; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Up to 9 hours of any remaining continuing education hours approved by the Commissioner for the renewal period immediately thereafter.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The licensee shall submit to the Administration the examination results issued by the nationally recognized designation organization that clearly identifies the national designation name, the licensee name, and the date the examination was passed with the renewal application.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The hours of continuing education granted from earning the following designations shall be applied as Life/Health course credits to the continuing education requirement of licensees who hold the Life and/or Health lines of authority:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Life Underwrite Training Council (LUTC);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>American College diploma curriculum for Chartered Life Underwriter (CLU);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Chartered Financial Consultant (ChFC);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Certified Employee Benefits Specialist (CEBS);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Registered Health Underwriter (RHU);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>College of Financial Planning diploma curriculum for Chartered Financial Planning (CFP);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Health Insurance Association of America Program (HIAA); or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Academy of Life Underwriting Education Council curriculum for LUEC program.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The hours of continuing education granted from earning the following designations shall be applied as Property/Casualty course credits to the continuing education requirement of licensees who hold the Property and/or Casualty lines of authority:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Associate in Risk Management Program (ARM);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Accredited Advisor in Insurance Program (AAI); or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>American Institute for Property and Liability Underwriters Chartered Property and Casualty Underwriter (CPCU).</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The hours of continuing education granted from the following designations shall be applied as Life/Health/Property/Casualty course credits to the continuing education requirement of licensees who hold the Life, Health, Property and/or Casualty lines of authority:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Program in General Insurance (INS);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Associate in Claims Program (AIC);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Associate in Underwriting Program (AIU);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Associate Premium Auditing Program (APA);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Associate in Research and Planning Program (ARP); or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Certified Insurance Counselor Program (CIC).</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A licensee may not apply any hours of continuing education granted by the Commissioner pursuant to this section towards the 3 hours of continuing education in Ethics requirement.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Hours of continuing education received for a passing score on a national examination are in addition to any hours of continuing education received for completing a course that is required in order to take the national examination and that has been approved by the Commissioner under this chapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>A course instructor shall earn 1-1/2 hours of continuing education for each approved hour of instruction of an approved course.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>A licensed insurance producer or a course instructor may not earn hours of continuing education:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For attending or instructing a subsequent offering of the same course in the same renewal period; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the same course was taken in two different renewal periods but within 6 months.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Holders of Expired Licenses Who Seek Reinstatement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The holder of an expired license who seeks reinstatement of the license under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|10-116">Insurance Article, §10-116</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland, shall fulfill the continuing education requirements for the renewal period that concluded on the day before the immediately preceding expiration date of the licensed insurance producer’s license in order to qualify for reinstatement.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A licensed insurance producer who does not have sufficient hours of continuing education on the day before the most recent expiration date of the license will have all hours of continuing education earned on or after the expiration date credited toward the requirement for the renewal period that concluded on the day before the license expired.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Nonresident Licensed Insurance Producers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A nonresident licensed insurance producer whose state of residence has a continuing education requirement shall fulfill all of the requirements of the state of residence, and the continuing education requirements of Maryland may not be applicable to the licensed insurance producer.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A nonresident licensed insurance producer whose state of residence does not have a continuing education requirement shall fulfill Maryland continuing education requirements, which may be fulfilled entirely through correspondence courses.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Licensed Insurance Producer Responsibilities.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A licensed insurance producer shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Maintain a record of the certificate of course completion received for 4 years following the date that the course was completed; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Upon request, submit with the renewal application each certificate of course completion needed to fulfill the licensed insurance producer’s hours of continuing education for the renewal period.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|10-126">Insurance Article, §10-126, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the Commissioner may suspend or revoke a license if a licensed insurance producer is found to have knowingly:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Falsified a certificate of course completion; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Submitted a falsified certificate of course completion.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Approval of Courses.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A continuing education course shall be submitted to the Commissioner for approval. The Commissioner may approve a course only if the course imparts substantive and procedural knowledge relating to the insurance field.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner may not approve a course covering any of the following subject areas:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A course in office or business skills, including typing, speed reading, or the use of computers, calculators, or other machines or equipment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A course in office management, client relations, or other matters aimed at improving the operation of the person's business; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A course in salesmanship or product promotion, stress management, time management, psychology, motivation, or written or oral communications.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Except for a self-study course, a course submitted to the Commissioner for approval does not need to require a textbook or an examination in order to receive approval.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner shall assign to each approved course:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The number of hours of continuing education that an individual taking the course may receive for successful completion of the course;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A designated course number that is provided on all certificates of course completion, all correspondence relating to the course, and on all forms filed with the Commissioner relating to the course;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A designation of “Property/Casualty”, “Life/Health”, “Long Term Care”, or “Ethics”; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A course expiration date.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Submission of Courses for Approval.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A provider shall submit to the Commissioner:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A fully completed course approval package consisting of the following forms provided by the Commissioner;</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Request for approval of continuing education course,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Course coordinator information,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Course instructor information and approval form,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Certificate of course completion, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Checklist of items that must accompany the course approval package;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A statement of the educational objectives;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A full and detailed description of the course content including the amount of time allotted to each subject covered by the course on an hour-by-hour basis;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>All course materials, including textbooks, written materials in place of textbooks, course syllabus, policy forms, and any other items used by the instructor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Promotional materials; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A statement of the refund policy, which shall include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Full refund of course fees due to cancellation by the sponsor; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The refund policy when the licensed insurance producer:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Withdraws from the course before commencement, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Fails to complete the course after it has commenced; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>If the Commissioner contracts with a vendor to review continuing education courses, the fee charged by the vendor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The provider shall submit a course approval package to the Commissioner as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A course previously approved in another state or jurisdiction that has adopted the “NAIC Uniform Declaration Regarding Continuing Education Reciprocity Course Approval Guidelines” shall be submitted using the NAIC Uniform Continuing Education Reciprocity Course Filing Form at least 30 days before the first date on which the course is to be taught; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A course that has not been previously approved in a state that has adopted the “NAIC Uniform Declaration Regarding Continuing Education Reciprocity Course Approval Guidelines” shall be submitted at least 45 days before the first date on which the course is to be taught.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner shall notify the provider in writing of a course approval and the period of time of the approval, which shall be from the date of the approval until the second anniversary of the date the course was approved.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A provider may offer only a course approved by the Commissioner.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Submission of Courses for Renewal.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>At least 90 days prior to the expiration of a course’s approval, the Commissioner shall mail to the provider of the approved course a notice that states:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The course name, the course content code, the course number, and the date on which the course approval expires;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The date by which the Commissioner must receive the request to renew; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The fee charged for reviewing continuing education courses submitted for renewal.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In order to renew a course, a provider must comply with the provisions of <cite path="31.03.02.08">COMAR 31.03.02.08</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Providers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A provider shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Comply with this chapter for each of the provider’s approved courses;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Use in all communication with the Commissioner or the Commissioner’s designee the provider identification number assigned by the Commissioner;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Use a course coordinator who meets the qualifications specified in this chapter;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Use an approved instructor; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Notify the Commissioner of the replacement of a course coordinator.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A provider who is an insurer authorized to do business in Maryland may not require an appointed insurance producers to obtain hours of continuing education by attending an approved course that the insurer is providing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Within 10 days of the completion of a course, the provider shall report a course completion roster to the Commissioner or the Commissioner’s designee in an electronic format specified by the Commissioner.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Course Coordinators.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The provider shall ensure that each approved continuing education course has at least one course coordinator who is responsible for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Supervising the administration of the course; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Compliance with this chapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A course coordinator shall possess one or more of the following qualifications:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A minimum of 5 years experience as an actively licensed insurance producer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A minimum of 3 years experience as an administrator of an education program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A degree in education and at least 2 years experience as a licensed insurance producer; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Full-time employment in the insurance education field as a coordinator with at least 6 months experience.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A course coordinator shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Assure compliance with this chapter;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Notify the Commissioner of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Any change in the instructor for an approved course;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The date, time, and location of a course offering and the name of the instructor not less than 14 calendar days in advance of the date that the course offering is scheduled to begin; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The cancellation of a course offering as soon as reasonably possible;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Assure that students are provided with current and accurate information;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Create an accurate record of student attendance and successful course completion for each offering of an approved course;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Supervise and evaluate courses and instructors;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Investigate complaints relating to course offerings and instructors;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Maintain accurate records relating to course offerings, instructors, student attendance, and student course completion for a minimum of 4 years following the date of the course offering; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Within 15 days of the student’s completion of the course, provide each student with a certificate of course completion on a form approved by the Commissioner.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Instructors.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The provider shall ensure that each continuing education course approved by the Commissioner is taught by an instructor who has been approved by the Commissioner as meeting the qualifications specified in this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The provider shall submit to the Commissioner a course instructor information and approval form for each instructor of an approved course.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An instructor shall possess one or more of the following qualifications:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A minimum of 2 years experience in the subject matter being taught;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A degree in the subject matter being taught; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A minimum of 2 years recent experience as a licensed insurance producer and a minimum of 6 months practical experience in the subject matter being taught.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner may not approve as an instructor a licensed insurance producer:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Who has been fined; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Whose license has been suspended or revoked.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An instructor shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Comply with this chapter;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide students with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Current and accurate information on the subject matter of the course; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A course syllabus that shall contain at least the following information:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Course title and designated course number assigned by the Commissioner;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Times and dates of the course offering;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Names, addresses, and telephone numbers of each course coordinator; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Detailed outline of the subject matter of the course.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner may revoke the approval of any course that is not taught by an approved instructor.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|03|02|.13">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Advertising of Approved Courses.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="31|03|02|.13|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>, a provider may not advertise or distribute promotional materials unless the course has been approved by the Commissioner.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Advertisements and promotional materials may not be deceptive or misleading and shall, at a minimum, clearly identify the number of hours of continuing education for which a course has been approved and the fee for taking the course.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A provider of an approved course who advertises or promotes a course that has not been approved or a course that is not eligible for approval shall prominently state that no hours of continuing education can be earned by taking the course.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A provider may request, in writing, permission to advertise a course before approval is obtained from the Commissioner by submitting:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A letter specifically requesting permission to advertise the course before approval is obtained; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>With the course approval package, all advertisements or promotional materials that will be used before approval and which shall prominently include the words "approval from the Insurance Administration pending".</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner shall issue the provider a written response either granting or denying the provider’s request. The provider may not advertise the course until the Commissioner has granted the request.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Prohibited Practices.</heading>
    <text>The following practices by a provider, course coordinator, or instructor are prohibited:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Offering or teaching a course that is not approved or that is not in substantial conformity with the course completion package submitted to and approved by the Commissioner;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Promoting a particular insurance agency or insurance company or products of the agency or company; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Requiring, as a condition of receiving a certificate of course completion, that students participate in other programs or services offered by the provider, course coordinator, or instructor.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Powers of the Commissioner.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner, the Commissioner’s designee, or the members of an advisory board may audit all course offerings with or without notice to the provider, course coordinator, or instructor of the course.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner may suspend or revoke the approval of a course for any of the following violations of this chapter:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Failure of the instructor to follow the approved course content;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Failure to use a course coordinator meeting the qualifications specified in this chapter;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Failure to use an approved instructor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Failure to notify the Commissioner of the date, time, location, and instructor of a course offering in accordance with <cite path="|31|03|02|.11|C.|(2)|(b)">Regulation .11C(2)(b) of this chapter</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Failure to report a course completion roster in accordance with <cite path="|31|03|02|.10|C.">Regulation .10C of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner may suspend or revoke all approved courses of a particular provider for a violation of this chapter or refuse to approve a course submitted by a specific provider if the Commissioner determines that a past course offering by that provider was not in compliance with this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner may suspend or revoke the approval of any instructor, course coordinator, or course provider who fails to comply with this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|03|02|.16">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Waiver of the Continuing Education Requirement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Subject to <cite path="31|03|02|.16|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, the continuing education requirements may be waived for a licensed insurance producer who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Submits a written request for a waiver; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is determined by the Commissioner, in the Commissioner's discretion, to warrant the waiver.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A waiver request shall be accompanied by supporting documentation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.17</num>
    <heading>Advisory Boards.</heading>
    <text>The Commissioner may appoint a life and health advisory board and a property and casualty advisory board as provided by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|10-110">Insurance Article, §10-110(b) </cite>and (c), Annotated Code of Maryland, for the purpose of reviewing the course approval packages submitted to the Commissioner and making recommendations on approval or disapproval of courses.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Insurance Article, , §§2-109, 10-115, and 10-116, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1987-11-16">Effective date: November 16, 1987 (14:23 Md. R. 2424)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1997-11-17">Regulations <cite path="|31|03|02|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|31|03|02|.12">.12</cite> repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|31|03|02|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|31|03|02|.17">.17</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective July 1, 1997 (24:17 Md. R. 1209); adopted permanently effective November 17, 1997 (24:23 Md. R. 1609)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-09-07" discontinuity="true">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|09.30.74">COMAR 09.30.74</cite> to <cite path="|31.03.02">COMAR 31.03.02</cite> effective September 7, 1998 (25:18 Md. R. 1439)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-08-20"><cite path="|31|03|02|.03|J.">Regulation .03J</cite> adopted effective August 20, 2001 (28:16 Md. R. 1484)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-08-20"><cite path="|31|03|02|.16">Regulation .16</cite> amended effective August 20, 2001 (28:16 Md. R. 1484)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-04-10" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective April 10, 2006 (33:7 Md. R. 675)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-02-01" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective February 1, 2015 (41:20 Md. R. 1114)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-11-06"><cite path="|31|03|02|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective November 6, 2017 (44:22 Md. R. 1038)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-11-06"><cite path="|31|03|02|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective November 6, 2017 (44:22 Md. R. 1038)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-02-01"><cite path="|31|03|02|.03|D.">Regulation .03D</cite> amended effective January 1, 2020 (46:19 Md. R. 816); ); February 1, 2023 (49:15 Md. R. 739)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-10-01"><cite path="|31|03|02|.03|F.">Regulation .03F</cite> amended effective October 1, 2023 (50:13 Md. R. 514)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-12-14"><cite path="|31|03|02|.03|H.">Regulation .03H</cite> amended effective December 14, 2020 (47:25 Md. R. 1067)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-01-27"><cite path="|31|03|02|.10|C.">Regulation .10C</cite> amended effective January 27, 2020 (47:2 Md. R. 62)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
