<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>13</num>
  <heading>Producer Registers and Documentation of Appointments</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definition.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following term has the meaning indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Term Defined. "Producer register" means a register of appointed insurance producers who are authorized to sell, solicit, or negotiate contracts of insurance on behalf of an insurer.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Producer Register.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Required. An insurer authorized to transact the business of insurance in the State shall maintain a producer register.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Form and Content.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within 30 days after appointing an insurance producer, an insurer shall add the following information to the insurer's producer register:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Maryland license number of the insurance producer;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the insurance producer is an individual, the first and last name and residence or business address of the individual;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If the insurance producer is a business entity:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The tax ID number of the insurance producer;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The name of the business entity; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The address of the business entity; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The date that the insurance producer was appointed.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Within 30 days after the effective date of an insurer's termination of an appointment of an insurance producer, the insurer shall add the following information to the insurer's producer register:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The effective date of the termination of the appointment; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An identifier that indicates if the termination was wholly or partly the result of a belief that the insurance producer engaged or is engaging in any of the activities set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|10-126">Insurance Article, §10-126, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Each item that an insurer is required to include in its producer register under §B(1) and (2) of this regulation shall be entered:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>On a separate line or space; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the producer register is maintained electronically, in a separate searchable field.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If an insurer maintains its producer register electronically, the insurer shall maintain the producer register in a manner that allows the information in the producer register to be retrieved within 10 working days after a request from the Insurance Commissioner.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Updating and Maintaining Producer Register.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>At least once every 31 days, an insurer shall determine whether the license of any insurance producer who currently is appointed by the insurer has been suspended or revoked.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>After determining that the license of an insurance producer who currently is appointed by an insurer has been suspended or revoked, the insurer shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within 5 business days after making the determination, terminate the appointment of the insurance producer; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Within 30 days after the effective date of the termination, update the insurer's producer register to reflect the termination of the appointment in accordance with <cite path="|31|03|13|.02|B.|(2)">Regulation .02B(2) of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An insurer shall maintain its producer register for as long as the insurer acts as an insurer in the State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If an insurer ceases to act as an insurer in the State due to a sale, merger, consolidation, or other transaction:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The insurer shall transfer its producer register to the successor insurer that acquires the business of the insurer; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The successor insurer shall maintain the producer register for as long as the successor insurer acts as an insurer in the State.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Documentation of Appointment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Within 30 days after appointing an insurance producer, an insurer shall provide the insurance producer with written documentation of the appointment that contains, at a minimum:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The name of the insurer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The date that the documentation was provided to the insurance producer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Maryland license number of the insurance producer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the insurance producer is an individual, the first and last name of the individual;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If the insurance producer is a business entity, the name of the business entity;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The date that the insurance producer was appointed; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The following statement, prominently displayed on the written documentation: "This document shall be retained while your appointment is in effect and for at least 5 years after the termination of your appointment."</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An insurer may provide the written documentation to an insurance producer electronically if the insurance producer agrees to receive the written documentation electronically.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|03|13|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Maintenance of Information by Insurance Producer.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A licensed insurance producer that has received written documentation of an appointment from an insurer shall maintain:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The documentation of the insurer's appointment that is provided by the insurer under <cite path="|31|03|13|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A list of insurers that have appointed the insurance producer.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If an insurance producer maintains the information required to be maintained by <cite path="31|03|13|.05|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> electronically, the insurance producer shall maintain the information in a manner that allows the information to be retrieved within 10 working days after a request from the Insurance Commissioner.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>With respect to a particular appointment, the insurance producer shall maintain the information required to be maintained by <cite path="31|03|13|.05|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>While the appointment is in effect; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For at least 5 years after the termination of the appointment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Producer Action on Behalf of Insurer.</heading>
    <text>On appointment by an insurer, a licensed producer that has written documentation of the appointment pursuant to <cite path="|31|03|13|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite> may act on behalf of the insurer before the insurer adds the producer to its register.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Insurance Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|2-109">2-109</cite>(a)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|1">1</cite>), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|10-103">10-103</cite>(c), and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|10-118">10-118</cite>(j), Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-06-21">Regulations <cite path="|31|03|13|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|31|03|13|.05">.05</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective January 1, 2004 (31:1 Md. R. 29); adopted permanently effective June 21, 2004 (31:12 Md. R. 915)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-02-21"><cite path="|31|03|13|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective February 26, 2007 (34:4 Md. R. 403); February 25, 2019 (46:4 Md. R. 191); February 21, 2022 (49:4 Md. R. 302)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-02-21"><cite path="|31|03|13|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite> amended effective February 25, 2019 (46:4 Md. R. 191); February 21, 2022 (49:4 Md. R. 302)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-04-10"><cite path="|31|03|13|.05|A.">Regulation .05A</cite> amended effective April 10, 2006 (33:7 Md. R. 675)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-08-14"><cite path="|31|03|13|.06">Regulation .06</cite> adopted effective August 14, 2006 (33:16 Md. R. 1366)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
