<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>09</num>
  <heading>Program Requirements</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|16|09|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Schedule of Daily Activities for All Children.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The operator shall prepare, post, and follow a written schedule of daily activities and offer activities that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Promote the sound emotional, social, intellectual, and physical growth of each child;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Are appropriate to the age, needs, and capabilities of the child based on the current recommendations of the American Academy of Pediatrics, such as short periods of tummy time, under adult supervision, while awake for a child under 12 months old;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Include opportunities for individual and group participation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Include a balance between self-selected and staff-directed activities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Include a balance between active and quiet periods;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Include periods of rest appropriate to the age, needs, and activities of the child; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Include outdoor play in the morning and afternoon except that outdoor play need not be included:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>When the weather is inclement; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>In a before-school program.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A before-school and after-school program schedule of activities shall take into consideration that the child has attended an instructional program during regular school hours.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Screen Time Activities.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Definitions. In this section, the following terms have the meanings indicated:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Interactive technology" means educational and age-appropriate technology, including programs, applications (apps), noncommercial television programming, videos, streaming media, and ebooks, that is designed to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Facilitate active and creative use of technology; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Encourage social engagement with other children and adults.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Passive technology" means noninteractive television, videos, and streaming media.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Limited use of appropriate interactive technology may support, but may not replace, creative play, physical activity, hands-on exploration, outdoor experiences, social interactions, and other developmentally appropriate learning activities for children 2 years old or older.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Viewing Restrictions. Except as set forth in <cite path="13A|16|09|.01|C.|(4)">§C(4) of this regulation</cite>, a child in attendance who is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Younger than 2 years old may not be permitted to view any passive technology; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>2 years old or older may not be permitted to view more than 30 minutes of age-appropriate, educational passive technology per week.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Exceptions.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An occasional exception to the weekly passive technology viewing limit set forth in <cite path="13A|16|09|.01|C.|(3)">§C(3) of this regulation</cite> may be made for a special event or project, including a holiday or birthday celebration, or for educational content that is related to the center's curriculum.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If an exception to the weekly passive technology viewing limit is made, a written record of the exception shall be made and retained on file that documents the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Nature and duration of the programming viewed; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Reason for the exception.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>No child may be permitted to view any:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Passive or interactive technology during a meal or a snack; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Media with brand placement or advertising for unhealthy or sugary food or beverages.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The operator shall give the parent of each enrolled child a written screen time policy that addresses the use of passive and interactive technology during child care hours.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Activity Plans for Infants and Toddlers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An operator shall assign one staff member primary responsibility for each infant or toddler in care during each staff shift.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Upon enrollment of an infant or toddler, the operator shall arrange for the director or senior staff, in consultation with the parent of the child, to prepare a written individualized activity plan for the child that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Addresses the child's normal pattern of activities, sleeping, and eating;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is consistent with the child's needs and capabilities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Identifies the staff member who is assigned primary responsibility for the care of the child during each staff shift;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Ensures that the child is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Held, played with, and talked to;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Except when sleeping, given opportunities to sit, crawl, toddle, or walk outside the infant's crib or playpen;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Except in inclement weather, taken outdoors daily; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Diapered as needed and in accordance with the approved diapering procedure.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>For an infant or toddler, the written activity plan required at the time of the child's admission to care shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Posted for reference in the space used by the child's group;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Implemented by each staff member having responsibility for care of the child;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Modified in consultation with the child's parent as necessitated by the child's developmental needs; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Reevaluated at least every 3 months.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Upon the request of a parent of a child in care, the operator shall assist the parent with scheduling a time and convenient location for the local lead agency responsible for administering the Maryland Infants and Toddlers Program to provide the appropriate screening for the child.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Activity Materials, Equipment, and Furnishings.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>For indoor and outdoor activities, an operator shall provide to each group of children in care a sufficient quantity and variety of activity materials, equipment, and furnishings according to the numbers, ages, and developmental needs of the children.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Activity materials and equipment shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provided for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Vigorous play;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Creative and dramatic play;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Socialization;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Manipulation, including construction materials;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Exploration of art, music, language arts, and science; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Individual pursuits;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Appropriate to each child's individual development of cognitive, social, emotional, and fine and gross motor skills;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Easily accessible to each child for whose use they are intended; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>In good repair, clean, nontoxic, and free from hazards including lead paint.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In reviewing materials and equipment in before-school and after-school programs, the office shall take into consideration that the child has attended an instructional program during regular school hours.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Furnishings used by a child shall be scaled in proportion to the child's size.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The operator shall provide multipurpose tables and chairs for children who are 2 years old or older.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|16|09|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Rest Furnishings.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>There shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A suitable cot or mat for each child 12 months old to 5 years old present in the center for more than 4 hours, and for children 5 years old or older who regularly take rest periods in the center;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A suitable bed for each child who is 12 months old or older and who is present in the center during those hours which are usual nighttime sleep hours for that child;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An adequate supply of clean bedding provided for each child who takes rest periods at the center; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A crib with a snugly fitting mattress, moisture-proof mattress covering, and tight fitting sheet for each child in the center who is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Younger than 12 months old; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An infant 12 months old or older or a toddler, if the child's parent requests a crib.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>When in use, all cots, mats, and beds shall be appropriately spaced to facilitate safe movement and evacuation of staff and children.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Each crib shall meet the current standards of the U.S. Consumer Product Safety Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Stackable cribs may not be used.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Each crib in use shall be placed so that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>It presents at least one long side without a wall, plexiglass panel, or other solid barrier;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Unless separated from an adjacent crib by a solid barrier, it does not rest against the other crib; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>There is a space of at least 3 feet if placed side-to-side and 18 inches if placed end-to-end between two adjacent cribs that are not separated by a solid barrier.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Each sleep surface used for a child under 12 months old shall be firm, flat, and non-inclined, unless the need for an incline is specified in writing by the child’s physician or other licensed health care provider.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Soft bedding items, including but not limited to pillows, quilts, comforters, and crib bumpers, may not be used as rest furnishings for a child using a crib.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>A child under 12 months who falls asleep in a furnishing other than a crib shall be moved immediately to an approved sleeping arrangement specified at <cite path="13A|16|09|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Infant-Toddler Equipment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A sufficient number of strollers or carriages with appropriate restraints shall be available to accommodate all non-walking infants present in care.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The use of walkers is prohibited.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The center shall have furnishings that allow the safe and easy feeding of children younger than 2 years old, including but not limited to high chairs, toddler tables, and chairs for staff members to use while holding infants for feeding.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If high chairs are used, each high chair shall be equipped with age-appropriate restraints.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Storage.</heading>
    <text>There shall be appropriate storage for:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Materials and equipment;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Mats, cots, beds, and bedding;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Portable equipment intended for outdoor use;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Each child's clothing and possessions in an individual space; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Materials, equipment, furnishings, and supplies being held in reserve.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Education Article,  §§9.5-115, 9.5-401, 9.5-404—9.5-411, and 9.5-413—9.5-418; <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-333">General Provisions Article, §4-333</cite>;<br/><cite doc="Md. Code" path="ghu|1-202">Human Services Article, §1-202</cite>; Annotated Code of Maryland<br/>Agency Note: Federal Statutory Reference — Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (42 U.S.C. §12101 et seq.);<br/>Pro-Children Act of 1994 (20 U.S.C. §6081 et seq.);<br/>Child Care Development Block Grant (45 CFR Parts 98 and 99 and 42 U.S.C. 9858 et seq.);<br/>Social Security Act §418 (42 U.S.C. 618)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-10-20">Effective date: October 20, 2008 (35:21 Md. R. 1826)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-04-29"><cite path="|13A|16|09|.01|A.">Regulation .01A</cite> amended effective April 29, 2024 (51:8 Md. R. 367)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-07-20"><cite path="|13A|16|09|.01|C.">Regulation .01C</cite> adopted effective July 20, 2015 (42:14 Md. R. 883)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-03-17"><cite path="|13A|16|09|.02|D.">Regulation .02D</cite> adopted effective March 17, 2025 (52:5 Md. R. 238)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-04-29"><cite path="|13A|16|09|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective April 29, 2024 (51:8 Md. R. 367)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-01-13"><cite path="|13A|16|09|.04|G.">Regulation .04G</cite> adopted effective January 13, 2020 (47:1 Md. R. 14)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
