<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>10</num>
  <heading>Safety</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|16|10|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Emergency Safety Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Emergency and Disaster Plan.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At least one center employee shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Complete emergency preparedness training that is approved by the office; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>As part of the approved emergency preparedness training, prepare a written emergency and disaster plan for the center.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The operator shall maintain the emergency and disaster plan prepared in accordance with <cite path="13A|16|10|.01|A.|(1)|(b)">§A(1)(b) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The emergency and disaster plan shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Establish procedures for:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Evacuating the center, including an evacuation route;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Relocating staff and children to a designated safe site;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Sheltering in place in the event that evacuation is not feasible;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Notifying parents of children in care; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Addressing the individual needs of children, including children with special needs;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Contain:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The name of, and contact information for the local emergency operations center;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Assignment of staff responsibilities during an emergency or disaster;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A list of local emergency services numbers; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>The radio station call sign and frequency for the local Emergency Alert System;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Be practiced by staff and children at least:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Once per month for fire evacuation; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Twice per year for other emergency and disaster situations; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Be updated at least annually.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A copy of the emergency escape route floor plan shall be posted in each area and room in the center.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Each employee shall be oriented to the contents of the written emergency and disaster plan required at <cite path="13A|16|10|.01|A.|(2)">§A(2) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>In the event of a declared emergency, the operator shall be prepared to respond as directed by the local emergency management agency through sources of public information.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>During an emergency evacuation or practice, a staff member shall take attendance records out of the center and determine the presence of each child currently in attendance.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the child care center is included within a comprehensive emergency and disaster plan, the center operator shall ensure that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The comprehensive plan contents meet all emergency and disaster plan requirements set forth at §A(2)(a) and (b) of this regulation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A copy of the comprehensive plan is available to all staff.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An operator shall post, immediately accessible to each telephone in the center, a notice stating the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>9-1-1 emergency telephone number to summon fire, police, and rescue services;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Center's name, address, and telephone number;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Telephone number of the protective services unit of the local department of social services;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Telephone number of a poison control center;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Name and telephone number of the local health department or a physician to consult about issues regarding health and illnesses;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Name and telephone number of the available adult as required by COMAR 13A.16.08.02D(3); and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Telephone number of the office.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|16|10|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>First Aid and CPR.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>At all times, including during an off-site activity, at least one child care teacher or the director shall be present who holds a current certificate indicating successful completion of approved:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Basic first aid training through the American Red Cross, or a program with equivalent standards, which is appropriate to all child age groups for which the center is approved; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Cardiopulmonary resuscitation (CPR) training through the American Heart Association, or a program with equivalent standards, which is appropriate to all child age groups for which the center is approved.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A center with an approved capacity of more than 20 children shall have in attendance, in a ratio of at least one staff member for every 20 children present, staff members who are currently certified in approved first aid and CPR as specified at <cite path="13A|16|10|.02|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Whenever a child in care is being transported under center auspices to or from the center, there shall be at least one adult present in the vehicle who is currently certified in approved CPR and first aid. This requirement may be met by the driver of the vehicle if the driver is an employee of the center.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text><cite path="13A|16|10|.02|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> does not apply if the driver of the vehicle is a parent of a child in care who is designated by the center operator to assist in transporting children in care.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An operator shall maintain first aid supplies as required by the office, conveniently accessible for each group of children at the center and at an off-site activity.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Safe Use of Materials and Equipment.</heading>
    <text>The operator shall ensure that furnishings, activity materials, and equipment, whether intended for indoor use or outdoor use, are used:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In a safe and appropriate manner by each employee and each child in attendance; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>As applicable, in accordance with manufacturer instructions or recommendations.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Potentially Hazardous Items.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An operator shall store all potentially harmful items, including but not limited to the items described in §§B—F of this regulation, in locations which are inaccessible to children in care.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Petroleum and flammable products shall be stored in an approved manner.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Cleaning and sanitizing agents and poisonous products shall be stored apart from food and beverages.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Containers of poisonous products may not be kept on the premises unless they are labeled clearly as to nature, content, and approved purposes.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A pesticide may be used only if it is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Approved by the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Used according to the manufacturer's instructions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Used only when children are not in care; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Stored apart from food, beverages, and cleaning agents.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Alcohol, tobacco, cannabis, cannabis edibles, and smoking and vaping paraphernalia and byproducts shall be stored in an approved manner.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Each electrical socket that is accessible to children in care shall be plugged or capped as required by the applicable fire code.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Except in a small center located in a residence, a firearm may not be kept on the premises.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>In a small center located in a residence where a firearm is maintained, the firearm shall be kept:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In a location not used by children in care; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Unloaded and partially disassembled in a locked container with ammunition stored in its own separate locked container.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Window Coverings. A window covering installed:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Before October 1, 2010, shall not have unsecured cords, beads, ropes, or strings that are accessible to a child in care; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>On or after October 1, 2010, shall be cordless.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Rest Time Safety.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Unless specified otherwise in writing by the child’s physician, or other licensed health care provider, a child who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Cannot roll over without assistance shall be placed for sleep on the child's back; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is younger than 12 months old but can roll over unassisted shall be placed for sleep on the child's back, but may be allowed to adopt whatever position the child prefers for sleep.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Unless the need for a positioning device is specified in writing by the child’s physician, or other licensed health care provider, a restricting device of any type, including swaddling, may not be applied to a resting child.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Weighted rest items, including but not limited to blankets, sleepers, and swaddles, may not be used for a child under 12 months old.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Transportation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Unless being transported in a licensed school bus or contract motor coach, each child who is transported in a vehicle while in care shall be separately secured in a child car seat or seat belt which is appropriate for the child's age and weight, as specified by Maryland law.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A vehicle used to transport a child in care shall comply with all applicable State and federal safety requirements.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Education Article, §§9.5-401, 9.5-404—9.5-411 and 9.5-413—9.5-418; <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-333">General Provisions Article, §4-333</cite>; <br/><cite doc="Md. Code" path="ghu|1-202">Human Services Article, §1-202</cite>; Annotated Code of Maryland<br/>Agency Note: Federal Statutory Reference — Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (42 U.S.C. §12101 et seq.);<br/>Pro-Children Act of 1994 (20 U.S.C. §6081 et seq.);<br/>Child Care Development Block Grant (45 CFR Parts 98 and 99 and 42 U.S.C. 9858 et seq.);<br/>Social Security Act §418 (42 U.S.C. 618)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-10-20">Effective date: October 20, 2008 (35:21 Md. R. 1826)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-04-19"><cite path="|13A|16|10|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective April 19, 2010 (37:8 Md. R. 618)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-03-21"><cite path="|13A|16|10|.01|A.">Regulation .01A</cite> amended effective March 21, 2011 (38:6 Md. R. 396)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-04-19"><cite path="|13A|16|10|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective April 19, 2010 (37:8 Md. R. 618)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-01-13"><cite path="|13A|16|10|.02|C.">Regulation .02C</cite> amended effective January 13, 2020 (47:1 Md. R. 14)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-02-05"><cite path="|13A|16|10|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective August 31, 2023 (50:20 Md. R. 885); amended permanently effective February 5, 2024 (50:2 Md. R. 76)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-03-21"><cite path="|13A|16|10|.04|I.">Regulation .04I</cite> adopted effective March 21, 2011 (38:6 Md. R. 396)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-04-29"><cite path="|13A|16|10|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective April 29, 2024 (51:8 Md. R. 367)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-01-13"><cite path="|13A|16|10|.05|B.">Regulation .05B</cite> amended effective January 13, 2020 (47:1 Md. R. 14)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
