<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>04</num>
  <heading>Applications Pursuant to the Public Utilities Article</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Financial Condition Defined.</heading>
    <text>Whenever a corporation subject to the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu">Public Utilities Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, is required or called upon to disclose its financial condition, whether under this subtitle or otherwise, the information shall be given, as far as practicable, in appropriate schedules, which shall show the following:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Amount and classes of stock authorized;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Amount and classes of stock issued;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Terms of preference of all preferred stock;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Brief description of each mortgage upon any property of the corporation, giving the date of execution, name of the trustee, amount of indebtedness authorized to be secured by the mortgage, amount of indebtedness actually secured, and brief description of the mortgaged property or collateral;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Number and amount of bonds authorized and issued under each mortgage, describing each class separately, giving date of issue, par value, rate of interest, date of maturity, and how secured;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Other indebtedness of all kinds, giving them by classes and describing security, if any;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Amount of interest paid during the previous fiscal year upon each species of indebtedness and the rate of interest, and if different rates were paid, the amount paid at each rate;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Amount of dividends paid upon each class of stock during the previous fiscal year and the rate;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Detailed statement of earnings and expenditures for the previous fiscal year and balance sheet showing the condition at the close of the year.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|07|04|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Applications for Authority to Issue Stocks, Bonds, Notes and Other Evidences of Indebtedness.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Application. Except for an application to issue rate stabilization bonds under <cite path="|20|07|04|.11">Regulation .11 of this chapter</cite>, an application made to the Commission by a public service company for authority under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|6-102">Public Utilities Article, §6-102, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, to issue any stock, bonds, notes, or other evidences of indebtedness shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The amount and terms of the proposed issue, the purposes for which the proceeds are to be used, and the nature of the security, if any.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the purpose is the acquisition of property, a general description of the property, from whom it is to be acquired, and the terms of the contract for the acquisition, if any has been made. Names of the owners of property to be acquired for rights of way need not be set out, but a general description of the proposed route will be sufficient.</text>
        <text>
          <em>Agency Note: The description of property should include the number, dimensions, type, and location of each class of items mentioned in the petition. For example, the item of "land" should state the area and the location of the property; expenditures for "building construction" should state dimensions of buildings, so that cubical contents may be ascertained, and also give the type of construction, including foundations; a description of plant, machinery, equipment, etc., should be given, including the number and size of each unit, its type, and similar information. It should also be stated whether the amount proposed to be expended on each item covers the entire cost thereof or whether a portion of the cost has been submitted in a prior statement to the Commission, or may be included in some future statement of expenditure, for which security may be proposed to be issued, and authority asked.</em>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the purpose is for the construction, completion, extension, or improvement of facilities, the existing facilities shall be set forth as well as those proposed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the purpose is the improvement or maintenance of service, the existing service shall be set forth as well as any improvements or betterments proposed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If the purpose is the refunding of obligations, the obligations shall be described fully, showing character, amount, date of issue, date of maturity, and all other material facts concerning them.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The financial condition of the applicant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>If the application is for the issue of bonds to be secured by an existing mortgage, the amount of the bonds, if any, already issued under the mortgage, and the amount and application made of the proceeds of them.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>If the proceeds are to be used for construction, completion, extension, or improvement purposes, the affidavit of a competent person shall be annexed, showing the estimated cost in reasonable detail.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>In applications for the issue of stock, the application shall state that no franchise or right is capitalized, directly or indirectly, except as authorized by the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu">Public Utilities Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>. If it is proposed to capitalize any franchise or right as therein authorized, there shall be filed with the application a verified copy of the franchise, and an affidavit of the proper officer of the State, county, or municipality granting it, showing the amount that has been actually paid for the franchise or right.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>If any contract, agreement, or arrangement, verbal or written, has been made to sell the stock, bonds, notes, or other evidence of indebtedness proposed to be issued, the contract, agreement, or arrangement shall be described in full, and a copy of it shall be attached to the application.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>If no contract, agreement, or arrangement has been made for the sale or other disposal of the stock, bonds, notes, or other evidence of indebtedness proposed to be issued, there shall be attached to the application an affidavit of a competent person showing the amount that can probably be realized from the sale or disposition of them and the reasons for the opinion of the affiant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>There shall be attached to the application an affidavit made by at least three of the directors of the applicant, showing that it is the intention of the applicant in good faith to use the proceeds of the stock, bonds, notes, or other evidence of indebtedness proposed to be issued, for the purposes set forth in the petition.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Notice. Within 2 weeks of the filing of an application, and for the next succeeding week, the public service company shall give notice of the filing of an application under <cite path="20|07|04|.02|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> with the Commission by publishing an advertisement in a newspaper of general circulation in each county in the distribution territory served by the company.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Final Order. An order of the Commission granting an application, or any part of it, shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Prescribe the purpose for which the proceeds of the security or obligation authorized shall be used;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Direct the applicant to report to the Commission under oath the sale or other disposition of the securities or obligations authorized, the terms and conditions of them, and the amount realized from them;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Require the applicant to make a report when funds have been fully expended showing in detail the use and application by it of the money so realized; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Contain such other provisions as the Commission may deem necessary or appropriate in each case.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|07|04|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Applications by Corporations for the Exercise of Franchises.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Exercise of Railroad Franchises. Applications by corporations subject to the provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|5-201">Public Utilities Article, §5-201, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, for permission to begin the construction of a railroad, or an extension of it, or to exercise any franchise or right, as provided in §5-201, shall state:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The route of the proposed railroad or street railroad, or extension of it, giving the names of all cities, villages, or towns in and through which it is to be constructed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The name of each corporation with which the proposed construction, right, or franchise may compete.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The facts showing whether the proposed construction, right, or franchise is required by public convenience or necessity.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>All other facts deemed material by the petitioner.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If the applicant has not exercised any of the powers or privileges of a corporation, the manner in which it proposes to finance the proposed construction or the proposed exercise of the franchise or right.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>If the applicant has exercised the powers of a corporation, the manner in which it proposes to finance the proposed construction, or the proposed exercise of the franchise or right, and also (unless waived by the Commission) the applicant's financial condition.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Unless waived by the Commission, the petition shall be accompanied by a certified copy of the articles of incorporation of the applicant, and all amendments to them.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Maps and profiles, showing the location and route of the proposed construction, shall be filed, and also proof of compliance with all conditions required by law as precedent to the application or the granting of it, including proof of the consent of the municipalities and counties having jurisdiction.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Unless waived by the Commission, there shall be annexed to the petition an affidavit made by at least three directors of the applicant, that it is the intention of the applicant in good faith to begin the construction or to exercise the right or franchise applied for, within a time to be specified in the affidavit.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Exercise of Gas or Electric Franchises. Applications by corporations subject to the provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-210">Public Utilities Article, §7-210, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, for permission to begin construction, or exercise any right or franchise as provided in §7-210, shall state:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The description of the proposed construction or of the proposed exercise of the right or franchise;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The location or locations in which the construction is to be had or the right or franchise exercised;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The requirements set forth in §A(2)—(9) of this regulation, unless waived by the Commission to the extent authorized in §A(2)—(9), except that the Commission may not waive the requirements of filing a certified copy of the applicant's charter, unless it is already on file in the office of the Commission; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The verified statement of the president and secretary of the corporation showing that it has received the required consent of the proper municipal authorities.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Exercise of Telephone and Telegraph, Water, Heat or Refrigerating, and Power Franchises. Applications by corporations subject to the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu">Public Utilities Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, for permission to begin construction or to exercise any right or franchise, shall state the matters and things set forth in <cite path="20|07|04|.03|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Applications for Approval of Assignment, Transfer, or Lease of Franchises.</heading>
    <text>In all applications under the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu">Public Utilities Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, for the approval of the assignment, transfer, or lease of a franchise, or of any right to or under a franchise, or of a corporation's works or system, or for the approval of a contract or agreement with reference to or affecting any of the same, the petition shall be made by all the parties to the proposed transaction, and shall show:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Unless waived by the Commission, the financial condition of each applicant;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In detail, the reasons upon the part of each applicant for making the proposed assignment, transfer, lease, contract, or agreement and all the facts warranting the same, and all facts which should be known to the Commission to enable it to pass upon the application; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The petition shall be accompanied by copies of the articles of incorporation of each applicant, duly certified, of the franchise, of the proposed assignment, transfer, lease, contract, or agreement, and of the laws or a reference to the laws which authorize them. If any of the instruments are already on file in the office of the Commission, they need not be refiled.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Applications for Authority to Acquire Shares of Stock.</heading>
    <text>In all applications made to the Commission by corporations for authority to purchase or acquire, take or hold, any part of the capital stock of any other corporation or corporations, the petition shall show:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In detail, the reasons why the applicant desires to make the proposed acquisition and all the facts warranting it, including the amount of stock in the same corporation or in any allied corporation already held by the applicant.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The market value of the stock proposed to be acquired, with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The highest and lowest price of the stock during a period of at least 1 year before the making of the petition;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The dividends, if any, paid for a period of 5 years before making the petition;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The price proposed to be paid or the loan proposed to be made;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The name of the present owner;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The terms of payment, or, in case of loan, of repayment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In case of an application for authorization to purchase stock of a certain description as opportunity may offer, the reasons for the purchase in full detail, with a statement of high and low market values and dividends paid each year for at least 5 years before making the petition, and the maximum price which the petitioner should be allowed to pay.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>There shall be submitted a certified copy of the articles of incorporation of each corporation, unless one is already on file in the office of the Commission, and a statement showing the amount of stock authorized and issued by each corporation, and also, unless waived by the Commission, the financial condition of each of the corporations.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Applications by Municipalities for Authority to Operate Gas or Electrical Works.</heading>
    <text>All applications of municipalities, except the Mayor and City Council of Baltimore, under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-210">Public Utilities Article, §7-210, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, for authority to build, maintain, and operate, for other than municipal purposes, any works or systems for the manufacture and supplying of gas or electricity for lighting purposes, shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Give the name and location of the principal office of all gas and electric corporations doing business within the municipality;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Give the names of the executive officers of each gas or electric corporation;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Give a general statement of the amount and character of services rendered within the municipality by each gas or electric corporation in the municipality;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Give a statement showing by what authority the municipality has the right to build the proposed work or system upon receiving a certificate of authority from the Commission;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Give a description of the works or system proposed to be constructed;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Give the manner in which the municipality proposes to pay for or finance the construction of the proposed works or system; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Comply with Regulations .02 and .03 of this chapter so far as they may be applicable and appropriate to the purposes of the application.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Applications for Authority to Increase Rates, Fares, and Charges.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A public service company earning in excess of $25,000,000 in gross annual intrastate revenue shall file with the Commission the direct testimony and exhibits of its witnesses concurrently with its application for authority to increase its rates and charges.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>All gas, electric, or telephone public service companies filing an application with the Commission for authority to increase rates and charges under the "make-whole" provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|4-207">Public Utilities Article, §4-207, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, shall concurrently file the direct testimony and exhibits of its witnesses. Failure by the Company to comply with this section shall be sufficient cause for the Commission to dismiss and reject the application, unless waived by the Commission for good cause shown.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Under §§A and B of this regulation, the applicant public service company shall file with the Commission an original and 15 copies of the rate increase application and 15 copies of the direct testimony and exhibits of its witnesses.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The applicant public service company, filing under §§A and B of this regulation, shall forward a copy of the application for authority to increase rates and charges, together with the testimony and exhibits of its witnesses, to the Office of People's Counsel at the same time as the filing with the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Rate Making—Revenues and Expenditures.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Revenues and expenditures credited or charged to Accounts 415 through and including 418 of the Uniform System of Accounts, as prescribed by the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission, relating to merchandising, jobbing, and contract work will not be allowed for rate making purposes in rate matters.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Charitable contributions, penalties, and lobbying expenses recorded in Account 426.1, 426.3, and 426.4, respectively, of the Uniform System of Accounts as prescribed by the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission will not be allowed for rate making purposes in rate matters.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Expenditures for advertising and promotion other than that classified as informational will not be allowed for rate making purposes unless it is demonstrated to the satisfaction of the Commission in a subsequent rate proceeding that the expense is of direct benefit to the rate payer and in the public interest. Informational advertising is presumed to be in the public interest unless otherwise demonstrated in a subsequent rate proceeding.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>For the purposes of determining whether these expenses shall be borne by the rate payer or stockholders, all advertising and promotion shall be divided into the following classifications:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Promotional;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Informational;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Community affairs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Institutional.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Definitions. In this regulation, the following terms have the meanings indicated:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Promotional" means directed toward selling services or promoting the addition of new customers or seeking additional use of utility service.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Informational" means directed toward informing customers of charges and conditions of service, safety precautions, energy conservation, temporary or emergency conditions, employment opportunities, rate cases, annual reports, legal and financial matters.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Community affairs" means directed toward influencing public opinion on a controversial issue, or the result of any legislative or administrative matter that would justify the utility civic and community position.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Institutional" means directed toward establishing a favorable image of the utility company or its employees and which serves to identify the sponsor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Unless a utility company demonstrates during a rate case proceeding before the Commission that a particular item of advertising or promotional expenditure was directly beneficial to the ratepayer and in the public interest, expenses classified as promotional, community affairs, and institutional shall be excluded as an expense for rate making purposes.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|07|04|.09">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Filing of Proposed Changes in Rates.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Every gas, electric, steam heat, telephone, water, or sewage disposal company when filing pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|4-203">Public Utilities Article, §4-203, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, any proposed change in rates or regulations to its current tariff (for a typical illustration of a currently effective schedule, see <cite path="20|07|04|.09|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>) shall show by brackets the rates or language proposed to be eliminated and show by underscorings the proposed rates or language (for an illustration of a typical schedule showing proposed changes, see <cite path="20|07|04|.09|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>). The underscored proposed rates shall be placed adjacent to the bracketed current rates.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Every gas, electric, steam heat, telephone, water, or sewage disposal company planning to file a proposed change in rates or regulations may make a written request to the Commission, with reasons therefore, for permission to submit as an alternative to the procedure specified in <cite path="20|07|04|.09|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, statements showing on separate sheets:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All changes in rates or regulations being proposed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The present rates or regulations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The proposed rates or regulations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The dollar increase or decrease; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Any changes in text and such other data that is meaningful with respect to the proposed changes.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Every filing by each gas, electric, steam heat, telephone, water, or sewage disposal company shall be accompanied by a letter of transmittal which shall set forth as a minimum, the following data:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The percentage increase or decrease and dollar amount of increase or decrease in operating revenues resulting therefrom.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The percentage increase or decrease and dollar amount of increase or decrease for the various classes of service.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The percentage increase or decrease and dollar amount of increase or decrease in the various rate blocks within the various classes of service (where rate blocking is utilized).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The purpose and the effect of any proposed change in language or regulations.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Currently Effective Tariff.</text>
      <text class="center">Current Tariff as Presently Filed</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="bottom">Leesburg Water Company, Inc.</td>
              <td/>
              <td data-text-align="center">P.S.C. Md. No.1 <br/>Original Page No. 1</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
      <text class="center">Residential Service</text>
      <text class="center">
        <u>Schedule of Meter Rates</u>
      </text>
      <text>AVAILABILITY: To Metered Consumers for Residential Use Only.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th colspan="3">MINIMUM CHARGES:</th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th>METER SIZE</th>
              <th>1000 GALLONS <br/>ALLOWED</th>
              <th>PER QUARTER</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>5/8" &amp; 3/4"</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">10</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$16.20</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>1"</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">34</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">34.65</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>11/2"</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">74</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">62.65</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>2"</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">124</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">97.65</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td colspan="3" data-vertical-align="middle">CONSUMPTION CHARGES:</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td colspan="2" data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="bottom">QUARTERLY</td>
              <td data-text-align="center">RATE PER<br/>1,000 GALLONS</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>FIRST</td>
              <td>10,000 GALLONS</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$1.62</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>NEXT</td>
              <td>15,000 GALLONS</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">.81</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>ALL OVER</td>
              <td>25,000 GALLONS</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">.70</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
      <text>CONDITIONS OF CONTRACT:</text>
      <text>The consumer shall pay the minimum charge only when the amount resulting by applying the meter rate to the quantity of water consumed is less than the said minimum rate.</text>
      <text>TERMS OF PAYMENT:</text>
      <text>Bills for water service will be rendered quarterly and must be paid within fifteen (15) days from date of bill.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Tariff Showing Proposed Changes.</text>
      <text class="center">Current Tariff with Proposed Changes as Indicated</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="bottom">Leesburg Water Company, Inc.</td>
              <td/>
              <td data-text-align="center">P.S.C. Md. No.1 <br/>1st. Revised Page No. 1 <br/>Cancelling <br/>Original Page No. 1</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
      <text class="center">Residential Service</text>
      <text class="center">
        <u>Schedule of Meter Rates</u>
      </text>
      <text>AVAILABILITY: To Metered Consumers for Residential Use Only.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th colspan="3">MINIMUM CHARGES:</th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th>METER SIZE</th>
              <th>1000 GALLONS <br/>ALLOWED</th>
              <th>PER QUARTER</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>5/8" &amp; 3/4"</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">10</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$16.36</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>1"</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">34</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">35.00</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>11/2"</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">74</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">63.28</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>2"</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">124</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">98.63</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th colspan="3">CONSUMPTION CHARGES:</th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th colspan="2">QUARTERLY</th>
              <th>RATE PER<br/>1,000 GALLONS</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>FIRST</td>
              <td>10,000 GALLONS</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$1.78</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>NEXT</td>
              <td>15,000 GALLONS</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">.90</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>ALL OVER</td>
              <td>25,000 GALLONS</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">.80</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
      <text>CONDITIONS OF CONTRACT:</text>
      <text>The consumer shall pay the minimum charge only when the amount resulting by applying the meter rate to the quantity of water consumed is less than the said minimum rate.</text>
      <text>TERMS OF PAYMENT:</text>
      <text>Bills for water service will be rendered quarterly and must be paid within fifteen (15) days from date bill is <u>rendered</u>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Notice of Proposed Changes in Rates.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A public service company engaged in the transportation of passengers by motor vehicle proposing any tariff revision or change of rate shall notify its customers and patrons of the proposed tariff revision or change of rate by use of a form of notice as follows:</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>NOTICE OF PROPOSED TARIFF CHANGE</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>___________________________(Name of Company)___</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>has filed with the Public Service Commission of Maryland</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>a proposal to</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(Here describe proposal)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Further details will be supplied upon request to the</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Company or to the Commission.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Any comment regarding this proposal should be submitted,</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>in writing, to the Public Service Commission of Maryland,</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>6 St. Paul Street, Baltimore, Maryland 21202,</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>within twenty (20) days after the date of this notice.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>____________                    __________________________</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(Date)                                  (Name of Company)</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Commission reserves the right to require that the procedure outlined above be applied in any instance of proposed tariff revision or change or any proposed change of rules, regulations, or practices of any public service company.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|07|04|.11">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Application for a Qualified Rate Order and Authority to Issue Rate Stabilization Bonds.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Application. An application filed with the Commission by an electric company for a qualified rate order and authority under Public Utilities Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-526">7-526</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-533">7-533</cite>, or 7-534, Annotated Code of Maryland, to issue rate stabilization bonds shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The amount and terms of the proposed qualified rate stabilization bond issue;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The components of the rate stabilization costs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A proposed qualified rate stabilization charge tariff and expiration date;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A description of any debt or equity securities to be refinanced or retired, including previously issued rate stabilization bonds;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The financial condition of the applicant;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>If a contract, agreement, or arrangement has been made for the sale of the rate stabilization bonds proposed to be issued, the contract, agreement, or arrangement described in full and attached to the application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>A calculation showing that the total amount of revenue to be collected under the proposed qualified rate order is less than the rate stabilization costs revenue that would be recovered over the same period using the electric company's weighted cost of capital;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>If the application proposes to refinance existing rate stabilization bonds, a calculation showing that the proposed qualified rate stabilization charge required to service the proposed rate stabilization bonds, including anticipated transaction costs, will be less than the future qualified rate stabilization charges required to service the rate stabilization bonds being refunded;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Any specific sections, terms, or conditions to be included in the qualified rate order that the electric company believes appropriate and the reason for each; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>An affidavit made by at least three of the directors of the applicant, showing that it is the intention of the applicant in good faith to use the proceeds of the stabilization bonds for the purposes identified in the application.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Notice of Filing of Application.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within 2 weeks of the filing of an application, and for the next succeeding week, the electric company shall give notice of the filing of an application under <cite path="20|07|04|.11|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> with the Commission by publishing an advertisement in a newspaper of general circulation in each county in the distribution territory served by the company.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The notice shall state:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>That the company has filed with the Commission an application for a qualified rate order and authority for a finance subsidiary to issue rate stabilization bonds;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The total amount of rate stabilization bonds the company requested in the application;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The proposed rate stabilization charge and the number of years it will be collected;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>That interested persons may send comments to the Commission; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The Commission's mailing and website addresses.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Review and Adjustment of Qualified Rate Stabilization Charges.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each year that a qualified rate stabilization charge is collected, an electric company shall file with the Commission, 60 days prior to the anniversary of the date of the issuance of any rate stabilization bonds and 30 days following the retirement of any refunded rate stabilization bonds:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A proposed tariff recalculating the qualified rate stabilization charge with supporting data to correct any over-collection or under-collection during the preceding 12 months;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A description of how the proposed tariff will ensure the recovery of amounts sufficient to timely provide all payments of debt service and other required amounts and charges in connection with the rate stabilization bonds; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>All calculations and supporting data for the proposed qualified rate stabilization charge.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An electric company shall perform a true-up of all qualified rate stabilization charges collected to ensure that the authorized amount of qualified rate stabilization costs have been recovered at the end of the period established in the qualified rate order issued by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Other Applications.</heading>
    <text>All applications relating to matters within the jurisdiction of the Commission, and which are not governed by any of the above regulations shall in every case be made by petition, setting forth clearly the matter complained of, and giving the name of the person, firm, or corporation complained of. Thereupon, the procedure shall be such as the Commission may prescribe.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Required Number of Copies.</heading>
    <text>Unless otherwise specifically required in this chapter, the applicant shall file with the Commission an original and 14 copies of the application and all required documents.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Public Utilities Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-112">2-112</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-115">2-115</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-121">2-121</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|3-101">3-101</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|3-104">3-104</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|4-101">4-101</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|4-207">4-207</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|4-503">4-503</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|5-103">5-103</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|5-201">5-201</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|5-203">5-203</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|5-205">5-205</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|6-101">6-101</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|6-104">6-104</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-210">7-210</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|9-103">9-103</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1910-08-15">Effective date: August 15, 1910</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1914-10-19">Regulations <cite path="|20|07|04|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|20|07|04|.06">.06</cite> and .12 revised effective May 8, 1911, May 3, 1912, and October 19, 1914</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-01-01"><cite path="|20|07|04|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective September 21, 1986 (13:19 Md. R. 2122); January 1, 2007 (33:26 Md. R. 1998)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-03-18"><cite path="|20|07|04|.02|C.">Regulation .02C</cite> amended effective March 18, 2013 (40:5 Md. R. 412)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1981-01-23"><cite path="|20|07|04|.07">Regulation .07</cite> adopted effective January 23, 1981 (8:2 Md. R. 118)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1982-05-10"><cite path="|20|07|04|.07|C.">Regulation .07C</cite> amended effective May 10, 1982 (9:9 Md. R. 911)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1968-08-03"><cite path="|20|07|04|.08">Regulation .08</cite> effective August 3, 1968 (Order No. 62950)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1973-08-01"><cite path="|20|07|04|.09">Regulation .09</cite> effective August 1, 1973 (Order No. 60353)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1963-05-15"><cite path="|20|07|04|.10">Regulation .10</cite> effective May 15, 1963 (Order No. 55165)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-01-01"><cite path="|20|07|04|.10">Regulation .10</cite> amended effective January 1, 2007 (33:26 Md. R. 1998)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1962-09-13"><cite path="|20|07|04|.11">Regulation .11</cite> effective September 13, 1962 (Order No. 54994)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-01-01"><cite path="|20|07|04|.11">Regulation .11</cite> repealed and new Regulation .11 adopted effective January 1, 2007 (33:26 Md. R. 1998)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1982-05-10"><cite path="|20|07|04|.13">Regulation .13</cite> adopted effective May 10, 1982 (9:9 Md. R. 911)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
