<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Prohibited Acts</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Deep fake” has the meaning stated in <cite path="33.13.07.02|H.|(1)">COMAR 33.13.07.02H(1)</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Political convention” means the act of a political party or central committee of the political party to select, nominate, or elect:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A replacement candidate to the ballot pursuant to Election Law Article, Title 5, Subtitles 9 and 10, Annotated Code of Maryland;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A member to the central committee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A person for appointment to fill a vacancy in accordance with Article III, Section 13, of <cite doc="Md. Const.">the Maryland Constitution</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A candidate for the general election.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Prohibited Acts.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A person may not directly or indirectly give, offer, or promise money, aid, a gift, an advantage, a preferment, an emolument, or any other valuable thing to another person for the purpose of inducing or procuring that person to vote or refrain from voting for or against:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An individual, question, or measure at an election or political convention; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The election of an officer by the General Assembly.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A person may not directly or indirectly receive, accept, request, or solicit money, aid, a gift, an advantage, a preferment, an emolument, or any other valuable thing from another person for the purpose of inducing or procuring a third person to vote or refrain from voting for or against an individual, question, or measure at an election or political convention.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A person may not vote or refrain from voting for or against an individual, question, or measure at an election or a political convention, in consideration of money, aid, a gift, an advantage, a preferment, an emolument, or any other valuable thing paid, received, accepted, or promised to the advantage of that person or of another person.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A person may not directly or indirectly give a contribution or contributions to a political committee in a name other than the person’s name.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Deep Fake. A person may not willfully or knowingly influence or attempt to influence a voter’s decision to go to the polls or to cast a vote by publishing, distributing, or disseminating material constituting or containing a deep fake within 90 days before an election without meeting the same requirements imposed on political committees under <cite path="33.13.07.02|H.">COMAR 33.13.07.02H</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Penalty.</heading>
    <text>A person who violates this section is guilty of a misdemeanor and on conviction is:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Subject to a fine not exceeding $1,000 or imprisonment not exceeding 1 year or both; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Ineligible to hold any public or party office for 4 years after the date of the offense.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Election Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|2-102">2-102</cite>(b)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|4">4</cite>), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|13-602">13-602</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|16-201">16-201</cite>(a), Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-02-29">Effective date: February 29, 2016 (43:4 Md. R. 338)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-07-11"><cite path="|33|18|02|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective July 11, 2022 (49:14 Md. R. 705)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-07-11"><cite path="|33|18|02|.02|E.">Regulation .02E</cite> adopted effective July 11, 2022 (49:14 Md. R. 705)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
