<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>08</num>
  <heading>Instruments and Procedures</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Equipment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Electrologists shall use only Board-approved modalities which are:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Electrolysis;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Thermolysis; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The blend.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Electronic tweezer or nonneedle methods are not defined as within the practice of electrology.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Epilators shall be approved by the Federal Communications Commission (FCC) and conform to federal Food and Drug Administration (FDA) standards relating to these devices.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Epilators shall be maintained in proper working condition.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Optimum timing and intensity shall be used during treatment to effect proper epilation of hair and to avoid tweezing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A professional lamp and magnification shall be used to view area during treatment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A professional treatment table or chair shall be used to administer treatments.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>A clean head towel or drape sheet shall be used for each patient.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Each office shall contain and use sterilization equipment according to <cite path="|10.53.09">COMAR 10.53.09</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Fresh disposable paper drapes shall be used on the treatment table or chair for each patient. Paper drapes shall be stored in a closed cabinet. Soiled disposable items shall be discarded into a container lined with a plastic bag, securely fastened, and removed daily.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Each treatment room shall have a covered trash container.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Smoking is prohibited in the treatment room.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>A clean lab coat or uniform is acceptable attire.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Explanation to Patient of Electrology Practices.</heading>
    <text>The electrologist shall explain the following to the patient before treatment:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The treatment procedure, including standard precautions;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The modality used;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Hair growth cycles;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Regrowth;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The importance of keeping the follow-up treatment schedule;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Possible tissue reactions following treatment;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The importance of after-treatment care; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The treatment fee.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Health Assessment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A complete past and current health history shall be obtained from each patient before treatment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The assessment shall be updated and evaluated on a current basis, and shall include the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Name, address, telephone number, and date of birth;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Medical history and current update;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Prior methods of controlling or removing hair;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Condition of tissue before initial treatment and any subsequent change;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Pattern and structure of hair growth initially presented and significant subsequent changes;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Date of each treatment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Area of treatment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Duration of treatment; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Fee charged.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Hand Washing and Use of Gloves.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Electrologists shall wash their hands using soap, warm water, and good mechanical action immediately before and after treating each patient.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A fresh pair of nonsterile, disposable examination gloves shall be worn during the treatment of each patient and while cleaning instruments.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Electrologists shall wash their hands before putting on gloves and immediately after removing gloves.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The electrologist shall follow universal/standard precautions.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Sterility.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A sterile needle and sterile tweezer shall be used for each patient.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A sterile instrument or sterile tweezer shall be used for each patient to release ingrown hairs.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Treatment solutions shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Labeled as to contents; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Covered when not in use.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Treatment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Skin area to be treated shall first be cleansed thoroughly with 70 percent isopropyl alcohol.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An electrologist may not treat any mucous membrane or the external auditory canal of the ear without written approval of a licensed physician.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An electrologist may not treat an infected area or skin malignancy.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Applications To Be Used After Treatment.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>One of the following applications shall be applied to the tissue after treatment:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>70 percent isopropyl alcohol;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Witch hazel;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Hydrogen peroxide; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Other approved antiseptic for the skin.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Ice, healing cream, or healing lotion may be used at the electrologist's discretion.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Specific home care instructions shall be given to each patient after treatment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Disinfection and Environmental Controls.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Disposable or damaged instruments shall be placed in a container which is impervious to puncture. The instruments shall be disinfected with a freshly prepared solution of household bleach and water consisting of 1 part bleach and 9 parts water, and allowed to stand for at least 30 minutes. The solution shall then be poured off, and the container securely sealed and disposed of in compliance with State, federal, and local laws.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Removable tips of epilator probe holders shall be removed after each treatment and cleaned with soap or detergent and water, rinsed, dried, and disinfected by submersion in 70 percent isopropyl alcohol for at least 10 minutes. The covered container used to hold alcohol shall be emptied at least daily or sooner if visibly contaminated, then cleaned, dried, and refilled with fresh alcohol.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Nonremovable tips of epilator probe holders shall be wiped with a detergent-germicide after each treatment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Epilator probe cords that have been in direct contact with a patient or practitioner shall be wiped with a detergent-germicide after each treatment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The treatment lamp shall be wiped with a detergent-germicide after each treatment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>After each use, patient eyeshields shall be cleaned with soap or detergent and water, then rinsed and dried.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A hospital grade disinfectant-detergent registered by the Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) shall be used for cleaning environmental surfaces.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-205">8-205</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-6">8-6</cite>B-01—8-6B-29, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1984-01-16">Effective date: January 16, 1984 (11:1 Md. R. 45)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-02-03"><cite path="|10|53|08|.01|A.">Regulation .01A</cite> amended effective February 3, 1992 (19:2 Md. R. 154)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-05-10"><cite path="|10|53|08|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective February 19, 1993 (20:5 Md. R. 511); amended permanently effective May 10, 1993 (20:9 Md. R. 779)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-06-20" discontinuity="true"><cite path="|10|53|08|.01">Regulation .01</cite>, Fees, repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|10|53|08|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|53|08|.07">.07</cite> adopted under new chapter, Instruments and Procedures, effective June 20, 2005 (32:12 Md. R. 1047)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-08-05"><cite path="|10|53|08|.05|A.">Regulation .05A</cite>, B amended effective August 5, 2024 (51:15 Md. R. 710)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
