<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>10</num>
  <heading>Advertising</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Advertising Standards.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An electrologist shall include one of the following qualifications in an advertisement:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Licensed electrologist;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Licensed electrology instructor; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Licensed by the Board of Nursing — Electrology Practice Committee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An electrologist shall include in any advertising the name and address of at least one licensed electrologist or licensed electrology instructor practicing at the location advertised.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An electrologist may not, on behalf of the electrologist, a partner, an associate, or electrology affiliate, use or participate in the use of any form of public communication which contains a deceptive or misleading statement or claim. A deceptive or misleading statement or claim is one that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>States or implies:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>That the electrologist is a certified or recognized specialist other than as licensed by the Board, unless the statement is true;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>That the electrologist has superior education or credentials that are different than any other licensed electrologist or licensed electrologist instructor, if they are not;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>An unwarranted claim of superior service;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A material misrepresentation of fact or presentation of fact that is likely to cause an ordinary prudent individual to misunderstand or to be deceived; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>An unreasonable claim likely to create unjustified expectations; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Fails to include any fact necessary to make a statement not misleading.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An electrologist may not use electronic media, including telephone, radio, internet, and motion pictures, in a manner that is unreasonable, misleading, or fraudulent.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Other Licenses.</heading>
    <text>Electrologists or electrology instructors advertising other services for which they are licensed within one advertisement shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>List each license held; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Clearly state each service offered under each license.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Fees.</heading>
    <text>A statement regarding fees shall be considered deceptive or misleading if the electrologist:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Charges more than the fee advertised for a service rendered; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Fails to offer the service at the fee advertised for a reasonable period of time after the advertisement unless a specific time limit is included in the original advertisement.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Responsibility.</heading>
    <text>An electrologist shall be responsible for an advertisement of service regardless of whether the advertising has been generated by the electrologist personally, by an employee, or by a proprietorship, partnership, corporation, union, clinic or institution, which uses the electrologist's services.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Penalties.</heading>
    <text>Violation of this chapter is a violation of Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-6">8-6</cite>B-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|23">23</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-6">8-6</cite>B-18(a)(10), Annotated Code of Maryland, and may result in disciplinary action pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-6">Health Occupations Article, §8-6</cite>B-18, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-205">8-205</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-6">8-6</cite>B-01—8-6B-29, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1984-01-16">Effective date: January 16, 1984 (11:1 Md. R. 45)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-07-20"><cite path="|10|53|10|.01|C.">Regulation .01C</cite>, D amended effective July 20, 1992 (19:14 Md. R. 1284)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-06-20" discontinuity="true"><cite path="|10|53|10|.01">Regulation .01</cite>, Requirements for Institutions Teaching the Theory or Clinical Practice of Electrology, repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|10|53|10|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|53|10|.05">.05</cite> adopted under new chapter, Advertising, effective June 20, 2005 (32:12 Md. R. 1047)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
