<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>09</num>
  <heading>Delegation and Assignment of Performance of Cosmetic Medical Procedures and Use of Cosmetic Medical Devices</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter governs the performance, delegation, assignment, and supervision of cosmetic medical procedures, and the use of cosmetic medical devices by a physician or under a physician's direction.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This chapter does not govern use of medical procedures or medical devices for the purpose of treating a disease.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>This chapter does not endorse or certify the safety of any cosmetic medical device or cosmetic medical procedure.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>This chapter does not authorize the delegation of any duties to any person who is not licensed under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"ACCME" means the Accreditation Council on Continuing Medical Education.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"ACGME" means the Accreditation Council for Graduate Medical Education.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"AOA" means the American Osteopathic Association.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Cosmetic Medical Device.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Cosmetic medical device" means a device that alters or damages living tissue.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Cosmetic medical device" includes any of the following items, when the item is used for cosmetic purposes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Laser;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Device emitting light or intense pulsed light;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Device emitting radio frequency, electric pulses, or sound waves; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Devices used for the injection or insertion of foreign or natural substances into the skin, fat, facial tissue, muscle, or bone.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Cosmetic Medical Procedure.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Cosmetic medical procedure" means a procedure using a cosmetic medical device or medical product to improve an individual's appearance.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Cosmetic medical procedure" includes the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Skin treatments using lasers;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Skin treatments using intense pulsed light;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Skin treatments using radio frequencies, microwave, or electric pulses;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Chemical peels that ablate living skin tissue;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Skin treatments with phototherapy;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Dermabrasion;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Subcutaneous, intradermal, or intramuscular injections of medical products;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Treatments intended to remove or cause destruction of fat; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ix)</num>
            <text>Any treatment using a cosmetic medical device for the purpose of improving an individual's appearance.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Delegate" means to entrust a duty to a physician assistant under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 15, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Delegation" means the entrusting of a duty by a physician to a physician assistant under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 15, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>”Dermabrasion” means an abrasive process to remove epidermis and superficial dermis, resulting in a smoothing of contour irregularities.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Direct supervision" means oversight exercised by a supervising physician who is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In the physical presence of a non-physician and a patient; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Instructing the non-physician in the performance of a cosmetic medical procedure, or observing the performance of a non-physician being trained in the procedure.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Immediately available supervision" means the responsibility of a licensed physician to provide necessary direction in person, by telephone, or by other electronic means.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Non-Physician" means an individual who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Meets the requirements of <cite path="|10|32|09|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is not licensed in Maryland as a physician.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>"On-site supervision" means oversight exercised by a supervising physician who is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Present at the site; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Able to respond in person during a delegated or assigned cosmetic medical procedure.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>"Physician assistant" means a physician assistant with a current certificate to practice in Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Physician Qualifications.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>License. A physician shall obtain a license to practice medicine in Maryland before the physician may perform, delegate, assign, or supervise cosmetic medical procedures or the use of cosmetic medical devices.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Education.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A physician who performs, assigns, supervises, or delegates the performance of cosmetic medical procedures by a non-physician first shall obtain training in the indications for and performance of the cosmetic medical procedures and operation of any cosmetic medical device to be used.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Training programs provided by a manufacturer or vendor of cosmetic medical devices or supplies may not be a physician's only education in the cosmetic medical procedures or the operation of the cosmetic medical devices to be used.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>ACCME or AOA approved continuing education, or completion of an ACGME or AOA accredited postgraduate program that includes training in the cosmetic medical procedure performed satisfies this requirement.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Qualifications of Individual to Whom Acts May Be Delegated and Assigned.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A cosmetic medical procedure may be delegated to a physician assistant or assigned to any other health care provider licensed under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, whose licensing board has determined that the procedure falls within the provider's scope of practice.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A physician may not permit any individual who performs cosmetic medical procedures delegated or assigned by that physician to operate a cosmetic medical device or perform a cosmetic medical procedure unless the individual has received:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Training as described in <cite path="|10|32|09|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Any training required by that individual's health occupations board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Physician Responsibilities.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A physician shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Develop and maintain at each site where the delegated, assigned, or supervised cosmetic medical procedures will be rendered written office protocols for each such cosmetic medical procedure;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Personally perform the initial assessment of each patient;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Prepare a written treatment plan for each patient, including diagnosis and planned course of treatment and specification of the device and device settings to be used;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Obtain informed consent of the patient to be treated by a non-physician;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Except as indicated in §B or C of this regulation, provide onsite supervision whenever a non-physician is performing cosmetic medical procedures or using cosmetic medical devices;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Retain responsibility for any acts delegated to a non-physician; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Create and maintain medical records in a manner consistent with accepted medical practice and in compliance with Health-General Article, Title 4, Subtitles 3 and 4, Annotated Code of Maryland, and with Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act of 1996 (42 U.S.C. §1320d-2, as amended, and 45 CFR Parts 160 and 164, as amended).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board may approve a delegation agreement for a physician assistant that permits the physician to delegate performance of cosmetic medical procedures under immediately available supervision after the physician has evaluated the patient and developed a written treatment plan.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A delegation agreement for a physician assistant that includes cosmetic medical procedures and is approved by the Board before May 2009, is not affected by this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Written Protocols.</heading>
    <text>Written protocols for cosmetic medical procedures and equipment shall include the following:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>List of all equipment, including:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Manufacturer's specifications;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Operating instructions; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Maintenance log;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Documentation regarding initial and periodic training of all users of the equipment;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Role of the physician for each procedure;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Role of the non-physician for each procedure;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Steps to address common complications and emergency situations; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Appropriate care and follow-up for the patient after the procedure.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Training of Non-Physicians.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The physician is responsible for assuring that any individual to whom the physician delegates or assigns the performance of a cosmetic medical procedure or the operation of a cosmetic medical device is properly trained. Training shall include both theoretical instruction and clinical instruction.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Theoretical instruction shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Cosmetic-dermatological indications and contraindications for treatment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Identification of realistic and expected outcomes of each procedure;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Selection, maintenance, and utilization of equipment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Appropriate technique for each procedure, including infection control and safety precautions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Pharmacological intervention specific to the procedure;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Identification of complications and adverse reactions for each procedure;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Emergency procedures to be used in the event of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Complications;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Adverse reactions;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Equipment malfunction; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Any other interruption of a procedure; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Appropriate documentation of the procedure in the patient's chart.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Clinical instruction shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Observation of performance of the procedure or use of the device by an individual experienced in performing the procedure; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Performing the procedure or using the device under the direct supervision of the delegating physician who is present and observing the procedure a sufficient number of times to assure that the non-physician is competent to perform the procedure without direct supervision.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Non-Physician's Responsibility.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A physician who delegates or assigns a cosmetic medical procedure or the use of a cosmetic medical device to a non-physician or who supervises a non-physician performing these functions shall assure that the non-physician complies with this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A non-physician may not use a cosmetic medical device or perform a cosmetic medical procedure unless the individual has received:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The training described in <cite path="|10|32|09|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Any training required by that individual's health occupations board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A non-physician shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Review and follow the written protocol with respect to a cosmetic medical procedure;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Verify that the physician has assessed the patient and given written treatment instructions for the procedure;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Discuss the procedure with the patient to ensure that the patient:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is aware that the treatment will be provided by a non-physician; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has given consent in writing to treatment by a non-physician;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Notify the delegating physician about any adverse events or complications before the patient leaves the site;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Document all relevant details of the procedure in the patient's chart, including any adverse events and complications; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Satisfy any requirements imposed by the licensing board of the non-physician.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Grounds for Discipline.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Physician. A physician may be disciplined for any of the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Delegating, assigning, or supervising a cosmetic medical procedure performed by an individual who is not a physician assistant or another licensed health care provider whose licensing board has determined that the procedure is within the scope of practice of the individual;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Delegating cosmetic medical procedures to an individual who has not had:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The training specified in <cite path="|10|32|09|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The training required by that individual's health occupations board; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Failure to adhere to any requirement of this chapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Non-Physician. A non-physician who violates any provision of this chapter is guilty of the practice of medicine without a license and may be subject to a fine of not more than $50,000 under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|14-606">Health Occupations Article, §14-606, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Other Individual. An individual using a cosmetic medical device or performing a cosmetic medical procedure who is not a licensed physician and is not authorized to perform the cosmetic medical procedure under this chapter, or under regulations promulgated by another licensing board established by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, is guilty of the practice of medicine without a license and may be subject to a fine of not more than $50,000 under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|14-606">Health Occupations Article, §14-606, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|14-205">14-205</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|14-306">14-306</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|14-404">14-404</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|14-606">14-606</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|15-302">15-302</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-08-23">Effective date: August 23, 2010 (37:17 Md. R. 1185)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-12-31"><cite path="|10|32|09|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective March 14, 2016 (43:5 Md. R. 386); December 31, 2018 (45:26 Md. R. 1246)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
