<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Contracts and Sanctions</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Contract Between Manager and Contestant.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as otherwise indicated, a contract between a contestant and a manager shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notarized; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Filed with the Commission 5 business days before the contestant first participates in a contest in this State.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Provisions of Contract.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An executed original contract between a manager and a contestant shall be filed with the Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A contract shall include the following provisions:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>That there is no financial interest in the earnings of the contestant by any person other than the manager or managers of the contestant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>That a manager or managers will receive not more than 33-1/3 percent of the gross earnings of the contestant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>That the contract has a duration of not more than 5 years;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>That the contract may not be extended beyond its initial term; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>That the contestant shall comply with all laws, regulations, and directives of the Commission.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An assignment of interest in a contract filed with the Commission may not be valid unless it is approved by the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A manager may not sign a promoter-contestant contract on behalf of a contestant which obligates the contestant to compete in an event scheduled to take place after the expiration of the contract between the manager and contestant.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A contestant may not sign a contract with any other manager during the term of an existing contract the contestant may have with a manager.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Contract Between Promoter and Contestant.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A contract between a promoter and a contestant shall include the following provisions:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The amount of guarantee or percentage promised by the promoter to the contestant;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The number and time limit of rounds;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The time and location that the contestants are scheduled to appear;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Weight specifications of the contestants;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A prohibition against the contestant engaging in a contest at least 14 days before the contest stated in the contract;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Legal rights and obligations of the contracting parties;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>A provision stating that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Drug testing is mandatory in boxing, kickboxing, and mixed martial arts contests sanctioned by the State Athletic Commission;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Signing the contract is consent to submit to drug testing supervised by the Commission;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Refusing to submit to the urine test subjects a contestant to disciplinary action by the Commission; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Testing positive for prohibited drugs:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Is cause for a contestant to forfeit the purse set; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Subjects a contestant to disciplinary action by the Commission; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The contestant agrees to comply with all laws, regulations, and directives of the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Unless the Commission otherwise approves, contracts for main event contestants shall be filed with the Commission with the request for sanction.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Unless the Commission otherwise approves, contracts for other contestants in a contest shall be submitted to the Commission not later than 5 business days before the date of the contest.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A promoter may not pay a purse specified in the contract until the Commission gives written approval to the promoter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Unless the Commission otherwise approves, a contestant, or a manager on behalf of a contestant, may not obligate a contestant to participate in any boxing, kickboxing, or mixed martial arts contest within 14 days before or after a date on which the contestant participates or is contracted to participate in another contest.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>For the purposes of this regulation, the promoter-contestant contract received first in time by the Commission prevails over any other promoter-contestant contract.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Failure to Appear.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as provided below, if a contestant absents himself from a contest for which the contestant is contractually obligated to participate, the contestant and the manager of the contestant are subject to disciplinary action.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a contestant is unable to fulfill a contract due to a physical disability, the contestant shall be placed on medical suspension until the Commission receives documentation of the contestant's physical disability signed by a licensed physician. Upon the expiration of the suspension, the contestant shall fulfill the contract against the same opponent or similar opponent within a reasonable amount of time as set by the Commission, unless the contestant obtains a written release from the contract by the promoter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If a contestant presents a valid written excuse for not fulfilling the contract, the contestant shall, when the reasons necessitating the excuse no longer apply, fulfill the contract against the same opponent or a similar opponent within a reasonable period of time.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|14|03|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Commission Sanction Required.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A contest may not take place unless sanctioned by the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Promoters shall file a written request for a sanction with the Commission at least 30 days before a boxing, kickboxing, or mixed martial arts contest containing the following information:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The names of the main event contestants;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The time, date, and location of the contest;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A plan for the employment of uniformed security at the contest; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Other information as may be required by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Before a contest is sanctioned by the Commission, a promoter may not:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Advertise or give notice through any medium that the contest is to take place; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Sell or distribute any tickets to the contest.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Substitution of Contestants.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If either of the contestants in the main event contest is unable to appear on the night of the contest, a substitute contestant may not participate unless a new sanction is obtained from the Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a substitution occurs under §D(1), of this regulation, the price of admission printed on tickets shall be refunded upon request to each spectator at the box office in accordance with <cite path="|09.14.09">COMAR 09.14.09</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Each contestant shall be insured through a group insurance policy provided by the Commission as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Minimum medical expense coverage of $10,000; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Minimum coverage of $10,000 for death, dismemberment, or loss of sight.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The terms and conditions of the coverage in <cite path="09|14|03|.03|E.">§E of this regulation</cite> shall be governed by the insurance policy between the Commission and its insurance carrier.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Nothing in this regulation shall preclude a promoter from providing coverage in excess of the coverage stated in <cite path="09|14|03|.03|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>If the promoter provides insurance coverage, a copy of the policy shall be given to the Commission not later than the final physical and shall list the Commission as an additional insured.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>The Commission may cancel a sanction obtained through fraud or misrepresentation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>A contest may be cancelled at the exclusive discretion of the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|4-205">Business Regulation Article, §4-205, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1965-10-01">Effective date: October 1, 1965</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-08-26">Subtitle revised effective August 26, 1985 (12:17 Md. R. 1705)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-07-06"><cite path="|09|14|03|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective June 24, 1991 (18:12 Md. R. 1338); July 6, 2009 (36:13 Md. R. 898)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-09-03"><cite path="|09|14|03|.01|C.">Regulation .01C</cite>, F amended effective September 3, 1990 (17:17 Md. R. 2079)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-07-06"><cite path="|09|14|03|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective December 28, 1987 (14:26 Md. R. 2744); June 24, 1991 (18:12 Md. R. 1338); July 6, 2009 (36:13 Md. R. 898)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-07-06"><cite path="|09|14|03|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective July 6, 2009 (36:13 Md. R. 898)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-09-03"><cite path="|09|14|03|.03|E.">Regulation .03E</cite> amended effective September 3, 1990 (17:17 Md. R. 2079)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
