<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Boxing and Kickboxing Facilities and Equipment</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Boxing or Kickboxing Ring.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A boxing or kickboxing ring shall meet the following requirements:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The boxing or kickboxing ring may not be less than 16 feet square or more than 24 feet square within the ring ropes;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The platform shall extend beyond the ropes for a distance of at least 2 feet;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The ring posts shall be at least 18 inches away from the ring ropes;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The ring floor, both within and outside the ropes, shall be padded with a minimum of 1 inch thick unicellular safety foam;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The platform shall have a top covering of canvas, duck, or equivalent material tightly stretched and laced to the platform;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The platform shall be a maximum height of 4 feet above the floor of the building and shall be provided with suitable steps for use by the boxers; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The mat and coverings shall be kept clean and free of odors at all times.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Ring posts shall meet the following requirements:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Constructed of metal with a maximum diameter of 3 inches;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Extend to the floor of the ring with a maximum height of 58 inches; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Properly padded.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Ring ropes shall meet the following requirements:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Four in number with a minimum diameter of 1 inch;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The lower rope shall be 18 inches above the ring floor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The top rope shall be 54 inches above the ring floor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The remaining two ropes shall be evenly spaced between the lower and top ropes;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The ropes shall be covered with a smooth plastic or other smooth, soft material;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The ropes shall be adjustable and shall be kept at the correct tautness; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The ring ropes shall be tied in the center of the ropes on all four sides.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Ring Equipment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The promoter shall provide all necessary equipment for use by seconds, boxers, and kickboxers at all events, subject to approval by the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A bell or gong shall be provided by the Commission and shall be positioned at the ring not higher than the floor level of the ring.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Gloves.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Gloves shall conform to specifications as determined by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Gloves shall be examined before a contest by a Commission representative and the referee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the padding is misplaced or lumpy, or if the gloves are otherwise defective, the gloves shall be changed before the contest starts.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Breaking, roughing, or twisting of gloves is not permitted.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Glove weights shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>8 ounces for weight classifications less than 148 pounds; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>10 ounces for weight classifications 148 pounds or greater.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The laces shall be knotted on the back of the wrist and tape shall be applied where the laces are knotted.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The gloves shall be thumb-attached.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Reserved.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Gloves — Main Event.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The promoter shall furnish approved new gloves designed to fit the hands of the contestants in a main event contest.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The promoter shall deliver the gloves to the Commission at the time of the final physical for approval by the main event boxers.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Upon approval, the Commission shall keep the gloves until the time of the main event contest.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Gloves — Preliminaries.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Used gloves for preliminary contests shall be whole, clean, in sanitary condition, and subject to inspection by the referee or Commission representative.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Unfit gloves shall be immediately discarded and replaced with gloves approved by the referee or Commission representative.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Gloves — Extra Set.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All promoters shall have at each contest an extra set of 8-ounce gloves and 10-ounce gloves.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Extra gloves may be used if the set of gloves currently in use are broken or damaged during the course of a contest.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|14|05|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Sanitation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Promoters shall be responsible for any violation of Commission regulations or applicable local health department requirements concerning sanitary conditions of dressing rooms, showers, water bottles, towels, or other equipment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Promoters shall provide at least one receptacle for medical waste, and properly dispose of the waste.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Promoters shall immediately correct any violation of the duties imposed by <cite path="09|14|05|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Round Cards.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The promoter shall provide a sufficient supply of round cards to designate the upcoming round.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>These cards shall be white and numbered on each side from 1 to 12.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Cards shall be displayed to be visible to all spectators.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|4-205">Business Regulation Article, §4-205, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1965-10-01">Effective date: October 1, 1965</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-08-26">Subtitle revised effective August 26, 1985 (12:17 Md. R. 1705)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1991-06-10"><cite path="|09|14|05|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite> amended effective June 10, 1991 (18:11 Md. R. 1187)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-09-03"><cite path="|09|14|05|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective September 3, 1990 (17:17 Md. R. 2079)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-07-06" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective July 6, 2009 (36:13 Md. R. 898)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-07-08"><cite path="|09|14|05|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective January 10, 2013 (40:3 Md. R. 216); amended permanently effective July 8, 2013 (40:13 Md. R. 1074)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-07-08"><cite path="|09|14|05|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective January 10, 2013 (40:3 Md. R. 216); amended permanently effective July 8, 2013 (40:13 Md. R. 1074)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
