<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>08</num>
  <heading>Wrestling Regulations</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|14|08|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Applicability.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>These regulations apply to persons conducting wrestling matches, including persons licensed by the Commission in the following capacities:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Wrestlers;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Managers;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Promoters; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Matchmakers.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Persons described in <cite path="09|14|08|.01|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, shall also be subject to all other appropriate regulations of the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Contestants and Substitutions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The promoter shall provide the Commission with a list of wrestlers scheduled to appear in a contest at least 21 days before the date of the wrestling contest.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Substitutions shall receive prior approval of the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A main event substitution shall be reported immediately to the Commission with an accompanying explanation for the substitution.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The wrestling card shall specify the number of falls required for each contest.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Conduct of Wrestling Contest.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A wrestling contest shall be determined by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>One fall; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Two out of three falls.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A one-fall contest shall be determined as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The wrestler scoring a fall within the time limit shall be declared the winner of the contest; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If neither wrestler scores a fall within the time limit, the referee shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Award the decision to one of the contestants, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Call the contest a draw.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A two-fall contest shall be determined as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The wrestler scoring two falls within the time limit shall be declared the winner of the contest;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If only one fall is scored within the time limit, the wrestler scoring the one fall shall be declared the winner of the contest; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If no wrestler has scored a fall or if both wrestlers have each scored one fall, the referee shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Award the decision to one of the contestants, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Call the contest a draw.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Scoring a Fall.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A fall is scored by a wrestler when the wrestler's opponent has both shoulders touching the mat for a count of three.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The referee shall signal the wrestler scoring a fall by immediately slapping the wrestler's back or shoulder.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Time Limits.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A wrestler shall be allowed 5 minutes between falls in a contest that provides for two out of three falls.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A wrestling match shall have a maximum time limit of 60 minutes.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Commission may authorize any other time limit.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Prohibited Activities.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The following actions are prohibited:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Striking an opponent with a fist or using the knuckles;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Scratching or gouging the opponent;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Butting the opponent;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Slamming an opponent into a ring post;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Striking an opponent with a foreign object;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Kicking an opponent unless a recognized wrestling move;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Stranglehold;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Pulling hair;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Inhibiting breathing by covering the nose and mouth at the same time;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Jumping from the ring ropes onto an opponent;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Deliberately leaving the ring enclosure during a contest;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>Unsportsmanlike or physically dangerous conduct; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>Deliberately lacerating oneself or one's opponent, or, by any other means, introducing human or animal blood into the ring.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A wrestler continuing to engage in prohibited activities after sufficient warning may be disqualified by the referee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Breaking. A wrestler:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall break a hold when instructed by the referee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Failing to break upon instruction shall be given a count of four to release the hold;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Failing to release the hold after the count of four shall be disqualified and the opponent shall be awarded the match by the referee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Wrestlers Out of the Ring.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a wrestler is out of the ring during the contest, the opponent shall immediately retire to the opposite side of the ring and remain until the wrestler has returned within the ring and the referee has instructed them to begin wrestling.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a wrestler leaves the ring and remains on the ring apron, the referee and timekeeper shall begin a count of ten.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A wrestler failing to return to the ring under §H(2) by the count of ten shall lose the match to the wrestler's opponent if the opponent is in the ring before the count of ten is concluded.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If both wrestlers leave the ring and remain on the ring apron through a count of ten, then the contest shall be ended with no winner declared.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If a wrestler leaves the ring and is on the floor outside of the ring, the referee and timekeeper shall begin a count of 20.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A wrestler failing to return to the ring under §H(5) by the count of 20 shall lose the match to the wrestler's opponent if the opponent is in the ring before the count of 20 is concluded.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>If both wrestlers leave the ring and remain on the floor outside of the ring through a count of 20, then the contest shall be ended with no winner declared.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Refusal or Inability to Continue. If a wrestler refuses or is physically unable to continue a match, the match shall be ended and the decision awarded to the wrestler's opponent.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>A wrestler may not touch or otherwise interfere with the referee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Tag Team Wrestling.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Tag team wrestling" means a contest between two teams each composed of two or more wrestlers.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The time limit for this type of contest shall be 60 minutes.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A team shall be awarded a fall when a member of the team scores a fall against a member of the opposing team.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A 2-minute rest period shall be permitted between falls.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A tag team contest shall be conducted as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The contest shall begin with one wrestler from each team inside the ring while the respective partners remain outside the ring on the apron;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The wrestler outside the ring may not enter the ring unless a fall is scored or his partner has tagged his hand;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>In order to be eligible to receive a tag, the wrestler's partner shall be outside the ring on the apron in the proper corner with both feet on the ring apron and only receive the tag over the top ring rope;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>When the tag is made, the wrestler making the tag shall leave the ring as the partner enters the ring;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Only two wrestlers from opposing teams shall be permitted to be in the ring at any one time;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>After the scoring of a fall a wrestler may relieve the partner;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>If a wrestler is unable to continue, the wrestler's partner shall continue the contest alone;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>The referee may call time after an injury to permit the injured wrestler to be removed from the ring; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>The decision in the match shall be governed under the guidelines in Regulation .03.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>In addition to the prohibited activities in §F, a wrestler may not:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Assist the partner or interfere in any manner with the opponents while outside the ring enclosure; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Release the rope provided in the team corner until officially tagged by the partner.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The referee shall warn a team of any prohibited conduct and may disqualify a team for persisting in prohibited conduct after a warning.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Timekeeping. A timekeeper:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Appointed by the Commission shall time all wrestling contests;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shall begin the beginning of the time limit of a contest upon the referee's signal and shall sound the gong at the referee's command.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>Reporting Time.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Wrestlers shall appear at least 1 hour before the scheduled contest begins.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Failure to comply with §M(1) shall be cause for disciplinary action.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>Time of Contest.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Wrestling contests shall begin not later than 8:30 p.m. and conclude before 11 p.m.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Commission may authorize different starting and concluding times.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>Seconds.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A wrestler may have a second who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Shall remain in the wrestler's corner outside the ring enclosure; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>May not interfere in any manner with the progress of the contest.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The referee may immediately eject from the ring area any second failing to comply with §O(1).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>P.</num>
      <text>Referee.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The referee shall have the authority to conduct the contest and enforce the regulations of the Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The referee's decision on any matter, whether arising under these regulations or not, shall be final.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Referees assigned to officiate a contest shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be properly attired 30 minutes before the scheduled time of the opening contest; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Remain attired and available until all matches have been concluded.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>Q.</num>
      <text>Wrestler's Equipment.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A wrestler shall be clothed in clean apparel with trunks and tights that are well-fitted and whole.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Two pairs of trunks, one over the other, may be worn.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If a wrestler wears shoes, they shall be fitted with soft tops, soft smooth soles, soft laces, and equipped with eyelets only.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A wrestler may not have any grease, lotion, or foreign substances on the body.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>R.</num>
      <text>Ring.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The ring shall have a minimum of three ropes with the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Lower rope 18 inches above the ring floor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Upper rope 52 inches above the ring floor; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Middle rope equidistant between the lower and upper ropes.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in §R(1), the ring shall meet the same requirements set forth in <cite path="09.14.05.01">COMAR 09.14.05.01</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>S.</num>
      <text>Ring Barrier.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A ring shall be enclosed within a barrier which shall be erected between the ring and the seating area in the arena.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The barrier shall be at least:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>6 feet away from the ring; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>4 feet away from the first row of the seating area.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The ring barrier shall conform to the following requirements:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be constructed of metal or other shatterproof material;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Be designed to prevent wrestlers from exiting through the barrier into the seating area during a contest;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Be built to a height of at least 42 inches from the floor of the arena; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Be stable.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The ring barrier shall be approved by the Commission or the Commission's representative before its use during a contest.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>T.</num>
      <text>"Ring enclosure" means the area within the ring barrier.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>U.</num>
      <text>Contests between a male and a female wrestler are prohibited, unless special permission is granted by the Commission after a review of the wrestlers' experience and physical fitness.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|14|08|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Physical Examinations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A wrestler shall be given a physical by a physician approved by the Commission before engaging in a contest.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A referee shall be given a physical before officiating a contest.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An inspector may permit a wrestler not examined under <cite path="09|14|08|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, to engage in a contest if the wrestler has been examined by a licensed physician within 15 days of the scheduled contest.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A wrestler shall submit, on a form provided by the Commission, the results of a physical examination performed within 21 days of the application for a license.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The examining physician may disqualify a contestant or referee for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Blood pressure elevation, systolic pressure or diastolic pressure outside of acceptable limits as determined by the examining physician;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An unhealed fracture or dislocation requiring splinting or casting; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any other medical condition that, in the physician's opinion, renders the contestant unfit to compete, or a referee to officiate a contest.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The ringside physician may remain at the contest after completing the physical examinations.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|14|08|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Records.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Licensees shall maintain true and accurate books of accounts showing receipts and distributions of funds in connection with a wrestling contest.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The records required under <cite path="09|14|08|.05|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall be made available upon request of the Commission's representative for inspection and audit.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Responsibility of Promoter.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A promoter shall be responsible to the Commission for the conduct of its representatives and employees.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The promoter shall be responsible for conducting wrestling contests in a safe, peaceable, and orderly fashion.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Violation of the Commission's regulations by a representative or employee of the promoter may be grounds for disciplinary action against the promoter.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|14|08|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Insurance Coverage.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each contestant shall be insured through a group insurance policy provided by the Commission as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Minimum medical expense coverage of $5,000; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Minimum coverage for death, dismemberment, or loss of sight of $5,000.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The terms and conditions of the coverage in <cite path="09|14|08|.07|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall be governed by the insurance policy between the Commission and its insurance carrier.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Nothing in this regulation shall preclude a promoter from providing coverage in excess of the coverage stated in <cite path="09|14|08|.07|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the promoter provides insurance coverage, a copy of the policy shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be given to the Commission not later than the final physical; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>List the Commission as an additional insured.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|4-205">Business Regulation Article, §4-205, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1965-10-01">Effective date: October 1, 1965</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-08-26">Subtitle revised effective August 26, 1985 (12:17 Md. R. 1705)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-12-06"><cite path="|09|14|08|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective December 6, 1993 (20:24 Md. R. 1864)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-09-03"><cite path="|09|14|08|.03|F.">Regulation .03F</cite> amended effective September 3, 1990 (17:17 Md. R. 2079)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-01-06"><cite path="|09|14|08|.03|U.">Regulation .03U</cite> amended effective January 6, 2005 (31:26 Md. R. 1861)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-09-03"><cite path="|09|14|08|.04|D.">Regulation .04D</cite> and E adopted effective September 3, 1990 (17:17 Md. R. 2079)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-05-22"><cite path="|09|14|08|.04|E.">Regulation .04E</cite> amended effective May 22, 2017 (44:10 Md. R. 471)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-09-03"><cite path="|09|14|08|.07|A.">Regulation .07A</cite> amended effective September 3, 1990 (17:17 Md. R. 2079)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
