<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>14</num>
  <heading>Kickboxing Regulations</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Applicable Boxing Regulations.</heading>
    <text>Unless otherwise indicated the regulations in COMAR Subtitle 14 pertaining to the sport of boxing shall apply to the sport of kickboxing.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Weight and Classes.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Commission recognizes the following weights and classes:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Atomweight — 112.9 pounds and under (51.3 kilograms and below);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Flyweight — 113 to 118 pounds (51.4—54.0 kilograms);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Bantamweight — 119 to 125.9 pounds (54.1—57.2 kilograms);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Featherweight — 126 to 132.9 pounds (57.3—60.4 kilograms);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Lightweight — 133 to 139.9 pounds (60.4—63.6 kilograms);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Light welterweight — 140 to 147.9 pounds (63.6—67.2 kilograms);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Welterweight — 148 to 155.9 pounds (67.3—70.8 kilograms);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Light middleweight — 156 to 163.9 pounds (70.9—74.5 kilograms);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Middleweight — 164 to 171.9 pounds (74.6—78.1 kilograms);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Light heavyweight — 172 to 179.9 pounds (78.2—81.4 kilograms);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Heavyweight — 180 to 194.9 pounds (81.5—88.3 kilograms);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Super Heavyweight — Over 195 pounds (over 88.3 kilograms).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The following weight spreads are permissible for matchmaking within each weight division. Any situation in which fighters from two different weight divisions are matched shall be approved by the Commission and the weight spread used will be that of the weight division of the lighter weight. Any weight spread greater than those listed below requires the advance approval of the Commission:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Atom and featherweight — Not more than 4 pounds (1.8 kilograms);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Bantamweight — Not more than 5 pounds (2.27 kilograms);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Featherweight — Not more than 6 pounds (2.72 kilograms);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Lightweight — Not more than 7 pounds (3.17 kilograms);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Light welterweight — Not more than 8 pounds (3.62 kilograms);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Welterweight — Not more than 9 pounds (4.08 kilograms);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Light middleweight — Not more than 10 pounds (4.53 kilograms);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Heavyweight — Not more than 12 pounds (5.44 kilograms);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Superweight — Not more than 14 pounds (6.34 kilograms).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Rounds.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Matches may not exceed nine 2-minute rounds with a 1-minute rest period between rounds.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Commission may permit an additional three rounds for the purpose of championship events.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Contestants' Safety Equipment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Male contestants shall wear:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A foul-proof groin protector;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Abdominal guard;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Footpads; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Shin guards.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Female contestants shall wear:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Foul-proof breast protectors; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A pelvic protective girdle which covers the pubic area, ovaries, coccyx, and side of hips.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Contestants shall meet the requirements of <cite path="09.14.04.07">COMAR 09.14.04.07</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Methods of Judging.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Judges shall score all contests and determine the winner through the use of the 10-point must system.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The 10-point must system shall be applied as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The winner of each round receives 10 points and the opponent a proportionally less number;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a round is even, each boxer shall receive 10 points; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Fractions of points may not be awarded.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>During each round the referee shall instruct the master scorekeeper of points assigned to any foul as it is committed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Following each round and at the termination of the contest, the referee shall collect the signed ballots of the judges and deliver them to the master scorekeeper, who shall tally each contestant's score and deduct any penalty points.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The contestant receiving the decision from a majority of the judges shall be declared the winner of the contest.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If neither boxer is granted the decision by a majority of the judges, the contest shall be declared a draw.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Minimum Kicking Requirement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each contestant shall execute a minimum of eight kicks during the course of each round.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If either contestant does not execute the minimum number of kicks, a penalty of one point per kick less than the eight-kick minimum shall be assessed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If both contestants fail to execute the minimum number of kicks, the round shall be declared a draw.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A contestant who fails in a contest of nine or more rounds to execute the minimum number of kicks in three rounds shall be disqualified.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A contestant who fails to execute five kicks per round shall be disqualified.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Fouls.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The following tactics are fouls and are forbidden:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Headbutts, elbow strikes, clubbing, kicks, or punches or any other strikes to the groin, attack with the knees, openhand attacks to the eyes or throat, and striking at the part of the body over the kidney or spine, or chopping the back of the neck or head;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Spitting, biting, or, in the referee's discretion, slapping;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Palm heel strikes (using the heel of the palm of the hand to deliver a blow to the face);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Arm bars (grabbing one arm with the other and pressing the grabbed arm against the opponent's throat);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Grabbing or holding onto an opponent's leg or foot, and grabbing or holding onto any part of the body;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Punching or kicking a contestant when he is down, when any part of his body, other than his feet, touches the floor; however, the opponent may continue to attack until the contestant has touched the floor with any part of the body other than the feet;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Leg checking (extending the leg to check an opponent's leg or to prevent him from kicking);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Purposely going down without being hit;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>The use of abusive language in the ring;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Any unsportsmanlike trick or action causing an injury to an opponent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Attacking on the break;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Attacking after the bell or gong has sounded ending the round, or when the opponent is out of the ring;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Intentionally pushing, shoving, or wrestling an opponent out of the ring with any part of the body;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>Kicking, striking, or kicksweeping below the belt, except blows to the side and back of thighs in a kung fu contest;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>Failure to make eight kicks per round;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>Any use of throws or any takedown not executed boot-to-boot;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>Continuous dropping of mouthpiece;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>Holding and hitting;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>Intentional evasion of contact;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>Hitting or flicking with an open glove.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Use of the tactics listed in §A(1)—(20) of this regulation shall result in a warning and a loss of points as determined by the referee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A contestant guilty of foul tactics in a contest may be disqualified.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Termination of a Contest.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A kickboxer suffering three knockdowns in any one round shall provide sufficient grounds to terminate a contest.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A referee may terminate the contest if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Either boxer fails to execute five kicks per round;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Either boxer fails to execute the minimum number of required kicks in three rounds; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>In the referee's opinion, the kickboxer is unable to continue the contest.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The senior physician may terminate a contest if, in his opinion, the health of either kickboxer is in serious jeopardy.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A kickboxer giving up a contest during a rest period between rounds shall be determined to lose the contest by technical knockout in the preceding round.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A kickboxer failing to respond to the bell or gong signaling the beginning of a round shall be determined to lose the contest by a technical knockout in the round begun by the bell or gong.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|4-205">Business Regulation Article, § 4-205, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-07-23">Effective date: July 23, 1990 (17:14 Md. R. 1756)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-02-17"><cite path="|09|14|14|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite> amended effective February 17, 1992 (19:3 Md. R. 303)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
