<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>17</num>
  <heading>Mixed Martial Arts — Amateur</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>General.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definition.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In this chapter, the following term has the meaning indicated.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Term Defined. "Organization" means an amateur kickboxing organization or an amateur mixed martial arts organization, as described in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|4-302">Business Regulation Article, §4-302(a)(3), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>All amateur mixed martial arts contests shall be conducted under the supervision of an organization.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Organization Supervising Amateur Mixed Martial Arts.</heading>
    <text>An organization seeking to supervise an amateur mixed martial arts contest shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Be approved by the Commission;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Ensure that all contests are conducted in accordance with these regulations regarding amateur mixed martial arts;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Have a Commission-approved training and certification program for officials;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Provide the Commission with evidence demonstrating:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A minimum of $100,000 in liability insurance coverage for the officials; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A minimum of $10,000 in medical insurance coverage for the amateur mixed martial arts contestants;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Provide the Commission with any other information it may request, provided the Commission request is neither arbitrary nor capricious;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Ensure the presence of two Commission-approved ringside physicians on-site and at ringside at all times during the amateur mixed martial arts contests being supervised by the organization;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Ensure the presence of the following equipment and personnel on-site at all times during the amateur mixed martial arts contests being supervised by the organization:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A stretcher;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A portable resuscitator or Ambubag with oxygen equipment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A hard cervical collar;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Endotracheal tubes with laryngoscope;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A portable defibrillator;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Advanced life support medications; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>An ambulance crew consisting of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>One emergency medical technician—paramedic (EMT-P); and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>One emergency medical technician—basic (EMT-B);</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Ensure that the officials used by the organization in the supervision of the amateur mixed martial arts contests have been approved by the Commission;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Ensure that none of the amateur mixed martial arts contestants receives any type of purse payment or other form of compensation other than Commission-approved travel expenses;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Obtain from each amateur mixed martial arts contestant a signed affidavit in which the amateur mixed martial arts contestant attests that he or she:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Has been trained in mixed martial arts, including the number of years of the training;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is sufficiently skilled, healthy, and prepared to compete in the scheduled amateur mixed martial arts contest;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Understands the dangers and risks attendant to participating in amateur mixed martial arts;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Waives any claim against the organization supervising the amateur mixed martial arts contest and the Commission related to any injury he or she sustains while participating in amateur mixed martial arts;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Is not under suspension in any jurisdiction or by any organization supervising amateur mixed martial arts contests;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Has never participated in a professional mixed martial arts contest; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Last participated in an amateur mixed martial arts contest on a specified date, and the result of that amateur mixed martial arts contest;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Obtain from the trainer of each amateur mixed martial arts contestant a signed affidavit in which the trainer attests to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The name, address, and telephone number of the gym or school in which the trainer performs his or her duties;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The length of time the trainer has trained the amateur mixed martial arts contestant; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The fact that the amateur mixed martial arts contestant:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is sufficiently skilled, healthy, and prepared to compete in the scheduled amateur mixed martial arts contest;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has never participated in a professional mixed martial arts contest; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Is not under suspension in any jurisdiction or by any organization supervising professional or amateur mixed martial arts;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Ensure that there are no exhibition bouts;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>Conduct a weigh-in, which shall be completed not later than 2 hours from the time the weigh-in begins;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>Ensure that each amateur mixed martial arts contestants has a:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Comprehensive physical examination conducted by a licensed physician, completed within 30 days of the amateur mixed martial arts contest, stating that the mixed martial arts contestant is healthy to compete in an amateur mixed martial arts contest;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Precontest physical examination conducted by a Commission-approved ringside physician; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Post-contest physical examination immediately following the conclusion of the contest in which the amateur mixed martial arts contestant competes;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>Conduct a precontest rules meeting, which shall be attended by each amateur mixed martial arts contestant scheduled to participate in a contest, and disqualify any amateur mixed martial arts contestant who fails to attend;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>P.</num>
      <text>Inspect the fighting area before the amateur mixed martial arts contest begins; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>Q.</num>
      <text>Supervise the hand wrapping and glove placement for each amateur mixed martial arts contestant.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Promoters.</heading>
    <text>The promoter of an amateur mixed martial arts contest shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Obtain sanctioning approval from an organization to supervise the contest, including the payment of any applicable fees;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Notify the organization of the date, time, and location of the amateur mixed martial arts contest at least 60 days prior to the date the contest is scheduled to be held;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Agree that the organization will be responsible for appointing the officials for the amateur mixed martial arts contests, and that the promoter will not be permitted to officiate the contests he or she promotes;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Be responsible for paying the officials the following fees, subject to increase if more than 15 contests are scheduled:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>One referee at a minimum of $100 per eight contests;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Three judges at a minimum of $100 each;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Two inspectors at a minimum of $75 each;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>One timekeeper at a minimum of $75;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>One scorekeeper at a minimum of $75; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Two ringside physicians at a minimum of $200 each; and</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Within 48 hours prior to a scheduled amateur mixed martial contest, submit to the organization, in writing:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A list containing the following for each amateur mixed martial arts contestant scheduled to participate in the contest:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Name;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Address;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Telephone number;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Age;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Height and weight;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Trainer;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Trainer's telephone number;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Training gym or school; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Amateur mixed martial arts record;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A certification that two Commission-approved ringside physicians will be on-site and at ringside at all times when competition is ongoing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A certification that the requirements of <cite path="|09|14|17|.02|G.">Regulation .02G of this chapter</cite> will be met;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A certification that the contests will be conducted under the amateur mixed martial arts regulations of the Commission;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The required medical insurance and accidental death insurance policies, as described in <cite path="|09|14|17|.02|D.">Regulation .02D of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Any other information the organization may reasonably request.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Additional Duties and Responsibilities of a Promoter.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A promoter shall provide the following equipment at an amateur mixed martial arts contest:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Gloves:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Approved by the organization;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Weighing from 4.0 to 7.5 ounces; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>In red and blue to denote the color for each corner;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Gauze and surgeon's tape for the contestant's wraps at each contest;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Shin and instep guards in various sizes, approved by the organization, in red and blue to denote the color for each corner;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Disposable gloves for each second, each referee, and each ringside physician; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>For each second, a form of identification indicating that person is allowed:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Access into the ring or fenced area; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>To be in a corner.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Prior to handing out equipment, a promoter shall clean each piece, inside and out, with antibacterial disinfectant wipes.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>After each amateur mixed martial arts contestant returns his or her equipment, a promoter shall clean each piece, inside and out, with antibacterial disinfectant wipes before issuing the equipment to another amateur mixed martial arts contestant.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>After all equipment is returned at the end of all of the contests, a promoter shall clean each piece of equipment, inside and out, with antibacterial disinfectant wipes.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A promoter shall make hand sanitizer available to all amateur mixed martial arts contestants, which shall be kept at the equipment table and used by each amateur mixed martial arts contestant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Prior to putting on his or her wraps; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>After his or her contest, when the wraps are removed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|14|17|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Physical Examination.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each amateur mixed martial arts contestant shall submit to the organization a comprehensive physical examination by a licensed physician, completed within 30 days of the amateur mixed martial arts contest, stating that the mixed martial arts contestant is healthy to compete in an amateur mixed martial arts contest.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Each amateur mixed martial arts contestant shall be examined by a Commission-approved ringside physician and be approved to participate prior to participating in an amateur mixed martial arts contest.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The failure of an amateur mixed martial arts contestant to be examined in accordance with §§A and B of this regulation shall result in the disqualification of the amateur mixed martial arts contestant.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Each amateur mixed martial arts contestant shall be examined by a Commission-approved ringside physician immediately after the amateur mixed martial arts contestant participates in an amateur mixed martial arts contest.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The failure of an amateur mixed martial arts contestant to be examined in accordance with <cite path="09|14|17|.05|D.">§D of this regulation</cite> shall result in a minimum 90-day suspension of the amateur mixed martial arts contestant.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Weight and Classes.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Men's Division. The Commission recognizes the following weights and classes in amateur mixed martial arts for male contestants:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Flyweight—up to 112 pounds;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Bantamweight—over 112 pounds to 118 pounds;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Super bantamweight—over 118 pounds to 122 pounds;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Featherweight—over 122 pounds to 126 pounds;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Super featherweight—over 126 pounds to 130 pounds;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Lightweight—over 130 pounds to 135 pounds;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Super lightweight—over 135 pounds to 140 pounds;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Welterweight—over 140 pounds to 147 pounds;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Super welterweight—over 147 pounds to 154 pounds;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Middleweight—over 154 pounds to 160 pounds;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Super middleweight—over 160 pounds to 167 pounds;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Light heavyweight—over 167 pounds to 175 pounds;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Super light heavyweight—over 175 pounds to 183 pounds;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>Cruiserweight—over 183 pounds to 190 pounds;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>Super cruiserweight—over 190 pounds to 195 pounds;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>Heavyweight—over 195 pounds to 210 pounds; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>Super heavyweight—all over 210 pounds.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Women's Division. The Commission recognizes the following weights and classes in amateur mixed martial arts for female contestants:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Flyweight—up to 105 pounds;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Bantamweight—over 105 pounds to 114 pounds;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Featherweight—over 114 pounds to 123 pounds;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Lightweight—over 123 pounds to 132 pounds;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Welterweight—over 132 pounds to 141 pounds;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Middleweight—over 141 pounds to 150 pounds;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Light heavyweight—over 150 pounds to 159 pounds;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Cruiserweight—over 159 pounds to 168 pounds; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Heavyweight—all over 168 pounds.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Weight differences between contestants may not exceed 7 pounds.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Weigh-In.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A weigh-in shall be completed within 2 hours from the time of its commencement.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If an amateur mixed martial arts contestant is not present at the weigh-in, the amateur mixed martial arts contestant may not be allowed to participate in the contest for which he or she was scheduled.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>At the weigh-in, if an amateur mixed martial arts contestant is over the allowable weight, a second weigh-in may be conducted not more than 1 hour after the initial weigh-in.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An amateur mixed martial arts contestant may not be permitted to lose more than 2 pounds between the first and second weigh-in.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If an amateur mixed martial arts contestant does not make weight or fails to attend the weigh-in, the contest in which the amateur mixed martial arts contestant was scheduled to participate shall be canceled.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Equipment, Attire, and Appearance.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An amateur mixed martial arts contestant shall use:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Hand wraps as described in <cite path="09.14.16.03|B.">COMAR 09.14.16.03B</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Open finger gloves, which shall weigh not less than 4 ounces and not more than 7.5 ounces;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A mouth guard;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Shin pads;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Instep pads; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>For male contestants, groin protection.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An amateur mixed martial arts contestant may not use:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shoes or sneakers;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shorts with a metal zipper;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A shirt, other than a female amateur mixed martial arts contestant, who shall wear a rashguard; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Grease, oil, balm, lotion, or an excessive amount of petroleum jelly on the face or body.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An amateur mixed martial arts contestant shall have properly trimmed fingernails and toenails.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Rounds.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Unless the organization agrees to fewer rounds per contest or rounds of a lesser duration, each amateur mixed martial arts contest shall consist of three 3-minute rounds with a 1-minute rest period between each round.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The organization shall prescribe the total number of rounds and the total number of amateur mixed martial arts contests a promoter is authorized to schedule.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Not more than one corner person for each amateur MMA contestant may be in the fighting area between rounds.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Seconds.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>More than three seconds may not be in the corner of each amateur mixed martial arts contestant.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>All seconds shall wear disposable gloves.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Legal Techniques.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The following techniques are permissible in amateur mixed martial arts while an amateur mixed martial arts contestant is in a standing position:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Closed hand strikes to head and body;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Kicking techniques to body;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Knees to body and legs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Throws, takedowns, and sweeps;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Standing submissions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Chokes;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Arm bars; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Shouldering.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The following techniques are permissible in amateur mixed martial arts while an amateur mixed martial arts contestant is on the ground:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Closed hand strikes to the body and legs; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Submissions restricted to those accomplished by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Chokes;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Arm bars; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Straight leg locks.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Illegal Techniques.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The following techniques are not permissible in amateur mixed martial arts while an amateur mixed martial arts contestant is in a standing position:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Striking an opponent with the elbows;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Striking with the knees to the head of an opponent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Kicking the knees of an opponent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Stomping the feet of an opponent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Striking the groin of an opponent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Striking the back of an opponent's head;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Striking the spine of an opponent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Slamming an opponent to the ground;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Throwing an opponent onto his or her head or neck;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Throwing an opponent against a joint;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Throwing an opponent out of the competition area;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Cranking the neck of an opponent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Pinching, biting, or gouging an opponent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>Holding onto the ropes of enclosure; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>Striking or kicking the kidney of an opponent.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The following techniques are not permissible in amateur mixed martial arts while an amateur mixed martial arts contestant is on the ground:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Any striking of an opponent's head;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Any striking of an opponent with an elbow;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Cranking of an opponent's neck;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Hooking an opponent's heel;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Locking an opponent's finger or toe;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Choking an opponent by the placement of a hand on the opponent's throat;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Smothering an opponent by the placement of a hand over the opponent's mouth;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Locking an opponent's spine;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Placing an opponent in a hammer lock;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Fish hooking an opponent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Striking an opponent in the groin;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Striking an opponent in the spine;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Slamming an opponent to the ground;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>Throwing an opponent out of the competition area;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>Pinching, biting, or gouging an opponent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>Twisting an opponent's leg, knee, or ankle; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>Striking or kicking the kidney of an opponent.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Injuries Sustained During Competition.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If an injury sustained during competition as a result of a legal maneuver is severe enough to terminate a contest, the injured amateur mixed martial arts contestant shall lose by a technical knockout.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If an injury sustained during competition as a result of an intentional foul is severe enough to terminate a contest, the amateur mixed martial arts contestant causing the injury shall be disqualified.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If an injury is sustained during competition as a result of an intentional foul and the contest is allowed to continue, the referee shall notify the scorekeeper to automatically deduct one or more points from the contestant who committed the foul.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If an injury sustained during competition as a result of an intentional foul causes the injured amateur mixed martial arts contestant to be unable to continue at a subsequent point in the contest:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The injured amateur mixed martial arts contestant shall win by technical decision if he or she is ahead on the scorecards at the time of the stoppage; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The contest shall be declared a technical draw if the injured amateur mixed martial arts contestant is even or behind on the score cards at the time of stoppage.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If an amateur mixed martial arts contestant injures himself or herself while attempting to foul his or her opponent:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The referee may not take any action in his or her favor; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The injury shall be treated in the same manner as an injury produced by a fair blow.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If an accidental foul occurs and the injured mixed martial arts contestant is able to continue, the referee shall notify both corners, the judges, and the organization of the accidental foul not later than the end of the round in which the accidental foul took place.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>If an injury sustained during competition as a result of an accidental foul is severe enough for the referee to stop the contest immediately or in a subsequent round, the contest shall result in a no contest if the accidental foul occurs before one round has been completed in a three-round contest.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>If an injury sustained during competition as a result of an accidental foul is severe enough for the referee to stop the contest immediately or in a subsequent round, the contest shall result in a technical decision awarded to the amateur mixed martial arts contestant who is ahead on the score cards at the time the contest is stopped if the contest is stopped after one round has been completed in a three-round contest.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>An incomplete round may not be scored.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Results of a Contest.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An amateur mixed martial arts contest may end under any of the results described in <cite path="09.14.16.12">COMAR 09.14.16.12</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The organization shall report the results of each amateur mixed martial arts contest, and any suspension resulting from the contest, to the mixed martial arts record keeper, certified by the Association of Boxing Commissions, within a time frame prescribed by the Association of Boxing Commissions.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Business Regulation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|4-205">4-205</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|4-302">4-302</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-07-06">Effective date: July 6, 2009 (36:13 Md. R. 898)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
