<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Registration Application and Maintenance</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|18|02|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Registration — General Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Requirement to Be Registered.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An individual may not operate a large family child care home unless:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Both the individual and the home meet the requirements for registration set forth in this subtitle; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The individual possesses a valid certificate of registration.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A large family child care home is not required to be registered if the provider:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is a relative of each child;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is a friend of each child’s parent or legal guardian and the care is provided on a nonregular basis of less than 20 hours a month; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Has received the care of the child from a child placement agency licensed by the Department of Human Services.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Conversion from a Small Center.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An individual currently licensed to operate a small center may apply to the office to convert the small center license to a certificate of registration to operate a large family child care home.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Application for conversion from a small center license shall be made as directed by the office.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A large family child care home that is converted from a small center shall continue to operate with or under the same:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Licensing status;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Approved child care capacity;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Approved months, days, and hours of operation;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Approved age ranges of children to be served;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Approved child care areas;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Variances, if any;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Special conditions or restrictions, if any; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Expiration date, if any.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Types of Registration. The office may issue:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An initial registration, which may be issued on a provisional basis pursuant to <cite path="|13A|18|02|.04|A.">Regulation .04A of this chapter</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A continuing registration, which may be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Issued on a provisional basis pursuant to <cite path="|13A|18|02|.04|A.">Regulation .04A of this chapter</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Replaced by a conditional registration pursuant to <cite path="|13A|18|02|.04|B.">Regulation .04B of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A certificate of registration:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>May not be transferred or applied to another individual, residence, or child care program; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Remains the property of the office.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The provider shall display conspicuously the certificate of registration in a location where it can easily be seen and read by parents whose children are in the provider's care or who are considering placing their children in the provider's care.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The provider shall surrender the certificate of registration to the office immediately when any of the following occurs or becomes effective:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The provider closes the child care home permanently;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The registration becomes invalid pursuant to <cite path="13A|18|02|.01|H.|(2)">§H(2) of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The registration is revoked;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The registration is suspended; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The initial registration expires, and:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The application for an initial or a continuing registration is denied; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The provider has not applied for a continuing registration.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Except as provided under <cite path="13A|18|02|.01|G.">§G of this regulation</cite>, a residence approved for use as a child care home may not also be used to operate a:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Child care home under a different registration; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Child care program that is subject to the requirements of COMAR 13A.15, COMAR 13A.16, or COMAR 13A.17.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A residence approved by the office before July 1, 2008, for the concurrent operation of more than one child care home or more than one type of child care program may continue to be used to operate those programs, except that, while concurrent approvals are in effect, the office may not approve a request by the provider for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An increase in child capacity;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A change in the hours of operation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A change in the ages of children served;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A change in the approved child care area; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A variance to a regulation under this subtitle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Residence of Applicant or Provider.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Unless currently approved for the purpose, the office may not approve a residence for use as a child care home that is not the primary residence of the family child care registration applicant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A child care home registration is subject to revocation if the home is no longer the primary residence of the provider.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>The provider may not allow an employee, staff member, substitute, or volunteer to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be assigned to a group of children or have access to a child in care until the individual has successfully passed the child abuse and neglect clearance and a federal or State criminal background check; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Be alone with a child or group of children until all checks have been successfully passed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|18|02|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Initial Registration.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An application for initial registration shall be filed with the office by an individual who wishes to operate a registered large family child care home and who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is not currently a registered large family child care home provider; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Has not been registered as a large family child care home provider for at least 6 months before the date of application.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Unless converting an existing small center to a large family child care home pursuant to <cite path="|13A|18|02|.01|A.|(2)">Regulation .01A(2) of this chapter</cite>, an applicant for an initial registration shall complete an orientation to large family child care home regulations that is offered or approved by the office.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Before the proposed opening date of the child care home, an applicant for initial registration shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provide the Social Security number of the applicant or, if the applicant does not have one, the individual taxpayer identification number of the applicant;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Ensure that an application for a federal and State criminal background check is submitted for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The applicant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Each employee, including substitutes and volunteers; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Each resident in the home who is 18 years old or older; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Submit to the office each item specified under <cite path="13A|18|02|.02|D.">§D of this regulation</cite> that was not submitted at the time the written application form was submitted.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The applicant shall submit:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Signed and notarized permission to examine records of abuse and neglect of children and adults for information about:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The applicant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Each employee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Each substitute;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Each volunteer;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Each resident in the home who is 18 years old or older; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>If required by the office, any other individual with access to the child care area during the approved hours of operation;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A medical evaluation for the applicant, each resident in the home, and each employee or staff member as specified under COMAR 13A.18.06.04 that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Was completed within 12 months before the date of application for registration;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Was conducted by a practicing physician, certified nurse practitioner, or registered physician’s assistant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Includes verification that the individual:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Is free of communicable tuberculosis, if indicated; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>If the applicant, is capable of performing the duties of their position; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Is signed or verified by the individual who conducted the evaluation;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Evidence of compliance with all applicable zoning and building codes;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A written plan of operation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>An emergency and disaster plan that meets the requirements of COMAR 13A.18.10.01A(3)(a) and (b);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Workers’ compensation insurance information;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>A complete personnel list, on a form supplied or approved by the office, and all related supporting documentation required by the office;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>A complete staffing pattern, on a form supplied or approved by the office, which specifies by staff name all child care assignments;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Documentation that all applicable training requirements set forth at COMAR 13A.18.06.05—.07 have been met by the applicant and each staff member;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>A 4-week menu of food to be served to children in care at the child care home;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>A written child discipline policy;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>If the child care home is located in a condominium or residence which requires homeowners’ association membership, written proof of homeowner’s liability insurance coverage as required by Maryland law;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Documentation that the home has met all lead safety requirements, as applicable, set forth in COMAR 13A.18.05.05;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>If the home is located in an apartment or other property that is rented or leased by the applicant, written authorization from the lessor, owner, or landlord permitting child care in the home; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>All other documentation required by law or regulation, including but not limited to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Proof of an on-site inspection and approval by the local fire authority having jurisdiction; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A building use and occupancy permit, if applicable.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If, within 6 months after the applicant submits a completed application form, the office has not received documentation that all applicable requirements of <cite path="13A|18|02|.02|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> have been met, the office may consider the application void.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Non-Maryland State Criminal Background Check. If an individual subject to the requirements of <cite path="13A|18|02|.02|C.|(1)">§C(1) of this regulation</cite> currently resides or has resided in a state other than Maryland within 5 years before the date of application for registration, the individual shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Apply for a state criminal background check to be performed by a duly authorized entity within that state; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Request the non-Maryland state entity performing the criminal background check to transmit the result of that background check directly to the Agency.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Continuing Registration.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Application for Continuing Registration. To obtain a continuing registration, a provider shall submit to the office before expiration of the initial registration:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A completed request, on a form supplied by the office, for continued registration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Documentation that the continued training requirements and the first aid and CPR certification requirements set forth in COMAR 13A.18.06.05—.07 have been met;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A medical evaluation that meets the requirements of <cite path="|13A|18|02|.02|D.|(2)">Regulation .02D(2) of this chapter</cite> for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The provider;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Each resident in the home who has child care responsibilities;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Each volunteer; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Each staff member;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A completed and notarized release of information form that permits the office to examine records of abuse and neglect of children and adults for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The provider;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Each provider substitute;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Each resident in the home who is 18 years old or older;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Each volunteer;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Each staff member; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>If required by the office, any other individual with regular access to the child care area during the approved hours of operation;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Documentation that the child care home has passed the most recent fire inspection required by the local fire authority having jurisdiction;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>If the home is located in an apartment or other property that is rented or leased by the applicant, written authorization from the lessor, owner, or landlord permitting the provider to continue providing child care in the home; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Any other documentation required by law or regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Maintenance of Continuing Registration.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>By the end of each 12-month period after the date of issuance of a continuing registration, the provider shall make available to the office documentation that the continued training requirements set forth in COMAR 13A.18.06.05—.07 have been met.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>By the end of each 24-month period after the date of issuance of a continuing registration, the provider shall make available to the office the items specified in §A(2)—(7) of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|18|02|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Provisional Status and Conditional Registration.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Provisional Status.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="13A|18|02|.04|A.|(2)">§A(2) of this regulation</cite>, to allow an applicant for an initial or a continuing registration additional time to meet all applicable requirements, the office may approve an initial or a continuing registration on a provisional basis for a period of up to 120 days after determining that the health and safety of the children in care are not in imminent danger.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An initial registration may not be approved if the office has not yet received evidence that the applicant and, as applicable, each individual specified in Regulation .02C(1) and D(1) of this chapter has successfully passed a federal and State criminal background check and a review of child and adult abuse and neglect records.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>At the end of the provisional period, if all requirements for the initial or continuing registration are not met due to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Failure by the applicant to take an action necessary to achieve compliance, the office shall deny the application for registration; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Circumstances beyond the control of the applicant, the office may reapprove the provisional status of the registration for one or more additional periods of up to 120 days per period, except that provisional registration status may not be continued for more than 24 months after the start of the first provisional period.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the office denies a certificate of registration at the end of the provisional period, the applicant or provider does not have a valid registration and shall cease operating.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Conditional Registration.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a provider who holds a continuing registration fails to remedy a violation as required, the office may replace the continuing registration with a conditional registration for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A period of up to 120 days; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Upon approval by the Agency's central office, an additional period of up to 120 days.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Upon replacing a continuing registration with a conditional registration, the office shall issue to the provider a revised certificate of registration that states the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Date that the continuing registration was replaced by the conditional registration;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Period of time of the conditional registration; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Requirements for reinstating the continuing registration.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Immediately upon receipt of the revised certificate of registration, the provider shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Remove from display in the child care home the certificate of continuing registration that was originally issued; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Display the revised certificate as required by <cite path="|13A|18|02|.01|D.">Regulation .01D of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the provider satisfies all requirements for reinstatement of the continuing registration, the office shall promptly notify the provider about the reinstatement of the continuing registration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If the provider fails to satisfy all requirements for reinstatement of the continuing registration within the specified period of time, the office may suspend or revoke the conditional registration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Resumption of Service.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An application to resume service shall be filed by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A registered provider who wishes to operate a large family child care home at an address different from that specified on the current certificate of registration; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An individual who was previously registered by the office to operate a large family child care home and who wishes to re-register, if the last effective date of the previous registration is within 6 months of the application.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The application to resume service shall meet all initial registration application requirements, except that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An abbreviated application form supplied by the office shall be used; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The office may accept as applicable to the new application the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Individual's original completion of the orientation specified in <cite path="|13A|18|02|.02|B.">Regulation .02B of this chapter</cite>, if required;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Original medical reports submitted for the applicant, each resident in the home who will have child care responsibilities, and each staff member if the reports are based on medical evaluations completed within 12 months of the new application;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Results of the original criminal background checks conducted pursuant to <cite path="|13A|18|02|.02|C.|(1)">Regulation .02C(1) of this chapter</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Results of the original child and adult abuse and neglect clearances conducted pursuant to <cite path="|13A|18|02|.02|D.|(1)">Regulation .02D(1) of this chapter</cite>, if the clearances were completed within 12 months of the application; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Approved continued training completed within 12 months of the application.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|18|02|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Response of the Office to Application.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as set forth at <cite path="13A|18|02|.06|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, upon receiving the completed application and all required documentation, whether for an initial registration or a continuing registration, the office shall determine compliance with the requirements of this subtitle by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Evaluating the application and required documentation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Interviewing the applicant;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Inspecting the residence proposed for use as a child care home;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Evaluating the information provided by State and federal criminal background investigations; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Evaluating the information provided from records of child and adult abuse and neglect.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Upon completing the procedures in <cite path="13A|18|02|.06|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, the office shall, within 30 days:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Issue a certificate of registration to operate the child care home in accordance with the provisions of this subtitle if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The application is complete;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>All required documentation has been received; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The office is satisfied that the applicant and the residence meet the requirements of this subtitle;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Deny the certificate of registration if the office determines that the applicant or the residence does not meet the requirements of this subtitle; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Issue a provisional certificate of registration in accordance with <cite path="|13A|18|02|.04|A.">Regulation .04A of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Within 30 days of receipt of a completed application for conversion of a small center license to a large family child care home registration pursuant to <cite path="|13A|18|02|.02">Regulation .02 of this chapter</cite>, the office shall issue a certificate of registration to the applicant.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|18|02|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Denial of a Registration Application.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The office may deny a certificate of registration if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The applicant, a resident, any staff member, or the residence in which child care is to be provided fails to meet the requirements of this subtitle;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An evaluation of the application or any documents required by the office reveals that the applicant reported false information;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The applicant has a documented history of serious or repeated regulatory violations of this subtitle or other regulations of any state concerning the care of children or adults that demonstrates an inability to provide for the health or safety of children;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The applicant has had a child care home registration, a child care center license, or a letter of compliance denied or revoked before the date on the registration application, unless the office is satisfied that the condition that was the basis for the denial or revocation has been corrected;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The applicant prevents the office from completing its responsibilities for registration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Upon evaluating the physical condition of the residence and surrounding premises, the office finds conditions that are unsafe or unhealthy;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>An evaluation of the medical report or other information about the applicant or a resident indicates that the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Physical or mental health of the applicant or resident may pose a risk to children;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Applicant is unable to care for children; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Applicant submitted false or altered medical documentation for the applicant, resident, substitute, or employee for consideration by the office;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>In addition to the requirements set forth at <cite path="13A|18|02|.07|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, an evaluation of the criminal record of the applicant, an employee including a substitute, volunteer, or a resident in the home reveals that the individual has a criminal conviction, probation before judgment disposition, or not criminally responsible disposition, or is awaiting a hearing for a criminal charge that indicates behavior harmful to children;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>An evaluation of the information provided in records of abuse and neglect of children and adults reveals that the applicant, a staff member including a substitute, a volunteer, or a resident is identified as responsible for abuse or neglect of children or adults, or is currently under investigation for alleged acts of abuse or neglect of children or adults;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Based on an interview with the applicant or an evaluation of other pertinent information, the office concludes that the applicant cannot provide for the health, safety, or welfare of children in care on the basis of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Substantial, credible evidence of the applicant's abuse of alcohol or controlled dangerous substances, mental instability, or other condition; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Other pertinent information received by the office which creates reasonable doubt as to the applicant's ability to provide child care in accordance with this subtitle.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>The applicant is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Providing treatment foster care to a child in other than a preadoptive capacity; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Filing an application for initial registration as a family child care provider.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The office shall deny a certificate of registration if an applicant or resident has received at any time a conviction, a probation before judgment disposition, a not criminally responsible disposition, or a pending charge for the commission or attempted commission of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A crime involving:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A child;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Cruelty to animals;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Domestic violence of an intimate partner or spouse; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A weapons or firearms violation of federal or state laws;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A sex offense;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A violent crime classified as a felony, including physical assault or battery;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Abduction or kidnapping;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Abuse of a child or an adult;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Confinement of an unattended child;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Manufacturing, distributing, or dispensing a controlled dangerous substance if committed during the preceding 5 years;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Perjury;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>A crime involving pornography;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Possession with intent to manufacture, distribute, or dispense a controlled dangerous substance if committed during the preceding 5 years; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Reckless endangerment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The office shall deny a certificate of registration if an applicant or resident has received at any time a felony conviction for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Murder;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Spousal abuse; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Arson.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The office shall deny a certificate of registration upon notification that the applicant is in noncompliance with Child Support Enforcement requirements pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-119">Family Law Article, §10-119</cite>.3, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If the office denies an application, the office shall notify the applicant in writing of the denial stating:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The reason for denial;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The specific regulation with which the applicant has failed to comply that is the basis for the denial;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>That the applicant is entitled to a fair hearing; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The procedure to be used if the applicant wishes to request a hearing to appeal the decision of the office.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If an evaluation of criminal records or records of abuse and neglect of children or adults reveals that a person designated by the applicant as a staff member may pose a risk to children in care, the office, instead of denying the registration certificate, may require the provider to designate another staff member.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Denial Before Complete Application.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The office may deny an application for registration at any point during the application process if, following evaluation of information received to that point, the office determines that a basis for denial exists as set forth in §A, B, C, or D of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the office decides to deny the application before the application process is complete, the office shall send written notice of that decision to the applicant within 30 calendar days after making the decision.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|18|02|.08">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Voluntary Surrender of Registration.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A provider may voluntarily surrender a child care home registration at any time by notifying the office in writing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If a registration is surrendered pursuant to <cite path="13A|18|02|.08|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The office shall note in the provider's file that the registration has been voluntarily surrendered; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The provider shall return the surrendered certificate of registration to the office.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Education Article, §§9.5-301—9.5-308, 9.5-310—9.5-312, 9.5-320, 9.5-321 and 9.5-414; Family Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|5-550">5-550</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|5-558">5-558</cite>; <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-333">General Provisions Article, §4-333</cite>; <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ghu|1-202">Human Services Article, §1-202</cite>; Annotated Code of Maryland<br/>Agency Note: Federal Statutory Reference — Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (42 U.S.C. §12101 et seq.);<br/>Child Care Development Block Grant (45 CFR Parts 98 and 99 and 42 U.S.C. 9858 et seq.);<br/>Social Security Act §418 (42 U.S.C. 618)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-02-06">Effective date: February 6, 2012 (39:2 Md. R. 142)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-01-13"><cite path="|13A|18|02|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective January 13, 2020 (47:1 Md. R. 17)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-06-24"><cite path="|13A|18|02|.01|E.">Regulation .01E</cite> amended effective June 24, 2013 (40:12 Md. R. 1043)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-06-24"><cite path="|13A|18|02|.01|H.">Regulation .01H</cite> adopted effective June 24, 2013 (40:12 Md. R. 1043)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-01-13"><cite path="|13A|18|02|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective July 20, 2015 (42:14 Md. R. 884); January 13, 2020 (47:1 Md. R. 17)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-04-14"><cite path="|13A|18|02|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective April 14, 2014 (41:7 Md. R. 423)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-11-13"><cite path="|13A|18|02|.02|C.">Regulation .02C</cite> amended effective November 13, 2023 (50:22 Md. R. 977)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-01-13"><cite path="|13A|18|02|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective January 13, 2020 (47:1 Md. R. 17)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-07-20"><cite path="|13A|18|02|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite> amended effective April 14, 2014 (41:7 Md. R. 423); July 20, 2015 (42:14 Md. R. 884)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-01-13"><cite path="|13A|18|02|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite> amended effective July 20, 2015 (42:14 Md. R. 884); January 13, 2020 (47:1 Md. R. 17)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-01-13"><cite path="|13A|18|02|.05|B.">Regulation .05B</cite> amended effective July 20, 2015 (42:14 Md. R. 884); January 13, 2020 (47:1 Md. R. 17)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-01-13"><cite path="|13A|18|02|.06|C.">Regulation .06C</cite> amended effective January 13, 2020 (47:1 Md. R. 17)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-01-13"><cite path="|13A|18|02|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective January 13, 2020 (47:1 Md. R. 17)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-04-18"><cite path="|13A|18|02|.07|B.">Regulation .07B</cite>, C amended effective April 18, 2022 (49:8 Md. R. 500)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-01-13"><cite path="|13A|18|02|.08|A.">Regulation .08A</cite> amended effective January 13, 2020 (47:1 Md. R. 17)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
