<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>General</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Application.</heading>
    <text>The Rural Legacy Board shall develop an application form for use by sponsors applying for rural legacy area designation and Rural Legacy Program funding. The application shall include:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definitions of key terms;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An overview of the rural legacy process;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A description of the criteria for the evaluation of applications;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A description of the application and review process;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A description of acquisition procedures;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A description of permitted project costs;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A description of the process for the reimbursement or advance payment of project costs;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>A description of project completion responsibilities;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>A description of the model system for appraising easement values and the fair market value of fee simple property interests;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>A description of the process by which transferable development rights may be acquired; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>All forms which are required to complete a rural legacy application.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Project Costs.</heading>
    <text>The Rural Legacy Board shall reimburse, or provide for the advance payment of, the following costs incurred by a sponsor of an approved rural legacy plan:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Direct costs, which means the actual costs of the real property interests acquired by a sponsor of an approved rural legacy plan;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Incidental costs, which means costs relating to the acquisition of real property interests, such as the costs of surveys, appraisals, title searches, and legal fees;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Administrative costs; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Program compliance costs.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Approval and Amendment of Rural Legacy Areas and Plans.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A rural legacy plan may encompass a geographic area the same size as, or smaller than, a rural legacy area.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Rural Legacy Board may not approve an:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Application without the approval of each local government whose jurisdiction is encompassed in whole or in part by the rural legacy area; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Amendment to an application without the approval of each local government whose jurisdiction is encompassed in whole or in part by the amendment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Time Limitation on Funds.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Rural Legacy Board may establish time limitations on the use of funds within the period of time stipulated within a grant agreement.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Rural Legacy Board may monitor the timely expenditure of funds by a sponsor and reallocate any unused funds.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Land Trusts.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Land purchased in fee with rural legacy funds by a land trust shall be protected by a conservation easement held by a qualified federal, State, county, or municipal conservation organization.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A conservation easement purchased with rural legacy funds by a land trust shall be jointly held by a qualified federal, State, or local conservation organization as co-grantee.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Transfer of Development Rights (TDRs).</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The title to a transferable development right (TDR) acquired by a sponsor shall be recorded jointly in the name of the sponsor or easement grantee and the Rural Legacy Board, and shall be described in detail in the project agreement.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Within 30 days of acquisition, the titleholders shall file the TDR in the land records of the local jurisdiction where the land is located, with a copy filed in the Maryland State Archives.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A TDR acquired with rural legacy funds shall only be acquired, held, and resold in accordance with the rules of the local TDR program under which it was acquired.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|05|01|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Appraisal of Easement Values.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Rural Legacy Board may develop a model easement valuation methodology, which shall place value on the following characteristics of a property:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Real estate development rights;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Agricultural and commercial forestry qualities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Natural resource qualities; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Features unique or specific to the objectives of, and conditions within, each rural legacy area, such as:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The contribution of a property to resource-based economies other than agriculture and forestry,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A measure of the development pressure on a property, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The location of a property within a rural legacy area.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A model easement valuation methodology approved by the Rural Legacy Board shall reflect each of the attributes described in <cite path="08|05|01|.07|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> based on its relative importance in the rural legacy area or to the rural legacy plan.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A sponsor may develop its own easement valuation methodology, which shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Reflect the agricultural, forestry, and natural resource qualities the easement is designed to protect;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Reflect the fair market values of properties in the rural legacy area; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Relate to the range of easement values paid by the Maryland Agricultural Land Preservation Foundation and other easement purchasing programs.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|5-9">Natural Resources Article, §5-9</cite>A-03, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1997-12-29">Regulations <cite path="|08|05|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|08|05|01|.07">.07</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective August 22, 1997 (24:19 Md. R. 1334); adopted permanently effective December 29, 1997 (24:26 Md. R. 1757)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
