<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Religious Services</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Business day” means a day other than a Saturday, Sunday, State Holiday, or day on which State administrative offices are closed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Ceremonial meal” means a religious meal associated with the commemorating of a formal religious or sacred observance.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Commissary manager” means the individual responsible for a facility commissary or the Department of Public Safety and Correctional Services (Department) contract monitor for a commissary vendor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Enhanced meal” means a dinner meal with additional portions of food provided in addition to the regular meal to meet the minimum daily nutritional needs during a religious observance of fasting.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Halal diet” means food that is certified by a recognized Muslim Certification Agency.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“High religious observance” means the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Jewish high holy days of Rosh Hashanah, Yom Kippur, and Passover; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Islamic high holy month of Ramadan.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Inmate.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Inmate” means an individual committed to the custody of the Department.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Inmate” does not include an individual detained without having been committed to the Department.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Kosher diet” means food that is certified by a recognized Orthodox Jewish Certification Agency.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“Passover” means a holiday that celebrates the deliverance of the ancient Hebrews from slavery.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>“Registered religious preference” is the faith group with which the inmate is affiliated within the Department’s Religious Services Program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>“Religious diet” means a dietary option that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Meets or exceeds established nutritional standards based on the Dietary Reference Intake (DRI), Food and Nutrition Board, Institute of Medicine, Nutritional Academies, for ages 19-50 years old and above, with the exception of iron for pregnant females;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Conforms to dietary restrictions of the inmate’s designated faith group; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Cannot be met by the Department’s standard menu.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>“Seasonal observance” means a worship or celebration recognized annually at a specific time of year, which, unlike a routine observance, has specific value to a particular religious group.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Seder Plate.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Seder Plate” means a ceremonial plate for the Seder service that is separate from the special Passover meal and is provided during Passover Seder service.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Seder Plate” for the Jewish, Messianic House of Yahweh, Assemblies of Yahweh, and Hebrew Israelites faith groups consists of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Matzo (unleavened bread);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Roasted lamb bone;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Bitter herb horseradish and romaine lettuce;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Parsley and celery or boiled potato;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Chopped apples and nuts (mixed) with grape juice; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>A cup of salt water.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Chaplaincy.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Exercise of Religious Belief.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within security and program limitations, the Commissioner of Correction, Commissioner of Pretrial and Detention Services, and the Director of Patuxent Institution shall ensure that each inmate has reasonable opportunity to exercise personal religious beliefs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Commissioner of Correction, Commissioner of Pretrial and Detention Services, and the Director of Patuxent Institution shall ensure that each religion receives equal access to religious services.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Inmate participation in religious programming is voluntary.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner of Correction, Commissioner of Pretrial and Detention Services, and the Director of Patuxent Institution shall ensure that religious services are conducted by chaplains or approved religious volunteers, or both, and are available to the general inmate population.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Religious activities are subject to supervision by facility security staff.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Ceremonial Meal.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A holy day or seasonal observance may be held with a meal if the meal is part of the holy day or observance based on religious tradition or mandate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Each Department-recognized religious faith group may have one ceremonial meal in a calendar year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An inmate may attend only one ceremonial meal during the calendar year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A ceremonial meal shall be served in the food service facility, except when the managing official, or a designee, approves another location.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Facility food services is the only source of food items for use with a ceremonial meal.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The facility chaplain shall coordinate with Food Services to ensure:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Appropriate ritual food items are available for the ceremonial meal; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>At least 60 days are afforded for preparation for the ceremonial meal.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Holy day or seasonal observances may be held for inmates in special confinement housing if operational capabilities of the facility permit without jeopardizing facility safety and security.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="12|03|02|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Religious Diet Program — General.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Department shall make reasonable accommodations to provide inmates in each correctional facility under the Department’s authority with dietary options that meet accepted religious dietary requirements.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Department’s Religious Diet Program (RDP) consists of the following two meal platforms:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Halal diet that shall be offered to an inmate who has designated the inmate’s religious faith as one of the following Islamic faith groups:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Shi’ite;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Sunni;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Nation of Islam (all recognized groups);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Moorish Science Temple (all recognized groups); or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Other recognized religions that have the same basic tenets that require the Halal diet; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Kosher diet that shall be offered to an inmate who has designated the inmate’s religious faith as one of the following faith groups:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Jewish;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>House of Yahweh;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Assemblies of Yahweh;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Messianic Jewish;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Hebrew Israelites; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Other recognized religions that have the same basic tenets that require the Kosher diet.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In October of each calendar year, the facility chaplain, or a designee, shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Prepare an annual religious services plan for the next calendar year (January—December);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Include in the religious services plan the dates for high religious observance, seasonal observances, fasting periods, and programs for each recognized faith group that requires a special ceremonial diet; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Distribute the annual religious services plan to the facility’s managing official, or a designee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Director of Food Service, or a designee, shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Ensure that the RDP dietary platforms are certified by an appropriate authority;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Ensure that the RDP meets or exceeds minimum daily nutritional requirements established and approved by the Academy of Nutrition and Dietetics as they relate to food service in a correctional facility;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Provide correctional dietary managers with a copy of the RDP menu, as well as announcements, updates, and changes to ensure that the RDP maintains compliance with both religious and nutritional dietary requirements;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Ensure that correctional dietary managers and food service contractors are adhering to RDP requirements regarding the use of designated Kosher emblem tape; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Ensure that a correctional dietary manager does not alter the RDP menu except where seasonal availability of fresh produce or unexpected unavailability of canned or frozen food items warrants acceptable substitution, as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A correctional dietary manager may make temporary nutritionally equal substitutions based on the availability of seasonal produce; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Substitutions for the RDP shall be in accordance with the Department’s Dietary Program.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An inmate:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>May abstain from regularly offered food items that the inmate believes to be prohibited by the inmate's religion; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Abstaining from certain food items under <cite path="12|03|02|.03|E.|(1)">§E(1) of this regulation</cite> may:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Still achieve a balanced diet by eating food items that are not prohibited by religious beliefs that are being offered to the inmate population;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Not be served pork, pork items, and foods prepared with pork renderings; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Choose to participate in the master cycle meat menu or the lacto-ovo vegetarian menu.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>An inmate who voluntarily withdraws or is involuntarily removed from the RDP in accordance with provisions under Regulations .05 and .06 of this chapter:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>May request a lacto-ovo vegetarian menu for nonreligious reasons; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>May not be reconsidered for the RDP until existing RDP-related sanctions end and the inmate files a request in accordance with <cite path="|12|03|02|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>An inmate designated to have a diet based on medical needs or a special management diet may not participate in the RDP.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>During a declared emergency and for up to 72 hours from the start of a lockdown of a housing area or facility that houses an RDP participating inmate, the facility’s managing official may suspend delivery of meals that are in compliance with RDP requirements.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>The facility shall provide an RDP bag lunch for an RDP inmate assigned to a work crew outside the facility.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="12|03|02|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Requesting and Processing an Inmate’s Request to Participate in the Religious Diet Program.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An inmate seeking to participate in the RDP shall submit a completed Religious Diet Application Form to the facility chaplain, or a designee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Upon receipt of a Religious Diet Application Form under <cite path="12|03|02|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, the facility chaplain, or a designee, shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Meet with the inmate to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Review with the inmate the requested RDP platform;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Review with the inmate the Religious Diet Agreement, specifically the violation and sanction section;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Inform the inmate that violation of RDP requirements may result in the inmate’s involuntarily suspension from the RDP independent of the inmate disciplinary process;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Inform the inmate that the inmate is required to reapply for participation in the RDP every 2 years;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Obtain information from the inmate concerning the inmate’s registered religious preference and the reasoning for the request to participate in the RDP; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Discuss other applicable information used in connection with the RDP request;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Use information provided by the inmate in connection with the inmate’s records and other available documentation to determine if the inmate is a designated participant in a Department-recognized faith group that requires a diet that can only be satisfied by the RDP; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Use forms approved by the Chief of Religious Services to record:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Information obtained from the inmate; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>RDP information provided to the inmate.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>When processing an inmate’s request to participate in the RDP, the facility chaplain, or a designee:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall complete a review of all forms and applicable information obtained in connection with the inmate’s RDP application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shall, based on the available information concerning the application to participate in the RDP, determine if the inmate is eligible to participate in the RDP based on the inmate’s recognized participation in a religious faith group listed under <cite path="|12|03|02|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>May not deny an inmate’s application to participate in the RDP because the inmate is assigned to special confinement housing or a medical unit;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>May deny an inmate’s application to participate in the RDP because the inmate falsified information;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>May require additional information from the inmate to complete or supplement the inmate’s RDP application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Shall decide based on all information available and considered to approve or deny the inmate’s RDP application; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Shall document the decision to approve or deny the inmate’s request to participate on the RDP application.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Upon completion of an inmate’s request to participate in the RDP, the facility chaplain or a designee shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a request for RDP participation is denied:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Meet with the inmate and provide the reason for the denial;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Record the date of the meeting to discuss the denial on the form approved by the Chief of Religious Services; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Ensure that the completed paperwork is forwarded to Case Management for inclusion in the inmate’s base file; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a request for RDP participation is approved:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Meet with the inmate to obtain the inmate’s signature on a Religious Diet Agreement Form;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Forward a copy of the inmate’s completed Religious Diet Agreement Form to the Correctional Food Services manager for the inmate’s facility; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Forward the completed paperwork to Case Management for inclusion in the inmate’s base file.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="12|03|02|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Voluntary Withdrawal from the RDP.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An inmate may voluntarily withdraw from participation in the RDP.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An inmate voluntarily withdrawing from the RDP, as soon as possible after deciding not to participate, shall notify the facility chaplain, in writing on a form approved by the Chief of Religious Services:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>That the inmate is voluntarily withdrawing from the RDP; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The reason for withdrawing from the RDP.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Upon receipt of notification under <cite path="12|03|02|.05|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, the facility chaplain, or a designee, shall meet with the inmate submitting the notification to advise the inmate that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Once voluntarily removed from the RDP, except for provisions under <cite path="12|03|02|.05|C.|(3)">§C(3) of this regulation</cite>, the inmate may not re-apply for RDP participation for 1 year from the date voluntary removal was accepted;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Except for provisions under <cite path="12|03|02|.05|C.|(3)">§C(3) of this regulation</cite>, once an inmate has requested voluntary withdrawal from the RDP three times, the inmate may not re-apply for participation in the RDP until after 2 years from the date of the last voluntary withdrawal from the RDP; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An inmate voluntarily withdrawing from the RDP may continue to participate in other faith group religious observances and ceremonial meals.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A facility chaplain, or a designee, processing an inmate’s voluntary withdrawal from the RDP shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Record the approval on a form approved by the Chief of Religious Services;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Record the meeting and conditions of the inmate’s voluntary withdrawal discussed with the inmate as required under <cite path="12|03|02|.05|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> on a form approved by the Chief of Religious Services;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Within 5 business days of the date the inmate’s voluntary withdrawal request is processed:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Notify the correctional dietary manager of the inmate’s withdrawal; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Provide the correctional dietary manager with an updated list of RDP participants; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Forward the completed forms recording the voluntary withdrawal to Case Management for inclusion in the inmate’s base file.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="12|03|02|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Involuntary Suspension from the RDP.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An inmate may be involuntarily removed from the RDP independent of the inmate disciplinary process for violating the agreed upon conditions of participation in the RDP.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An employee with knowledge that an inmate enrolled in the RDP has consumed or purchased from the commissary a food item that is not part of the inmate’s approved RDP dietary platform shall report the allegation:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In a manner or on a form approved by the Chief of Religious Services; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>To the facility chaplain, or a designee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Upon receipt of an allegation under <cite path="12|03|02|.06|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, the facility chaplain, or a designee, shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Review the allegation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Handle the allegation in accordance with provisions under <cite path="12|03|02|.06|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A facility chaplain, or a designee, handling an alleged RDP agreement violation shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Meet and discuss the alleged RDP agreement violation with the inmate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Determine if the inmate violated the agreed-to RDP conditions; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If determining that a violation of the RDP conditions did occur, except for provisions under <cite path="|12|03|02|.05|C.|(3)">Regulation .05C(3) of this chapter</cite>, determine a sanction as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>First offense, the inmate shall be:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Counseled regarding commissary or food items that may be purchased or consumed under the RDP;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Required to sign a new RDP agreement acknowledging understanding the consequences of a second offense; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Permitted to continue in the RDP;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Second offense, the inmate shall be:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Counseled regarding commissary or food items that may be purchased or consumed under the RDP;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Suspended from the RDP for 90 days; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Upon completion of the 90-day suspension, required to sign a new RDP agreement acknowledging understanding the consequences of a third offense before being permitted to participate in the RDP following the 90-day suspension; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Third offense, the inmate shall be:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Counseled regarding commissary or food items that may be purchased or consumed under the RDP;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Suspended from the RDP for 1 year; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Upon completion of the 1-year suspension, required to reapply to participate in the RDP in accordance with procedures established under this chapter;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Meet with the affected inmate to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Discuss the decision, any imposed sanctions, and the impact of continued violations of the agreed-to RDP conditions; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Obtain the inmate’s signature on a new RDP Agreement form;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Document the process and meetings in a manner or on a form approved by the Chief of Religious Services; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>If after 5 business days from the date the inmate is notified of a decision under <cite path="12|03|02|.06|D.|(3)">§D(3) of this regulation</cite>, the inmate does not appeal the facility chaplain’s, or a designee’s, action:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Forward a copy of the documentation to Case Management for inclusion in the inmate’s base file; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the decision results in changes to notification previously made to the facility’s correctional dietary manager, within 5 business days of the end of the period for filing an appeal, provide written notification of the appropriate updates to the facility correctional dietary manager.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Occurrences of involuntary suspension from the RDP continue to accrue for the purpose of progressive sanctions under <cite path="12|03|02|.06|D.|(3)">§D(3) of this regulation</cite> regardless of an inmate’s voluntary withdrawal from the RDP.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>An inmate involuntarily suspended from the RDP may continue to participate in other faith group religious observances and ceremonial meals.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="12|03|02|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Appeal of Involuntary Suspension from the RDP.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An inmate may appeal a facility chaplain’s, or a designee’s, decision made in accordance with <cite path="|12|03|02|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An inmate filing an appeal under <cite path="12|03|02|.07|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>File the appeal within 5 business days of the date of the adverse decision;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Submit the appeal on a form or in a manner approved by the Chief of Religious Services to the facility chaplain, or a designee; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Remain in the RDP during the appeal process.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Within 10 business days of receipt of an appeal under <cite path="12|03|02|.07|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, the facility chaplain, or a designee, shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Attach the inmate’s appeal to other forms completed as part of the action taken by the facility chaplain, or a designee, to remove the inmate from the RDP;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide a written recommendation regarding the appeal that includes the reason and support for the recommendation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Forward the documents to the facility’s managing official, or a designee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Within 10 business days of receipt of an appeal under <cite path="12|03|02|.07|C.|(3)">§C(3) of this regulation</cite>, the managing official, or a designee, shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Review and, if necessary, obtain additional information concerning the documents received;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Decide to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Affirm the original decision and sanction;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Affirm the original decision and reduce the original sanction; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Overturn the original finding that a violation occurred;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Provide a written decision that includes the reason and support for the decision; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Forward the documents to the facility chaplain, or a designee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Upon receipt of a decision under <cite path="12|03|02|.07|D.|(4)">§D(4) of this regulation</cite>, the facility chaplain, or a designee, shall comply with applicable requirements established under <cite path="12|03|02|.07|D.|(2)">§D(2) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Re-admittance to the RDP Following Involuntary Suspension.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An inmate who was previously involuntarily suspended from the RDP for 1 year may re-apply to participate in the RDP.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An inmate reapplying for the RDP following being involuntarily suspended from the RDP for 1 year shall be readmitted if the inmate:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Has completed the period of suspension related to the involuntary suspension;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Makes a request in accordance with provisions under <cite path="|12|03|02|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Is approved for the RDP in accordance with provisions under <cite path="|12|03|02|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>RDP Commissary Products.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>RDP-approved food products shall be available from the commissary.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The commissary manager shall ensure that food items approved for use with the RDP are:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Certified by the appropriate recognized religious certification authority; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Appropriately marked on the commissary products list to identify the RDP diet platform to which the items apply.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An inmate approved for participation in the RDP, as an agreed-to condition of participation in the RDP, may only purchase commissary food items approved for the specific RDP diet platform for which the inmate has been approved.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If requested by the commissary manager, the facility chaplain, or a designee, shall provide the commissary manager:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>With a list of inmates approved for the RDP; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Indicate for each inmate on the list the RDP platform for which the inmate is approved.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If a facility chaplain, or a designee, has knowledge that an inmate is allegedly violating the agreed-to terms for participation in the RDP, the chaplain, or a designee, shall address the alleged violation according to procedures established under <cite path="|12|03|02|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Halal Diet Platform Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The RDP Halal Diet platform is a lacto-ovo vegetarian diet that is Halal Certified.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>At a minimum, 30 days before the observance of Ramadan, the facility chaplain, or a designee, shall inform the facility’s correctional dietary manager, or a designee, of the following to ensure that an inmate who will observe the ceremonial fasting (dawn to sunset) is provided with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If needed, an early breakfast served before dawn; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A late dinner served immediately after sunset that consists of an enhanced meal as prescribed by the Office of Food Services.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Daily during the Ramadan observance, the facility chaplain, or a designee, shall inform the correctional dietary manager, or a designee, of changes to the list of inmates approved to participate in the observance.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An inmate currently prescribed a medical diet shall, before participating in the Ramadan fasting:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Review health and medical diet concerns with the facility’s medical staff;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If applicable, sign a medical waiver for the period of the Ramadan observance; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>After the period of the Ramadan observance ends, return to the applicable medical diet, if the medical condition warranting the diet still exists.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The commissary manager shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Ensure that appropriate Ramadan food items, traditionally used breaking a fast, such as dried date palms (dates), are available for purchase by the inmates a minimum of 60 days before the Ramadan observance; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Advise the facilities when the Ramadan food items, including dried dates, are available for purchase and the cost of each item.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A facility chaplain, or a designee, shall notify the facility’s Islamic inmate population, at least 60 days before the Ramadan observance, of the availability of the Ramadan food items, including dried dates, and the cost of each item.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="12|03|02|.11">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Kosher Diet Platform Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Food service employees and applicable food services contactor staff in a facility that provides the RDP Kosher platform diet shall be trained in the Kosher Diet procedures according to the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>On an annual basis, a mandatory RDP Kosher platform training shall be provided for all food service employees and contractors;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>RDP Kosher platform training shall be provided for newly hired food service employees and contractors within 60 days of hiring;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Upon completing the Kosher Diet training, a food service employee shall sign and date the Food Service Staff Religious Diet Training Acknowledgement form; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Food service personnel shall prepare Kosher Diet food in the area specifically designated for that purpose.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If an inmate worker is assigned to prepare Kosher Diet meals, the facility’s correctional dietary manager, or a designee, shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provide the inmate worker with Kosher Diet training that is required under <cite path="12|03|02|.11|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> and approved by the Director of Food Services, or a designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Upon completion of the training, ensure that the inmate worker signs and dates the Food Service Inmate Worker Religious Diet Training Acknowledgement form;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Ensure that each inmate worker meets:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Annual COMAR requirements for medical screening, as related to food handling and preparation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Requirements established in the Food Service Manual, such as training in sanitation and inspections, Hazard Analysis and Critical Control Points, health and safety codes, personal hygiene, foodborne illness, care and use of equipment, and food temperatures; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Other applicable statutory and regulatory and policy and procedural requirements; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Supervise the inmate worker assigned to prepare Kosher Diet meals.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A food item used for the RDP Kosher Diet platform, except fresh fruits and vegetables, shall be certified by a recognized orthodox standard accepted by the Department’s Religious Services Program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Kosher Diet Hot Entree — Availability and Preparation.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A hot RDP Kosher Diet platform entree shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be available and served at a minimum six times during a week (Sunday—Friday); and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Include Kosher certified, purchased precooked, or dehydrated food items whenever possible.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Only Kosher Diet approved equipment that is clearly marked “RDP” may be used to rehydrate and heat items for the Kosher Diet.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A food service employee or inmate worker may not:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Cook or reheat a non-Kosher Diet platform food item in the Kosher Diet preparation area; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Use a pot, utensil, electric burner, or microwave oven that has been designated and marked “RDP” for the Kosher Diet platform for any other purpose.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Kosher Beverages. Beverages available for the general population, such as soda from the dispenser, pure juice with the exception of grape, nonflavored coffee or tea, water, and milk are currently Kosher-certified and may be used as part of the RDP Kosher Diet platform.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Kosher Food Storage.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Upon delivery of an RDP Kosher Diet platform food product, a food service employee or inmate worker having been trained in the Kosher Diet procedures shall place the Kosher Diet products in a designated location for staging or storage until the product is to be used.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An RDP Kosher Diet platform refrigerated food product shall be stored in a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Separate, clearly identified, and “RDP” marked refrigerated unit or freezer; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Common refrigerator or freezer that has space designated and marked for Kosher Diet platform food products.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An RDP Kosher Diet dry storage food product shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Stored in a dry storage location separate from food that is not part of the RDP Kosher Platform and clearly identified as “RDP”; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Placed in a designated and marked “RDP” area of a common dry food storage location, and clearly identified as “RDP”.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Serving Trays and Utensils.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>RDP identified reusable serving trays, covers, and cups shall be used for the RDP Kosher Diet platform as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Items are to be stored separately from non-Kosher Diet platform items; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>In the absence of reusable items, Styrofoam disposable items are acceptable.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Kosher Diet serving trays, covers, and cups shall be washed and sanitized before non-Kosher Diet platform equipment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Dish water shall be drained from sinks and clean water shall be used to wash an RDP Kosher Diet platform item.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Kosher Diet Platform Food and Utensil Handling.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A food service utensil used to prepare, serve, or transport RDP Kosher Diet platform food items shall be stored, handled, used, and cleaned separately from non-Kosher Diet platform food utensils.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A utensil used for the RDP Kosher Diet platform shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Marked with “RDP”;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Washed and sanitized in the pot and pan area before non-Kosher Diet platform utensils have been cleaned; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Stored in a separate:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Area in the tool room identified as the Kosher Diet area; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Tool box clearly marked as “RDP” within a common tool room.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A three-compartment sink shall be washed, rinsed, sanitized, and refilled with clean water before an RDP Kosher Diet platform utensil is cleaned in the sink.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A food service employee or inmate worker may not handle non-Kosher Diet food items while preparing or cooking RDP Kosher Diet platform food items.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A food service employee or inmate worker handling non-Kosher Diet food items before entering the Kosher Diet food preparation area to prepare kosher food shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Wash hands thoroughly;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Change into a clean apron; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Put on clean gloves.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Serving RDP Kosher Diet Platform Food Items.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An RDP Kosher Diet platform food item shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Prepared in advance of the meal period and, except for the RDP Kosher Diet platform hot entree, placed under refrigeration in RDP designated refrigeration; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Prior to being served, placed on serving trays designated for the RDP Kosher Diet platform.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Except for beverages currently certified as Kosher, inmates participating in the RDP Kosher Diet platform may not select or be served non-RDP Kosher Diet platform food or beverages.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Kosher Specific Requirements for the Passover Observance.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Religious diet accommodations provided for Passover meals shall meet or exceed basic nutritional requirements.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>During the Passover observance, RDP Kosher Diet platform meals shall consist of Kosher-for-Passover approved food items, as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Breakfast shall consist of Kosher-for-Passover:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Cereal;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Coffee;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Sugar;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Jelly or honey;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Matzo;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Fresh milk;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Hard boiled eggs (processed or cooked prior to the start of the Passover period); and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Fresh fruit;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>On Sunday through Friday of the Passover observance, lunch and dinner trays shall consist of a Kosher-for-Passover entree and Kosher-for-Passover vegetables (with the exception of legumes and foods containing soy, corn, or a derivative of either food);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>When the Passover Seder falls on a Friday or Saturday evening, the Seder meal shall include the hot entree that is not prepared until after the Kosher preparation area has been made Kosher-for-Passover acceptable in accordance with the RDP Kosher Diet training handouts that detail:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Kosher-for-Passover preparation; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Pre-Passover notification reminders from the Director of Food Services regarding Passover preparation; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>When the Passover Seder does not fall on a Friday or Saturday, on Saturdays (Sabbath) during the Passover observance the lunch and dinner meals shall consist of an entree of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Kosher-for-Passover American cheese, cottage cheese, tuna, sardines and condiments; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Boiled eggs with assorted fresh vegetables and fruit.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Seder Service and Seder Plate.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The facility chaplain or a designee shall determine if each participating congregative faith group will observe the Seder in full.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>During the first 2 nights of Passover when the Seder service is held, in addition to the special Passover meals, a Seder plate shall be provided to each participating congregative faith group, as follows:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>For congregational Seder services, each table shall be provided one Seder plate, generally four inmates per table whether the Seder service is held in the dining area, chapel, or another meeting room; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>In special confinement housing units, each inmate shall be provided a Seder plate.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>No later than January 10 of each year, the Chief of Religious Services shall forward in writing or by email the dates that Passover is observed  to the managing official, or a designee, Director of Food Services, and facility chaplain, or a designee, of each correctional facility.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>The Director of Food Services shall notify correctional dietary managers of the dates Passover is observed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>Nine weeks before the beginning of the Passover observance, the facility chaplain, or a designee, shall meet with the inmates of the groups that observe Passover to provide the official dates that Passover is observed that year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>Eight weeks before the date of the start of Passover, inmates who want to observe Passover shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Make the request using a form approved by the Chief of Religious Services; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Submit the completed form to the facility chaplain, or a designee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>The commissary manager shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Ensure that Kosher-For-Passover items are available for purchase by an inmate at a minimum of 60 days before the Passover observance; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Advise the facility chaplain, or a designee, of the dates the Kosher-For-Passover items are available for purchase and the cost.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>P.</num>
      <text>Kosher-for-Passover Facility Preparation.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Seven weeks before the beginning of the Passover observance, a facility chaplain or a designee shall notify the correctional dietary manager of the expected number of inmates participating in the Passover observance.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The correctional dietary manager shall ensure sufficient Kosher-for Passover related food items are ordered from vendors supplying items for the Passover observance, and restocking when necessary.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The correctional dietary manager shall, to the extent possible, ensure that the order of Passover food items includes extra portions to accommodate last minute changes to the number of participating inmates based on new intakes.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Eight days before Passover, each kitchen and related areas used to prepare and serve meals during Passover shall be made Kosher and only Kosher for Passover food may be prepared and served from the Kosher kitchens and related areas.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>Q.</num>
      <text>A managing official, or a designee, may not change the dates or menu of the planned Passover observance, except during an emergency and after consulting with the Director of Food Services and the Office of Religious Services.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>R.</num>
      <text>An inmate observing Passover shall only be provided RDP Kosher-For-Passover approved food items and beverages.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>S.</num>
      <text>If changes occur during Passover, the Office of Religious Services shall provide the correctional dietary manager with changes to the list of inmates who are participating in the special Passover ceremonial meals.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Correctional Services Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|2-109">2-109</cite>(c), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|3-205">3-205</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|4-208">4-208</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|5-201">5-201</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-03-12">Effective date: March 12, 2018 (45:5 Md. R. 286)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
