<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Issuance, Transfer, and Relinquishment of Licenses</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter governs the issuance, transfer, and relinquishment of licenses for commercial ambulances.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Issuance of Licenses.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>SOCALR shall issue a license to an applicant that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Files the required application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Files the required supporting documentation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Pays the required fees; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Meets the other requirements of this subtitle for licensure.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Before issuing a license, SOCALR may verify information relating to an application by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Inspecting supporting documents;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Inspecting a commercial ambulance service;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Inspecting commercial ambulances; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Requiring a conference with the applicant.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>SOCALR may not issue a license to an applicant whose name is, in the judgement of SOCALR, confusingly similar to another person doing business in Maryland, or who otherwise has the right to use the name in Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A licensed commercial ambulance service shall produce its license upon demand of any person.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Unless revoked or surrendered, a commercial ambulance service license or ambulance license shall expire at midnight on the date indicated on the license.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A revoked or surrendered commercial ambulance service license or ambulance license shall expire immediately upon notification.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>SOCALR shall affix a licensing decal to a commercial ground ambulance when it is licensed. The decal shall be displayed at all times on the outside of the back surface of the ambulance in a manner clearly visible to the public.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>A licensing decal is not proof of a valid license.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Licenses and licensing decals issued by MIEMSS at all times remain the property of MIEMSS.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>License Renewal for Commercial Ambulance Services and Ambulances.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A licensee shall apply for a new license at least 14 calendar days before the current license expires.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>To renew a license, the licensee shall apply to SOCALR under <cite path="|30.09.03">COMAR 30.09.03</cite>—30.09.05.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If a commercial ambulance license is not renewed, the ambulance owner shall contact SOCALR to have the ambulance licensing decals removed from its ambulances under <cite path="|30|09|05|.09">Regulation .09 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Transfer of Licenses.</heading>
    <text>A commercial ambulance service license or ambulance license issued by MIEMSS may not be transferred or assigned without the prior written approval of MIEMSS.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Merger or Acquisition.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The owner of a Maryland licensed commercial ambulance service wishing to merge with or acquire the assets or stock of another Maryland licensed commercial ambulance service may submit a letter of intent for the purpose of transferring the service and ambulance licenses to the successor service.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Information submitted to SOCALR relating to the possible transfer of vehicle licenses in a potential merger or acquisition are confidential until a license is issued to the successor, except as otherwise required by law.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If a successor service continues to do business in the name of and at the principal address of a merged or acquired service as it appears on the service license issued to the merged or acquired service and vehicles are not added at the time of merger or acquisition, the ground ambulance transfer fee is not imposed on the successor service in connection with the merger or acquisition.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If a successor service changes the name or principal address of a merged or acquired service or any other information appearing on a ground ambulance license, a transfer fee shall be paid for each ground ambulance which is relicensed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The licensing fee required by <cite path="30.09.04.07">COMAR 30.09.04.07</cite> shall be paid for any additional ground ambulances licensed at the time of a merger or acquisition.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Preliminary Determination for Successor Commercial Ambulance Service.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A prospective purchaser of the stock or assets of a commercial ambulance service, with the written permission of current ownership, may apply to SOCALR for a preliminary determination of the eligibility of the prospective purchaser for a commercial ambulance service license based on the eligibility criteria in <cite path="|30.09.04">COMAR 30.09.04</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>There is a fee for preliminary review of a license application submitted by a prospective buyer.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Any information submitted to SOCALR relating to a potential acquisition of a commercial ambulance service is confidential until a license is issued to the successor, except as otherwise required by law.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the purchaser changes the name or principal address of the acquired service or any information on a ground ambulance license, a vehicle license transfer fee shall apply for each vehicle to be relicensed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The licensing fee required in <cite path="30.09.04.07">COMAR 30.09.04.07</cite> shall be paid for any additional ground ambulance licensed at the time of purchase.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Transfer of Vehicle License.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A licensed commercial ambulance service may apply to SOCALR to transfer a commercial ground ambulance license from one of its ambulances to another if the transfer does not result in a net increase in the number of ground ambulances operated by the licensee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Any net increase in the number of ground ambulances operated by the licensee is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Treated as an addition to the fleet rather than a transfer; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Subject to payment of the entire annual, semiannual, or quarterly ambulance licensing fee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Sale or Cessation of Operations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A commercial ambulance service shall contact SOCALR to have the ambulance licensing decals removed from its ambulances:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Before it is sold; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Within 14 calendar days of cessation of operations.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If a licensed commercial ambulance service is sold or ceases to operate, the service shall return the ambulance service license and all ground ambulance licenses to SOCALR within 14 calendar days of the sale or cessation of operation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Vehicle Sold or Permanently Placed Out of Service.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A commercial ambulance service shall contact SOCALR to have the ambulance's licensing decals removed:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Before the ambulance is sold; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Within 14 calendar days of the date the ambulance is permanently placed out of service.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A commercial ambulance service shall return to SOCALR a commercial ambulance license:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Before selling the ambulance; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Within 14 calendar days of permanently placing the ambulance out of service.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|13-508">13-508</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|13-515">13-515</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-10-12">Effective date: October 12, 1992 (19:20 Md. R. 1816)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|14.22.05">COMAR 14.22.05</cite> to <cite path="|30.09.05">COMAR 30.09.05</cite>, August, 1997</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-01-10">Regulations <cite path="|30|09|05|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|30|09|05|.07">.07</cite>, Operational Requirements, repealed effective January 10, 2000 (26:27 Md. R. 2017)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-01-10" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|30|09|05|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|30|09|05|.09">.09</cite>, Issuance, Transfer, and Relinquishment of Licenses, adopted effective January 10, 2000 (26:27 Md. R. 2017)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-10-15"><cite path="|30|09|05|.02|G.">Regulation .02G</cite> amended effective October 15, 2004 (31:20 Md. R. 1486)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-10-15"><cite path="|30|09|05|.05|C.">Regulation .05C</cite>—E amended effective October 15, 2004 (31:20 Md. R. 1486)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-10-15"><cite path="|30|09|05|.06|D.">Regulation .06D</cite>, E amended effective October 15, 2004 (31:20 Md. R. 1486)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-10-15"><cite path="|30|09|05|.07|A.">Regulation .07A</cite>, B amended effective October 15, 2004 (31:20 Md. R. 1486)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-10-15"><cite path="|30|09|05|.08|B.">Regulation .08B</cite> amended effective October 15, 2004 (31:20 Md. R. 1486)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
