<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>13</num>
  <heading>Air Ambulance Service</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter governs the requirements for a commercial air ambulance service.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>In General.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>To be licensed as a commercial care air ambulance service, a commercial air ambulance service shall comply with the requirements of this chapter in addition to the other applicable requirements of this subtitle.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An applicant for a commercial air ambulance service license shall submit an application to SOCALR on the required form.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An applicant for a commercial air ambulance service license shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be accredited by CAMTS; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If ineligible to apply for CAMTS accreditation, because it has been in service for less than 1 year:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Submit to SOCALR a CAMTS consultation report indicating compliance with the CAMTS standards; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Apply for and receive full CAMTS accreditation within 18 months of being licensed by SOCALR.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A licensed commercial air ambulance service shall notify SOCALR within 24 hours of any change in CAMTS accreditation status and the reason for the change.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A licensed commercial air ambulance service may provide ALS, critical care, or neonatal transport service, or any combination of these, if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The equipment and personnel requirements of this subtitle are met for the specific type of transport;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The submitted service license application includes the information required, demonstrating compliance for the specific type of transport; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The service is accredited by CAMTS at that level.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A licensed commercial air ambulance service may not provide services with an unlicensed air ambulance unless:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The unlicensed air ambulance is used as a temporary replacement for a licensed air ambulance that is out of service for routine maintenance or repair;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The temporary replacement air ambulance meets all FAA requirements;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The temporary replacement air ambulance has all required staffing and equipment; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>It has notified SOCALR of the use of the replacement air ambulance and provided the following information:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The unit designation number assigned for operational purposes;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The FAA registration number; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The make, model, and year of manufacture.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A licensed commercial air ambulance service that provides services with an unlicensed air ambulance shall notify SOCALR when the licensed air ambulance is returned to service.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Additional Personnel Requirements for Commercial Air Ambulance Services.</heading>
    <text>A commercial air ambulance shall be staffed by:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A pilot who meets the requirements of licensure established by the Federal Aviation Administration 14 CFR Parts 61, 67, and 135; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>At least two additional individuals who meet or exceed the requirements for CAMTS accreditation at the level which the service is providing.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Additional Equipment Requirements for Air Ambulances.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each air ambulance shall carry sufficient equipment and supplies listed in <cite path="|30.09.10">COMAR 30.09.10</cite>—13 to assure:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The ability to carry out all procedures in the Maryland Medical Protocols for EMS Providers; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>That when transporting specialty care patients, the additional equipment necessary to care for the patient being transported is available;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A list of medical equipment and supplies will be provided to SOCALR with the licensing application.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>All medical, communications, and associated equipment on-board:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If routinely carried, shall be EMI certified for air operations; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If not routinely used, shall be approved by the pilot.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Operational Requirements for Air Ambulance Services.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Pilots of rotary wing air ambulances shall remain with the aircraft when the aircraft is occupying a hospital helipad with room for landing a single aircraft.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>SYSCOM shall coordinate the landing sequence of multiple emergency medical services aircraft in consultation with the pilots-in-command based on patient priority.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Commercial air ambulance services shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Comply with the requirements of <cite path="|30.07">COMAR 30.07</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Keep SYSCOM apprised of the location of their air ambulance at all times while the aircraft is in Maryland or in geographic proximity to the Maryland border in a contiguous state.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|13-508">13-508</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|13-515">13-515</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-10-15">Effective date: October 15, 2004 (31:20 Md. R. 1486)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
