<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>07</num>
  <heading>Chesapeake Bay</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|18|07|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Eastern Shore.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Eastern Shore areas, with their corresponding speed limits, are set forth in §§B—K of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Fairlee Creek.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Fairlee Creek encompasses the area beginning at a point at or near Lat. 39° 16.040'  N., Long. 76° 12.358' W., then running 142° (True) to a point, at or near Lat. 39° 16.028'  N., Long. 76° 12.347' W., and running upstream to a line beginning at a point at or near Lat. 39° 15.685'  N., Long. 76° 12.667' W., then running 87° (True) to a point, at or near Lat. 39° 15.702'  N., Long. 76° 12.250' W.  This area has a 6-knot speed limit during the boating season.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Fairlee Creek entrance channel encompasses the area beginning at a point at or near Lat. 39° 16.190'  N., Long. 76° 12.668' W., then running 61° (True) to a point 200 feet northeast of U.S. Coast Guard Light "2F", at or near Lat. 39° 16.265'  N., Long. 76° 12.497' W., then running 163° (True) to Fairlee Creek Entrance Channel Buoy "5" , at or near Lat. 39° 16.148'  N., Long. 76° 12.450' W., then running 106° (True) to a point at the intersection of a jetty and the shore, at or near Lat. 39° 16.108'  N., Long. 76° 12.268' W.  and north of a line across Fairlee Creek beginning at a point on the west side of the creek, at or near Lat. 39° 16.040'  N., Long. 76° 12.358' W., then running 142° (True) to a point, at or near Lat. 39° 16.028'  N., Long. 76° 12.347' W. This area has a 6-knot speed limit during the boating season.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Kent Island Narrows encompasses all of the waters of Kent Island Narrows south and west of a line beginning at  Ferry Point, at or near Lat. 38° 58.815'  N., Long. 76° 14.623' W., then running 179° (True) to a point on the shore at the south side of Kent Narrows, at or near Lat. 38° 58.603'  N., Long. 76° 14.617' W., and north and east of a line beginning at a point at or near the shore at the southeast corner of the Kent Island Yacht Club, at or near Lat. 38° 58.013'  N., Long. 76° 14.823' W., then running 173° (True) to a point near the N. end of the N. breakwater at Kent Narrows, at or near Lat. 38° 57.963'  N., Long. 76° 14.815' W., then running 142° (True) along the breakwater to a point at or near the south end of the N. breakwater at Kent Narrows, at or near Lat. 38° 57.807'  N., Long. 76° 14.657' W., then running 138° (True) to a point near DBN 5,  at or near Lat. 38° 57.698'  N., Long. 76° 14.530' W., then running 37° (True) to a point near the shore at Wells Point, at or near Lat. 38° 57.755'  N., Long. 76° 14.475' W. This area has a 6-knot speed limit all year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Kent Island Narrows Channel North Area. This area is enclosed by a line beginning at or near Lat. 38° 58.705’N., Long. 76° 14.620’ W., then running 60° (True) to a point at or near Lat. 38° 58.753’N., Long. 76° 14.513’ W., then running 15° (True) to a point at or near Lat. 38° 58.828’N., Long. 76° 14.488’ W., then running 330° (True) to a point at or near Lat. 38° 59.017’N., Long. 76° 14.625’ W., then running 329° (True) to a point at or near Lat. 38° 59.212’N., Long. 76° 14.775’ W., then running 57° (True) to a point at or near Lat. 38° 59.225’N., Long. 76° 14.748’ W., then running 150° (True) to a point at or near Lat. 38° 59.028’N., Long. 76° 14.603’ W., then running 150° (True) to  a point at or near Lat. 38º58.830’N., Long. 76° 14.455’ W., then running 198° (True) to a point at or near Lat. 38° 58.738’N., Long. 76º14.493’W., then running 243° (True) to a point at or near Lat. 38° 58.707’N., Long. 76° 14.573’ W., then running 231° (True) to a point at or near Lat. 38° 58.677’N., Long. 76° 14.620’ W., then running approximately 358° (True) to the point of beginning. In the event of shoaling in the channel the regulated area will shift to encompass the channel marked by the United States Coast Guard or its agent(s). Except as otherwise restricted, the speed limit for this area is 6 knots.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Knapps Narrows Area. This area is enclosed by a line beginning at or near Lat. 38° 43.030’N., Long. 76° 19.623’ W., then running 218° (True) to a point on shore at the southeast end of Knapps Narrows, at or near Lat. 38° 42.950’N., Long. 76° 19.703’ W., and east of a line beginning at the west end of Knapps Narrows, at or near Lat. 38° 43.232’N., Long. 76° 20.398’ W., then running 44° (True) to a point on shore, at or near Lat. 38° 43.293’N., Long. 76° 20.323’ W. Except as otherwise restricted, the speed limit for this area is 6 knots.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Rock Hall Harbor encompasses the area upstream (northeasterly) of a line beginning at a point at the south end of the west jetty at or near Lat. 39° 7.868'  N., Long. 76° 14.862' W., then running 226° (True) to a point on the west end of the east jetty, at or near Lat. 39° 7.830'  N., Long. 76° 14.913' W., and running to the head of the harbor. This area has a 6-knot speed limit all year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Swan Creek encompasses the area upstream (east) of a line beginning at a point on shore, at or near Lat. 39° 8.832'  N., Long. 76° 15.740' W., then running 137° (True) to a point on the north shore of Swan Creek, at or near Lat. 39° 8.762'  N., Long. 76° 15.655' W., and downstream (south) of a line beginning on the east side of Swan Creek, at or near Lat. 39° 9.342'  N., Long. 76° 15.303' W., then running 270° (True) to a point on the west side of Swan Creek, at or near Lat. 39° 9.342'  N., Long. 76° 15.468' W., including The Haven, and Denby Creek and all tributaries. This area has a 6-knot speed limit Saturdays, Sundays, and State holidays, during the boating season.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Worton Creek encompasses the area south of a line beginning at a point, at or near Lat. 39° 17.045'  N., Long. 76° 10.092' W., then running 68° (True) to a point, at or near Lat. 39° 17.078'  N., Long. 76° 9.9850' W., and running to the head of the creek, including all tributaries. This area has a 6-knot speed limit Saturdays, Sundays, and State holidays, all year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Churn Creek is located in Kent County off Still Pond, and encompasses the area upstream (southeast) of a line beginning at a point at or near Lat. 39° 19.178'  N., Long. 76° 7.942' W., then running 65° (True) to a point, at or near Lat. 39° 19.223'  N., Long. 76° 7.820' W., to the head of the creek. This area has a minimum wake zone all year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Kent Island Narrows South. All of the navigation channel at the southerly approach to Kent Island Narrows enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the south end of the north breakwater at Kent Narrows, at or near Lat. 38° 57.807'  N., Long. 76° 14.657' W., then running 138° (True) to marker 5, at or near Lat. 38° 57.698'  N., Long. 76° 14.530' W., then running 37° (True) to the shore at Wells Point, at or near Lat. 38° 57.755'  N., Long. 76° 14.475' W., then running 170° (True) to marker 4, at or near Lat. 38° 57.618'  N., Long. 76° 14.443' W., then running 249° (True) to marker 3, at or near Lat. 38° 57.607'  N., Long. 76° 14.482' W., then running 326° (True) to the point of beginning. This area has a 6-knot speed limit all year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Big Thoroughfare encompasses all of the waters of Deale Island Harbor and Scott's Cove east of a line beginning at a point at the west end of the north jetty at or near Lat. 38°10.181'N., Long. 75°56.866'W., then running 218° (True) to a point at the west end of the south jetty, at or near Lat. 38°10.158'N., Long. 75°56.888'W., and west of a line beginning at a point on the southwest abutment of the MD 363 bridge at or near Lat. 38°9.991'N., Long. 75°56.749'W., then running 34° (True) to a point on the northwest abutment of the MD 363 bridge, at or near Lat. 38°10.197'N., Long. 75°56.573'W. This area has a 6-knot speed limit all year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>East Bay Bridge Construction Area.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Area. All of the waters enclosed by a line beginning at or near Lat. 38° 59.388' N., Long. 76° 22.828'  W., then running 17° True, approximately 777 meters to a point at or near Lat. 38° 59.790' N., Long. 76° 22.667' W., then running 107° True, approximately 3541 meters to a point at or near Lat. 38° 59.230' N., Long. 76° 20.322' W., then running 200° True, approximately 769 meters to a point at or near Lat. 38° 58.840' N., Long. 76° 20.507' W., then running 288° True, approximately 3503 meters to the point of beginning.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The area described in <cite path="08|18|07|.01|L.|(1)">§L(1) of this regulation</cite> has a 6-knot speed limit at all times.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>This regulation shall be effective through March 31, 2026.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|18|07|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Western Shore.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Western Shore areas, with their corresponding speed limits, are set forth in §§B—M of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Deep Cove Creek encompasses the area beginning at a point at or near Lat. 38° 48.317' N., Long. 76° 30.542' W., then running 265° (True) to a point, at or near Lat. 38° 48.315' N., Long. 76° 30.565' W., and running to the head of the creek, including all tributaries. This area has a 6-knot speed limit Saturdays, Sundays, and State holidays, all year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Fishing Creek — Chesapeake Beach encompasses the area beginning at a point at the east end of the north jetty at or near Lat. 38° 41.517'N., Long. 76° 31.768' W., then running 185° (True) to the east end of the south jetty, at or near Lat. 38° 41.448'N., Long. 76° 31.775' W., and running to the head of the creek. This area has a 6-knot speed limit all year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Flag Harbor area. This area is enclosed by a line beginning at or near Lat. 38º27.875' N., Long. 76° 28.278' W., then running 149° (True) to a point, at or near Lat. 38° 27.855' N., Long. 76° 28.263' W., and running to the head of the harbor. Except as otherwise restricted, the speed limit for this area is 6 knots.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Hawk Cove; Brown's Creek.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Hawk Cove encompasses the area of Hart-Miller Island beginning at a point at or near Lat. 39° 15.710'N., Long. 76° 21.380' W., (northeast point of Hart-Miller Island) then running 287° (True) to a point, at or near Lat. 39° 15.758' N., Long. 76° 21.585' W., then running 237° (True) to a point, at or near Lat. 39° 14.953' N., Long. 76° 23.183' W (Drum Point). This area has a 6-knot speed limit all year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Brown's Creek encompasses the area beginning at a point on the west side of the entrance to the creek at or near Lat. 39° 16.532'N., Long. 76° 23.893' W., then running 89° (True) to a point on the east side of the entrance of the creek, at or near Lat. 39° 16.533'N., Long. 76° 23.755' W., and running to the head of the creek. This area has a 6-knot speed limit all year.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Oyster Creek entrance channel which lies between the Severn and South rivers encompasses the area beginning at a point at or near Lat. 38° 55.643' N., Long. 76° 27.795' W., then running 224° (True) to a point on the opposite shore, at or near Lat. 38° 55.637' N., Long. 76° 27.803' W., and running upstream to a line beginning at a point at or near Lat. 38° 55.632'N., Long. 76° 27.887' W., then running 142° (True) to a point on the opposite shore, at or near Lat. 38° 55.627' N., Long. 76° 27.882' W. This area has a 6-knot speed limit all year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Pleasure Island channel encompasses the area south of a line beginning at a point at or near Lat. 39° 14.292'N., Long. 76° 23.908' W., then running 112° (True) to the northern tip of Pleasure Island, at or near Lat. 39° 14.123'N., Long. 76° 23.377' W., and north of a line beginning at a point, at or near Lat. 39° 13.762'N., Long. 76° 23.895' W., then running 154° (True) to a point, at or near Lat. 39° 13.558'N., Long. 76° 23.770' W., then running 19° (True) to the south tip of Pleasure Island, at or near Lat. 39° 13.915'N., Long. 76° 23.608' W. This area has a 6-knot speed limit Saturdays, Sundays, and State holidays, all year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Pleasure Cove yacht basin encompasses the area beginning at a point at or near Lat. 39° 1.980'N., Long. 76° 24.233' W., then running 142° (True) to a point, at or near Lat. 39° 1.9680' N., Long. 76° 24.222' W., and running to the head of the basin. This area has a 6-knot speed limit Saturdays, Sundays, and State holidays, all year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Rockhold Creek — Deale Area encompasses the area upstream (northwest) of a line beginning at a point at the north end of the Rockhold Creek jetty near Owings Beach, at or near Lat. 38° 46.187' N., Long. 76° 33.285' W., then running 151° (True) to a point approximately 250 feet northeast of Rockhold Creek Channel Light 1, at or near Lat. 38° 45.963'N., Long. 76° 33.127' W., then running 201° (True) to USCG Light 1, at or near Lat. 38° 45.923' N., Long. 76° 33.147' W., then running 289° True) to a point on shore at Leitch, at or near Lat. 38° 46.040' N., Long. 76° 33.582' W., and running to the head of the creek. This area has a 6-knot speed limit all year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Seneca Creek encompasses the area beginning at a point at or near Lat. 39° 19.063' N., Long. 76° 22.142' W., then running 17° (True) to a point, at or near Lat. 39° 19.321' N., Long. 76° 22.040' W., and running to the head of the creek, including all tributaries. This area has a 6-knot speed limit Saturdays, Sundays, and State holidays, all year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Blackwalnut Creek encompasses the area beginning at a point at or near Lat. 38° 55.835'N., Long. 76° 27.773' W., then running 0° (True) to a point, at or near Lat. 38° 55.838' N., Long. 76° 27.773' W., and running to the head of the creek. This area has a minimum wake zone all year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Mezick Pond encompasses the area beginning at a point at the south end of the east jetty at or near Lat. 39° 0.387' N., Long. 76° 24.108' W., then running 239° (True) to pier 7A of the westbound Lane Memorial Bridge, at or near Lat. 39° 0.375' N., Long. 76° 24.133' W., then running 333° (True) to the shore near the east side of the westbound Lane Memorial Bridge, at or near Lat. 39° 0.508' N., Long. 76° 24.220' W., and running to the head of the pond. This area has a minimum wake zone all year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>Parker Creek encompasses the area beginning at a point at or near Lat. 38° 32.228' N., Long. 76° 31.067' W., then running 15° (True) to a point, at or near Lat. 38° 32.238' N., Long. 76° 31.063' W., and running to the head of the creek. This area has a minimum wake zone all year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>Sandy Point State Park.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Bathing Beach Zones.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>North Zone. All of the waters of the Chesapeake Bay offshore of Sandy Point State Park enclosed by a line beginning at a point at the shore near the west end of the north jetty, at or near Lat. 39° 1.095' N., Long. 76° 23.810' W., then running 73° (True) to a point near the east end of the north jetty, at or near Lat. 39° 1.113' N., Long. 76° 23.736' W., then running 158° (True) to a point at or near Lat. 39° 0.787' N., Long. 76° 23.564' W., then running 264° (True) to a point at the shore of Sandy Point State Park, at or near Lat. 39° 0.777' N., Long. 76° 23.695' W., then running northerly along the shore to the point of beginning. Unless otherwise permitted in advance by the Maryland Department of Natural Resources or Maryland Park Service, access to this area is limited to only non-motorized vessels at all times.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>South Zone. All of the waters of the Chesapeake Bay offshore of Sandy Point State Park enclosed by a line beginning at a point at the shore, at or near Lat. 39° 0.747' N., Long. 76° 23.682' W., then running 83° (True) to a point, at or near Lat. 39° 0.760' N., Long. 76° 23.550' W., then running 158° (True) to a point, at or near Lat. 39° 0.643'N., Long. 76° 23.488' W., then running 242° (True) to a point near the south end of the Mezick Pond jetty, at or near Lat. 39° 0.390' N., Long. 76° 24.107' W., then running 331° (True) to a point on the shore at the Mezick Pond jetty, at or near Lat. 39° 0.464'N., Long. 76° 24.161' W., then running easterly and northerly along the shore to the point of beginning. Unless otherwise permitted in advance by the Maryland Department of Natural Resources or Maryland Park Service, access to this area is limited to only non-motorized vessels at all times.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Soft Launch Channel. Beginning at a point, at or near Lat. 39° 0.760' N., Long. 76° 23.550' W., then running 263° (True) to a point on the shore of Sandy Point State Park, at or near Lat. 39° 0.747'N., Long. 76° 23.682' W., then running 340° (True) to a point on the shore, at or near Lat. 39° 0.777' N., Long. 76° 23.695' W., then running 84° (True) to a point, at or near Lat. 39° 0.787' N., Long. 76° 23.564' W., then running 158° (True) to the point of beginning. This area has a 6 knot speed limit at all times.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>Western Shore Bay Bridge Construction Area.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Area. All of the waters enclosed by a line beginning at or near Lat. 39° 0.276' N., Long. 76° 24.347' W., then running 62° 0'  to a point at or near Lat. 39° 0.444' N., Long. 76° 23.943' W., then running 145°0’ to a point at or near Lat. 39° 0.015' N., Long. 76° 23.554' W., then running 107°0’ to a point at or near Lat. 38° 59.874' N., Long. 76° 22.995' W., then running 198°0’ to a point at or near Lat. 38° 59.465' N., Long. 76° 23.161' W., then running 292° 0' to a point at or near Lat. 38° 59.693' N., Long. 76° 23.878' W., then running 328° 0' to the point of beginning.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The area described in <cite path="08|18|07|.02|O.|(1)">§O(1) of this regulation</cite> has a 6-knot speed limit at all times.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>This regulation shall be effective through March 31, 2026.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Natural Resources Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|8-703">8-703</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|8-704">8-704</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-02-03">Effective date: February 3, 1992 (19:2 Md. R. 153)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-07-22"><cite path="|08|18|07|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective March 30, 1992 (19:6 Md. R. 671); October 8, 2007 (34:20 Md. R. 1736); July 22, 2013 (40:14 Md. R. 1173)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-02-09"><cite path="|08|18|07|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective November 3, 2008 (35:24 Md. R. 2068); amended permanently effective February 9, 2009 (36:3 Md. R. 208)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-09-29"><cite path="|08|18|07|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective September 29, 2003 (30:19 Md. R. 1330)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-06-26"><cite path="|08|18|07|.01|C.">Regulation .01C</cite> amended effective June 26, 2000 (27:12 Md. R. 1138)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-03-13"><cite path="|08|18|07|.01|D.">Regulation .01D</cite> amended effective May 18, 1998 (25:10 Md. R. 745); March 13, 2017 (44:5 Md. R. 291)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-03-13"><cite path="|08|18|07|.01|E.">Regulation .01E</cite> amended effective March 13, 2017 (44:5 Md. R. 291)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-05-24"><cite path="|08|18|07|.01|I.">Regulation .01I</cite> adopted effective May 24, 1993 (20:10 Md. R. 850)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-04-04"><cite path="|08|18|07|.01|K.">Regulation .01K</cite> adopted effective April 4, 2011 (38:7 Md. R. 430)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-07-10"><cite path="|08|18|07|.01|L.">Regulation .01L</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective May 4, 2023 (50:11 Md. R. 444); adopted permanently effective July 10, 2023 (50:13 Md. R. 511)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-07-22"><cite path="|08|18|07|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective July 22, 2013 (40:14 Md. R. 1173)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-11-23"><cite path="|08|18|07|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite>, F amended effective November 23, 1992 (19:23 Md. R. 2039)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1997-04-21"><cite path="|08|18|07|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended effective June 17, 1996 (23:12 Md. R. 870); April 21, 1997 (24:8 Md. R 615)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-03-13"><cite path="|08|18|07|.02|D.">Regulation .02D</cite> amended effective March 13, 2017 (44:5 Md. R. 291)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-03-09"><cite path="|08|18|07|.02|E.">Regulation .02E</cite> amended effective March 9, 2009 (36:5 Md. R. 422)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-05-31"><cite path="|08|18|07|.02|I.">Regulation .02I</cite> amended effective May 31, 1999 (26:11 Md. R. 853)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1996-06-17"><cite path="|08|18|07|.02|K.">Regulation .02K</cite> adopted effective June 17, 1996 (23:12 Md. R. 870)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1997-04-21"><cite path="|08|18|07|.02|L.">Regulation .02L</cite>, M adopted effective April 21, 1997 (24:8 Md. R. 615)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-10-12"><cite path="|08|18|07|.02|N.">Regulation .02N</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective June 12, 2015 (42:14 Md. R. 876); amended permanently effective October 12, 2015 (42:20 Md. R. 1264)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-09-18"><cite path="|08|18|07|.02|O.">Regulation .02O</cite> adopted effective September 18, 2023 (50:18 Md. R. 794)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
