<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>36</num>
  <heading>Blackwater River</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Blackwater River.</heading>
    <text>The Blackwater River includes all the waters of the Blackwater River and its tributaries westerly of a line beginning at a point, at or near Lat. 38° 21.288’ N., Long. 76° 0.313’ W., then running 338° (True) to a point, at or near Lat. 38° 21.827’ N., Long. 76° 0.593’ W.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Blackwater River Prohibited Areas.</heading>
    <text>Except for employees and permitees of the United States Fish and Wildlife Service, and employees of the Department, an individual may not operate a vessel in the interior of Blackwater National Wildlife Refuge on the following portions of the Blackwater River from October 1 through March 31 each year:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>All the waters southeasterly of a line beginning at a point, at or near Lat. 38° 26.308’ N., Long. 76° 8.738’ W., and then running southeast along the Refuge boundary in mid-channel of the Big Blackwater River to a point on the south shore of a cove which is referred to locally as Fisherman Cove where the Refuge boundary enters the marshland, at or near Lat. 38° 25.652’ N., Long. 76° 8.650’ W.;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>All the waters northerly of a line beginning at a point on the north shore of Meekins Creek, at or near Lat. 38° 24.562’ N., Long. 76° 8.870’ W., then running along the Refuge boundary in mid-channel of Meekins Creek eastward to a point on the eastern shore of Meekins Creek at or near Lat. 38° 24.732’ N., Long. 76° 7.663’ W.;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>All the waters north and west of a line beginning at a point at the end of Blackwater Road at Barnes Landing, at or near Lat. 38° 23.408’ N., Long. 76° 6.280’ W., and then running along the Refuge boundary following the north shore of Coles Creek to the west entrance of Swan Pond, at or near Lat. 38° 23.420’ N., Long. 76° 5.717’ W., then running 126° (True) to a point, at or near Lat. 38° 23.402’ N., Long. 76° 5.685’ W., then continuing along the north shore of the creek to a point, at or near Lat. 38° 23.157’ N., Long. 76° 5.218’ W., then running 115° (True) to a point, at or near Lat. 38° 23.152’ N., Long. 76° 5.205’ W., then continuing along the north shore of the creek to a point on the west side of the Blackwater River, at or near Lat. 38° 23.162’ N., Long. 76° 4.560’ W., then running 93° (True) to a point, at or near Lat. 38° 23.160’ N., Long. 76° 4.523’ W., then continuing along the north shore of the river to a point, at or near Lat. 38° 23.295’ N., Long. 76° 3.832’ W., then running 11° (True) to a point, at or near Lat. 38° 23.302’ N., Long. 76° 3.830’ W., then continuing along the north shore of the river to the entrance of Backgarden Creek, at or near Lat. 38° 23.072’ N., Long. 76° 2.903’ W., then continuing along the north shore of Backgarden Creek to a point, at or near Lat. 38° 23.313’ N., Long. 76° 2.427’ W., then running 349° (True) to a point, at or near Lat. 38° 23.327’ N., Long. 76° 2.430’ W., then continuing along the north shore of the creek to a point, at or near Lat. 38° 23.448’ N., Long. 76° 2.408’ W., then running 76° (True) to a point, at or near Lat. 38° 23.453’ N., Long. 76° 2.383’ W.; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>All the waters south and west of a line beginning at a point north of Windmill Point where the Refuge boundary enters the Little Blackwater River, at or near Lat. 38° 27.172’ N., Long. 76° 5.277’ W., then running along the Refuge boundary in mid-channel southward to a point where the Refuge boundary turns east in the marshland, at or near Lat. 38° 26.182’ N., Long. 76° 5.207’ W.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Natural Resources Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|8-703">8-703</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|8-704">8-704</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-10-02">Effective date: October 2, 2000 (27:19 Md. R. 1725)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-02-16"><cite path="|08|18|36|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective February 16, 2015 (42:3 Md. R. 315)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-02-16"><cite path="|08|18|36|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective February 16, 2015 (42:3 Md. R. 315)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
