<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>09</num>
  <heading>Dry Needling</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter establishes standards for the provision of dry needling as an intervention performed by occupational therapists who are certified hand therapists (CHTs).</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Board” means the Maryland Board of Occupational Therapy Practice.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Dry needling” means a physical agent modality as defined in <cite path="10.46.06.03">COMAR 10.46.06.03</cite>, also known as intramuscular manual therapy, that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Involves the insertion of one or more solid needles, a mechanical device, into the muscle and related tissues to effect change in muscle and related tissues of the hand, wrist, elbow, and shoulder;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Requires ongoing evaluation, assessment, and re-evaluation of the impairments;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Is only utilized in parts of the body with neuromuscular or musculoskeletal links to the impairments; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Is not performed for:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The purposes of acupuncture and East Asian medicine as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|1A-101">Health Occupations Article, §1A-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Any purpose outside the scope of occupational therapy</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|46|09|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Minimum Education and Training Necessary to Perform Dry Needling.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In order to perform dry needling, an occupational therapist shall be a certified hand therapist in good standing, in addition to having completed at least 52 total hours of further instruction, which includes:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A total of at least 27 hours of instruction in the following dry-needling-specific course content areas:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Theory and application of dry needling to the hand, wrist, elbow, and shoulder;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Dry needling technique to the hand, wrist, elbow, and shoulder;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Dry needling indications and contraindications;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Infection control, the Occupational Safety and Health Administration’s Bloodborne Pathogen Protocol, and safe  handling of needles;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Emergency preparedness and response procedures related to complications associated with dry needling; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Appropriate documentation of dry needling; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>At least 25 hours of practical, hands-on instruction in the application and technique of dry needling, under the supervision of a licensed health care practitioner competent in dry needling procedures who has:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Completed the requisite course work under <cite path="10|46|09|.03|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Practiced dry needling for at least 5 years.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The instruction required under <cite path="10|46|09|.03|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite> shall be provided by a continuing education course approved by the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>All instruction required under this regulation shall include an assessment of competency.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The instruction required under <cite path="10|46|09|.03|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite> shall be offered:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In person at a face-to-face session; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In real time through electronic means that allow for simultaneous interaction between the instructor and the participants.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An occupational therapist may not fulfill any portion of the practical, hands-on instruction required under <cite path="10|46|09|.03|A.|(2)">§A(2) of this regulation</cite> with online or distance learning.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>An occupational therapist shall have practiced occupational therapy for at least 2 years, in addition to having been certified as a hand therapist, before performing dry needling in the State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Registration.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An occupational therapist shall be registered with the Board as having the appropriate education and training required by this regulation to be approved to practice dry needling.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In order to be registered to practice dry needling, an occupational therapist shall submit a completed application on a form supplied by the Board with proof of the hand therapist certification.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>In order to continue to practice dry needling, an approved occupational therapist shall submit proof of their certified hand therapy recertification.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>An occupational therapist who practices dry needling without the education and training required by this regulation shall be subject to discipline pursuant to <cite path="|10.46.07">COMAR 10.46.07</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Standards of Practice in Performing Dry Needling.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An occupational therapist shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Fully explain dry needling to the patient in advance of treatment; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Obtain written informed consent specific to dry needling that shall be included in the patient’s medical record.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An occupational therapist shall perform dry needling to the hand, wrist, elbow, and shoulder in a manner consistent with standards set forth in the Maryland Occupational Safety and Health Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gle">Labor and Employment Article, Title 5, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An occupational therapist shall document the provision of dry needling services in accordance with the documentation requirements set forth under <cite path="10.46.01.03">COMAR 10.46.01.03</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An occupational therapist who practices dry needling in a manner inconsistent with the standards of practice enumerated in this regulation shall be subject to discipline pursuant to <cite path="|10.46.07">COMAR 10.46.07</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Dry needling is not within the scope of practice of limited occupational therapy and shall only be performed by a licensed occupational therapist with a hand therapy certification.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|10-101">10-101</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|10-205">10-205</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-09-16">Effective date: September 16, 2024 (51:18 Md. R. 810)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
