<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>10</num>
  <heading>Telehealth</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter governs the practice of massage therapy using telehealth as an adjunct to, or replacement for, in-person client visits.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Nothing in this chapter restricts or limits reimbursement requirements pursuant to Health-General Article and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin">Insurance Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Asynchronous” means not occurring in real time.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Board” means the Maryland Board of Massage Therapy Examiners.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Health Care Services.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Health care services” means to provide client instruction through telehealth using:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Techniques that include, but are not limited to, stretching, movement, breathing, and self-massage; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Applications, such as nonlegend topicals and hot and cold packs or pads.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Health care services” does not include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Mental health counseling; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Nutritional counseling.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“In-person” means within the physical presence of the client.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Synchronous” means occurring in real time.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Telehealth” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|1-1001">Health Occupations Article, §1-1001, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Telehealth practitioner” means a Maryland licensed massage therapist or a registered massage practitioner performing telehealth services within their respective scope of practice as defined under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|6-101">Health Occupations Article, §6-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Licensure and Registration.</heading>
    <text>Subject to the provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 6, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, a telehealth practitioner shall be licensed or registered in Maryland when providing telehealth services to a client located in the State.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Standards of Practice for Telehealth.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Before performing telehealth services, a telehealth practitioner shall develop and follow a procedure to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Verify the identification of the client receiving telehealth services through use of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A government-issued photograph identification;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Documentation of the client’s:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Date of birth; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Home address; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Except for registered massage therapists, an insurance, Medicaid, or Medicare card;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For an initial client-telehealth practitioner encounter, disclose the telehealth practitioner’s:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Name;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Maryland license or registration number; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Contact information;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Obtain oral or written consent from a client or client’s parent or guardian if State law requires the consent of a parent or guardian, including informing clients of the risks, benefits, and side effects of the recommended health care services;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Securely collect and transmit a client’s medical health information, clinical data, clinical images, laboratory results, and self-reported medical health and clinical history, as necessary, and prevent access to data by unauthorized persons through encryption or other means;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Notify clients in the event of a data breach;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Ensure that the telehealth practitioner provides a secure and private communication modality that complies with federal and state privacy laws; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Establish safety protocols to be used in the case of an emergency, including contact information for emergency services at the client’s location.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Except when providing asynchronous telehealth services, a telehealth practitioner shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Obtain or confirm an alternative method of contacting the client in case of a technological failure;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Confirm whether the client is in Maryland and identify the specific practice setting in which the client is located; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Identify all individuals present at each location and confirm they are allowed to hear the client’s health information.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A telehealth practitioner shall be held to the same standards of practice and documentation as those applicable for in-person massage therapy practice appointments.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Client Evaluation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A telehealth practitioner shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Perform a synchronous or asynchronous clinical client evaluation that is appropriate for the client and the condition with which the client presents before providing health care services through telehealth; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If clinically appropriate for the client, provide or refer a client to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In-person treatment; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Another type of telehealth service.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A telehealth practitioner may not treat a client based solely on an online questionnaire.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Telehealth Practitioner Discipline.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board shall use the same standards of evaluating and investigating a complaint about and in disciplining a telehealth practitioner who practices telehealth as it would use for a licensee or registrant who does not use telehealth technology in the licensee’s or registrant’s practice.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The failure of a telehealth practitioner to comply with this chapter shall constitute unprofessional conduct and may be subject to disciplinary action by the Board</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|1-1001">1-1001</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|1-1006">1-1006</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|6-206">6-206</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-09-18">Effective date: September 18, 2023 (50:18 Md. R. 799)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
