<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Correction or Amendment of Public Records</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter governs procedures for a person in interest to request the correction or amendment of public records under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-502">General Provisions Article, §4-502, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, in the Maryland Institute for Emergency Medical Services Systems (MIEMSS).</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Custodian" means an authorized individual employed by MIEMSS having physical custody and control of public records of MIEMSS.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Person in interest" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-101">General Provisions Article, §4-101(e), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Public record" has the meaning defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-101">General Provisions Article, §4-101(h), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Who May Request.</heading>
    <text>A person in interest may request that MIEMSS correct or amend any public record under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-502">General Provisions Article, §4-502, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Contents of Request.</heading>
    <text>The person in interest shall request the correction or amendment in writing. Each request shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Identify the public record the person is seeking to correct or amend;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>State the precise correction or amendment requested;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>State the reason the correction or amendment is sought;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Include the statement that the public record is, to the belief of the person in interest, currently inaccurate or incomplete; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Represent that the requested correction or amendment will make the public record accurate or complete.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Filing the Request.</heading>
    <text>A request for correction or amendment of the record shall be filed with MIEMSS by addressing it to the custodian of the record. If the custodian is unknown to the person in interest, the request may be addressed to the Executive Director.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Return of Request.</heading>
    <text>A request for correction or amendment is considered filed with MIEMSS when received only to the extent that it reasonably complies with <cite path="|30|01|05|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>. If a request does not reasonably comply with <cite path="|30|01|05|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>, it shall be returned to the person who filed it with an explanation of the reason for the return and a statement that, upon completion, it may be refiled with MIEMSS.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Response to Request.</heading>
    <text>Within 30 days after the completed request for correction or amendment that complies with Regulations .04 and .05 of this chapter is received, the custodian of the record shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Make the requested correction or amendment and inform the person in interest in writing of the action;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Inform the person who made the request in writing of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>MIEMSS' refusal to make the requested correction or amendment, and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The reason for the refusal; or</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Inform the person who made the request in writing that the request will not be acted on because:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The person who made the request is not a person in interest,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The record sought to be corrected or amended is not a public record,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The person who made the request is not entitled to inspect the record under Parts I—IV of the Public Information Act; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Of any reason that is authorized by law.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Refusal of Request.</heading>
    <text>If MIEMSS' final determination under <cite path="|30|01|05|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite> is to refuse the requested correction or amendment, as authorized by <cite path="|30|01|05|.07|B.">Regulation .07B of this chapter</cite>, the person in interest may file with MIEMSS a concise statement of the reasons for:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The requested correction or amendment; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Disagreement with MIEMSS' refusal to make the correction or amendment.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Requirements for Statement of Disagreement.</heading>
    <text>The statement specified in <cite path="|30|01|05|.08">Regulation .08 of this chapter</cite> shall be filed on pages up to 8 1/2 x 11 inches in size. Only one side of the page shall contain the statement. More than 5 pages will not be accepted by MIEMSS in connection with a single request for correction and amendment.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Information Provided to Third Parties.</heading>
    <text>When MIEMSS discloses to a third party information from public records about which a statement in compliance with Regulations .08 and .09 of this chapter has been filed, MIEMSS shall furnish a copy of the statement to the third party.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Administrative Review.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A person who has made a request under this chapter for an amendment or correction may request an administrative review by the EMS Board by filing a request for a hearing with the Executive Director, if the person has been denied:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An amendment or correction record;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The right to file a statement; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The right to have a statement to a third party forwarded under <cite path="|30|01|05|.10">Regulation .10 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A request for a hearing shall be filed within 30 days of the date the person is advised of MIEMSS' action.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If a hearing is requested, the hearing shall be conducted by the EMS Board or the Office of Administrative hearings if the EMS Board so elects.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The hearing procedures in <cite path="|28.02.01">COMAR 28.02.01</cite> apply.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If the hearing is conducted by the Office of Administrative Hearings, the hearing procedures of <cite path="30.02.06.22">COMAR 30.02.06.22</cite> and .23 also apply.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A person who has requested administrative review may seek judicial review of the EMS Board's final action under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-222">State Government Article, §10-222, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>. The EMS Board shall be party to the proceeding.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">General Provisions Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-201">4-201</cite>(b) and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-502">4-502</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-12-15">Effective date: December 15, 1999 (26:24 Md. R. 1859)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-10-12"><cite path="|30|01|05|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective October 12, 2015 (42:20 Md. R. 1265)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-10-12"><cite path="|30|01|05|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective October 12, 2015 (42:20 Md. R. 1265)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-10-12"><cite path="|30|01|05|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective October 12, 2015 (42:20 Md. R. 1265)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-10-12"><cite path="|30|01|05|.07|C.">Regulation .07C</cite> amended effective October 12, 2015 (42:20 Md. R. 1265)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
