<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>Definitions</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this subtitle, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Basic telecommunicator course” means a course specified by the Maryland 9-1-1 Board dealing with the basic skills required to function as a call taker or call allocator in a communications center.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Communications center” means a public safety answering point (PSAP) or dispatch center, or a dispatch center operated by a licensed commercial ambulance service.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Course approved by the EMS Board” means a course of study and training intended to prepare an individual for licensure, certification, or renewal as a Maryland EMS provider which is conducted by an education program approved by the EMS Board under <cite path="|30.04">COMAR 30.04</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Curriculum” means the required educational content of an EMS training course as established by the EMS Board.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Emergency medical services (EMS)” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Medical services provided prehospital to prevent imminent death or aggravation of illness or injury;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Transport from the scene of a medical emergency to a hospital or appropriate facility whether or not medical services are provided;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Medical interfacility transport services to an appropriate facility; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Medical interfacility critical care transport to an appropriate facility.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Licensed nurse” means an individual holding a current and valid license issued by the Board of Nursing to practice nursing in Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Licensed physician” means an individual holding a current and valid license issued by the State Board of Physicians to practice medicine in Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Maryland 9-1-1 Board” means the Board established by the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|1-305">Public Safety Article, §1-305, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“National Registry of Emergency Medical Technicians” means the not-for-profit independent nongovernment agency that provides standardized national testing and registration for emergency medical technicians based on national training standards.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>“Physician assistant” means an individual licensed by the State Board of Physicians as a physician assistant to practice under a collaborative agreement.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>“Proprietary emergency medical dispatch (EMD) training program” means a private corporation, organization, or other entity which provides emergency medical dispatch training and materials consistent with the standards established by the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>“Public safety answering point (PSAP)” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|1-301">Public Safety Article, §1-301(q), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>“Service member” means an individual who is an active duty member of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Armed Forces of the United States;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A reserve component of the Armed Forces of the United States; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The National Guard of any state.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|13-516">Education Article, §13-516, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-01-01">Effective date: January 1, 1999 (25:26 Md. R. 1926)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-07-01"><cite path="|30|02|01|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective July 1, 2002 (29:12 Md. R. 930)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-06-09"><cite path="|30|02|01|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective December 19, 2005 (32:25 Md. R. 1944); May 12, 2014 (41:9 Md. R. 523); June 9, 2025 (52:11 Md. R. 533)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-05-01"><cite path="|30|02|01|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective May 1, 2000 (27:8 Md. R. 806)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-10-30"><cite path="|30|02|01|.02">Regulation .02</cite> repealed effective October 30, 2000 (27:21 Md. R. 1977)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
