<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Controlled Dangerous Substances</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope and Purpose.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Secretary of the Maryland Department of Health recognizes that the public interest requires control over the use of controlled substances in the legitimate manufacturing, distributing, dispensing, storing, and ordering of controlled substances.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This chapter applies to every registrant who manufactures, distributes, dispenses, stores, and orders any controlled substances within the State of Maryland, unless exempted from registration by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|5-301">Criminal Law Article, §5-301(d), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or 21 CFR §§1301.22 — 1301.24.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In the event of conflict between a provision of the Code of Federal Regulations referenced under a provision of this chapter and the provision of this chapter, the registrant shall comply with the more stringent provision.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Incorporation by Reference.</heading>
    <text>In this chapter, 21 CFR §§1300 —1317, as amended, are incorporated by reference.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|19|03|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Applicability to Chapter. In this chapter, the terms defined in <cite path="10|19|03|.03|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> have the meanings indicated. In addition, and unless otherwise provided in this chapter, the definitions appearing in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|5-101">Criminal Law Article, §5-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, shall also apply to this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Act” means the Maryland Controlled Dangerous Substances Act, Criminal Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|5-101">5-101</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|5-1101">5-1101</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Administrative probable cause” means a valid public interest, sufficient to justify an administrative warrant, allowing the inspection of the area, premises, or building to enforce this chapter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Agent” means a person who acts on behalf of the Department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Authorized provider” or “provider” means a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Person licensed, registered, or otherwise allowed to dispense, order, and store controlled substances;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Pharmacy, laboratory, hospital, or other institution licensed, registered, or otherwise allowed to manufacture, distribute, dispense, store, and order controlled substances; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Person licensed, registered, or otherwise allowed to conduct research on a controlled substance in the State in the course of professional practice or research.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Board” means the Maryland Boards of Physicians, Podiatry, Dental Examiners, Nursing, and Veterinary Medicine.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Chemical analysis” means the act of decomposing a substance into its constituent elements.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Civil fine” means a fine assessed by the Department against an authorized provider, including establishments.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Commercial Container.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Commercial container” means any bottle, jar, tube, ampule, or other receptacle in which a substance is held for distribution or dispensing to an ultimate user.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Commercial container” includes any box or package in which a receptacle is held for distribution or dispensing to an ultimate user.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>“Commercial container” does not include any package liner, package insert, or other material kept with or within a commercial container, or any carton, crate, drum, or other package in which commercial containers are stored or are used for shipment of controlled substances.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Controlled Premises.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Controlled premises” means places where original or other records or documents required under the Act are kept or required to be kept.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Controlled premises” includes factories, warehouses, other establishments, and conveyances, where persons registered under the Act or exempt from registration under the Act may lawfully hold, manufacture, distribute, dispense, administer, or otherwise dispose of controlled substances.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>“Department” means the Maryland Department of Health.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>“Disciplinary action” includes but is not limited to a penalty, reprimand, restriction, suspension, or revocation of a license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>“Federal Act” means the Controlled Substance Act (84 Stat. 1242; 21 U.S.C. 801) or the Controlled Substance Import and Export Act (84 Stat. 1285; 21 U.S.C. 951).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>“Fee exempt” means an authorized provider that is required to register with the Department but is not required to pay the registration fee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>“In good standing” means having a professional license that is not subject to any form of sanction by the Board or Criminal Law.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>“Inspector” means an officer or employee of the Department authorized by the Secretary to make inspections under the Act.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>“Labeling” means all labels and other written, printed, or graphic matter on any controlled substance or any of its commercial containers or wrappers accompanying controlled substances.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>“License” has the same meaning as <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-226">State Government Article, §10-226, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>Manufacture.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Manufacture” means:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Producing, preparation, propagation, compounding, or processing of a drug or other substance;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Packaging or repackaging of the substance; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Labeling or re-labeling of the commercial container of the substance.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Manufacture” does not include the activities of a provider who, as an incident to the provider’s administration or dispensing the substance in the course of the provider’s professional practice, prepares, compounds, packages, or labels the substance.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>“Manufacturer” means a person who manufactures a drug or other substance under:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A registration as a manufacturer; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Authority of registration as a researcher or chemical analyst.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>“Office of Controlled Substances Administration (OCSA)” refers to the division within the Maryland Department of Health responsible for administering the enforcement of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr">Criminal Law Article, Title 5, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>“Penalty” means monetary penalty, including but not limited to a fine.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>“Person” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An authorized provider;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The responsible party listed on the application licensed by the DEA; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The responsible party listed on the application for an establishment not licensed by the DEA.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>“Peyote” means the controlled substance in Schedule I under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|5-402">Criminal Law Article, §5-402, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>. This schedule I listing does not apply to the nondrug use of peyote in bona fide religious ceremonies of the Native American Church, and members of the Native American Church using peyote in this manner are exempt from registration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(24)</num>
        <text>“Pharmacist” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A pharmacist licensed in the State or otherwise authorized to dispense controlled substances; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An individual, for example, a pharmacist intern, authorized by a state to dispense controlled substances under the supervision of a pharmacist licensed by that state.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(25)</num>
        <text>Prescription.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Prescription” means an order for medication that is dispensed to or for an ultimate user.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Prescription” does not include an order for medication which is dispensed for immediate administration to the ultimate user, such as an order to dispense a drug to a bed patient for immediate administration in a hospital.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(26)</num>
        <text>“Registration” means initial registration or subsequent re-registration with OCSA.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(27)</num>
        <text>“Secretary” means the Secretary of the Maryland Department of Health.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(28)</num>
        <text>“Sufficient application” means an application that is completed in full and has provided all of the information required by the Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Registration: Requirements and Qualifications.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except for military and federal employees working within the scope of federal employment, a person shall register with the Department and obtain a registration certificate before the person:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Manufactures, distributes, dispenses, stores, and orders controlled substances;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Conducts research or instructional activities with controlled substances listed in Schedules II through V of Criminal Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|5-403">5-403</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|5-406">5-406</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Conducts research or instructional activities with a controlled substance listed in Schedule I of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|5-402">Criminal Law Article, §5-402, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, with prior registration from the DEA;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Conducts a chemical analysis with controlled substances listed in any schedule;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Installs and maintains an automated dispensing machine containing controlled substances; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Manufactures peyote for, or distributes peyote to, the Native American Church for bona fide religious ceremonies of the Native American Church.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An authorized provider shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Apply for a registration certificate on a form made available by the Department to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Obtain one registration for all locations that a provider prescribes only and no controlled substances are stored; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Obtain a single registration for each separate location where the provider prescribes, dispenses, orders, and stores controlled substances;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Have a professional license in good standing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Be of good moral character;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Have no convictions for crimes of moral turpitude;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Be 18 years of age or older;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Be registered with the Prescription Drug Monitoring Program if the authorized provider is also a prescriber as defined under Health-General Article, §21-2A-04.1, Annotated Code of Maryland; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Except for researchers, have completed 2 continuing education credit hours:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Prior to applying for an initial controlled substance registration occurring on or after October 1, 2018; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Prior to the first renewal of a controlled substance registration occurring on or after October 1, 2018.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Continuing Education.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The continuing education shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be accredited by the Accreditation Council for Continuing Medical Education; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Meet the requirements for approval by the authorized providers professional board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The continuing education shall pertain to the prescribing or dispensing of controlled substances.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Authorized providers shall meet the requirements of §§B and C of this regulation upon the completion of the 2 credit hours of continuing education.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Recent graduates meet the requirements of §§B and C of this regulation upon initial application if two academic course credits were issued relating to controlled substances.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An establishment shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Apply for a registration certificate on a form made available by the Department;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Obtain one registration for each separate place of business, professional practice, or location where controlled substances are:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Ordered;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Purchased;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Administered;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Delivered to the ultimate user;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Stored;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Manufactured; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Distributed; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Have a professional or occupational license in good standing to perform any of the following functions related to controlled substances:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Manufacture;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Distribute;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Deliver to the ultimate user;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Administer;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Store;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Order;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Prescribe;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Package;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Label; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Compound.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Registration: Application.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A person shall complete an application to be considered for a registration certificate.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Submit a completed application made available by the Department;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Except for fee exempt applicants, pay the appropriate fee as set forth in <cite path="|10|19|03|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Unless exempt from payment of a registration fee, apply for and obtain a registration certificate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Provide an explanation for any not-applicable responses on the applications;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Notify the Department of any criminal convictions related to controlled substances;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Notify the Department of any actions taken on the applicant’s professional license;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Have the application and accompanying documents required for registration signed by the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Applicant, if an individual;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>General partner, if the applicant is a partnership; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Officer responsible for the applicant, if the applicant is a corporation or other entity; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Provide additional documentation required by the Department pertinent to the registration, to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Clarify application information; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Determine if the applicant meets the requirements of this chapter.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>New applications that are unable to be processed 6 months from the payment deposit date:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>May be determined invalid;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Will not be issued a refund, unless:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The payment is a duplicate; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Approved by the Department; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Will require a new application to be resubmitted.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Renewal applications that are unable to be processed 45 days from the payment deposit date:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>May be determined invalid;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Will not be issued a refund, unless:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The payment is a duplicate; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Approved by the Department; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Will require a new renewal application to be submitted.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|19|03|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Registration: Fees.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An authorized provider or establishment required to obtain and maintain a registration certificate as set forth under this chapter shall pay the appropriate fees as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>New registration certificate — $120;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Renewal registration certificate — $120;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Amend a registration certificate — $50;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Change of ownership fee — $144;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Duplicate registration certificate — $30; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Reinstatement — $50.00.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Applicants exempt from registration fees include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except for contractual positions, an employee of a hospital, clinic, institution, facility, or unit operated by a local or State government agency;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An agency, excluding a State agency and its employees, for which the State is responsible for payment of the fee, provided that the exemption is approved by the Secretary; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person included in 21 CFR §§1301.21.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Refunds and Credits.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Secretary may not issue a credit towards or refund any registration fees to an applicant, including but not limited to, an applicant who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Withdraws a registration application;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Voluntarily or involuntarily ceases to manufacture, distribute, dispense, order, and store a controlled substances before a registration certificate expires; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Does not complete the application as set forth in <cite path="|10|19|03|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Secretary, or the Secretary’s designee, shall review the refund request and determine if a refund of any amount is appropriate.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A registrant who has lost a registration certificate is required to pay a duplicate registration fee as set forth in <cite path="10|19|03|.06|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Department may not issue a new or a renewed registration certificate until all required fees are paid.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Department-issued registration certificate shall be readily available to any agent or representative of the Secretary within the registered location.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Registration: Term, Expiration, Renewal, and Reinstatement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Term. The Secretary may issue a registration certificate that is valid for not more than 3 years.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Expiration.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A registration certificate expires on the date shown on the certificate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Secretary shall notify the registrant that the registration will expire not less than 30 days before the expiration date shown on the certificate.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Renewal.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A registration for which a sufficient application for renewal was submitted:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Shall be received at least 2 weeks before the expiration; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Will remain in effect until the Department takes a final action.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The failure to receive a renewal notice does not excuse a registrant from complying with this chapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Reinstatement.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A registrant whose registration has been surrendered in lieu of further investigation, revoked, suspended, or limited may not be eligible to request reinstatement for a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>2-year period;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Specified period designated in a consent order from the Department; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Specified time period determined by the Department.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>To apply for reinstatement, a registrant shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Complete and submit an application on a form provided by the Department; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Pay a reinstatement fee shown in <cite path="|10|19|03|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Registration Certificate: Assignment, Transfer, or Termination.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A registration certificate is not transferable.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A registration certificate becomes void when the registrant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Dies;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Discontinues business or professional practice in the State; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Changes ownership, including when:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Partners are added or deleted from the partnership;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>There is a change in the president or chief executive officer of the corporation; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>There is a change in the ownership of 10 percent or more of the outstanding shares in the corporation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A registrant who discontinues business or professional practice in the State shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notify the Secretary in writing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Surrender the registrant’s current registration certificate; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Legally transfer or dispose of any controlled substances relative to the registrant’s operation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A registrant who changes ownership of the business or professional practice shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notify the Secretary in writing at least 30 days before the change occurs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Complete and submit a change of ownership application to the Department;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Pay the change-of-ownership fee in <cite path="|10|19|03|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Surrender the registrant’s current registration certificate after the ownership change is finalized; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Allow the Department to inspect the business or professional practice of the new owners.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A registrant who changes the location of a registrant’s place of business or professional practice shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notify the Department at least 30 days before there is a change in the location of the registrant’s place of business or professional practice;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Apply to amend a current registration certificate; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Pay the fee to amend a certificate in <cite path="|10|19|03|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>During the 3-year registration period, the registrant shall notify the Office of Controlled Substances Administration within 30 days of the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Any criminal convictions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Any disciplinary actions taken against the registrant’s professional or occupational license; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any disciplinary actions taken against the registrant’s federal Drug Enforcement Agency registration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>After an application for registration has been filed, the Secretary may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Inspect the place of business or professional practice described in the application; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Investigate the applicant to determine whether the applicant meets the requirements of this chapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The registrant shall inform the Office of Controlled Substances Administration prior to any address changes.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Labeling and Packaging Requirements for Controlled Substances.</heading>
    <text>A registrant shall comply with the provisions of 21 CFR §1302, as amended.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Records and Reports Required of Registrants.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|5-306">Criminal Law Article, §5-306, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, a registrant shall comply with the provisions of 21 CFR §1304, as amended.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Inventories developed under the Federal Act dated May 1, 1971, and subsequent biennial inventory dates are acceptable for purposes of the Maryland Act.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>On the effective date a substance is added to any schedule of controlled substances pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|5-202">Criminal Law Article, §5-202, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, registrants required to keep records, who possess that substance, shall take an inventory of all stocks of that substance on hand.  Thereafter, that substance shall be included in each inventory made by the registrant.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Reports required in this section shall be accessible to the representative of the Secretary.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Order Forms.</heading>
    <text>A registrant shall comply with the provisions of 21 CFR 1305, as amended.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Prescriptions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Persons Entitled to Issue Prescriptions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A prescription for a controlled substance may be issued only by an authorized provider who is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Authorized to prescribe controlled substances in the State of Maryland; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Either registered or exempted from registration pursuant to 21 CFR §1301.22(c) and 21 CFR §1301.23.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A prescription issued by an authorized provider may be communicated to a pharmacist by an employee or agent of the authorized provider.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Purpose of Issue of Prescription.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A controlled substance prescription shall only be issued for a legitimate medical purpose by a provider.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A controlled substance prescription shall be issued by a provider in the usual course of the individual provider’s professional practice.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The responsibility for the proper prescribing and dispensing of controlled substances is upon the prescribing provider.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A pharmacist has a corresponding responsibility to ensure, prior to dispensing, that a controlled substance prescription is issued for a legitimate medical purpose.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>An order purporting to be a prescription issued not in the usual course of professional treatment or in legitimate and authorized research is not a prescription within the meaning and intent of the Maryland Controlled Dangerous Substances Act, Criminal Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|5-501">5-501</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|5-505">5-505</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A prescription may not be issued in order for an individual provider to obtain controlled substances for supplying the individual provider for the purpose of general dispensing to patients.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A prescription for a Schedule II-V controlled substance shall be dispensed within 120 days from the date of issue.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Unless the State has stricter requirements, if a provider has complied with 21 CFR §1306, the provider is deemed to have complied with this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Partial Fill of a Prescription.</heading>
    <text>A partial fill of a C-II prescription is permitted if:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The pharmacist is unable to fill the full quantity of the prescription, pursuant to 21 CFR §1306.13(a);</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The prescription is issued for a patient in a long-term care facility or for a patient with a medical diagnosis documenting a terminal illness pursuant to 21 CFR 1306.13(b) or (c);</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Requested by the patient or the practitioner that wrote the prescription, pursuant to 21 CFR §1306.13(b); or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The total quantity dispensed in all partial fillings does not exceed the total quantity prescribed.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Refilling of Prescriptions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A prescription for a controlled substance listed in Schedule II may not be refilled.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A prescription for a controlled substance listed in Schedule III, IV, or V:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>May not be refilled more than 6 months after the date on which the prescription was issued;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>May not be refilled more than five times; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Shall require a new and separate prescription to be issued if additional quantities are deemed necessary by the authorized prescribing provider.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The prescribing provider may authorize additional refills of Schedule III, IV, or V substances on the original prescription through an oral refill authorization transmitted to the pharmacist if the following conditions are met:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The total quantity authorized, including the amount of the original prescription, does not exceed five refills or extend beyond 6 months from the date of issue of the original prescription;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The pharmacist obtaining the oral authorization records on the reverse of the original paper prescription or annotates the electronic prescription record with the date, quantity of refill, and number of additional refills authorized, and initials the paper prescription or annotates the electronic prescription record showing who received the authorization from the prescribing practitioner who issued the original prescription;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The quantity of each additional refill authorized is equal to or less than the quantity authorized for the initial filling of the original prescription; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The prescribing practitioner executes a new and separate prescription for any additional quantities beyond the five-refill, 6-month limitation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Required Documentation.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each refilling of a prescription shall be documented on the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Back of the prescription;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>With Department approval, on another appropriate uniformly maintained, readily retrievable record, such as medication records; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>electronic prescription record.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The documentation shall indicate the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Number of the prescription;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Name of the controlled substance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Dosage form of the controlled substance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Date of each refilling;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Quantity dispensed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Identity or initials of the dispensing pharmacist in each refilling;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Total number of refills for that prescription;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Pharmacist’s initials; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Date by the pharmacist as of the date of dispensing.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Each refilling of a prescription shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>State the amount dispensed; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the amount dispensed is not specifically stated, be deemed to have been dispensed for the full face amount of the prescription.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Physical Security Controls for Registrants.</heading>
    <text>A registrant shall comply with the provisions of 21 CFR §§1301.71—1301.77 as amended.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|19|03|.16">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Controlled Substance Disposal.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Any registrant in possession of legally obtained controlled substances and desiring or required to dispose of any of these substances may ask the Office of Controlled Substances Administration of the Maryland Department of Health for authority and instructions to dispose of this substance. This does not eliminate the requirement on registrants under federal regulations to report destruction of controlled dangerous substances.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Disposal of Medical Waste.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A registrant in possession of legally obtained controlled substances deemed medical waste shall render the controlled substances irretrievable by disposing of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Liquid waste in an approved containment unit; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Non-liquid in a receptacle.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Two licensed personnel shall keep Waste Destruction Logbooks and maintain the record for 2 years. The Destruction Log shall be readily available upon inspection.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Disposal for Registrants Required to Register with the DEA.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Office of Controlled Substances Administration shall authorize and instruct the registrant to dispose of the controlled substance in one of the following manners, provided complete records of the disposition are maintained by the registrant:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>By transfer to a person registered under the Act and authorized to possess the substance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>By destruction in the presence of an agent of the Office of Controlled Substances Administration or another authorized person;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>By forwarding to the District Office of the Drug Enforcement Administration pursuant to the procedures of that agency;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>By returning unused controlled substances dispensed by registered hospital pharmacies for administration to in-patients to the pharmacy for appropriate disposition; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>By other means that the Secretary may determine to assure that the substance does not become available to unauthorized persons.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A registrant that has complied with 21 CFR §1304 is deemed to have complied with this section.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If a registrant is required regularly to dispose of controlled substances, the Special Agent in Charge of the Federal Drug Enforcement Administration may authorize the registrant to dispose of these substances, in accordance with 21 CFR §1307.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Disposal for Registrants Not required to Register with the DEA. Any registrant who is registered to administer only and is in possession of legally obtained controlled substances shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>List the controlled substance or substances which the registrant desires to dispose of on a drug destruction form provided by the Department;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Have two members of the professional staff, limited to an administrator, nurse, or pharmacist, destroy controlled drugs on premises;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Dispose per instructions given in <cite path="10|19|03|.16|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Forward a copy of the completed drug destruction form to the Office of Controlled Substances Administration within 10 days of destruction; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Keep a copy of the drug disposal form on location for a period of 2 years.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Abandoned controlled substances may be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Destroyed in the presence of an agent of the Office of Controlled Substances Administration or another authorized person or persons;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Disposed of by other means that the Secretary may determine to assure that the substance does not become available to unauthorized persons; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Impounded under Health-General Article, §21-1113, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Aforementioned procedures do not preclude release of medication to discharged patients if ordered in writing by the attending physician.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.17</num>
    <heading>Transfer of Controlled Substances.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>When closing business activities, a registrant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Dispose of all controlled dangerous substances in accordance with <cite path="|10|19|03|.16">Regulation .16 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Return the controlled substances registration certificate to the Office of Controlled Substances Administration inspector at the time of the closing inspection.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Change of Ownership.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A Change of Ownership requires the registrant to notify the Department in writing, Attention to the Office of Controlled Substances Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The written notification shall be submitted:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In person;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>By registered mail; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>By certified mail with a return receipt request.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The written notification must be received 14 days before the transfer occurs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Secretary has the authority to waive the 14-day time limitation in individual instances.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The written notification shall contain the following information:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The name;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The address;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The registration number; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The authorized business activity of the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Registrant-transferor discontinuing the business; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Registrant-transferee acquiring the business;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Whether the business activities will be:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Continued at the location registered by the person discontinuing business; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Moved to another location and, if so, the address of the new location; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The date on which the transfer of controlled substances will occur.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Except for transfer denials by the Secretary, the registrant-transferor may distribute, without being registered to distribute, controlled substances in the registrant-transferor’s possession to the registrant-transferee in accordance with the following procedures, on the date of transfer of the controlled substances:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A complete inventory of all controlled substances being transferred shall be taken and serve as the final inventory of the registrant-transferor and the initial inventory of the registrant-transferee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A copy of the inventory shall be included in the records of both the transferor and transferee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A copy of the inventory shall be filed with the Department if requested by the Secretary;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Transfers of Schedule I or II controlled substances shall require the use of order forms in accordance with 21 CFR §1305;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>All transferor-controlled substance records shall be transferred to the transferee; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Pursuant to 21 CFR §1304, transferors are required to make reports, which shall be marked as “Final”.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.18</num>
    <heading>Administrative Inspections and Warrants.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Administrative Inspections.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Procedures regarding administrative inspections and warrants pursuant to Criminal Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|5-305">5-305</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|5-804">5-804</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|5-805">5-805</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland, are governed generally by those sections of the Annotated Code and specifically by this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Authority to make inspections is authorized in accordance with Criminal Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|5-804">5-804</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|5-805">5-805</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland, to enter controlled premises and conduct administrative inspections for the purpose of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Documents required to be kept or made pursuant to 21 CFR §1304, under the Act, or regulations promulgated under the Act may be:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Inspected;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Copied;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Verified for correctness; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Inventoried;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Collecting samples of controlled substances or precursors (if samples are collected during an inspection, the inspector shall issue a receipt for these samples to the owner, operator, or agent in charge of the premises);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Review of records and information on the distribution of controlled substances by the authorized provider;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Reviewing the authorized providers processes;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Reviewing the authorized providers controls; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Inspecting the authorized providers facility operations;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Entry.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An inspection shall be carried out by an inspector.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An inspector shall have the right to enter the premises and conduct inspections at reasonable times and in a reasonable manner, upon the following conditions:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Stating the inspector’s purpose; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Presenting to the owner, operator, or agent in charge of the premises to be inspected, appropriate credentials and written notice of the inspector’s inspection authority under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|5-305">Criminal Law Article, §5-305, </cite>5-804, or 5-805, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Consent to Inspection of Financial Data, Sales Data Other than Shipment Data, or Pricing Data.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If inspection is desired of financing, sales, or pricing data, written consent shall first be obtained from the owner, operator, or agent in charge of the premises to be inspected.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>This written consent shall contain the following information:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>That the owner, operator, or agent in charge has the right to refuse to consent to an inspection of these items;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>That anything of an incriminating nature which may be found may be seized and used against the owner, operator, or agent in charge in a criminal prosecution;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>That the owner, operator, or agent in charge has been presented with a notice of inspection;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>That the consent is given by the owner, operator, or agent in charge voluntarily and without threats of any kind; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>That the owner, operator, or agent in charge may withdraw the owner’s, operator’s, or agent in charge’s consent at any time during the course of inspection.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The written consent shall be produced in duplicate and be distributed as follows:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The original will be retained by the inspector; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The duplicate will be given to the authorized provider inspected.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Administrative Warrants.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Probable Cause. If the Department is satisfied that administrative probable cause exists, the Department shall issue an administrative warrant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Execution of Warrants. An administrative inspection warrant shall be executed as required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|5-804">Criminal Law Article, §5-804(d), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Refusal to Allow Inspection with an Administrative Warrant. If an authorized provider or any person subject to the Act refuses to permit execution of an administrative warrant, or impedes the inspector in the execution of that warrant, the authorized provider or person shall be advised that this refusal or action constitutes a violation of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|5-902">Criminal Law Article, §5-902(a)(3), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.19</num>
    <heading>Hearings, Enforcement, and Disciplinary Sanctions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Authority for Enforcement Proceeding.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A hearing may be ordered or granted by the Secretary, at the Secretary’s discretion, to permit any person against whom criminal or civil action is contemplated under the Controlled Dangerous Substances Act an opportunity to present the individual’s views and the individual’s proposals for bringing the individual’s alleged violations into compliance with the law. The hearing will also permit the individual to show cause why prosecution should not be instituted, or to present the individual’s views on the contemplated proceeding.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The rules of procedure for hearings before the Secretary of the Maryland Department of Health shall be governed by <cite path="|10.01.03">COMAR 10.01.03</cite> and State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-201">10-201</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-226">10-226</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Administrative Hearings. Procedures for administrative hearings shall be governed by the rules set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|5-308">Criminal Law Article, §5-308, </cite>if applicable, Health-General Article, §2-207, and State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-201">10-201</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-226">10-226</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland, and <cite path="|10.01.03">COMAR 10.01.03</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>After a hearing pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|5-308">Criminal Law Article, §5-308, </cite>if applicable, and State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-201">10-201</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-226">10-226</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland, and <cite path="|10.01.03">COMAR 10.01.03</cite>, the Secretary may impose a sanction or penalty against any registrant that possesses a Maryland-issued controlled substances registration pursuant to Criminal Law Article, Title V, Annotated Code of Maryland, instead of or in addition to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The denial of an application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The refusal to renew a registration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Suspending a registration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Revoking a registration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Placing restrictions on a registration pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|5-307">Criminal Law Article, §5-307, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Issuing a nonpublic advisory letter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Imposition of Monetary Penalty.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>After a hearing pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|5-308">Criminal Law Article, §5-308, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the Department may impose a monetary penalty against a controlled substance registration holder pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|5-908">Criminal Law Article, §5-908, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The monetary penalty may be imposed instead of or in addition to the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Suspension of the controlled substances registration;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Revocation of the controlled substances registration; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Restrictions placed on the controlled substances registration.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The monetary penalty shall be paid within 30 calendar days of the order, unless the order specifies otherwise.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Until the imposed fine is paid, the registration may not be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Restored;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Reinstated; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Renewed.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>In its discretion, the Department may refer all cases of delinquent payment to the Central Collection Unit of the Department of Budget and Management for collection.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Notwithstanding the guidelines set forth in this chapter, in order to resolve a pending disciplinary action, the Department and the registrant may agree to a surrender of a registration, or a consent order with terms, sanction, and penalties agreed to by the Department and the registrant.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Nothing in this chapter prohibits the Department from staying any period of non-active suspension.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.20</num>
    <heading>Additional Controlled Substances in Maryland.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The following substance, also known as a “bath salt”, is added to the Maryland Controlled Dangerous Substances Act, Schedule I of the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|5-402">Criminal Law Article, §5-402, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>: F. 4-Methoxymethcathinone (Methedrone, bk-PMMA, PMMC).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The following substances are added to the Maryland Controlled Dangerous Substances Act, Schedule III of the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|5-404">Criminal Law Article, §5-404, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Butalbital, Acetaminophen, caffeine C-III Fioricet®; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Opium &lt; or = 100mg per 100Gm or 100ml or not more than 5mg per dosage unit C-III.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Criminal Law Article, Title 5; Health-General Article, §21-220; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1977-01-19">Effective date: January 19, 1977 (4:2 Md. R. 87)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-12-24"><cite path="|10|19|03|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite> amended effective December 17, 1984 (11:25 Md. R. 2134); February 17, 1992 (19:3 Md. R. 304); December 24, 2001 (28:25 Md. R. 2190)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-08-17"><cite path="|10|19|03|.07|E.">Regulation .07E</cite> and J amended effective August 17, 1992 (19:16 Md. R. 1474)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-07-12"><cite path="|10|19|03|.07|H.">Regulation .07H</cite> amended effective July 12, 1998 (25:14 Md. R. 1132)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1978-02-10">Regulations .07N, R and .10B amended effective February 10, 1978 (5:3 Md. R. 138)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-03-30"><cite path="|10|19|03|.08|G.">Regulation .08G</cite> amended effective March 30, 1992 (19:6 Md. R. 673)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1980-04-18"><cite path="|10|19|03|.09|A.">Regulation .09A</cite> amended effective April 18, 1980 (7:8 Md. R. 771)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-04-26" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective April 26, 2004 (31:8 Md. R. 646)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-04-24"><cite path="|10|19|03|.03">Regulation .03</cite> repealed and new Regulation .03 adopted effective April 24, 2006 (33:8 Md. R. 732)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-01-01"><cite path="|10|19|03|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective January 1, 2016 (42:22 Md. R. 1377)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-12-26"><cite path="|10|19|03|.13">Regulation .13</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective October 18, 2011 (38:24 Md. R. 1495); adopted permanently effective December 26, 2011 (38:26 Md. R. 1697)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-10-14" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|10|19|03|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|19|03|.13">.13</cite> repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|10|19|03|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|19|03|.20">.20</cite> adopted effective October 14, 2024 (51:20 Md. R. 899)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
