<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>06</num>
  <heading>Federal Bureau of Investigation, Next Generation Identification Rap Back Program</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>This chapter establishes procedures for participation in the Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI), Next Generation Identification Rap Back Program.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Criminal History Record Information (CHRI)” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcp|10-201">Criminal Procedure Article, §10-201, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Criminal History Records Check” has the meaning stated in <cite path="12.15.01.03|B.|(6)">COMAR 12.15.01.03B(6)</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Federal Bureau of Investigation, Next Generation Identification Rap Back Program (FBI Rap Back Program)” means the federal service that informs an authorized non-criminal justice government agency of subsequent criminal history record information for an employee or licensee during a specified term.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Non-criminal justice government agency” means a government agency that is not a criminal justice agency defined under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcp|10-201">Criminal Procedure Article, §10-201(d), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and receives CHRI for licensing and employment purposes.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Submitting Fingerprints to the FBI Rap Back Program.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Central Repository is responsible for submitting all fingerprints to the FBI Rap Back Program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Central Repository shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Submit the fingerprints of employees or licensees of authorized non-criminal justice government agency to the FBI; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Retain the fingerprints of an employee or licensee of authorized non-criminal justice government agencies for future submission to the FBI Rap Back program or for national fingerprint searches.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="12|15|06|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Issuance of a Revised Printed Statement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If a non-criminal justice government agency is authorized by State statute to receive federal criminal history records information, the Central Repository shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Enroll the non-criminal justice government agency in the FBI Rap Back Program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Maintain a record of each previously processed individual employed or licensed by the non- criminal justice government agency; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Distribute CHRI in accordance with the FBI Rap Back program and federal regulations.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Pre-Notification of CHRI Release.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Central Repository shall electronically notify a non-criminal justice government agency enrolled in the FBI Rap Back Program of the availability of subsequent CHRI for an employee or a licensee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A non-criminal justice government agency notified under <cite path="12|15|06|.04|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite> shall electronically respond to the Central Repository within 3 business days of receipt of notification from the Central Repository:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Confirming that the individual is currently an employee or a licensee and the CHRI should be released to the non-criminal government agency; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Advising that the individual is no longer an employee or a licensee and the individual should be removed from the non-criminal justice government agency FBI Rap Back Program service.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Annual Review of Previously Processed Individuals.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At least annually the Central Repository shall prepare and distribute a list of previously processed individuals to each non-criminal justice government agency enrolled in the FBI Rap Back Program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>From the list of previously processed individuals required under <cite path="12|15|06|.04|C.|(1)">§C(1) of this regulation</cite>, the non-criminal justice government agency shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Delete an individual who no longer works for and may not resume work for the non-criminal justice government agency; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Delete an individual who is no longer licensed by the non-criminal justice government agency.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The non-criminal justice government agency shall return the adjusted list required under <cite path="12|15|06|.04|C.|(2)">§C(2) of this regulation</cite> to the Central Repository within 15 working days of receipt.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Central Repository shall cease sending revised printed statements when notified that the previously processed individual has been deleted from the annually prepared list.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Except when prohibited by law, the Central Repository may charge a fee for providing the Rap Back Program service.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcp|10-221">Criminal Procedure Article, §10-221, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-03-30">Effective date: March 30, 2015 (42:6 Md. R. 512)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
