<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>07</num>
  <heading>Educational Equivalency Requirements</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter applies to an applicant who seeks eligibility to sit for the applicable examination for licensure as a professional land surveyor, as described in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo">Business Occupations and Professions Article, Title 15, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|15-305">Business Occupations and Professions Article, §15-305, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, an applicant for the appropriate licensing examination as a professional land surveyor shall meet certain experiential requirements. The experience that an applicant is to demonstrate pursuant to the above statutory authority must be acceptable to the Board for Professional Land Surveyors.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In order to assure a minimum acceptable level of competence of an applicant immediately after the passage of the applicable examination, the Board considers that it is in the best interests of Maryland consumers that the applicant has a diversified prelicensing experience in different aspects of land surveying.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>To further the Board's goal in protecting the interests of Maryland consumers and also in order to guide an applicant in obtaining an appropriate type and amount of pre-licensing experience, the Board is promulgating these regulations to set forth the criteria for the type and amount of work experience that may be acceptable to the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|13|07|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Guidelines for Acceptable Work Experience.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Applicants claiming the respective number of years of land surveying experience required in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|15-305">Business Occupations and Professions Article, §15-305(b), </cite>(c), (d), (e), or (f), Annotated Code of Maryland, shall demonstrate that the experience was gained by performing tasks in a variety of diverse surveying categories, including, but not limited to, the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Control surveys;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Boundary surveys;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Topographic surveys;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Subdivision planning;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Road and street grade design, sediment and erosion control design, storm drainage systems design, and storm water management design, all as more particularly described in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|15-101">Business Occupations and Professions Article, §15-101(k)(1)(vi), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and commonly known as “minor engineering experience”;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Construction surveys; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Location drawings.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The acceptable work experience described in <cite path="09|13|07|.02|A.|(5)">§A(5) of this regulation</cite> may be acquired by a combination of education and experience approved by the Board, as more particularly described in Regulations <cite path="|09|13|07|.03">.03</cite>—<cite path="|09|13|07|.05">.05</cite> of this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Board has the final authority with regard to both the quality and quantity of acceptable work experience.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An applicant for the principles and practice examination under Business Occupation and Professions Article, §15-305, Annotated Code of Maryland shall have 18 months of work experience generally described in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|15-101">Business Occupations and Professions Article, §15-101(k)(2)(vi), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and commonly known as “minor engineering experience”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An applicant may be able to meet an 18-month experiential requirement set forth in this regulation by the following methods:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Acceptable work experience;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Acceptable education; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A combination of acceptable work experience and acceptable education.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|13|07|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Educational Equivalency.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant may claim 3 semester credit hours as an equivalent of 6 months of minor engineering experience after the completion, to the Board's satisfaction, of the courses described in this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In order to be eligible for the Board's approval, the courses of instruction shall be in the following areas:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Hydraulics;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Surface water hydrology;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Route surveying or road design;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Storm drainage system design;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Storm water management design;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Sediment and erosion control design; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Infiltration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Board may choose to approve courses of instruction in areas other than those listed in <cite path="09|13|07|.03|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The courses described in §§B and C of this regulation are collectively referred to as eligible courses.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Board may approve the eligible course if the following requirements are met:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The course is offered by a university, community college, professional surveying organization, or other qualified provider acceptable to the Board; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Board approves the individual course syllabus and description submitted by either an applicant or directly by the provider before the applicant takes the eligible course.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Board may, at its discretion, approve courses successfully completed by an applicant before the effective date of this chapter if the courses meet the criteria and standards set forth in this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Determination of Value.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant shall furnish, at the time of filing the appropriate examination application, evidence of having completed, to the Board's satisfaction, the eligible course or courses, as described in <cite path="|09|13|07|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A semester credit hour is defined as not less than 15 standard 50-minute classroom hours of instruction.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Board's Discretion.</heading>
    <text>The Board has the final authority with regard to the approval of the type and value of courses and any other matters related to the educational equivalency requirements described in this chapter.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Business Occupations and Professions Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|15-208">15-208</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|15-305">15-305</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-04-03">Effective date: April 3, 2000 (27:6 Md. R. 641)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-10-09"><cite path="|09|13|07|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective October 9, 2017 (44:20 Md. R. 945)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-04-06" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective April 6, 2020 (47:7 Md. R. 384)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-01-06"><cite path="|09|13|07|.02|D.">Regulation .02D</cite>, E adopted effective January 6, 2025 (51:26 Md. R. 1186)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-01-06"><cite path="|09|13|07|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite> amended effective January 6, 2025 (51:26 Md. R. 1186)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
