<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>11</num>
  <heading>Small Employer Group Health Insurance — Disclosure Statement</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter applies to all carriers that offer the Comprehensive Standard Health Benefit Plan to the small employer market.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Additional benefits" means benefits offered in addition to the Comprehensive Standard Health Benefit Plan that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Are offered separately from the plan;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Are priced separately from the plan;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Are guarantee issued subject to the provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-1213">Insurance Article, §15-1213, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Are guarantee renewed subject to the provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-1212">Insurance Article, §15-1212, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Are community rated subject to the provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-1205">Insurance Article, §15-1205, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Do not duplicate any of the benefits in the Comprehensive Standard Health Benefit Plan.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Carrier" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-1201">Insurance Article, §15-1201, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Comprehensive Standard Health Benefit Plan" means the health benefit plan adopted by the Maryland Health Care Commission in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-1207">Insurance Article, §15-1207, </cite>and Health-General Article, Title 19, Subtitle 1, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Small employer" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-1201">Insurance Article, §15-1201, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|11|11|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Required Notice — Initial Purchase of Coverage.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>At the time of the initial purchase of coverage, a carrier who offers benefits additional to the benefits offered in the Comprehensive Standard Health Benefit Plan shall obtain a signed disclosure statement certifying that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The small employer was offered the Standard Comprehensive Health Benefit Plan; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Additional benefits were offered and priced separately.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The disclosure statement required in <cite path="31|11|11|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall be in at least 12-point type and shall read as follows:</text>
      <text>"MARYLAND HEALTH INSURANCE REFORM ACT COMPREHENSIVE STANDARD HEALTH BENEFIT PLAN DISCLOSURE STATEMENT</text>
      <text>Under Maryland law, small employers, including self-employed individuals and certain government and nonprofit organizations, as defined by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-1203">Insurance Article, §15-1203, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, must be offered the Comprehensive Standard Health Benefit Plan ("Standard Plan") by each carrier when health coverage is elected or renewed.</text>
      <text>A carrier may not offer small employers a health benefit plan having fewer benefits than the Standard Plan. A carrier may offer benefits in addition to those in the Standard Plan provided the optional, additional benefits are offered and priced separately from the Standard Plan. A small employer who is subject to the federal Mental Health Parity and Addiction Equity Act of 2008 shall be offered, at a minimum, the Standard Plan plus an additional benefit rider to make the mental health and substance abuse benefits comply with the federal Mental Health Parity and Addiction Equity Act of 2008.</text>
      <text>I HAVE READ AND UNDERSTAND THIS DISCLOSURE STATEMENT. I ACKNOWLEDGE THAT I HAVE RECEIVED A DESCRIPTION OF THE STANDARD PLAN AND RATES AND ANY ADDITIONAL BENEFITS AND RATES HAVE BEEN SHOWN AND PRICED SEPARATELY.</text>
      <text>Name of Carrier:</text>
      <text>Name of Producer:</text>
      <text>Employer Name:</text>
      <text>Employer Signature: Date: ".</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The disclosure statement required by <strong>§</strong>A of this regulation may be included on the carrier's sales proposal sheet.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The carrier or insurance producer shall maintain the signed disclosure statement for not less than 5 years.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|11|11|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Required Notice — Renewal of Coverage.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>At the time of renewal of coverage, a carrier who offers benefits additional to the benefits offered in the Comprehensive Standard Health Benefit Plan shall provide a disclosure statement that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Indicates that, except as described in <cite path="31|11|11|.04|A.|(4)">§A(4) of this regulation</cite>, the Comprehensive Standard Health Benefit Plan is the only plan required by State law;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Identifies any additional benefits offered by the carrier at renewal;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Identifies the cost of any additional benefits offered by the carrier at renewal; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Specifies that all additional benefits to the Comprehensive Standard Health Benefit Plan are not required by State law, with the exception of the additional benefit for compliance with the federal Mental Health Parity and Addiction Equity Act of 2008 for small employers subject to the federal Mental Health Parity and Addiction Equity Act of 2008.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The disclosure statement required by <cite path="31|11|11|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> may be included on the renewal notice or another document.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Insurance Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|2-109">2-109</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-1204">15-1204</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-05-10">Effective date: May 10, 2004 (31:9 Md. R. 713)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-03-21"><cite path="|31|11|11|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite> amended effective March 21, 2011 (38:6 Md. R. 397)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-03-21"><cite path="|31|11|11|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite> amended effective March 21, 2011 (38:6 Md. R. 397)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
