<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Safety</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>The purpose of this chapter is to establish a requirement for development of fire safety plans and a vehicle safety program for institutions and facilities, including State Use Industries.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Commissioner" means the Commissioner of the Division of Correction or a designee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Division" means the Division of Correction.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Evacuation" means to move inmates and staff from a threatened area of fire or hazard of fire.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Fire plan" means the plan of evacuation, security, first aid, and firefighting for the institution.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Fire safety" means a policy and procedures which ensure an institution's safety from fire hazards.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Fleet safety coordinator" means a person who is the assigned representative in each motor vehicle safety activity.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Institution" means a building that is occupied by inmates and staff.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Motor vehicle" means a device which transports a person or property.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"State vehicle" means a motor vehicle titled or leased to the State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Support agency" means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A utility company;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An emergency medical service;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A law enforcement agency;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Another Division institution;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Another agency which may assist an institution in case of fire; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>An organization, business, or firm involved by a grant or contract.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Fire Plan Elements.</heading>
    <text>The Commissioner shall ensure that:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each warden develops a procedure to establish a fire plan in conjunction with the fire marshal of the locality.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Each warden appoints a fire safety officer who has completed a qualified fire safety program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Each fire plan includes the following elements:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Inspection by the fire safety officer of the institution on a monthly basis with required documentation sent to the warden and the Division headquarters.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Annual review and revision as needed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Availability of the plan to staff.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Posting of the fire plan in designated areas.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Establishment of teams to conduct fire fighting, evacuation, security, and first aid.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Fire stations for individual extinguishers.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Teams for each extinguishing device.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Conduct of quarterly fire drills which meet the following criteria:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Under varying conditions;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>On a staggered basis;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>On random days;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>At random times; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>On all shifts.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Evacuation procedure associated with the conduct of a fire drill which considers security requirements and public safety.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Establishment of an ongoing relationship with the local fire department to ensure:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Understanding of community emergency service capabilities by institutional administration and staff; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Ongoing communication and coordination.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Provision for good housekeeping standards within the institution.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Requirement for constant vigilance by staff to detect and eliminate fire hazards.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Development of a master list of each institutional fire extinguisher which includes the following provisions:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Monitoring extinguisher charge levels;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Recharging or filling of an extinguisher; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Replacement of an extinguisher which is being repaired with a fully charged, operational extinguisher.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>Testing of each alarm system by the fire safety officer on a quarterly basis with requirement for maintenance of appropriate documentation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>Immediate notification of any fire of significance to Division headquarters. When the fire department is summoned to an institution, the warden or designee shall ensure that Division headquarters' personnel are notified according to the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Deputy Commissioner during normal business hours; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Division duty officer during hours other than those set for normal business.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>Establishment of a contingency plan, coordinated with all participants, for transferring inmates to alternate facilities under emergency conditions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>Mandatory training requirements for each employee to ensure understanding of the fire safety plan.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>Establishment of a list of support agencies which shall be reviewed and updated annually.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Each employee acknowledges awareness of the institution fire plan for the employee's place of employment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>When a fire occurs within an institution and the estimate of damage exceeds $1,000, the warden submits a written report to the Division fire safety officer within 5 working days.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Each inmate is made aware of the institution's fire response plan for inmates.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Conduct of Fire Drills.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner shall ensure that during a fire drill an entire inmate population is not evacuated at one time. Sections of an institution may be evacuated to other sections of the institution.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Each warden may simulate fire drill evacuations under conditions in which evacuation would not jeopardize institutional safety and control.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Vehicle Safety and Preventive Maintenance.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner shall ensure that Division guidelines for establishment of a vehicle safety program are based on requirements contained in the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Maryland State Vehicle Fleet Policies and Procedures as published by the Department of Budget and Fiscal Planning; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Governor's State Fleet Safety Committee Handbook.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner shall ensure that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A fleet safety coordinator is designated for each institution having a vehicle assigned to it;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Each fleet safety coordinator implements requirements included within the Governor's State Fleet Safety Committee Handbook.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner shall ensure that each warden establishes a preventive maintenance program for each vehicle.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|2-109">Correctional Services Article, §2-109(c), </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1991-05-27">Effective date: May 27, 1991 (18:10 Md. R. 1117)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
