<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>08</num>
  <heading>Custody and Security</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Adverse job action" means a disruption to the normal operational order of the institution by concerted action or inaction of an institution's employees.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Disturbance" means a situation which disrupts the normal operational order of an institution, and for which the assistance of additional off-duty staff may be required.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Division" means Division of Correction.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Major emergency" means a situation occurring within a facility or on surrounding State property under the jurisdiction of the Division requiring the deployment of resources internal or external to save lives, protect property and public safety, or to avert or lessen the severity of the situation. An emergency condition exists if the situation poses a severe threat to maintaining the desired level of security and safety of those inside.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Maximum security" means the second highest security level which provides secure housing for an inmate who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Poses a high risk of violence;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is a significant escape risk;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Has a history of serious institutional disciplinary problems; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Is likely to have serious disciplinary problems.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Medium security" means the third highest security level which provides housing for an inmate who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Poses some risk of violence;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is a moderate escape risk; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Has a limited history of institutional disciplinary problems.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Minimum security" means the next to lowest security level which provides housing for an inmate who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Poses less risk of violence;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Poses less risk of escape; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Has a minimal history of disciplinary problems.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Perimeter" means the wall or fence surrounding an institution.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Prerelease security" means the lowest security level which provides housing for an inmate who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Presents the least risk of violence;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Presents the least risk of escape; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Has a record of satisfactory institutional behavior.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Security"means an institution's physical features which help control inmate behavior and prevent escape.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Super maximum security" means the highest security level. A super maximum security institution provides secure housing within a secure perimeter. Features include single-celling, extremely limited institutional movement, constant observation, and limited inmate-to-staff and inmate-to-inmate contact to control the behavior of an inmate who has demonstrated an inability to be housed in an institution of lesser security.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Security Levels.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A super maximum security institution provides the highest level of secure housing within a secure perimeter for an inmate who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Poses a high risk of violence;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is a significant escape risk;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Has a history of serious institutional disciplinary problems or is likely to have serious disciplinary problems; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Has demonstrated an inability to be housed in an institution of lesser security.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A maximum security institution provides secure housing within a secure perimeter to control the behavior of an inmate who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Poses a high risk of violence;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is a significant escape risk;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Has a history of serious institutional disciplinary problems; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Is likely to have serious disciplinary problems.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A medium security institution provides secure housing within a secure perimeter for an inmate who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Poses some risk of violence;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is a moderate escape risk; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Has a limited history of institutional disciplinary problems.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A minimum security institution has fewer security features for an inmate who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Poses less risk of violence;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Poses less risk of escape; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Has a minimal history of disciplinary problems.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A prerelease security institution has the security features for an inmate who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Presents the least risk of violence;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Presents the least risk of escape; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Has a record of satisfactory institutional behavior.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The assignment of an inmate to a security level is based on the following three principles:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An inmate is assigned to the appropriate security level necessary to control the inmate's behavior;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Security may not be increased as a means of punishment; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Assignment of a security level is based on objective behavior-oriented factors.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The following factors relate to the physical configuration of an institution and are used to establish security levels:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The number and type of perimeter barriers;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Existence and period of operation of gun towers;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Use of external perimeter patrols;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Use of detection devices; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Housing configuration of the institution.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The following factors relate to the degree of staff supervision of an inmate:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Level of observation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Day movement;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Night movement;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Meal movement;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Access to jobs and programs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Institutional visits;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Transportation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Special, compassionate, or family leaves.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner shall ensure that when a group of maximum or medium security level inmates are being transported, the shift commander:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Ensures that the inmates are transported in a secured vehicle;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Determines the number of correctional officers assigned to escort duty and authorizes the appropriate weapons to be carried;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Assigns to escort duty at least one correctional officer of the same sex as the inmates being transported; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If minimum or prerelease security level inmates are included in the group, ensures that they are restrained in the same manner as the maximum or medium security level inmates.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>If a group of minimum or prerelease level inmates are being transported, the shift commander may transport them without restraints by on-duty staff other than correctional officers.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner shall ensure that correctional officers assigned to escort duty:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Are qualified in the use of firearms, trained and experienced in transporting inmates, familiar with good security practices, and have appropriate vehicle operators' permits;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide supervision to a probationary correctional officer who is assigned to escort duty;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Obtain from the institutional control center an escort I.D. card for an inmate to be transported, and return the card to the institution control center when the inmate is returned to the institution;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Ensure that restraint devices remain on an inmate while in a courtroom unless the presiding judge or magistrate orders otherwise;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>While escorting an inmate being treated or admitted to outside medical facilities:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Notify medical facility security personnel when an inmate arrives at a medical facility,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Ensure that restraint devices remain on an inmate while in a medical facility, unless a health care provider, due to medical circumstances, directs otherwise,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Maintain an inmate in view at all times, unless an inmate's medical treatment makes this impossible, in which case the officer shall assume a position as close to the inmate as possible,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Ensure that an inmate receives only items which have been approved by Division or medical facility staff,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Ensure that an inmate is allowed to make a telephone call only when the warden or designee has granted specific written permission,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Ensure that any visit the inmate receives is in accordance with <cite path="|12.02.16">COMAR 12.02.16</cite>, institutional directives, and medical facility policies,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Ensure that an inmate is allowed only in an authorized area of a medical facility,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Ensure that an inmate does not receive personal visitors, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Obtain a written receipt for an inmate who is left in the custody of a law enforcement or other authorized agency.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Emergency Preparedness Program.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner shall develop and implement an emergency preparedness program for major emergencies which may affect the safety and security of a facility. The program shall include procedures for the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Establishment of command responsibility;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Isolation, containment, and control of the emergency situation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Reestablishment to normal operational order following resolution of the emergency situation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An emergency preparedness program shall ensure the personal safety for each of the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Visitors;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Civilian and security staff; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Inmates.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner shall ensure that a major emergency included within the emergency preparedness plan is documented in accordance with Division regulations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner shall ensure that emergency preparedness program plans are coordinated with, and communicated to, allied agencies which may be called upon for assistance during institutional emergency conditions.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner shall ensure staff awareness of emergency preparedness programs.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|2-109">Correctional Services Article, §2-109(c), </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1991-05-27">Effective date: May 27, 1991 (18:10 Md. R. 1117)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
