<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>29</num>
  <heading>Inmates Convicted as Adults While Younger than 18 Years Old</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This regulation applies solely to an inmate convicted of a crime that the inmate committed while younger than 18 years old and for which the inmate was sentenced to life imprisonment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This regulation supersedes any conflicting regulation or policy.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Case manager” means the case management specialist assigned to an inmate during the case management process.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Commissioner” means the Commissioner of Correction.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Division” means the Division of Correction.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Inmate” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|1-101">Correctional Services Article, §1-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Inmate case record” means documentation assembled, maintained, and used under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|3-601">Correctional Services Article, §3-601, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Juvenile lifer” means an inmate serving a life sentence for a crime committed while younger than 18 years old.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Outside detail” means a work assignment at a location other than the facility where an inmate is housed, and during which the inmate is under the direct supervision of a correctional officer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Programming” means the process of placing an inmate in programs that address the inmate’s risks and needs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Release.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Release” means any type of discharge from custody of the Division.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Release” includes administrative release, parole, court ordered release, mandatory supervision release, expiration of sentence, work release, and community leave.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>“Release” does not include an escape.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>“Release date” means the date a juvenile lifer may be released from incarceration if the juvenile lifer:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Has been conditionally approved for parole by the Governor; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is entitled to release on mandatory supervision.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>“Secretary” means the Secretary of Public Safety and Correctional Services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>“Security” means a correctional facility’s physical features which help control inmate behavior and prevent escape.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Classification.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Initial Security Classification.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Upon intake of a juvenile lifer to a Division correctional facility and in accordance with the procedures established in <cite path="|12.02.24">COMAR 12.02.24</cite>, a case manager shall use the Division’s initial security classification instrument to conduct an individualized assessment of the juvenile lifer to determine an appropriate security level as defined in <cite path="12.02.08.02">COMAR 12.02.08.02</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A Division case manager shall assign the juvenile lifer to the least restrictive security level consistent with the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Outcome of the security classification instrument;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Identified risk and needs;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Public safety; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Safe and orderly operation of the facility.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>After a juvenile lifer’s initial classification, eligibility for a less restrictive security level that includes participation in an outside detail, a work release program, or specific programs shall be determined during the juvenile lifer’s annual classification status review in accordance with the Case Management Manual and other applicable directives and regulations.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Security Reclassification and Status Review.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A Division employee shall use the Division’s security reclassification instrument to conduct an individualized assessment of the juvenile lifer to determine an appropriate security level as defined in <cite path="12.02.08.02">COMAR 12.02.08.02</cite>:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Annually in accordance with the Case Management Manual and other applicable directives and regulations; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Upon the Maryland Parole Commission’s request following a hearing conducted in accordance with the provisions established in <cite path="|12.08.01">COMAR 12.08.01</cite> to improve a juvenile lifer’s suitability for parole.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A juvenile lifer, regardless of whether the juvenile lifer has a release date, shall be eligible for reclassification to a security level below medium security, if approved by the Commissioner, or a designee of the Commissioner.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A Division employee shall presume that a juvenile lifer is permitted to be assigned to the least restrictive security level, if the juvenile lifer’s score on the security reclassification instrument indicates eligibility for a less restrictive security level than the juvenile lifer’s current classification.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A Division employee may not apply the mandatory override in the security classification instrument that precludes a juvenile lifer from assignment to a security level below medium security.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Any override of the security classification instrument requires the Division employee to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Document the reason for the override in the inmate’s case record; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Provide the juvenile lifer with a written explanation of the reason for the decision.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>If the Commissioner, or the Commissioner’s designee, denies a juvenile lifer assignment to a security level below medium security, the Commissioner, or the Commissioner’s designee, shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Document the reason for the denial in the inmate’s case record; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Provide the juvenile lifer with a written explanation of the reason for the decision.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>In order to improve a juvenile lifer’s suitability for parole, a case manager, the warden, and the Commissioner shall give significant weight to the requests or recommendations of the Maryland Parole Commission that a juvenile lifer be permitted to be assigned to a less restrictive security level or participate in specified inmate programming.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>A juvenile lifer may not lose a privilege, job, or housing assignment in order to undergo a risk assessment or security status review as requested by the Maryland Parole Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Program Eligibility.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Juvenile Lifer with a Release Date.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A juvenile lifer who has a release date shall be eligible for an outside detail or the work release program, if approved by the Commissioner, or the Commissioner’s designee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the Commissioner, or the Commissioner’s designee, denies a juvenile lifer’s participation in an outside detail or the work release program, the Commissioner, or the Commissioner’s designee, shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Document the reason for the denial in the inmate’s case record; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Provide the juvenile lifer with a written explanation of the reason for the decision.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Juvenile Lifer Without a Release Date.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If warranted by exceptional circumstances, a juvenile lifer who does not have a release date shall be eligible for an outside detail if recommended by the Commissioner of Correction, or a designee of the Commissioner, and approved by the Secretary.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the Secretary denies an outside detail for a juvenile lifer, the Secretary or the Secretary’s designee shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Document the reason for the denial in the inmate’s case record; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Provide the juvenile lifer with a written explanation of the reason for the decision.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Correctional Services Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|2-109">2-109</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|3-205">3-205</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-09-20">Effective date: September 20, 2021 (48:19 Md. R. 802)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
