<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Early Voting Centers</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="33|17|02|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Number of Early Voting Centers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Date to Determine Number of Registered Voters.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The State Administrator shall determine the number of registered voters in each county as of 5 p.m. on the Tuesday that is 8 months before the primary election.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For purposes of making this determination, the State Administrator shall include only active voters.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Determination of Early Voting Centers. Within 5 days of the determination in <cite path="33|17|02|.01|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, the State Administrator shall provide each local board with the number of early voting centers, as required under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|10-301">Election Law Article, §10-301</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="33|17|02|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Selecting Early Voting Centers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Considerations for Early Voting Centers. A local board shall consider the following factors when determining the location of an early voting center:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Accessibility of the early voting center to historically disenfranchised communities, including cultural groups, ethnic groups, and minority groups;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Proximity of the early voting center to dense concentrations of voters such that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If a county is required by <cite path="|33|17|02|.01">Regulation .01 of this chapter</cite> to have one or two early voting centers, 50 percent of the registered voters in the county live within 10 miles of one of the proposed early voting center; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If a county is required by <cite path="|33|17|02|.01">Regulation .01 of this chapter</cite> to have three or more early voting centers, 80 percent of the registered voters live within 5 miles of one of the early voting centers;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Accessibility of the early voting center by public transportation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Ensuring equitable distribution of early voting centers throughout the county;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Maximizing voter participation, including through the use of community centers and public gathering places as locations for early voting centers;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Whether the early voting center can accommodate long lines of voters, including taking into consideration how voters waiting in line are protected against inclement weather; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Whether the early voting center has parking facilities sufficient for early voting, taking into consideration the normal business activities of the proposed early voting center.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Requirements for Early Voting Centers. A local board shall propose early voting center locations that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Allow a local board to install the required telecommunication needs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Are of sufficient size and layout to conduct early voting, including adequate access to electricity;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Are accessible or can be made accessible for voters with disabilities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Can store voting equipment and supplies in a secure location during non-early voting hours;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Have sufficient and reliable heating and air-conditioning capabilities; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Can accommodate a no electioneering zone as required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|16-206">Election Law Article, §16-206, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, exit polling as required by <cite path="|33.07.08">COMAR 33.07.08</cite>, and electioneering outside of the no-electioneering zone.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Form for Proposed Early Voting Center.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The State Board shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Prescribe a form for a local board to use to provide information about a proposed early voting center; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Provide each local board with the form at least 1 year before a primary election.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Form Submission for Early Voting Center.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>At least 7 months before a primary election, a local board shall submit a form for each proposed early voting center.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If a local board is required to have more than one early voting center, the local board shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Complete a form for each proposed early voting center; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Submit the forms for each proposed early voting centers at the same time.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Contents of Form. The form shall include questions related to whether the proposed early voting center meets the considerations and requirements defined in §§A and B of this Regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Additional Information. For each proposed early voting center, a local board shall submit with the form required in <cite path="33|17|02|.02|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A diagram of the facility, including the proposed layout of the voting equipment and electrical and telecommunications connections in the voting area and the proposed locations of the election judges;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The State of Maryland's Accessibility Survey form;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Digital photographs of the outside of and entrance to the proposed early voting center; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The security plan required by <cite path="|33|17|02|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Inability to Identify Proposed Early Voting Center. If the proposed early voting center does not meet all of the criteria listed on the form required in <cite path="33|17|02|.02|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, a local board shall provide on the form:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A list of other facilities that were considered, and why those facilities are not being proposed as early voting centers; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A description of the factors that mitigate the fact that the proposed early voting center does not meet all of the criteria listed on the form required in <cite path="33|17|02|.02|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Use of Local Board Office. If a local board proposes to use the offices of the local board as an early voting center, the local board shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Have a clearly marked space for early voting that is distinct and separate from absentee voting that occurs at the office; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Post signs and include in all election-specific materials the business hours of the local board and the early voting hours.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Approval of Early Voting Centers.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Upon receipt of a form for a proposed early voting center, the State Administrator shall review and make a recommendation to the State Board as to whether to accept or reject the proposed early voting center.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The State Board shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Vote on a local board's proposed early voting center within 30 days of receipt of the form required in <cite path="33|17|02|.02|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Give deference to a proposed early voting center for which a local board considered the factors required in <cite path="33|17|02|.02|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> and the requirements of <cite path="33|17|02|.02|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Within 2 days after its vote on a proposed early voting center, notify the local board of this outcome of the State Board's vote.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Upon approval by the State Board, a local board shall include in its disaster recovery plan the name, address, and contact information for the early voting center.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Alternate Early Voting Centers.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A local board shall identify an alternate early voting center for use if an approved early voting center becomes unavailable.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A local board shall give preference to the offices of the local board or a government facility when considering the location of an alternate early voting center.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A local board shall identify:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>One alternate early voting center if the local board is required to establish one, two, or three early voting centers; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Two alternate early voting centers if the local board is required to establish four or more early voting centers.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A local board shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>At least 3 months before a primary election, complete and submit to the State Administrator the form required by <cite path="33|17|02|.02|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> for each proposed alternate early voting center; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Upon approval by the State Administrator of the alternate early voting center:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Submit the form to the appropriate local government agencies; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Include in its disaster recovery plan the name, address, and contact information for each alternate early voting center, a plan for notifying the public if the alternate center is needed, and a plan for transitioning operations to an alternate center.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Agreement for Early Voting Center.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Agreement Required. A local board shall enter into a legally binding agreement with an authorized representative of the facility where early voting will be conducted.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Required Provisions. The agreement shall contain the following provisions:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The dates and times when a local board requires access to the facility;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The amount of compensation, if any, a local board is required to pay to use the facility as an early voting center;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Authorization to install and test equipment and telecommunications connections before early voting, and remove equipment and connections after early voting;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Authorization to install temporary measures to improve access to the early voting center for voters with disabilities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Require the facility to provide a local board with its policies and procedures for inclement weather and other emergency situations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Whether the facility or the local board is responsible for providing appropriate services in case of inclement weather or other emergency situations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>If agreed to by the facility's authorized representative, a copy of the facility's disaster recovery plan;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Authorization to establish a no electioneering zone during early voting; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Authorization to allow exit polling within the no electioneering zone.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Filing with State Administrator. Within 30 days of executing the agreement, a local board shall file a copy of the signed agreement with the State Administrator.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Security Plans for Early Voting Center.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Security Plan Required. With the form required by <cite path="|33|17|02|.02|C.">Regulation .02C of this chapter</cite>, an election director shall submit an early voting security plan for approval to the State Administrator.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Contents of Plan.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The early voting security plan shall describe in detail how a local board will keep voting equipment, electronic pollbooks, ballots, and other election equipment and supplies secure during early voting and non-early voting hours.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The plan shall include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A description of each entrance, including windows, to the area where equipment and supplies will be secured during non-early voting hours and how the entrance is secured;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The names and titles of all individuals who have a key or keys to the room where equipment and supplies will be secured during non-early voting hours;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A description of existing building security, such as alarms and closed circuit or Internet accessible cameras, and armed and unarmed guards at the facility; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Any additional security measures that will be taken during early voting and non-early voting hours.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>At the request of the State Administrator or when it is considered necessary, an election director shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Review and update the early voting security plan; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If updated, within 2 days of updating the plan, submit a copy of the updated plan to the State Administrator.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Review and Acceptance of Plan.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The State Administrator shall review a local board's early voting security plan and may require a local board to make changes to the plan, including implementing additional security measures.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Within 30 days of receipt of an early voting security plan, the State Administrator shall review and provide feedback to a local board.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A local board shall update its plan according to the feedback provided the State Administrator.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Election Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|2-102">2-102</cite>(b)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|4">4</cite>), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|2-202">2-202</cite>(b), and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|10-301">10-301</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-01-14">Effective date: January 14, 2010 (37: 1 Md. R. 17)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-08-22"><cite path="|33|17|02|.01|A.">Regulation .01A</cite> amended effective August 22, 2011 (38:17 Md. R. 1015)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-07-10"><cite path="|33|17|02|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective April 4, 2022 (49:7 Md. R. 469); July 10, 2023 (50:13 Md. R. 514)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-09-25"><cite path="|33|17|02|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite>, F amended as an emergency provision effective September 25, 2020 (47:22 Md. R. 934); emergency provision expired December 31, 2020</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-05-31"><cite path="|33|17|02|.02|G.">Regulation .02G</cite> amended effective May 31, 2010 (37:11 Md. R. 768)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-07-10">Regulation 04A, C amended effective July 10, 2023 (50:13 Md. R. 514)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
