<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Election Judges</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="33|17|05|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Local Board Employees.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If a local board appoints an employee to serve as an election judge, the employee may not perform any duties other than those of an election judge.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>At least one employee or board member of a local board shall be present at an early voting center for the following activities:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Setting up the early voting center each day of early voting; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Closing down the early voting center each day of early voting.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Applicability.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="33|17|05|.01|C.|(2)">§C(2) of this regulation</cite>, all federal and State laws, regulations, and procedures that apply to voting during early voting and on election day apply to voting at a voting center.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An employee or board member of a local board shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be present at an early voting center to open and close an early voting center on the first day of early voting;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Be present at an early voting center to close an early voting center on the last day of early voting; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Provide remote support to open or close an early voting center on the other days of early voting if the local board does not have an employee or board member present.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Number of Election Judges.</heading>
    <text>For each early voting center, a local board shall appoint the following:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Two election judges of different party affiliations to serve as chief judges;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>At least one election judge to facilitate provisional voting;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>One election judge for each electronic pollbook;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>At least two election judges to facilitate voting at the voting booths and ballot marking devices; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>One technical judge, unless the local board assigns an individual who is not an election judge to provide any necessary technical support.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Training of Election Judges.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Required Materials. The State Administrator shall develop and issue for the local boards:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A judges' manual that includes all information necessary to conduct early voting; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Instruction sheets summarizing certain early voting procedures.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Development of Manual. The State Administrator shall comply with the process established in <cite path="|33.02.03">COMAR 33.02.03</cite> for developing the judges' manual.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Use of Training Materials. Each local board shall use the manual and instruction sheets, or electronic copies of them, approved by the State Administrator for early voting.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Judges Training Program.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For an election judge who serves during early voting, each election director shall conduct training in accordance with <cite path="33.02.03.04">COMAR 33.02.03.04</cite>. and include instruction necessary to conduct early voting.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Requirements for Training Program Completion.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Each election judge shall complete the required training program.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An election director may require an election judge to attend additional classes.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Unless appointed under emergency circumstances, an individual may not serve as an election judge unless the individual completes the required training program.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Requirements for Training Compensation.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A local board shall pay at least $50 to an election judge who completes the training program, with the following stipulations:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Attendance at additional classes to train on the conduct of early voting does not entitle an election judge to further compensation.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>If the training program includes a training class that is offered through virtual instruction or online delivery and a hands-on practice session, the election judge shall complete the hands-on practice session to be entitled to compensation.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An election judge who is required to complete a training program prior to both a primary and general election is entitled to compensation for each training program.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Election Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|2-102">2-102</cite>(b)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|4">4</cite>), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|9-102">9-102</cite>(i), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|10-206">10-206</cite>(g), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|10-301">10-301</cite>.1(h), and 12-106(a), Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-02-22">Effective date: February 22, 2010 (37:4 Md. R. 343)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-09-04"><cite path="|33|17|05|.01|C.">Regulation .01C</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective September 4, 2020 (47:20 Md. R. 873); emergency provision expired December 31, 2020</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-01-13"><cite path="|33|17|05|.01|C.">Regulation .01C</cite> adopted effective January 13, 2022 (49:1 Md. R. 16)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-10-18"><cite path="|33|17|05|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective October 18, 2010 (37:21 Md. R. 1439)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-06-03"><cite path="|33|17|05|.02|D.">Regulation .02D</cite> amended effective June 3, 2019 (46:11 Md. R. 517)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-06-28"><cite path="|33|17|05|.03|E.">Regulation .03E</cite> adopted effective June 28, 2010 (37:13 Md. R. 853)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-10-02"><cite path="|33|17|05|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective October 2, 2023 (50:19 Md. R. 854)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
