<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Emergency Plans</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter sets forth the requirements for emergency plans that shall be developed and implemented by each local school system in Maryland.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meaning indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Local school system" means any of the 24 local public school systems in the State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"School emergency plan" means a plan for each public school grounds within the local school system that addresses mitigation, prevention, preparation, response, and recovery to an emergency including responding to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Violent or traumatic events on school grounds during regular school hours or during school-sponsored activities; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Events in the community that affect normal school functioning.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Central administration emergency plan" means a plan for each local school system and the SEED School that addresses mitigation, prevention, preparation, response, and recovery to an emergency including responding to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Violent or traumatic events on school grounds during regular school hours or during school-sponsored activities; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Events in the community that affect normal school functioning.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Drill" means a formalized exercise by which school system personnel, school staff, or students rehearse the plan or portions of the plan.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Mitigation" means a preventative action taken to reduce the loss of life or damage to property from all hazards.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Public school grounds” means local school system owned or leased buildings, the SEED School, and the land that surrounds the school building.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“SEED School” means the residential boarding education program operated under the supervision of the Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Incorporation by Reference.</heading>
    <text>The Maryland State Department of Education Emergency Planning Guidelines for Local School Systems and Schools (December 2019) is incorporated by reference.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Emergency Plan.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In consultation with other health and safety officials in the local community, each local school system and the SEED School shall develop an emergency plan for all public school grounds to include maintenance, transportation, and central administration office under its jurisdiction that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Deals with the contingencies of man-made, technological, and natural hazards;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Conforms to the requirements of this chapter; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Aligns with the Maryland State Department of Education Emergency Planning Guidelines for Local School Systems and Schools (December 2019).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Each local school system and the SEED School shall ensure that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each school facility under its jurisdiction has a school emergency plan that is aligned with the criteria outlined in the MSDE Emergency Planning Guidelines for Local School Systems and Schools (December 2019) and that a copy of each school emergency plan is on file at the central administration office.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A central administration emergency plan that is aligned with the criteria outlined in the MSDE Emergency Planning Guidelines for Local School Systems and Schools (December 2019) is on file in each school grounds under its jurisdiction.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Each local school system and the SEED School shall develop and implement an annual schedule of drills for each school grounds within the system. In addition to fire drills, the following drills shall be conducted annually:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Evacuation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shelter in place;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Reverse evacuation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Lock down;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Drop, cover, and hold; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Severe weather.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Annual Certification.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>By September 30 of each year, each local superintendent of schools and the Head of the SEED School shall certify to the State Superintendent that the requirements of this chapter are being implemented.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>By September 30 of each year, each local superintendent of schools and the Head of the SEED School shall send a copy of the local school system’s central administration emergency plan to the State Superintendent of Schools, if updated from the previous year.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|2-205">2-205</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|7-435">7-435</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|7-1510">7-1510</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-702">8-702</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland;<br/>Federal Statutory Reference: 20 U.S.C. 7114 and 20 U.S.C. 7118</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-01-06">Effective date: January 6, 2005 (31:26 Md. R. 1864)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-11-25" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective November 25, 2013 (40:23 Md. R. 1935)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-06-29"><cite path="|13A|02|02|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective June 18, 2018 (45:12 Md. R. 618); June 29, 2020 (47:13 Md. R. 641)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-06-29"><cite path="|13A|02|02|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite>, B amended effective June 18, 2018 (45:12 Md. R. 618); June 29, 2020 (47:13 Md. R. 641)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
