<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>10</num>
  <heading>Parking on Maryland Transportation Authority Property</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Applicability.</heading>
    <text>This chapter applies to vehicles as defined in these regulations located on Authority property.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Abandoned vehicle" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|25-201">Transportation Article, §25-201(b), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Authority" means the Maryland Transportation Authority.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Authority Property.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Authority property" means property owned, leased, operated by or under the control of the Maryland Transportation Authority.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Authority property" includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A transportation facilities project as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|4-101">Transportation Article, §4-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>An Authority highway as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|21-1401">Transportation Article, §21-1401, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Official sign" means a sign that conforms to the system set forth in the most recent edition of the Manual on Uniform Traffic Control Devices for Streets and Highways as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|25-104">Transportation Article, §25-104, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Park", "parking", or "parked" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|11-144">Transportation Article, §11-144, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Police" means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A person designated as a member of the Maryland Transportation Authority Police Force under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|4-208">Transportation Article, §4-208, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A police officer as defined under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|3-201">Public Safety Article, §3-201(e), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Unattended Vehicle.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Unattended vehicle" means a vehicle that:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Is parked on Authority property other than in a designated area; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Has not been occupied or attended for a period of 12 or more hours.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Unattended vehicle" does not include an abandoned vehicle as defined under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|25-201">Transportation Article, §25-201, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Vehicle" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|11-176">Transportation Article, §11-176, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Permitted Areas.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A valid permit issued by the Authority may be required at designated parking areas on Authority property.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The operator of a vehicle parked in an area that requires a permit shall clearly display the required permit on or through the front windshield of the vehicle.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Restrictions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except when authorized by an official sign, the police, or when required by a traffic control device, a vehicle may not stop, stand, or park:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In front of, across, or blocking a driveway or gate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Within 15 feet of a fire hydrant or standpipe;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>On a sidewalk or in a crosswalk;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Within 20 feet of a crosswalk at an intersection, or within 30 feet of the approach to any stop sign, yield sign, or traffic control signal;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Within 20 feet of the pedestrian or vehicle entrance or access point to any building, except where designated for parking;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Within 50 feet of the nearest rail of a railroad, except where designated for parking;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>In an area where stopping, standing, or parking is prohibited by an official sign, or by markings on the adjacent curb or pavement;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>On the roadway side of a vehicle stopped or parked at the edge of the roadway;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>On the roadway where parking is otherwise permitted but where any part of the nearest side of the parked vehicle is in excess of 12 inches from the nearest curb, side, or edge of the roadway;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>In such a way as to obstruct traffic;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>In such a way as to cause or be likely to cause a hazard to the health and safety of individuals on Authority property;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>In a designated handicapped parking space without displaying a valid handicapped registration plate or placard;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>In excess of a time limit on a time restricted space; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>In an area designated for permit parking without displaying a valid parking permit.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>When parking or stopping a vehicle in any lined parking area, the vehicle may not occupy more than one lined space.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Removal of Vehicles.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>At the registered owner's expense, the police may remove or direct removal of the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A vehicle in violation of <cite path="|11|07|10|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A vehicle impeding the movement and handling of cargoes by its position; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An unattended vehicle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The police may take into custody any vehicle or other object parked or placed in violation of <cite path="|11|07|10|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite> or otherwise parked or placed so as to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Constitute a hazard to public safety; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Impede or obstruct the normal movement of vehicular or pedestrian traffic on Authority property.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Authority may use its own personnel, equipment, and facilities, or use those of its designee in accordance with <cite path="|11.07.03">COMAR 11.07.03</cite>, for the purpose of removing, taking into custody, and storing vehicles.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Authority shall keep accurate records of all vehicles removed, including the reasons for removal, and shall make reasonable attempts to contact vehicle owners to facilitate voluntary removals.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Vehicles moved by the Authority pursuant to this regulation shall be handled in accordance with <cite path="|11.07.08">COMAR 11.07.08</cite> and <cite path="11.07.03.14">COMAR 11.07.03.14</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Abandoned vehicles shall be removed in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr">Transportation Article, Title 25, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Violations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Citations.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The police may issue citations for violations committed under <cite path="|11|07|10|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person receiving a citation for a parking violation shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Pay for the parking violation; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Elect to stand trial for the violation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Election to Pay. If the person charged in the citation elects to pay for the parking violation, the person shall pay by mailing a certified check or money order, payable to the Maryland Transportation Authority in the amount stated on the citation, to the Division of Finance, 300 Authority Drive, Baltimore, Maryland 21222.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Election to Stand Trial.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If the person charged in the citation elects to stand trial, the person shall send a notice of intention to stand trial by mail to the Division of Finance, Maryland Transportation Authority, 300 Authority Drive, Baltimore, Maryland 21222, at least 5 days before the payment due date specified in the citation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the person charged desires the officer who issued the citation to be present at the trial, the person shall expressly request so on the notice electing trial that the officer appear.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the officer's presence is not specifically requested in the notice, the officer need not appear and a copy of the citation bearing a certification of the officer is prima facie evidence of the facts stated in the citation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If a timely notice to stand trial is received, the Authority shall forward the notice and citation to the District Court, which shall schedule the trial and notify the person charged in the citation of the date, time, and location of the trial.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Parking violations resulting in the issuance of citations are subject to the provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr">Transportation Article, Title 26, Subtitle 3, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and the procedures adopted by the Chief Judge of the District Court of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Penalties.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A parking violation is a misdemeanor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The registered owner of a vehicle found in violation of <cite path="|11|07|10|.04|A.|(12)">Regulation .04A(12) of this chapter</cite> is subject to a fine in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|27-106">Transportation Article, §27-106, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The registered owner of a vehicle found in violation of any other section of this chapter is subject to a $75 fine.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|4-204">4-204</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|4-205">4-205</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|4-208">4-208</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|4-208">4-208</cite>.1, 21-1402, 21-1403, 21-1407, and 26-301 et seq., Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-04-11">Effective date: April 11, 2005 (32:7 Md. R. 682)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-04-05"><cite path="|11|07|10|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective April 5, 2010 (37:7 Md. R. 574)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-11-09"><cite path="|11|07|10|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective April 5, 2010 (37:7 Md. R. 574); November 9, 2015 (42:22 Md. R. 1379)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-04-05"><cite path="|11|07|10|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective April 5, 2010 (37:7 Md. R. 574)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-04-05"><cite path="|11|07|10|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective April 5, 2010 (37:7 Md. R. 574)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-04-05"><cite path="|11|07|10|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective April 5, 2010 (37:7 Md. R. 574)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-04-05"><cite path="|11|07|10|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective April 5, 2010 (37:7 Md. R. 574)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-04-05"><cite path="|11|07|10|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective April 5, 2010 (37:7 Md. R. 574)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
