<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>06</num>
  <heading>Issuance of Citations by Motor Vehicle Administration Personnel</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>The purpose of this chapter is to establish:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Qualifications for employees designated under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-104">Transportation Article, §12-104</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland, including prerequisites of character, training, experience, and education; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Standards for the performance of the duties assigned to employees designated under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-104">Transportation Article, §12-104</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Administrator" means the Administrator of the Maryland Motor Vehicle Administration or the Administrator's designated representative.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Citation" means a document issued under the authority of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|26-201">Transportation Article, §26-201, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, for violations of the following provisions:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr">Transportation Article, Title 13, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, relating to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The vehicle excise tax,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Vehicle titling and registration,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Special registration plates for individuals with disabilities, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Parking permits for individuals with disabilities;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr">Transportation Article, Title 14, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, relating to falsified, altered, or forged documents and plates;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr">Transportation Article, Title 15, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, relating to unlicensed business activity, and §§15-113 and 15-113.1, relating to maintenance of and access to required business records;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr">Transportation Article, Title 16, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, relating to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Unlawful application for a driver's license, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Vehicle operation during periods of cancellation, revocation, or suspension of a driver's license;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr">Transportation Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, relating to required security; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr">Transportation Article, Title 21, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, relating to special residential parking permits issued by the Administration.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Enforcement agent" means any person authorized to issue a citation under these regulations or <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-104">Transportation Article, §12-104</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>General.</heading>
    <text>The Administrator may:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Designate employees of the Investigative Division of the Motor Vehicle Administration as enforcement agents who shall be empowered to issue citations under the authority of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-104">Transportation Article, § 12-104</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>For good cause, remove the authority to issue citations granted to a person authorized as an enforcement agent.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Employee Qualifications.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Character.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person designated as an enforcement agent shall successfully pass a preemployment background investigation and may not have been convicted of a felony.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person designated as an enforcement agent who fails to maintain a good character shall be immediately relieved of the authority to issue citations under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-104">Transportation Article, § 12-104</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland, and may not be reinstated as an enforcement agent without the express authority of the Administrator.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Training. A person designated as an enforcement agent shall be trained:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In all provisions of the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr">Transportation Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, with particular emphasis on Titles 11, 13, 17, and 26;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In the preparation of citations, by an instructor who has been certified by the Maryland Police Training Commission; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>In courtroom procedures.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Experience and Education. A person to be designated as an enforcement agent shall have a minimum of 3 years experience in an investigative or law enforcement capacity, or shall have satisfactorily completed a minimum of 3 years at an accredited college or university.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Performance Standards for Enforcement Agents.</heading>
    <text>Employees designated as enforcement agents under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-104">Transportation Article, § 12-104</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland, and these regulations shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Conduct themselves in such a manner as to bring credit both to themselves and to the Motor Vehicle Administration;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Conduct themselves in a reasonable manner so as to avoid confrontations which may lead to personal injury or embarrassment to the Motor Vehicle Administration; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Continually keep abreast of changes to all aspects of the law, regulations, and policies which may impact on their duties.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-104">12-104</cite>(b), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-104">12-104</cite>.1 and 26-201, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1991-12-09">Effective date: December 9, 1991 (18:24 Md. R. 2644)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-10-16"><cite path="|11|12|06|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective November 17, 1997 (24:23 Md. R. 1611); October 16, 2000 (27:20 Md. R. 1841)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
