<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>06</num>
  <heading>Reporting Pharmacist's, Pharmacy Intern's, and Pharmacy Technician's Mailing Address and Location of Employment</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter applies to each pharmacist, pharmacy intern, and pharmacy technician licensed or registered by the Maryland Board of Pharmacy.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In these regulations, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Board" means the State Board of Pharmacy.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Mailing address" means the address the pharmacist or pharmacy technician specifies that the Board use when communicating with the pharmacist or pharmacy technician.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Primary employment location" means the establishment where the pharmacist or pharmacy technician is employed on a regular basis or works most often.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|34|06|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Mailing Address.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each licensed pharmacist, pharmacy intern, and registered pharmacy technician shall report to the Board the pharmacist’s, pharmacy intern’s, or pharmacy technician’s current mailing address on the pharmacist’s, pharmacy intern’s, or pharmacy technician’s biennial license or registration renewal form.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The mailing address:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>May be the pharmacist’s residence address;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shall be the pharmacy intern’s residence address; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Shall be the pharmacy technician’s residence address.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Within 30 days of the date a pharmacist, pharmacy intern, or pharmacy technician changes the pharmacist’s, pharmacy intern’s, or pharmacy technician’s mailing address, the pharmacist, pharmacy intern, or pharmacy technician shall notify the Board in writing of any change in the information in <cite path="10|34|06|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Place of Employment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This regulation applies only to pharmacists, pharmacy interns, and pharmacy technicians employed in Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Each licensed pharmacist, registered pharmacy intern, and registered pharmacy technician shall report to the Board the pharmacist’s, pharmacy intern’s, or pharmacy technician’s place of employment on the pharmacist, pharmacy intern, or pharmacy technician biennial license or registration renewal form. A pharmacist, pharmacy intern, or pharmacy technician employed at more than one location shall report the primary employment location at the time the renewal form is submitted to the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Within 30 days of a change in the pharmacist’s, pharmacy intern’s, or pharmacy technician’s primary employment location, the pharmacist, pharmacy intern, or pharmacy technician shall notify the Board in writing of any change in the information required by this regulation. If the pharmacist’s, pharmacy intern’s, or pharmacy technician’s primary employment location changes and the pharmacist’s, pharmacy intern’s, or pharmacy technician’s new primary employment location is owned by the same corporation, partnership, or individual owner, the pharmacist, pharmacy intern, or pharmacy technician is not required to report the change except when completing a biennial license or registration renewal form.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Grounds for Disciplinary Action.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A pharmacist’s failure to report the information required in Regulations .03 and .04 of this chapter or failure to provide the Board with complete, up-to-date, and accurate information shall constitute grounds for action under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|12-313">Health Occupations Article, §12-313(b)(25), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and may, in appropriate cases, constitute grounds for action under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|12-313">Health Occupations Article, §12-313(b)(1), </cite>(7), or (8), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A pharmacy technician’s failure to report the information required in Regulations .03 and .04 of this chapter or failure to provide the Board with complete, up-to-date, and accurate information shall constitute grounds for action under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|12-6">Health Occupations Article, §12-6</cite>B-09(25), Annotated Code of Maryland, and may, in appropriate cases, constitute grounds for action under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|12-6">Health Occupations Article, §12-6</cite>B-09(2), (7), or (8), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A pharmacy intern’s failure to report the information required in Regulations .03 and .04 of this chapter or failure to provide the Board with complete, up-to-date, and accurate information:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall constitute grounds for action under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|12-6">Health Occupations Article, §12-6</cite>D-11(18), Annotated Code of Maryland; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>May, in appropriate cases, constitute grounds for action under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|12-6">Health Occupations Article, §12-6</cite>D-11(3), (7), or (8), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|12-205">Health Occupations Article, §12-205, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1980-07-25">Effective date: July 25, 1980 (7:15 Md. R. 1425)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1984-04-09">Chapter, Posting of Prescription Prices and Services, repealed effective April 9, 1984 (11:7 Md. R. 625)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-02-19" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|10|34|06|.01">.01</cite> — <cite path="|10|34|06|.05">.05</cite>, Reporting Pharmacist's Mailing Address and Location of Employment, adopted effective February 19, 1990 (17:3 Md. R. 298)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-03-18">Regulations <cite path="|10|34|06|.01">.01</cite> — <cite path="|10|34|06|.05">.05</cite>, Reporting Pharmacist's and Pharmacy Technician's Mailing Address and Location of Employment amended effective March 18, 2013 (40:5 Md. R. 411)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-07-01">Regulations .01, .03, .04, and .05, Reporting Pharmacist's, Pharmacy Intern's, and Pharmacy Technician's Mailing Address and Location of Employment amended effective  July 1, 2015 (42:7 Md. R. 569)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
