<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>18</num>
  <heading>Continuing Education for Pharmacists</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>These regulations govern any person who desires to renew a license to practice pharmacy in Maryland.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01-1</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following term has the meaning indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Live Instruction.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Live instruction” means a course offering the ability for the participant to have real-time interaction with the presenter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Live instruction” includes programs approved by the American Council on Pharmaceutical Education (ACPE) that are designated by the letter “L” in the course identification number.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Exceptions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter does not apply to pharmacists applying for renewal for the first renewal period following the issuance of the original license, if the pharmacist obtains a license within 1 year of the completion of the pharmacist's pharmaceutical education.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board may grant an exception from the continuing education requirements if the pharmacist presents evidence that failure to comply was due to circumstances beyond the pharmacist's control.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Requirements for Pharmacists Practicing in Maryland.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A pharmacist license expires on the last day of the pharmacist's birth month every other year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Before the expiration date of the pharmacist's license, the pharmacist shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>File a renewal application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Pay any applicable fees; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Earn continuing pharmaceutical education (CE) credits required by this chapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>CE Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A pharmacist licensed to practice in Maryland applying for renewal shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Earn 30 hours of approved CE within the 2-year period immediately preceding the license expiration date that include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>1 hour on the topic of preventing medication errors, such as appropriate dispensing of opioids; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>2 hours of CE obtained through live instruction;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Attest to the fact that the pharmacist has completed the CE requirement on a Board approved form; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Retain supporting documents for inspection by the Board for 4 years after the date of renewal for which the CE credits were used.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A pharmacist certified to administer vaccinations in Maryland applying for renewal shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>As part of the 30 hours of approved CE requirement, complete 4 hours of CE credits related to vaccinations; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If registered to administer vaccines before October 1, 2008 for the first renewal of the registration after that date, demonstrate that 4 CE credits taken include education about the herpes zoster and pneumococcal pneumonia vaccines.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Requirements for Pharmacists Not Practicing in Maryland.</heading>
    <text>A licensed pharmacist not practicing in Maryland shall fulfill the continuing education requirements of Maryland.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Requirements for Pharmacists who are Authorized Prescribers.</heading>
    <text>A pharmacist who is also an authorized prescriber licensed by a board (in Maryland or another state) may use the continuing education (CE) credits applied toward that board toward the Board of Pharmacy's CE requirements.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Accredited Continuing Education Programs.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board and the following providers are approved for any programs they offer which otherwise qualify for continuing education (CE) credit:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>American Council on Pharmaceutical Education (ACPE);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Schools of pharmacy accredited by ACPE;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Food and Drug Administration (FDA);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Drug Enforcement Administration (DEA); and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Additional providers of programs approved by the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Procedures for Approval of Additional Programs.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An additional provider shall request approval for an individual program by submitting a Board application at least 60 days before the date of offering of their individual program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An approval request shall fulfill the program requirements set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|12-309">Health Occupations Article, §12-309(g), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An approval request shall include a description of course work including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Measurable learning objectives;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A course outline; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Self-assessment questions.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Board's decision to approve or disapprove a program is final.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Record Keeping for Providers of Approved Programs.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Providers of approved programs shall maintain program records for 3 years from the date of presentation of the program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Providers of approved programs of CE shall furnish a certificate of completion to participants who qualify. The provider shall include the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Name of the participant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Name of the provider;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Title of the course;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Number of CE hours;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Date of completion; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>A program identification number or provider number on the certificate.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Board may rescind approval of a CE program if it determines that the program no longer meets the requirements of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|12-309">Health Occupations Article, §12-309, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|34|18|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Acceptance of Previously Unapproved Continuing Education Programs.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A pharmacist who completes a program of continuing education that is not previously approved by the Board may request in writing that the Board approve the program for credit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The pharmacist making a request for Board approval under <cite path="10|34|18|.07|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall make the request at least 90 days before licensed expiration.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Miscellaneous.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Credits may not be carried over from one licensing renewal period to another.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Falsifying continuing education CE records is grounds for disciplinary action.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The pharmacist shall use a Board approved form to supply the pharmacist's CE information to the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>CE requirements imposed by the Board upon a pharmacist as part of an informal action, consent order, or final order, as defined in <cite path="10.34.01.02">COMAR 10.34.01.02</cite>, shall be in addition to the requirements of this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Pharmacists may receive 2 CE credits for attending a public Board meeting in its entirety.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board shall issue a certificate of proof of attendance at a public Board meeting.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A pharmacist may not earn more than 4 CE credits per renewal period for attendance of a public Board meeting.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|12-205">12-205</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|12-309">12-309</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1988-08-08">Effective date: August 8, 1988 (15:16 Md. R. 1915)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-07-03"><cite path="|10|34|18|.06|A.">Regulation .06A</cite> amended effective July 3, 1995 (22:13 Md. R. 967)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-07-03"><cite path="|10|34|18|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective July 3, 1995 (22:13 Md. R. 967)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1997-11-03"><cite path="|10|34|18|.08">Regulation .08</cite> adopted effective November 3, 1997 (24:22 Md. R. 1552)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-07-01" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective July 1, 2010 (37:10 Md. R. 722)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-04-30"><cite path="|10|34|18|.01-1">Regulation .01-1</cite> adopted effective April 30, 2012 (39:8 Md. R. 536)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-06-05"><cite path="|10|34|18|.03|C.">Regulation .03C</cite> amended effective June 5, 2017 (44:11 Md. R. 525)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
