<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>24</num>
  <heading>Record of Drug Inventory Acquisition</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>The purpose of this chapter is to establish the minimum requirements for drug acquisition records to be maintained by pharmacy permit holders.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter applies to all pharmacy permit holders in this State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This chapter applies to the acquisition of all prescription medication drug inventories.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>This chapter applies to a pharmacy's acquisition of drug inventory from all sources including, but not limited to, pharmacies, distributors, and manufacturers, and through all means including, but not limited to, purchases, barter or exchange, free goods, rebates, and replacement products.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Minimum Requirements for Maintenance of Drug Acquisition Records.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A pharmacy permit holder shall maintain records of all drug inventory acquisitions.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The records maintained shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The name and principal address of the source of the drugs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The identity and quantity of the drugs received; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The date the drugs were received.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The acquisition records shall be kept for a period of 2 years from the date the inventory was received.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Violation and Inspection.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A pharmacy permit holder shall make the drug inventory acquisition records required under this chapter available for inspection upon request by any federal, state, or local law enforcement agent, or any other duly authorized agent of the Board of Pharmacy or the Division of Drug Control, within 72 hours of the request.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A pharmacy permit holder shall produce and maintain the records required under this chapter for drug acquisitions for all acquisitions except those replaced within 7 days.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|12-205">Health Occupations Article, §12-205(a)(3)(ii), </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-09-17">Effective date: September 17, 2001 (28:18 Md. R. 1621)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
