<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>38</num>
  <heading>Pharmacy Interns</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter applies to applicants for registration as pharmacy interns and to registered pharmacy interns.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This chapter does not apply to pharmacy students:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In a school of pharmacy sanctioned experiential learning program; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Registered as pharmacy technicians with the Board performing delegated pharmacy acts.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>This chapter applies to individuals functioning as a pharmacy intern regardless of whether they are paid.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Board” means the State Board of Pharmacy.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Direct supervision” means that a licensed pharmacist is physically available, notwithstanding appropriate breaks, on-site and in the prescription area or in an area where pharmacy services are provided to supervise the practice of pharmacy and delegated pharmacy acts.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Pharmacy student” means an individual who is enrolled as a student in a school or college of pharmacy:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Accredited by the Accreditation Council for Pharmacy Education; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Having precandidate or candidate status by the Accreditation Council for Pharmacy Education.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Registered pharmacy intern” means an individual who is registered with the Board to practice pharmacy under the direct supervision of a pharmacist.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Registration” means in this chapter, unless the context requires otherwise, a registration issued by the Board to practice pharmacy under the direct supervision of a licensed pharmacist.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Supervision” means reviewing the work, guiding and directing the activities, and monitoring the performance of an individual.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Prohibited Pharmacy Acts.</heading>
    <text>A registered pharmacy intern may not:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Delegate a pharmacy act;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Perform a final verification of a prescription drug or device before dispensing;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Perform any act that has not been authorized by the supervising pharmacist;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Represent themselves as a pharmacist;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Dispense prescription medications when the pharmacist is not in the pharmacy;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Be present in the pharmacy when the pharmacist is not physically available onsite;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Act within the parameters of a therapy management contract as provided under Health Occupations Article, Subtitle 6A, Annotated Code of Maryland;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Independently compound prescriptions; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Accept the return of prescription drugs or devices directly from a patient.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>General Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each registered pharmacy intern shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Display the pharmacy intern’s registration in the office or place of business in which the pharmacy intern is practicing pharmacy under the direct supervision of a licensed pharmacist; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Have the registration on the pharmacy intern’s person available for viewing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>When practicing pharmacy under the direct supervision of a licensed pharmacist, the registered pharmacy intern shall wear identification that conspicuously identifies the registered pharmacy intern as a registered pharmacy intern.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>When performing tasks in the prescription area, a pharmacy intern shall maintain proper:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Sanitation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Hygiene;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Biohazard precautions; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Infection control.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A pharmacy intern, who has obtained a registration as an actively enrolled student, shall immediately notify the Board if the pharmacy intern’s enrollment as a student has been revoked, suspended, terminated, or otherwise discontinued.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Limitation on Supervision.</heading>
    <text>A licensed pharmacist may not directly supervise more than two registered pharmacy interns at one time.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|34|38|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Registration Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant shall be an individual who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is currently enrolled and has completed 1 year of professional pharmacy education in a doctor of pharmacy program:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Accredited by the Accreditation Council for Pharmacy Education; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Having precandidate or candidate status by the Accreditation Council for Pharmacy Education;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Has graduated from a doctor of pharmacy program accredited by the Accreditation Council for Pharmacy Education; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Is a graduate of a foreign school of pharmacy who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Has established educational equivalency as approved by the Board; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has passed an examination of oral English approved by the Board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An applicant identified in <cite path="10|34|38|.06|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Submit to the Board a signed completed application on a form provided by the Board;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Pay a fee as set forth in <cite path="|10.34.09">COMAR 10.34.09</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Submit a request for a State Criminal History Records check; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Be of good moral character.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Board may not approve an application until the State Criminal History Records Check is completed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Board of Pharmacy shall provide the pharmacy intern with a registration card and pocket identification card upon initial registration and renewal.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|34|38|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Renewal Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The pharmacy intern’s registration shall expire on the last day of the birth month following 1 year after initial registration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="10|34|38|.07|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, the Board shall send to each registrant, at least 1 month before a registration expires, a renewal notice by first–class mail to the last known address of the registrant.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If requested by a registrant, the Board shall send to the registrant, at least two times within the month before a registration expires, a renewal notice by electronic means to the last known electronic address of the registrant.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If a renewal notice sent by electronic means under <cite path="10|34|38|.07|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> is returned to the Board as undeliverable, the Board shall send to the registrant a renewal notice by first-class mail to the last known address of the registrant.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A renewal notice sent under this regulation shall state:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The date on which the current registration expires;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The date by which the renewal application must be received by the Board for the renewal to be issued and mailed before the registration expires; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The amount of the renewal fee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A registered pharmacy intern who qualifies for registration under <cite path="|10|34|38|.06|A.|(1)">Regulation .06A(1) of this chapter</cite> may renew the registration one time if the registered pharmacy intern is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Otherwise entitled to be registered as a pharmacy intern;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Submits to the Board a renewal application on the form that the Board requires; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Pays to the Board a renewal fee set by the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A registered pharmacy intern who qualifies for registration under Regulation .06A(2) and (3) of this chapter may not renew the registration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The registration of a pharmacy intern registered under this chapter is void when the registered pharmacy intern becomes a licensed pharmacist.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>The Board shall renew the registration of each pharmacy intern who meets the requirements of this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health-Occupations Article, §§12-205, 12-206, 12-301, 12-315 — 12-317, 12-319, 12-320, 12-505, 12-6D-01 — 12-6D-15, and 12-707, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-07-01">Effective date: July 1, 2015 (42:7 Md. R. 569)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
