<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>39</num>
  <heading>Pharmacist Administration of Self-Administered Drugs</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter does not limit or affect the right of an individual to practice a health occupation that the individual is authorized to practice.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Board” means the State Board of Pharmacy.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Pharmacist” means an individual who practices pharmacy regardless of the location where the activities of practice are performed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Pharmacy” means an establishment holding a permit under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|12-401">Health Occupations Article, §12-401, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Pharmacy Experiential Program” means a program under the American Council on Pharmacy Education.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Practice Pharmacy.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Practice pharmacy” means to engage in any of the following activities:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Providing pharmaceutical care;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Compounding, dispensing, or distributing prescription drugs or devices;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Compounding or dispensing nonprescription drugs or devices;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Monitoring prescriptions and nonprescription drugs or devices;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Providing information, explanation, or recommendations to patients and health care practitioners about the safe and effective use of prescription or nonprescription drugs or devices;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Identifying and appraising problems concerning the use or monitoring of therapy with drugs or devices;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Acting within the parameters of a therapy management contract, as provided under Health Occupations Article, Subtitle 6A, Annotated Code of Maryland; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Administering vaccinations in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|12-508">Health Occupations Article, §12-508, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite> or self-administered drugs in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|12-509">Health Occupations Article, §12-509, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ix)</num>
            <text>Delegating a pharmacy act to a registered pharmacy technician, pharmacy student, or an individual engaged in a Board approved pharmacy technician training program;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(x)</num>
            <text>Supervising a delegated pharmacy act performed by a registered pharmacy technician, pharmacy student, or an individual engaged in a Board approved pharmacy technician training program; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xi)</num>
            <text>Providing drug therapy management in accordance with Health-General Article, §19-713.6, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Practice pharmacy” does not include the operations of a person who holds a permit issued under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|12-602">Health Occupations Article, §12-602, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Registered pharmacy intern” means an individual who is registered with the Board to practice pharmacy under the direct supervision of a pharmacist.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Self-Administered Drug.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Self-administered drug” means a drug that is regularly administered by the patient for whom the drug is prescribed or by an individual who is not otherwise authorized to administer drugs under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|12-509">Health Occupations Article, §12-509, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Self–administered drug” includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Eye drops;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A drug that is administered by an intramuscular injection or a subcutaneous injection;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Ear drops;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Inhalation therapies;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Intranasal therapies; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Topical therapies.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Requirements to Administer Self-Administered Drugs.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A licensed pharmacist shall attest that the pharmacist has the appropriate training in administration of self-administered drugs that consists of instruction on:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Ear drops;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Eye drops;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Inhalation therapies;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Intramuscular injections;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Intranasal therapies;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Subcutaneous injections; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Topical therapies.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A licensed pharmacist shall possess an active certification in basic cardiopulmonary resuscitation obtained through in-person classroom instruction.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A licensed pharmacist, certified under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|12-508">Health Occupations Article, §12-508, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, is deemed to have satisfied the training requirements in this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A licensed pharmacist may administer a self-administered drug in accordance with a prescription.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A pharmacy student in a Pharmacy Experiential Program or a registered pharmacy intern, may administer a self-administered drug under direct supervision of a licensed pharmacist who meets the requirements in §A or B of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Record Keeping.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The pharmacist shall document in the patient record the administration of a self-administered drug that includes the following information:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Name of the drug;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Dosage administered;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Site of administration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Date and time of administration; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Any instructions provided to the patient.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The patient record shall be maintained for 5 years, unless otherwise required by law, and be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Readily retrievable; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Made available on the request of the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health-Occupations Article, §§12-101, 12-102(b), and 12-509, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-05-09">Effective date: May 9, 2016 (43:9 Md. R. 530)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
