<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>41</num>
  <heading>Administration of a Maintenance Injectable Medication</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter does not limit or otherwise affect the right of an individual to practice pharmacy or any other health occupation that the individual is authorized to practice.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Authorized prescriber” means a practitioner licensed and authorized under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, to prescribe prescription drugs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Board” means the Maryland Board of Pharmacy.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Maintenance Injectable Medication.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Maintenance injectable medication” means a medication that:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Is administered by injection other than intravenously;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Except as authorized for a self-administered drug pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|12-509">Health Occupations Article, §12-509, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, is not a biological product; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Treats a chronic need, condition, or disorder.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Maintenance injectable medication” includes, but is not limited to, a medication for:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The treatment of a psychiatric disorder;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The treatment of a substance use disorder;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Contraception; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Vitamins.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Pharmacist” means an individual who practices pharmacy under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|12-101">Health Occupations Article, §12-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Practicing pharmacy” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|12-101">Health Occupations Article, §12-101(x), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Primary care practitioner” means a licensed health care practitioner who provides an individual’s primary care services and is the primary coordinator of health care services for the individual.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Requirements to Administer a Maintenance Injectable Medication — Pharmacist’s Responsibilities.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Upon completion of all requirements established by the Board in this chapter, and after review of all relevant information, a pharmacist may administer a maintenance injectable medication.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In order to administer a maintenance injectable medication, a pharmacist shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Utilize and follow the Board-approved procedure set forth in <cite path="|10|34|41|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite> to administer a maintenance injectable medication;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Refer a patient for additional care to the patient’s primary care practitioner or the authorized prescriber, if necessary;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Provide the patient and the authorized prescriber with a copy of the visit summary, including a written record of the maintenance injectable medication that was administered;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Document the encounter and maintain records pursuant to <cite path="|10|34|41|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Notify the authorized prescriber that the medication was administered to the specific patient and any relevant information about the patient’s condition.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A pharmacist shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Obtain written approval from the patient’s authorized prescriber prior to administering an initial dose of a maintenance injectable medication; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Notify the patient of all fees that the patient is required to pay before administering a maintenance injectable medication.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|34|41|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Training Program Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="10|34|41|.04|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, a pharmacist shall successfully complete a Board-approved training program for the administration of injectable maintenance medications prior to administering injectable maintenance medications.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>At a minimum, a Board-approved training program consists of the following elements:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Administration of a maintenance injectable medication;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Management of the patient populations served by a pharmacist;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Knowledge of the specific maintenance injectable medications that a pharmacist may administer; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Current guidelines relating to the specific patient populations served by a pharmacist and the specific maintenance injectable medications that a pharmacist may administer, if applicable.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The training program requirement set forth in <cite path="10|34|41|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> is waived for a pharmacist who has undergone the training as part of a formal education program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A pharmacy student in a Pharmacy Experiential Program or a registered pharmacy intern, who has successfully completed a Board-approved certification course under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|12-508">Health Occupations Article, §12-508, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, may administer a maintenance injectable medication under the direct supervision of a licensed pharmacist who meets the requirements set forth in <cite path="|10|34|41|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|34|41|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Record Keeping.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A pharmacy that staffs a pharmacist that administers a maintenance injectable medication shall maintain the records of a minor patient, including the information listed in <cite path="10|34|41|.05|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, until the minor patient attains the age of majority plus 3 years or for 5 years after the record was made, whichever is later.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>For a minimum of 5 years, except for records related to minors, a pharmacy that staffs a pharmacist that administers a maintenance injectable medication shall maintain documentation, in electronic or other form, including:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The type and dose of maintenance injectable medication administered;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The name, address, and date of birth of the patient;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The name of the pharmacist who administered the maintenance injectable medication;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The date that the maintenance injectable medication was administered;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A copy of the patient’s visit summary, including any pertinent details about the patient’s condition; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The name and address of the authorized prescriber of the maintenance injectable medication.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A pharmacist who administers an injectable maintenance medication as an independent provider at a location that is not a pharmacy shall maintain records as required by §§A and B of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Patient Information and Consent.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A pharmacist that administers a maintenance injectable medication shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Obtain a paper or electronic consent form signed by the patient, or the patient’s legal guardian, that authorizes the pharmacist to administer the maintenance injectable medication;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide the patient, or the patient’s legal guardian, with a copy of the consent form for future reference upon request;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Provide the patient, or the patient’s legal guardian, and the authorized prescriber with a copy of the visit summary, including a written record of the maintenance injectable medication that was administered; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Notify the patient of the need to attend any upcoming appointments the patient has scheduled with the prescriber for additional care.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The administering pharmacist shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Disclose their credentials on the consent form; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide every patient with notification of the fee for service prior to administration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Standard Procedures.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Before a pharmacist administers a maintenance injectable medication, a pharmacist shall have and maintain a written procedure for any maintenance injectable medication that may be administered.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A pharmacist shall administer a maintenance injectable medication in accordance with the written procedure, including:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Recording and maintaining the prescription files in accordance with <cite path="|10|34|41|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Reviewing and screening for the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Indications;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Precautions;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Contraindications; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Allergies;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Reviewing the process for handling adverse reactions, including but not limited to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Acute anaphylactic reactions; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Other acute emergencies;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Following injection or administration procedures;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Advising the patient of post-administration procedures, including waiting requirements; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Documenting and maintaining a maintenance injectable medication record, including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Patient’s:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Name;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Date of birth;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Address;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Consent form;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Authorized prescriber; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Administering pharmacist’s name and license number;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Administration:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Date;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Dose;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Site; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Route;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Maintenance injectable medication:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Name, generic or brand;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Manufacturer;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Lot number; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Expiration date;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Notification to the authorized prescriber that the patient received a specific maintenance injectable medication; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Verification that the prescription is:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Not for the patient’s initial dose, if applicable; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>For the patient’s initial dose and the patient’s record contains documented approval from the authorized prescriber.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The pharmacist shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Sign and date the standard procedure at least annually;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Make the standard procedure available for inspection by the Board upon request; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Review and update the standard procedure as necessary.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health-Occupations Article, §§12-101(o-1) and 12-509, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-06-13">Effective date: June 13, 2022 (49:12 Md. R. 640)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
