<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Supervision</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <text>Supervision means direction and review by the:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Broker of professional real estate activities by associate brokers, designated sales managers and salespersons associated with that brokerage, regardless of the type of work relationship existing between them;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Broker of the supervisory activities of each branch office manager; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Branch office manager of professional real estate activities by the associate brokers and salespersons registered with that office.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Requirement of Supervision.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A broker shall exercise reasonable and adequate supervision over the activities of the broker's associate brokers and salespersons.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A branch office manager shall exercise reasonable and adequate supervision over the activities of the associate brokers and salespersons registered with that office.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The exercise of reasonable and adequate supervision as defined in this chapter may not be construed or deemed to create an employer/employee relationship between the broker and licensed associated brokers and licensed salespersons under the broker's supervision, or to alter the status of an individual as an independent contractor.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|11|05|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Reasonable and Adequate Supervision.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Initially, the operations characteristics of the brokerage firm shall be considered by determining the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Number of licensed salespersons and associate brokers affiliated with the broker;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Number of branch offices and salespersons assigned to each office;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Number of management personnel in each office;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Normal and routine working days and hours of the broker and management personnel;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Type of real estate activities of firm.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Factors to be considered in determining whether supervision is reasonable and adequate include, but are not limited to, the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Availability of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Training or education sessions held regularly at least once every 2 months;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Experienced supervisory personnel to review and discuss:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Contract provisions;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Brokerage agreement provisions; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Advertising;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Written procedures and policies which provide clear guidance in the following areas:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Proper handling of deposit monies and other funds in accordance with Business Occupations and Professions Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|17-501">17-501</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|17-508">17-508</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Compliance with federal, State, and local fair housing laws and regulations;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Advertisement requirements applicable to real estate transactions;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Review of contracts, leases, and brokerage agreements upon execution by all parties to the contract, lease, or brokerage agreement;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Use and limitations of unlicensed personal assistants;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Disclosure of agency relationships by licensees in residential real estate transactions;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Distribution and dissemination of information on new or changed requirements in real estate laws and regulations enacted by local, State, and federal governments and regulatory agencies;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>The obligation of all licensees to comply with all applicable provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo">Business Occupations and Professions Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite> (the Maryland Real Estate Brokers Act), the Code of Ethics as adopted and as amended from time to time by the Commission, and all applicable local, State, and federal laws and regulations;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ix)</num>
            <text>Requirements, restrictions, and limitations applicable to the sale or lease of real property personally owned by a licensee and the purchase or lease of real property by a licensee for the licensee's personal use; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(x)</num>
            <text>The unauthorized practice of law by a licensee; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Evidence of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Records of attendance at sales meetings;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Review by the broker, branch office manager, or designee of the broker or branch office manager of contracts of sale, leases, and brokerage agreements executed by all parties to the contract, lease, or brokerage agreement;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Review by the broker, branch office manager, or designee of the broker or branch office manager of advertisements to be placed by licensees affiliated with the broker;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Compliance with the written policies and procedures as specified in <cite path="09|11|05|.03|B.|(1)|(c)">§B(1)(c) of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Dissemination of the written policies and procedures as specified in <cite path="09|11|05|.03|B.|(1)|(c)">§B(1)(c) of this regulation</cite> to licensees affiliated with the broker.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>On a showing that the broker has not provided reasonable and adequate supervision in the areas under <cite path="09|11|05|.03|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, the burden of proof shall be on the broker to show that the supervision which the broker did provide was reasonable and adequate.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Business Occupations and Professions Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|17-208">17-208</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|17-320">17-320</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1988-03-21">Effective date: March 21, 1988 (15:6 Md. R. 739)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-09-17">Chapter revised effective September 17, 2001 (28:18 Md. R. 1620)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
