<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Firearms Training</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter establishes Commission requirements for an individual regulated by the Commission for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Firearms classroom instruction and training and qualification; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Authorization to use or carry a firearm.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Commission requirements are minimum requirements. Therefore, a law enforcement agency may adopt more stringent requirements for firearms classroom instruction and training and qualification.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>This chapter does not apply to a firearm authorized by a law enforcement agency for use by a police officer which discharges a projectile that is not intended to cause death.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Academy" means a college, school, training unit, or training facility certified or approved by the Commission to conduct entrance-level and other training programs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Agency Head.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Agency head" means:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A police chief, sheriff, administrator, department head, an individual in an equivalent position, or a designee; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>An individual appointed, employed, or elected to manage, administer, or supervise a law enforcement agency.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Agency head" includes a director of an academy or a training unit, or a designee, authorized to act in employment or training matters.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Barricade" means an object, fixed position or portable, that in whole or in part provides cover or concealment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Certification" means that an individual meets the requirements for firearms classroom instruction, training, and qualification established under <cite path="|12.04.06">COMAR 12.04.06</cite> for a provisional, line, and firearms instructor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Classroom Instruction.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Classroom instruction" means training conducted in a traditional educational setting; for example, in a room with desks, chairs, books, paper, and other educational tools or equipment.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Classroom instruction" does not include training conducted on a firing line.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Commission" means the Police Training and Standards Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Course of Fire.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Course of fire" means a sequence of activities related to the actual discharge of a firearm on a firing line for training or qualification.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Course of fire" does not include classroom instruction.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Day-Fire.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Day-fire" means firearms training or qualification, or both, conducted during normal outdoor lighting conditions that exist between dawn and dusk.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Day-fire" includes the indoor equivalent or other lighting conditions that simulate normal outdoor lighting conditions that exist between dawn and dusk.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Deputy Director" means the Deputy Director of the Police and Correctional Training Commissions, or a designee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Entrance-level" means initial classroom instruction, training, or qualification with a firearm regardless of experience or training with a different type of firearm.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Firearm" means a pistol, revolver, or long gun.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>"Firearms instructor" means an individual certified by the Commission according to the requirements established under <cite path="|12.04.06">COMAR 12.04.06</cite> to perform firearms classroom instruction and conduct firearms training and qualification.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>"Firing line" means those areas and positions from which an individual actually discharges a firearm with live ammunition for training or qualification, or both, as part of a course of fire.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>Firing Line Controller.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Firing line controller" means the line instructor or firearms instructor responsible for issuing commands on a firing line during firearms training and qualification.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Firing line controller" includes a line instructor actually on the firing line or in a structure overseeing the firearms training and qualification conducted on the firing line.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>Handgun.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Handgun" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|5-101">Public Safety Article, §5-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Handgun" includes a:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Pistol; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Revolver.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>Iron Sight.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Iron sight" means a system of shaped alignment markers, typically metal or plastic that are used as a sighting device to assist an individual in aiming a firearm.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Iron sight" does not mean an optical, computing, red dot, or reflex style sighting device.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>"Judgmental or decision training" means instruction and skills development conducted in the classroom, using firearms simulation, or on a firing line, to enable an individual to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Differentiate between threat levels; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Respond appropriately to an identified threat.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>Law Enforcement Agency.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Law enforcement agency" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|3-201">Public Safety Article, §3-201, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Law enforcement agency" includes an academy, personnel unit, or training unit authorized by the Commission to act in training matters or provide law enforcement training.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>Line Instructor.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Line instructor" means an individual certified by the Commission according to the requirements established under <cite path="|12.04.06">12.04.06</cite> to conduct law enforcement firearms training and qualification on a firing line.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Line instructor" may not perform classroom instruction.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>Long Gun.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Long gun" means a firearm designed to be fired from the shoulder.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Long gun" includes a:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Type 1 long gun;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Type 2 long gun;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Type 3 long gun; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Type 4 long gun.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>Optical Sighting Device.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Optical sighting device" means an optic mechanism that assists an individual in sighting a firearm by enhancing or magnifying the image of the target and superimposing a reticle, or an aligned aiming point, over the image.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Optical sighting device" does not include an iron sight or a red dot sight.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>"Pistol" means a handgun that operates semi-automatically:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Discharging a single round of ammunition with a pull of the trigger;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Clearing the chamber of the spent casing; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Loading the next round of ammunition in the chamber.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>"Police officer" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|3-201">Public Safety Article, §3-201, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(24)</num>
        <text>"Power" means a measurement used to describe levels of visual magnification, with a number representing the level of magnification above the normal visual range.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(25)</num>
        <text>"Primary handgun" means the handgun authorized or issued by a law enforcement agency and designated by that agency for a police officer to use or carry as the officer's principal handgun.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(26)</num>
        <text>"Qualification" means proficiency testing by discharging a firearm on a Commission-approved course of fire to receive a score that the Commission measures against established requirements to determine if the individual is authorized to use or carry a specific firearm.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(27)</num>
        <text>Red Dot Sight.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Red dot sight" means a generic term to describe a visual, computing, or reflex sighting device that reflects a reticle, or an aligned aiming point that can be any shape or color, onto a combining glass for superimposition on a target.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Red dot sight" does not include an optical sighting device or an iron sight.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(28)</num>
        <text>Reduced Light.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Reduced light" means the normal outdoor lighting conditions that exist between dusk and dawn.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Reduced light" includes simulated natural outdoor lighting conditions such as:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Artificial light; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Goggles, headgear, or an apparatus worn to cover the eyes designed to reduce the availability of light to simulate natural reduced lighting conditions.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(29)</num>
        <text>"Revolver" means a handgun that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Fires a single round of ammunition with each pull of the trigger; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has a cylinder containing additional rounds of ammunition that rotates to position the next round of ammunition for firing.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(30)</num>
        <text>"Secondary handgun" means a handgun, other than a primary handgun, that a police officer is authorized by the officer's law enforcement agency to use or carry on-duty or off-duty.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(31)</num>
        <text>"Strong hand" means the hand:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>On the same side of the body where an individual would normally carry a handgun in a holster; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>That the individual would primarily use to discharge a firearm.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(32)</num>
        <text>Training.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Training" means a demonstration or an exercise, in addition to classroom instruction, provided by an individual certified under <cite path="|12.04.06">COMAR 12.04.06</cite>, to enhance understanding, proficiency, marksmanship, and other skills related to proper firearm use and tactics such as movement, multiple targets, judgmental or decision training, and use of cover and concealment.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Training" may include drills that involve discharging rounds.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(33)</num>
        <text>"Type 1 long gun" means a long gun with an optical sighting device greater than 4 power intended for use as a counter-sniper firearm.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(34)</num>
        <text>"Type 2 long gun" means a long gun with an optical sighting device greater than 4 power intended for use other than as a counter-sniper firearm.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(35)</num>
        <text>"Type 3 long gun" means a long gun without an optical sighting device, or with an optical sighting device of 4 power or less.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(36)</num>
        <text>Type 4 Long Gun.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Type 4 long gun" means a long gun manufactured and sold as a shotgun that is designed to discharge a single projectile or multiple projectiles from a single round of ammunition.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Type 4 long gun" includes a long gun manufactured and sold as a shotgun regardless of the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Action; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Use of an optical sighting device.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(37)</num>
        <text>"Weak hand" means the hand that is not considered the strong hand.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>General Requirements — Authorized Firearms Classroom Instruction, Training, and Qualification, and Firing Line Supervision.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Handgun and Firearms Classroom Instruction, Training, and Qualification Requirements — General.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A police officer may not use or carry a firearm unless:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The firearm and any attached devices or equipment are approved by the police officer's law enforcement agency;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The law enforcement agency authorizes the police officer to use or carry the firearm; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The police officer successfully completes the applicable firearms classroom instruction, training, and qualification for the firearm established under this chapter.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a firearm becomes defective or unavailable to a police officer during firearms training or qualification, a substitute firearm may be used for the firearms training or qualification if the substitute firearm is the same type, model, manufacture, caliber, and barrel length as the defective or unavailable firearm.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All handguns must be equipped with usable iron sights whether used as the primary sighting device or as a back-up, secondary sighting device.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Entrance-Level Firearms Classroom Instruction, Training, and Qualification.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>For an individual to be initially authorized to use or carry a firearm, except a secondary handgun or a firearm for which authorization is provided through conversion under <cite path="|12|04|02|.09">Regulation .09 of this chapter</cite>, the individual shall successfully complete entrance-level firearms classroom instruction, training, and qualification required for the firearm established under this chapter.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Entrance-level firearms classroom instruction, training, and qualification may be:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Included in entrance-level law enforcement classroom instruction, training, and qualification under <cite path="|12.04.01">COMAR 12.04.01</cite>; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Independent of entrance-level law enforcement classroom instruction, training, and qualification.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Commission firearms training objectives required for the entrance-level firearms classroom instruction, training, and qualification are available from the Commission upon written request.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Secondary Handgun.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Before a police officer may use or carry a secondary handgun, the police officer shall successfully complete entrance-level classroom instruction, training, and qualification for a primary handgun established under <cite path="|12|04|02|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>After completing entrance-level classroom instruction, training, and qualification with a primary handgun, a police officer shall successfully complete the following requirements for the secondary handgun:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Annual handgun classroom instruction, training, and qualification course of fire requirements if the secondary handgun is the same type as the officer's primary handgun and the officer's agency does not require handgun conversion for the secondary handgun under <cite path="|12|04|02|.09">Regulation .09 of this chapter</cite>; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Handgun conversion classroom instruction, training, and qualification requirements under <cite path="|12|04|02|.09">Regulation .09 of this chapter</cite> for the secondary handgun if the secondary handgun is a different type than the officer's primary handgun.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Firing Line Supervision Requirements — General.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At least one provisional instructor, line instructor, or firearms instructor shall be present for every five or fewer individuals on the firing line.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If more than one provisional instructor, line instructor, or firearms instructor is required to be present, the individual responsible for the firearms training and qualification shall designate a firearms instructor or line instructor to supervise the firing line.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If more than 15 individuals are on the firing line:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The individual responsible for the firearms training and qualification shall assign a firing line controller; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The firing line controller may not be counted as part of the one-to-five ratio required under this regulation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Firearms Classroom Instruction, Training, and Qualification Approval and Minimum Hours.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Commission Approval.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Written approval by the Commission is required for firearms classroom instruction, training, and qualification.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A law enforcement agency requesting approval shall submit the request to the Commission 20 days before the agency plans to start the classroom instruction, training, or qualification.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The minimum hours required for firearms classroom instruction, training, and qualification established under this chapter:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Only include the actual hours of firearms classroom instruction, training, and qualification; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Do not include meals and breaks.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="12|04|02|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Entrance-Level Firearms Classroom Instruction, Training, and Qualification — Primary Handgun.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An individual shall successfully complete the minimum requirements for entrance-level handgun classroom instruction, training, and qualification established under this regulation before using or carrying a primary handgun.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Except as required in <cite path="12|04|02|.04|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, the minimum entrance-level classroom instruction, training, and qualification for a primary handgun includes:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>35 hours of classroom instruction, training, and qualification;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Classroom instruction topics marked with an "X" under Entrance-Level Handgun Training in the table under <cite path="|12|04|02|.10|B.">Regulation .10B of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The following activities conducted over a minimum of three calendar days:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Firearms training exercises; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A course of fire for qualification for scoring that includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Three consecutive day-fire courses of fire; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>One reduced light course of fire;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Use of ammunition authorized by the individual's law enforcement agency, or the ballistic equivalent when firing for qualification;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Discharging a minimum of 1,000 rounds of ammunition for firearms training and qualification collectively; and if the primary sighting device is a red dot sight then a minimum of 20 percent of the rounds must be fired using the firearm's iron sight; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The course of fire requirements outlined in the table under <cite path="|12|04|02|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The following requirements shall be imposed if the handgun is equipped with a red dot sight:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>At least one of the three consecutive day-fire courses must be fired with the iron sight; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>One reduced light course will be fired with each of the handgun's sighting devices.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Course of Fire Requirements for Handgun Qualification.</heading>
    <text>The following table establishes the minimum entrance-level, annual, and conversion courses of fire requirements for primary handgun qualification:</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>Type of Requirement</th>
            <th>Handgun <br/>Day-Fire Required Course of <br/>Fire for Qualification</th>
            <th>Handgun<br/>Reduced Light Required Course of<br/>Fire for Qualification</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td class="text-indent-1">(1) Rounds to be discharged with one finger on the trigger</td>
            <td>Minimum of 30 rounds on each course of fire</td>
            <td>Minimum of 30 rounds on the course of fire</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td class="text-indent-1">(2) Minimum passing score</td>
            <td>70 percent on each of the three successive courses of fire</td>
            <td>70 percent</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td class="text-indent-1">(3) Target description</td>
            <td>Depiction of human torso or silhouette marked to indicate scoring values in a maximum scoring area of 725 square inches</td>
            <td>Depiction of human torso or silhouette marked to indicate scoring values in a maximum scoring area of 725 square inches.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td class="text-indent-1">(4) Required percentages of rounds to be fired, and required firing distances</td>
            <td>A minimum of 10 percent, but not more than 40 percent, of the course of fire rounds shall be discharged at each of the following four range of distances: <br/>   (a) Less than 5 yards; <br/>   (b) 5 yards to less than 10 yards; <br/>   (c) 10 to less than 25 yards; and <br/>   (d) 25 yards or farther.</td>
            <td>A minimum of 10 percent, but no more than 40 percent, of the course of fire rounds shall be discharged at each of the following three range of distances: <br/>   (a) Less than 5 yards; <br/>   (b) 5 yards to less than 15 yards; and <br/>   (c) 15 yards or farther</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td class="text-indent-1">(5) Maximum time permitted per round of ammunition fired at specified distances</td>
            <td class="text-indent-2">(a) 2 seconds per round when firing at less than 5 yards; <br/>   (b) 3 seconds per round when firing at 5 yards to less than 10 yards; <br/>   (c) 4 seconds per round when firing at 10 yards to less than 25 yards; <br/>   (d) 5 seconds per round when firing at 25 yards, or farther</td>
            <td class="text-indent-2">(a) 2 seconds per round when firing at less than 5 yards; <br/>   (b) 3 seconds per round when firing at 5 yards to less than 15 yards; <br/>   (c) 4 seconds per round when firing at 15 yards, or farther</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td class="text-indent-1">(6) Maximum time permitted to move from one specified firing position to the next</td>
            <td>5 seconds</td>
            <td>5 seconds</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td class="text-indent-1">(7) Maximum time permitted for each instance of reloading the handgun during the course of fire</td>
            <td>Revolver—17 seconds <br/>Pistol—8 seconds</td>
            <td>Revolver—17 seconds <br/>Pistol—8 seconds</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td class="text-indent-1">(8) Minimum requirements for holding the handgun while discharging rounds during the course of fire</td>
            <td class="text-indent-2">(a) Strong hand supported by weak hand; <br/>   (b) Strong hand with no support; <br/>   (c) Weak hand supported by strong hand; and <br/>   (d) Weak hand with no support</td>
            <td class="text-indent-2">(a) Strong hand supported by weak hand; <br/>   (b) Strong hand with no support; <br/>   (c) Weak hand supported by strong hand; and <br/>   (d) Weak hand with no support</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td class="text-indent-1">(9) Minimum body positions from which rounds are to be fired during the course of fire</td>
            <td class="text-indent-2">(a) Standing; <br/>   (b) Kneeling; and <br/>   (c) Two different positions from barricade</td>
            <td class="text-indent-2">(a) Standing; and <br/>   (b) Kneeling</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td class="text-indent-1">(10) Supplemental lighting conditions suggested during course of fire</td>
            <td>Not Applicable</td>
            <td>At least one of the following: <br/>   (a) Flares; <br/>   (b) Street lights; <br/>   (c) Vehicle lights; <br/>   (d) Flashlights; <br/>   (e) Vehicle emergency lights; or <br/>   (f) Alternate lighting source</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Entrance-Level Firearms Classroom Instruction, Training, and Qualification — Long Guns.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An individual shall successfully complete the minimum requirements for entrance-level long gun classroom instruction, training, and qualification established under this regulation before using or carrying a long gun.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The minimum requirements for entrance-level long gun classroom instruction, training, and qualification include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Classroom instruction topics marked with an "X" under the column for Entrance-Level Long Gun Training on the table under <cite path="|12|04|02|.10|B.">Regulation .10B of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The following total hours of classroom instruction, training, and qualification for a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Type 1 long gun, 35 hours;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Type 2 long gun, 35 hours;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Type 3 long gun, 14 hours; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Type 4 long gun, 7 hours;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Discharging the following number of rounds of ammunition at a target for training and qualification for a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Type 1 long gun, 150 rounds;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Type 2 long gun, 350 rounds;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Type 3 long gun, 350 rounds; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Type 4 long gun, 50 rounds; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Successfully completing qualification requirements on a day-fire course of fire for the specific type of long gun established in the table under <cite path="|12|04|02|.07|A.">Regulation .07A of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Course of Fire Requirements for Long Gun Qualification.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A Type 1 and Type 2 long gun qualification may only be conducted using agency approved ammunition.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A Type 3 and Type 4 long gun qualification may be conducted using agency approved ammunition or the ballistic equivalent as defined and authorized by the individual’s agency.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The following table establishes the minimum requirements for entrance-level, annual, and conversion courses of fire for type 1 through type 4 long gun qualification:</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Requirement</th>
              <th>Type 1 <br/>Long Gun</th>
              <th>Type 2 <br/>Long Gun</th>
              <th>Type 3 <br/>Long Gun</th>
              <th>Type 4 <br/>Long Gun</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Rounds to be Discharged</td>
              <td>Minimum of 20 rounds on one day-fire course of fire</td>
              <td>Minimum of 30 rounds on one day-fire course of fire</td>
              <td>Minimum of 30 rounds on one day-fire course of fire</td>
              <td>Minimum of 10 rounds on one day-fire course of fire</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Passing Score</td>
              <td>100 percent</td>
              <td>80 percent</td>
              <td>80 percent</td>
              <td>70 percent</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(3) Target Description</td>
              <td>The target scoring area may not exceed 80 square inches. 80 square inches equals the 9 and 10 ring of a "B-27" target</td>
              <td>The target scoring area may not exceed 183 square inches. 183 square inches equals a "TQ19" target or the 8, 9 and 10 ring of a "B-27" target</td>
              <td>The target scoring area may not exceed 255 square inches. 255 square inches equals a "Q" target</td>
              <td>The target scoring area may not exceed 725 square inches. 725 square inches equals a "B-27" full size target</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(4)  Required percentages of rounds to be fired and required firing distances</td>
              <td>A minimum of 10 percent but not more than 30 percent of the course of fire rounds shall be discharged at each distance within the following parameters: <br/>   (a) 25 yards; <br/>   (b) Two distances greater than 25 yards and less than 200 yards; and <br/>   (c) At least one distance 200 yards or greater</td>
              <td>A minimum of 10 percent but not more than 30 percent of the course of fire rounds shall be discharged at each distance within the following parameters: <br/>   (a) 15 yards; <br/>   (b) Two distances greater than 15 yards and less than 100 yards; and <br/>   (c) At least one distance 100 yards or greater</td>
              <td>A minimum of 10 percent but not more than 30 percent of the course of fire rounds shall be discharged at each distance within the following parameters: <br/>   (a) 15 yards; <br/>   (b) Two distances greater than 15 yards and less than 50 yards; and <br/>   (c) At least one distance 50 yards or greater</td>
              <td>A minimum of 20 percent but not more than 40 percent of the course of fire rounds shall be discharged at each distance within the following parameters: <br/>   (a) 5 yards to less than 15 yards; <br/>   (b) 15 yards to less than 25 yards; and <br/>   (c) At least one distance 25 yards or greater</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(5)  Maximum time permitted per round at specified distances</td>
              <td>5 seconds per round when firing at 25 yards or less; The number of seconds per round when firing at distances between 25 yards and 200 yards shall be proportional to the distances and times allowed; 10 seconds per round when firing at 200 yards, or farther</td>
              <td>4 seconds per round when firing at 15 yards or less; The number of seconds per round when firing at distances between 15 yards and 100 yards shall be proportional to the distances and times allowed; 8 seconds per round when firing at 100 yards, or farther</td>
              <td>4 seconds per round when firing at 15 yards or less; The number of seconds per round when firing at distances between 15 yards and 50 yards shall be proportional to the distances and times allowed; 8 seconds per round when firing at 50 yards, or farther</td>
              <td>3 seconds per round when firing at 5 yards to less than 15 yards; 4 seconds per round when firing at 15 yards to less than 25 yards; and 5 seconds per round when firing at 25 yards, or farther</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(6) Maximum time permitted to move from one specified firing position to the next</td>
              <td colspan="4" data-vertical-align="middle">5 seconds</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(7) Reloading times</td>
              <td colspan="4" data-vertical-align="middle">Reloading Time: When qualifying on any type of long gun; an additional 5 seconds may be added to the maximum seconds:<br/>   (a) For each round of ammunition reloaded on a long gun with an integral magazine; and<br/>   (b) For reloading a long gun with a detachable box magazine.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(8)  Firing positions from which the long gun shall be discharged</td>
              <td colspan="3" class="text-indent-1">(a) Standing (unsupported) <br/>   (b) Standing (supported) <br/>   (c) Kneeling or sitting (supported or unsupported); <br/>   (d) Prone; and <br/>   (e) Using a barricade to discharge the long gun from at least one of the above firing positions</td>
              <td class="text-indent-1">(a) Standing (unsupported) <br/>   (b) Standing (supported) <br/>   (c) Kneeling or sitting (supported or unsupported); and <br/>   (d) Using a barricade to discharge the long gun from at least one of the above firing positions</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(9)  Stress</td>
              <td colspan="3" data-vertical-align="middle">To simulate stress when qualifying on type 1, 2, or 3 long gun, the individual shall perform physical exercise before firing from at least one position listed in this table under the firing positions (No. 5 in this table).</td>
              <td>Optional</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="12|04|02|.08">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Annual Firearms Classroom Instruction, Training, and Qualification Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General Requirements — All Firearms.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>During each calendar year, a police officer shall successfully complete the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Classroom instruction for each firearm type the police officer is authorized to use or carry;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Training for each firearm the police officer is authorized to use or carry; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Qualification for each firearm the police officer is authorized to use or carry.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Annual Classroom Instruction.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A police officer shall complete a minimum of 2 hours of classroom instruction as part of the requirements established under this regulation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Classroom instruction shall include the classroom instruction topics marked with an "X" under Annual Firearms Training in the table under <cite path="|12|04|02|.10|B.">Regulation .10B of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Commission may accept up to 2 hours of a police officer's annual firearms classroom instruction as part of a police officer's annual in-service training required under <cite path="|12.04.01">COMAR 12.04.01</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Annual Handgun Requirements — Training and Qualification.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Required Firearms Training — Primary Handgun.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A police officer shall annually discharge a minimum of 30 rounds of ammunition approved by the police officer's law enforcement agency, or the ballistic equivalent, for training with the police officer's primary handgun.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Training drills to improve the police officer's skills may be incorporated into a course of fire.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Training may not include practicing the actual course of fire used for qualification.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Course of Fire for Qualification — Primary and Secondary Handgun.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>For each handgun a police officer is authorized to use or carry, with one finger on the trigger the police officer shall discharge a minimum of 30 rounds of ammunition using ammunition authorized by the police officer's agency, or the ballistic equivalent, on each of the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>One day-fire course of fire;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>One reduced light course of fire; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>If the handgun is equipped with a red dot sight, a one-day course of fire and a one-day reduced light course shall be fired with both the iron sights as well as the red dot sight.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Police officer annual course of fire for qualification consists of requirements 3 through 10 in the Course of Fire Requirements for Handgun table under <cite path="|12|04|02|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A minimum score of 70 percent is required on both a day-fire and a reduced light course of fire for qualification for each handgun for which annual certification to be a police officer is required by <cite path="12.04.01.12">COMAR 12.04.01.12</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Annual Long Gun Requirements — Firearms Training and Qualification.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Firearms training for each long gun a police officer is authorized to use or carry consists of demonstrations to familiarize a police officer with the nomenclature, operation, safety, care, and cleaning of the specific long gun type.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Course of Fire for Annual Long Gun Qualification.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>During each calendar year, a police officer authorized to use or carry a specific type of long gun shall successfully complete the course of fire requirements for qualification for the specific long gun, as described in this subsection.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Type 1 Long Gun Qualification. Annual firearms qualification requires a police officer to successfully complete four courses of fire for qualification, one during each quarter of a calendar year, for the specific type of long gun the police officer is authorized to use or carry according to the requirements established in the Course of Fire Requirements for Long Gun Qualification table under <cite path="|12|04|02|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Type 2 and Type 3 Long Gun Qualification. Annual firearms qualification requires a police officer to successfully complete two courses of fire for qualification, one during each half of the calendar year, for the specific type of long gun the police officer is authorized to use or carry according to the requirements established in the Course of Fire Requirements for Long Gun Qualification table under <cite path="|12|04|02|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Type 4 Long Gun Qualification. Annual firearms qualification requires a police officer to successfully complete one course of fire for qualification, each calendar year, for the specific type of long gun the police officer is authorized to use or carry according to the requirements established in the table under <cite path="|12|04|02|.07|A.">Regulation .07A of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Reporting Firearm Qualification Scores to the Commission. By January 31 of the calendar year immediately following firearms qualification, an agency head shall submit to the Commission a police officer's required firearms qualification score for each firearm the police officer is authorized to use or carry.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Failure to Meet Commission Annual Firearms Classroom Instruction, Training, and Qualification Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a police officer fails to successfully complete Commission annual firearms classroom instruction, training, and qualification requirements for an authorized firearm within a calendar year, the agency head:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Shall remove the firearm, or authorization to use or carry the firearm if personally owned, from the police officer by January 1 of the next calendar year; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>May not return or authorize the police officer to use or carry the firearm until the police officer successfully completes the appropriate firearms classroom instruction, training, and qualification required under this chapter.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Failure to Qualify with a Firearm.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A police officer who fails an annual firearms qualification required under <cite path="|12|04|02|.08">Regulation .08 of this chapter</cite> shall successfully complete qualification within:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>30 consecutive calendar days of the initial attempt; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The same calendar year as the initial attempt.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If a police officer does not successfully meet qualification requirements within the period established under <cite path="12|04|02|.08|E.|(2)|(a)">§E(2)(a) of this regulation</cite>, the police officer's agency head shall immediately:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Report to the Commission the police officer's failure to qualify;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Require the police officer to surrender the firearm to the agency, if it was issued by the agency; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Withdraw the police officer's authority to use or carry the firearm, if personally owned.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A police officer may not use or carry a firearm that has been surrendered or for which authority to carry or use has been withdrawn, except during supervised training to meet the police officer's annual firearms training and qualification for the firearm required under this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="12|04|02|.09">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Firearms Conversion — Classroom Instruction, Training, and Qualification.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A police officer who has successfully completed entrance-level firearms classroom instruction, training, and qualification for a specific type of firearm, who is also required or requesting to use or carry a firearm with a red dot sight or of a different type for which the police officer has qualified, shall successfully complete:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Firearms conversion classroom instruction, training, and qualification requirements established under this regulation for the different firearm type; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Entrance-level classroom instruction, training, and qualification established under this chapter for the different firearm.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A police officer shall successfully complete firearms conversion requirements under this regulation before being authorized to use or carry a different type of firearm if the police officer is currently authorized to use or carry a:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Primary handgun type and is seeking authorization to use or carry a handgun of a different type as a primary handgun;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Primary handgun type and is required or requesting to add a red dot sight;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Type 1 long gun, and is seeking authorization to use or carry a type 2 or 3 long gun; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Type 2 long gun, and is seeking authorization to use or carry a type 3 long gun.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Conversion Classroom Instruction, Training, and Qualification for Primary Handgun and Long Gun within the Same Type.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except for provisions under <cite path="12|04|02|.09|C.|(2)">§C(2) of this regulation</cite>, a police officer is not required to complete firearms conversion classroom instruction, training, and qualification under this regulation before the police officer is authorized to use or carry a primary handgun or a long gun that is the same type that the police officer is currently authorized to use or carry.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A police officer is required to complete firearms conversion classroom instruction, training, and qualification under this regulation before the police officer is authorized to use or carry a primary handgun or a long gun that is the same type that the police officer is currently authorized to use or carry if the police officer's agency determines:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>There is a difference in operation between the firearms; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Conversion classroom instruction, training, and qualification are warranted to ensure safe and effective use of the firearm.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Primary Handgun Conversion — Classroom Instruction, Training, and Qualification.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a police officer is required to complete conversion classroom instruction, training, and qualification according to §B or C(2) of this regulation, the police officer shall successfully complete:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>For a different type primary handgun, the classroom instruction topics marked with an "X" for Handgun Conversion Training — Different Type Handgun in the table under <cite path="|12|04|02|.10|B.">Regulation .10B of this chapter</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For a handgun within the same type, the classroom instruction topics marked with an "X" for Handgun Conversion Training — Within a Handgun Type in the table under <cite path="|12|04|02|.10|B.">Regulation .10B of this chapter</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>For adding a red dot sight, the classroom instruction topics marked with an "X" for Handgun Conversion Training — Red Dot Sight.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Course of Fire.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If a police officer is required to complete conversion classroom instruction, training, and qualification according to §B or C(2) of this regulation, with one finger on the trigger the police officer shall discharge a minimum of 30 rounds of ammunition for each course of fire required for conversion qualification.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Ammunition used for a required course of fire for conversion qualification shall be ammunition that is:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Authorized by the police officer's law enforcement agency; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The ballistic equivalent of the ammunition authorized by the police officer's law enforcement agency.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The required course of fire for conversion qualification shall be completed according to requirements 3 through 10 of the table under <cite path="|12|04|02|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The following table specifies the minimum requirements for classroom instruction, training, and qualification for primary handgun conversion:</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th>Type of Requirement</th>
                <th>Conversion for Red Dot Sight</th>
                <th>Conversion for Different Primary Handgun Type</th>
                <th>Conversion Within Primary Handgun Type</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td>(1) Total minimum hours of classroom instruction, training, and qualification</td>
                <td>14 hours</td>
                <td>14 hours</td>
                <td>7 hours</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(2) Training drill topics</td>
                <td colspan="3" data-vertical-align="middle">(a) Reinforcement of the fundamentals of shooting; <br/>(b) Reloading techniques; <br/>(c) Clearing malfunctions <br/>(d) Finding the dot; <br/>(e) Sight occlusion; <br/>(f) Close up techniques; and <br/>(g) Target focusing.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(3) Minimum number of training rounds to be discharged at a target</td>
                <td>400 rounds</td>
                <td>400 rounds</td>
                <td>200 rounds</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(4) Minimum passing score for each required qualification course of fire</td>
                <td colspan="3" data-vertical-align="middle">70 percent for each of one day-fire and one reduced light course of fire</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Long Gun Authorization for which Conversion Training is Permitted.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Before a police officer may participate in conversion classroom instruction, training, and qualification for a long gun, the police officer shall currently be authorized to use or carry a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Type 1 long gun, if conversion is for another type 1 long gun, a type 2 long gun, or a type 3 long gun;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Type 2 long gun, if conversion is for another type 2 long gun or a type 3 long gun; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Type 3 long gun, if conversion is for another type 3 long gun.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A police officer converting from one type of long gun to another type of long gun not listed under <cite path="12|04|02|.09|E.|(1)">§E(1) of this regulation</cite> shall successfully complete entrance-level firearms classroom instruction, training, and qualification for the long gun to which the police officer is converting.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Long Gun Conversion — Classroom Instruction, Training, and Qualification.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Long gun conversion classroom instruction shall, at a minimum, include the Classroom Instruction Topics marked with an "X" under Firearms Conversion Training—Long Gun in the table under <cite path="|12|04|02|.10|B.">Regulation .10B of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Long gun conversion classroom instruction, training, and qualification shall, at a minimum, meet the applicable criteria in the following table:</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th>Requirements</th>
                <th>Within Type 1 <br/>Long Gun</th>
                <th>Within Type 2 <br/>Long Gun</th>
                <th>Within Type 3 <br/>Long Gun</th>
                <th>From <br/>Type 1 to Type 2</th>
                <th>From <br/>Type 1 or 2 to Type 3</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td>(1) Minimum rounds discharged</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">80</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">150</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">150</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">150</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">150</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(2) Minimum hours for classroom instruction and training and qualification</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">14</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">14</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">7</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">14</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(3) Number of day-fire courses of fire</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">1</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">1</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">1</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">1</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">1</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The course of fire for long gun conversion qualification shall meet the requirements specified for the type of long gun established in the table under <cite path="|12|04|02|.07|A.">Regulation .07A of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Crediting Conversion Classroom Instruction, Training, and Qualification Toward Annual Training.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A law enforcement agency may use the following conversion training toward a police officer's annual firearms classroom instruction, training, and qualification requirements for the specific firearm used in the conversion training conducted in the same calendar year:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>One day-fire conversion qualification score; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>One reduced light conversion qualification score.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If firearms conversion classroom instruction is less than 14 hours, a law enforcement agency may use a maximum of 2 hours of the firearms conversion classroom instruction toward meeting a police officer's annual firearms classroom instruction requirements in the same calendar year the conversion training was conducted.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If firearms conversion classroom instruction is 14 hours or more, a law enforcement agency may use a maximum of 6 hours of the firearms conversion classroom instruction toward meeting a police officer's annual firearms classroom instruction requirements for the same calendar year the conversion training was conducted.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="12|04|02|.10">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Classroom Instruction Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The table in <cite path="12|04|02|.10|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> establishes minimum required classroom instruction topics for firearms classroom instruction.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An "X" in the following table indicates that the corresponding classroom instruction topic is required for the specified type of training:</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Classroom Instruction Topics</th>
              <th>Entrance-Level Handgun Training</th>
              <th>Entrance-Level Long Gun Training</th>
              <th>Annual Firearms Training</th>
              <th>Handgun Conversion Training-Different Type Handgun</th>
              <th>Handgun Conversion Training Red Dot Sight</th>
              <th>Handgun Conversion Training-Within a Handgun Type</th>
              <th>Firearms Conversion Training-Long Gun</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Legal aspects in the use of firearms</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td/>
              <td/>
              <td/>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Nomenclature relevant to the firearm and any added equipment for which the training is being given</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(3) Care and cleaning of the firearm and any added equipment for which the training is being given</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(4) Safe handling and safe storage of firearms</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td/>
              <td/>
              <td/>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(5) Fundamentals of marksmanship and shooting related to the firearm and optic, where applicable</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td/>
              <td/>
              <td/>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(6) Explanations and reasons for a qualification course of fire</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td/>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td/>
              <td/>
              <td/>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(7) Ballistic properties, if applicable</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td/>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(8) Potential situations for which the long gun is intended</td>
              <td/>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td/>
              <td/>
              <td/>
              <td/>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(9) Unusual characteristics</td>
              <td/>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td/>
              <td/>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td/>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(10) Optical sighting devices, or red dot sight, where applicable</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td/>
              <td/>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td/>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(11) Reduced light firing techniques</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td/>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td/>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td/>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(12) Mechanical Operation of the firearm</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td/>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(13) Malfunction causes and clearing</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Legal aspects in the use of firearms, at a minimum, shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Rules for the use of deadly force;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Alternatives to the use of deadly force;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Emotional, mental, and psychological preparation needed for the possibility of a deadly force shooting situation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Judgmental or decision training on the use of deadly force; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Criminal, civil, and administrative liability for misuse of deadly force.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Safe handling and safe storage of firearms, at a minimum, shall address safe handling and safe storage in the following settings:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At home;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In a law enforcement facility;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>On the firing line; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>On patrol.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|2-109">Correctional Services Article, §2-109</cite>; Public Safety Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|3-208">3-208</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|3-209">3-209</cite>; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1981-02-20">Effective date: February 20, 1981 (8:4 Md. R. 342)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1983-03-14">Regulations .01, .02, .04, .06—.16 amended effective March 14, 1983 (10:5 Md. R. 465)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1983-07-04"><cite path="|12|04|02|.02|G.">Regulation .02G</cite> and I amended, and J adopted effective July 4, 1983 (10:13 Md. R. 1180)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1984-09-24">Chapter, Public Information Requests, repealed effective September 24, 1984 (11:19 Md. R. 1667)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-01-01" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|12|04|02|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|12|04|02|.21">.21</cite>, Firearms Training and Instructor Certification Regulations, adopted effective January 1, 1992 (18:20 Md. R. 2199)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-07-01"><cite path="|12|04|02|.10|C.">Regulation .10C</cite> amended effective July 1, 2000 (27:10 Md. R. 967)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-11-22"><cite path="|12|04|02|.11|E.">Regulation .11E</cite> amended effective November 22, 1993 (20:23 Md. R. 1805)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-02-09"><cite path="|12|04|02|.13">Regulation .13</cite> amended effective February 9, 1998 (25:3 Md. R. 146)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-07-01"><cite path="|12|04|02|.14|B.">Regulation .14B</cite>, C amended effective July 1, 2000 (27:10 Md. R. 967)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-01-20"><cite path="|12|04|02|.14|C.">Regulation .14C</cite>, D amended effective January 20, 2003 (30:1 Md. R. 25)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-11-22"><cite path="|12|04|02|.19|B.">Regulation .19B</cite>, C amended effective November 22, 1993 (20:23 Md. R. 1805)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-11-22"><cite path="|12|04|02|.20|A.">Regulation .20A</cite>, B amended effective November 22, 1993 (20:23 Md. R. 1805)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-01-01" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|12|04|02|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|12|04|02|.21">.21</cite> repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|12|04|02|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|12|04|02|.13">.13</cite> adopted effective January 1, 2009 (35:24 Md. R. 2078)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-01-01" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective January 1, 2013 (39:15 Md. R. 964)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-04-04"><cite path="|12|04|02|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective November 25, 2013 (40:23 Md. R. 1935); April 4, 2022 (49:7 Md. R. 468)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-04-04"><cite path="|12|04|02|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite> amended effective April 4, 2022 (49:7 Md. R. 468)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-09-02"><cite path="|12|04|02|.03|C.">Regulation .03C</cite> amended effective September 2, 2013 (40:17 Md. R. 1420)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-04-04"><cite path="|12|04|02|.04|B.">Regulation .04B</cite> amended effective April 4, 2022 (49:7 Md. R. 468)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-04-04"><cite path="|12|04|02|.04|C.">Regulation .04C</cite> adopted effective April 4, 2022 (49:7 Md. R. 468)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-04-04"><cite path="|12|04|02|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective April 4, 2022 (49:7 Md. R. 468)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-04-04"><cite path="|12|04|02|.08|B.">Regulation .08B</cite> amended effective April 4, 2022 (49:7 Md. R. 468)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-04-04"><cite path="|12|04|02|.09">Regulation .09</cite> amended effective April 4, 2022 (49:7 Md. R. 468)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-04-04"><cite path="|12|04|02|.10|B.">Regulation .10B</cite> amended effective April 4, 2022 (49:7 Md. R. 468)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
