<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>04</num>
  <heading>Minimum Standards for Certified Firearms Safety Training</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter applies to:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An individual who is required by law to attend a certified firearms safety training course in order to purchase, rent, or transfer a regulated firearm;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A person seeking certification from the Commission to offer certified firearms safety training under this chapter;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A firearms safety training course approved by the Commission; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A firearms safety instructor certified by the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Certified firearms safety instructor" means an individual certified under this chapter to conduct a certified firearms safety training course.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Certified firearms training course" means an instructional program approved by the Commission to teach the safe handling of a regulated firearm.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Commission" means the Police Training Commission or an employee authorized to act in its behalf.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Deputy Director" means the Deputy Director of the Police and Correctional Training Commissions, or a designee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Police officer" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|3-201">Public Safety Article, §3-201(e), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Regulated firearm" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|5-101">Public Safety Article, §5-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="12|04|04|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Certified Firearms Safety Instructor.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A firearms safety instructor shall be certified in order to conduct a certified firearms safety training course under this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Requirements for a Certified Firearms Safety Instructor. An individual is eligible to conduct a certified firearms safety training course if the individual is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A certified police officer who has completed:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Commission requirements for entrance-level firearms training; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Probationary employment requirements as a police officer; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Certified to conduct a certified firearms safety training course by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Commission;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Department of Natural Resources;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Department of State Police; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A reputable organization having as one of its objectives the promotion of competency and safety in handling handguns.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Commission Certification Procedure. An individual seeking certification as a firearms safety instructor under <cite path="12|04|04|.03|B.|(2)|(a)">§B(2)(a) of this regulation</cite> shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Submit a request for certification to the Deputy Director for approval; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Include a resume or other documentation indicating the individual's qualification to conduct the certified firearms safety training course.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Certified Firearms Safety Training Course.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Commission approval is required for a certified firearms safety training course designed to meet the requirements specified under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|3-208">Public Safety Article, §3-208, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A certified firearms safety training course shall include the following elements:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A handgun safety component;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Safe handling of a regulated firearm;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Rendering a regulated firearm safe;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Safe carrying and transporting of a regulated firearm;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Security and storage of a regulated firearm; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Restricting access to a regulated firearm by an individual:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Younger than 21 years old; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Not legally permitted to possess a regulated firearm.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A certified firearms safety training course shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be approved by the Commission;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Have a handgun safety component; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Be conducted by a certified firearms safety instructor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the certified firearms safety training course is offered by the Commission, it:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be presented by a certified firearms safety instructor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Be open to all individuals required by law to complete a certified firearms safety training course;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Be offered at least weekly in all geographic areas of Maryland after regular business hours;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Require attendance throughout the duration of the course for successful completion; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Be free of charge to all individuals seeking to take the course; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>May not:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be more than 2 hours in length; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Include a test, examination, or other measure of comprehension.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Commission Approval Procedure. A person seeking approval for a certified firearms safety training course under this regulation shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Submit a request for approval to the Deputy Director; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Include a description of the course to be presented.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Documentation of Completion.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The certified firearms safety instructor shall provide to each individual attending the certified firearms safety training course a certificate of completion.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The certificate of completion shall contain the following information:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Full name of the individual attending the course;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Address of the individual;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Date and location of the training course; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Name of the certified firearms safety instructor.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The certified firearms safety instructor shall forward a list of all individuals attending the certified firearms safety training course to the Commission within 2 weeks.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|3-208">Public Safety Article, §3-208, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-09-03">Effective date: September 3, 2001 (28:17 Md. R. 1558)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
