<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>11</num>
  <heading>Police Complaint Mediation Program</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter establishes a police complaint mediation program which provides an alternative method to address minor, nonviolent police misconduct complaints outside of the standard complaint process.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A law enforcement agency may refer a nonviolent complaint made against a police officer, subject to the agreement of the complainant and the involved police officer, to an independent mediation provider.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>General Provisions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Mediation is a process for settling minor police misconduct disputes based on the voluntary participation of the disputing parties.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If eligible, voluntary mediation between community members and police officers may be used in place of the traditional administrative complaint process and administrative charging committees (ACC).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The mediation process can bridge the communication gap and create a greater understanding and appreciation between community members, police officers, and employing law enforcement agencies.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Confidential material” means any communication occurring during a mediation session that may not be disclosed outside the mediation except as allowed pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcj|3-1804">Courts and Judicial Proceedings Article, §3-1804, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Impasse” means an outcome of a mediation session in which the parties are unable to resolve the dispute.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Independent mediation provider” means an organization, separate and apart from a law enforcement agency, that can provide mediators to conduct mediation sessions between complainants and law enforcement personnel.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Letter of conclusion” means a document signed by staff of the independent mediation provider that is delivered to a law enforcement agency indicating that a mediation session was held between a complainant and police officer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Letter of consent to mediate” means a document signed by the parties in mediation indicating each party’s voluntarily participation in mediation, and witnessed by the mediator.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Mediation” has the meaning stated in <cite path="12.04.10.03|B.">COMAR 12.04.10.03B</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text><em>“</em>Mediator” means a trained, impartial third party, affiliated with an independent mediation provider, who will facilitate a mediation session between parties to assist them in reaching a voluntary resolution to their dispute<em>.</em></text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Police misconduct” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|3-101">Public Safety Article, §3-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“Resolution” means a mutual agreement resolving a conflict between two or more disputing parties.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Establishing a Police Complaint Mediation Program.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Maryland Police Training and Standards Commission (MPTSC) in collaboration with community-based mediation resources shall establish and maintain a listing of qualified mediation providers located within the State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A law enforcement agency interested in establishing a mediation program shall contact MPTSC for referral to an appropriate mediation provider.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Prior to establishing a mediation process, a law enforcement agency shall enter into a memorandum of understanding (MOU) with a local independent mediation provider approved by MPTSC.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A local law enforcement agency shall establish guidelines for mediation consistent with this regulation and any policy guidelines provided by MPTSC.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A law enforcement agency that enters into an MOU with a qualified mediation provider shall report the establishment of a program to MPTSC and forward a copy to ensure the program meets the requirements of the regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Mediation Participation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Participant Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Participation in a mediation program is voluntary and shall be agreed upon by the complainant, law enforcement agency, and police officer identified in the complaint.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A complainant or police officer who is the subject of a complaint of police misconduct has the right to decline mediation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If a police officer who is the subject of a complaint declines the offer to mediate the complaint, the decision to not participate may not be considered during any disciplinary proceeding.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A party to mediation shall sign a letter of consent to mediate as an alternative to the formal police misconduct complaint process, outlined in <cite path="|12.04.09">COMAR 12.04.09</cite> and the uniform citizen complaint process.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Confidentiality.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All parties involved in a potential mediation process shall agree to the confidentiality requirements as set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcj|3-1803">Courts and Judicial Proceedings Article, §3-1803, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcj|3-1804">Courts and Judicial Proceedings Article, §3-1804, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, statements shared during a mediation are considered confidential material and may not be disclosed in any judicial, administrative, or other proceeding.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Costs associated with participating in a mediation program are the responsibility of the law enforcement agency employing the involved police officer.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Complaints Eligible for Mediation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Complaint Eligibility.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A nonviolent complaint of a minor nature is eligible for mediation if it falls into one of the following categories:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Violation category A, as stated in <cite path="12.04.10.04|D.|(2)">COMAR 12.04.10.04D(2)</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Violation category B, as stated in <cite path="12.04.10.04|D.|(3)">COMAR 12.04.10.04D(3)</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A law enforcement agency shall review the nature of the complaint and determine if mediation is appropriate, based on the following factors:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Type and severity of the alleged violation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Circumstances of the alleged police misconduct; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Work history and past disciplinary record of the involved police officer.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Even if a complaint is eligible for mediation, the agency head or designee has the authority to decide, for any reason, that a case may not be assigned for mediation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Complaints Not Eligible.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A complaint of police misconduct that involves any level of force is not eligible for mediation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A complaint is not eligible for mediation if it falls into one of the following categories:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Violation category C, as stated in <cite path="12.04.10.04|D.|(4)">COMAR 12.04.10.04D(4)</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Violation category D, as stated in <cite path="12.04.10.04|D.|(5)">COMAR 12.04.10.04D(5)</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Violation category E, as stated in <cite path="12.04.10.04|E.|(6)">COMAR 12.04.10.04E(6)</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Violation category F, as stated in <cite path="12.04.10.04|D.|(7)">COMAR 12.04.10.04D(7)</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A complaint of police misconduct not eligible for mediation shall be handled through the process set forth in <cite path="|12.04.09">COMAR 12.04.09</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Complaint Procedures.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>When a minor complaint from a member of the public has been made to a law enforcement agency or police accountability board, a law enforcement agency shall review the nature of the complaint and determine if it is eligible for the mediation program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Notification to Involved Parties.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If the complaint is eligible and conforms to <cite path="|12|04|11|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>, the law enforcement agency shall notify the police officer who is the subject of the complaint of the mediation option.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the police officer agrees to mediation, the law enforcement agency shall notify the complainant of the mediation option.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the police officer or a complainant decline to participate in mediation, the matter shall be referred back to the administrative complaint process set forth in <cite path="|12.04.09">COMAR 12.04.09</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If all parties to the complaint agree to the mediation process, the law enforcement agency shall contact the independent mediation provider in which there is a current memorandum of understanding (MOU) and proceed with the process pursuant to the MOU.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>When a case has been referred to the mediation service, the independent mediation provider will manage the case through mediation and resolution.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Resolution.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>When the mediation process has concluded, the outcome shall be determined by the independent mediation provider to be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A successful resolution if all parties agree with the resolution; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An impasse if one or more parties to the complaint cannot agree to a satisfactory resolution.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An impasse shall be referred back to the law enforcement agency of the involved police officer for investigation and handled through the administrative complaint process set forth in <cite path="|12.04.09">COMAR 12.04.09</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A successful resolution shall be documented by the independent mediation provider in a written statement, signed by both parties and the mediator.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The mediator shall send a letter of conclusion to the referring law enforcement agency indicating the results of mediation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Results of the mediation shall be tracked by the law enforcement agency and forwarded to the local police accountability board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Complaint mediation statistics shall be included in the law enforcement agency’s annual reporting of complaints involving the public, and the statistics shall include the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Total number of complaints handled through mediation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Number of successful resolutions; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Number of mediation impasses.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>If the police officer fails to comply with the actions and deadlines identified in the mediation agreement, a new complaint shall be initiated and the actions of the original complaint of misconduct shall be considered as a potential aggravating factor.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Public Safety Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|3-207">3-207</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|3-208">3-208</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-03-20">Effective date: March 20, 2023 (50:5 Md. R. 182)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
