<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>Advisory Committees</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Coastal and Watershed Resources Advisory Committee.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Coastal and Watershed Resources Advisory Committee has the duty of advising the Secretary of Natural Resources on all matters referred to the Committee by the Director of the Coastal Zone Management Program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Members may not receive compensation, but shall be reimbursed for necessary expenses incident to their attendance of the meetings of the Committee according to the provisions of the standard travel regulations of the State and within budgetary limitations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Coastal and Watershed Resources Advisory Committee shall elect annually, at the first meeting after January 1, a chairman, who shall be eligible for reelection in any subsequent year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Meetings shall be held at the call of the chairman or the Director, Coastal Zone Management Program, or, within budgetary limitations, upon petition of a majority of the members, stating the purpose of the meeting. No less than two meetings shall be held in each fiscal year.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|01|01|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Maryland Boat Act Advisory Committee.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Maryland Boat Act Advisory Committee has the duty of advising the Secretary of Natural Resources on all matters referred to the Committee by the Director of the Boating Service.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Members may not receive compensation, but shall be reimbursed for necessary expenses incident to their attendance of the meetings of the Committee according to the provisions of the standard travel regulations of the State and within budgetary limitations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Terms of Membership.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The term of a member is 3 years.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Except as stated in <cite path="08|01|01|.02|C.|(3)">§C(3) of this regulation</cite>, a term shall begin on January 1 of the year of appointment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An individual who has been appointed to replace a member who resigned or has been removed from the committee prior to the end of the term:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Shall serve for the remainder of the original term; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>May be reappointed in accordance with this regulation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Members are eligible for reappointment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Members serve in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|1-102">Natural Resources Article, §1-102(c), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Maryland Boat Act Advisory Committee shall elect annually, at the first meeting after January 1, a chair, who shall be eligible for reelection in any subsequent year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Meetings shall be held at the call of the chair or the Director of the Boating Service, or, within budgetary limitations, upon petition of a majority of the members, stating the purpose of the meeting. Not less than two meetings shall be held in each fiscal year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Secretary may release an appointee at any time.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Forest and Park Advisory Commission.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Forest and Park Advisory Commission shall have the duty of advising the Director of the Forest and Park Service on all matters referred to the Commission by the Director of the Forest and Park Service.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Members may not receive compensation, but shall be reimbursed for necessary expenses incident to their attendance of the meetings of the Commission according to the provisions of the standard travel regulations of the State and within budgetary limitations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Forest and Park Advisory Commission shall elect annually, at the first meeting after July 1, a chairman, who shall be eligible for reelection in any subsequent year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Meetings shall be held at the call of the chairman or the Director of the Forest and Park Service, or, within budgetary limitations, upon petition of a majority of the members, stating the purpose of the meeting. Not less than two meetings shall be held in each fiscal year.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Repealed.</heading>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Wildlife Advisory Commission.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Wildlife Advisory Commission shall have the duty of advising the Administrator of the Wildlife Administration on all matters referred to the Commission by the Administrator of the Wildlife Administration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Members may not receive compensation, but shall be reimbursed for necessary expenses incident to their attendance of the meetings of the Commission according to the provisions of the standard travel regulations of the State, and within budgetary limitations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Wildlife Advisory Commission shall elect annually at the first meeting after July 1, a chairman, who shall be eligible for re-election in any subsequent year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Meetings shall be held at the call of the chairman or the Administrator of the Wildlife Administration, or, within budgetary limitations, upon petition of a majority of the members, stating the purpose of the meeting. Not less than two meetings shall be held in each fiscal year.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Tidal Fisheries Advisory Commission.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Tidal Fisheries Advisory Commission has the duty of advising the Director of the Fisheries Service on all matters referred to the Commission by the Director of the Fisheries Service.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Members may not receive compensation, but shall be reimbursed for necessary expenses incident to their attendance of the meetings of the Commission according to the provisions of the standard travel regulations of the State, and within budgetary limitations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Tidal Fisheries Advisory Commission shall elect annually, at the first meeting after July 1, a chairman, who shall be eligible for re-election in any subsequent year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Meetings shall be held at the call of the chairman or the Director of the Fisheries Service, or, within budgetary limitations, upon petition of a majority of the members, stating the purpose of the meeting. Not less than two meetings shall be held in each fiscal year.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Sport Fisheries Advisory Commission.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Sport Fisheries Advisory Commission shall have the duty of advising the Director of the Fisheries Service on all matters referred to the Commission by the Director of the Fisheries Service.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Members may not receive compensation, but shall be reimbursed for necessary expenses incident to their attendance of the meetings of the Commission according to the provisions of the standard travel regulations of the State and within budgetary limitations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Sport Fisheries Advisory Commission shall elect annually, at the first meeting after July 1, a chairman, who shall be eligible for reelection in any subsequent year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Meetings shall be held at the call of the chairman or the Director of the Fisheries Service, or, within budgetary limitations, upon petition of a majority of the members, stating the purpose of the meeting. Not less than two meetings shall be held in each fiscal year.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Natural Resources Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|1-102">1-102</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|1-105">1-105</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-204">4-204</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|8-704">8-704</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1973-10-01">Effective date: October 1, 1973</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-11-22"><cite path="|08|01|01|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective June 25, 1977 (4:13 Md. R. 1030); November 22, 1993 (20:23 Md. R. 1802)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-11-22"><cite path="|08|01|01|.02">Regulation .02</cite> repealed effective November 22, 1993 (20:23 Md. R. 1802)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-12-27"><cite path="|08|01|01|.02">Regulation .02</cite> adopted effective December 27, 2021 (48:26 Md. R. 1110)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1983-08-15">Regulations .03 amended and .04 repealed effective August 15, 1983 (10:16 Md. R. 1450)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-11-22"><cite path="|08|01|01|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective November 22, 1993 (20:23 Md. R. 1802)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-06-22"><cite path="|08|01|01|.06|A.">Regulation .06A</cite>, D amended effective June 22, 2015 (42:12 Md. R. 761)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-06-22"><cite path="|08|01|01|.07|A.">Regulation .07A</cite>, D amended effective June 22, 2015 (42:12 Md. R. 761)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
