<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>07</num>
  <heading>Chesapeake Forest Lands</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Chesapeake Forest Land road" means a road on, or adjacent to, the Chesapeake Forest that is maintained by the service.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Department" means the Department of Natural Resources.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Director" means the Director of the Forest Service.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Hunt club" means an organization made up of hunters with a club president.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Hunting lease agreement" means a legal agreement between a hunt club and the Department, giving the hunt club exclusive hunting rights to a tract of Chesapeake Forest Lands.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Program Open Space" means the program under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr">Natural Resources Article, Title 5, Subtitle 9, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, that provides funding for the State and its subdivisions to acquire land for open space and for outdoor public recreation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Public road" means any road that is maintained by either a county or the Maryland State Highway Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Secretary" means the Secretary of Natural Resources.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Service" means the Forest Service, a unit within the Department of Natural Resources.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Sustainable forestry" means the stewardship and use of forests and forest lands in a way, and at a rate, that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Maintains their biodiversity, productivity, regeneration, capacity, vitality, and potential to fulfill, now and in the future, relevant ecological, economic, and social functions at local and regional levels; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Does not cause damage to other ecosystems.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Tract" means an individual land unit of Chesapeake Forest Lands that is recorded by deed description in the local county land records office.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Vehicle.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Vehicle" means a mode of transportation by which an individual or property may be transported on a roadway.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Vehicle" includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A trailer;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>An automobile;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A truck;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>A bus;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>A moped;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>An animal;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>An animal-drawn vehicle;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>A bicycle;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ix)</num>
            <text>An all-terrain vehicle (ATV); and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(x)</num>
            <text>An off-road vehicle (ORV).</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|01|07|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Chesapeake Forest Lands.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Purpose. In accordance with Natural Resources Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|5-207">5-207</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|5-903">5-903</cite>(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|2">2</cite>)(i), Annotated Code of Maryland, a group of lands has been acquired by the Department with Program Open Space funds and through the gift of lands. These lands were acquired specifically to be retained as working forest, producing forest products to help maintain local employment, to protect outdoor recreational values, and for other environmental benefits for the local communities on Maryland's Eastern Shore. None of these areas has been accorded a formal land unit designation and existing land unit designations do not fulfill the purposes for which these lands were acquired.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This chapter:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Establishes a new official land unit designation, Chesapeake Forest Lands; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is intended to remedy the concerns set forth in <cite path="08|01|07|.02|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Chesapeake Forest Lands—Composition. Chesapeake Forest Lands comprise:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The units in <cite path="08|01|07|.02|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>, as delineated on maps filed by the Office of the Secretary; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Other State lands that in the future may be given or purchased in whole or part with Program Open Space funds or other funds targeted for sustainable forestry.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Chesapeake Forest Lands are comprised of over 60,000 acres in various tracts in the following six counties: Caroline, Talbot, Dorchester, Wicomico, Worchester, and Somerset, including the Wicomico Demonstration Forest located in Wicomico County, Seth Demonstration Forest located in Talbot County, and the Fred W. Besley Demonstration Forest, named after Maryland’s first State Forester, located in Dorchester County. Maps indicating size and location of each tract are maintained on file in the office of the forest manager for Chesapeake Forest Lands.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Management and Use.</heading>
    <text>All uses and management of Chesapeake Forest Lands shall be in accordance with the purposes of sustainable forestry.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|01|07|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Hunting.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Director may establish areas designated for public hunting and areas for leased hunting.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Notice.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The areas open to public hunting and leased hunting shall be posted.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The designated public hunting areas shall be published annually in the Guide to Hunting and Trapping in Maryland.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Only members of the hunt club listed in the hunting lease agreement may hunt on their club's designated tract or tracts between the dates of September 1 and June 1.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The hunting season in all designated hunting areas shall be in accordance with State and federal laws and regulations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Except by written permit, an individual may not trap or attempt to trap on Chesapeake Forest Lands. The permit shall be issued by the Director.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Except by written permit, issued by the Director, an individual may not use a dog to chase fur-bearing mammals on Chesapeake Forest Lands. The Director shall review applications for a permit consistent with <cite path="|08|01|07|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>An individual may not hunt within 150 yards of an occupied structure or camp.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>An individual hunting on Chesapeake Forest Lands, may not hunt within 150 feet of any Chesapeake Forest Lands boundary, adjacent to private land, nor shoot on, from, or across any public road. The hunting of wild waterfowl, as defined in <cite path="08.03.01.36">COMAR 08.03.01.36</cite>, is exempt from the 150 foot restriction where the boundary coincides with the shoreline of the waters of the State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="08|01|07|.04|A.|(10)">§A(10) of this regulation</cite>, an individual may only erect on Chesapeake Forest Lands blinds or treestands that are brought in and taken out with the individual each day.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>With written permission from the Service, an individual may use or construct permanent blinds or tree stands on Chesapeake Forest Lands.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>A person may not enter onto a leased hunting tract between the dates of September 1 and June 1 without written permission from the Service.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Baiting or Feeding on Chesapeake Forest Lands.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="08|01|07|.04|B.|(2)">§B(2) of this regulation</cite>, an individual may not place, cause to be placed, scatter, or distribute:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Shucked or unshucked corn, wheat, or other grain;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Salt; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Other feed.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Baiting or feeding on designated leased hunting areas is allowed only by written permission from the Service from September 1 through January 31.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An individual may not hunt, shoot, kill, or attempt to hunt, shoot, or kill, a game bird or a mammal by the aid of bait, on or over the baited area on any public hunting area.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Guiding on Chesapeake Forest Lands. A person may not guide hunting parties for economic gain on any Chesapeake Forest Lands tract owned or controlled by the Department of Natural Resources and managed by the Service.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Closing Against Entry.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This regulation does not apply to employees of the Department on official business.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Service may, by notice, close certain areas of Chesapeake Forest Lands to public entry and travel.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The use of Chesapeake Forest Land roads is subject to the provisions of the laws of Maryland and the regulations of the Department. Roads may be closed to traffic when this action is considered necessary by the Service.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Fires.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An individual shall obtain a permit from the Service before kindling, building, maintaining, or using an open fire within a Chesapeake Forest Land tract.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A fire permit may be revoked at any time by the Service.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Camping.</heading>
    <text>Camping on Chesapeake Forest Lands is limited to only those areas designated by the Department and requires a valid camping permit issued by the Service. The permit shall specify place and time period for camping.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Refuse and Rubbish.</heading>
    <text>An individual may not deposit garbage, tires, sewage, waste, foodstuffs, paper, or other litter in Chesapeake Forest Lands.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|01|07|.09">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Plants, Rocks, Minerals, and Animals.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This regulation does not apply to Department personnel performing their duties.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Except as authorized in <cite path="|08|01|07|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite> and <cite path="08|01|07|.09|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, an individual may not remove, disturb, damage, or destroy any plant, rock, mineral, or animal in Chesapeake Forest Lands.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Timber, firewood, or other forest products may be taken from Chesapeake Forest Lands after a sales contract or permit has been obtained from the Service.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Vehicles.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Service may restrict the use of bicycles, mountain bikes, and animals on certain forest roads and trails on Chesapeake Forest Lands.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Except by written permit from the Service, the use of any all-terrain vehicle or off-highway vehicle is prohibited on Chesapeake Forest Lands.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Vehicles may not be parked so they block access to any gate or road on Chesapeake Forest Lands.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Advertising.</heading>
    <text>Unless a permit is obtained from the Service, an individual may not erect or post a sign, notice, or literature on Chesapeake Forest Lands.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Encroachment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Private encroachments are prohibited on Chesapeake Forest Lands.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Encroachments include, but are not limited to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Fences;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Walls;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Dog runs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Dog houses;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Storage structures;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Driveways;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Compost piles;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Swimming pools;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Tree houses;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Play houses;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Woodpiles;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Gardens;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Play equipment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>Television or radio reception devices; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>Other devices, structures, refuse, or material.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Pets.</heading>
    <text>Pets shall be kept under reasonable control consistent with the safety of forest users and forest wildlife. An individual with a pet shall prevent the pet from biting individuals. Pets may not be permitted to disturb forest wildlife outside of hunting activities.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Weapons.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definition.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In this regulation, the following term has the meaning indicated.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Term Defined. "Weapon" means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A device capable of propelling a projectile at high velocity by mechanical means, by explosion, or by expanding gas, including but not limited to a firearm, crossbow, or long bow;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A dirk knife, bowie knife, switchblade (except a penknife without a switchblade), sand club, metal knuckles, razor, or nunchaku; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A device capable of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Inflicting death or bodily harm to an individual;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Maiming or killing wildlife; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Destroying property.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="|08|01|07|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite> and §§C and D of this regulation, possession or use of weapons or firearms by an individual other than a law enforcement officer is prohibited in Chesapeake Forest Lands.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Target shooting is permitted only at designated shooting ranges. The regulations governing the use of these ranges shall be posted and strictly enforced.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Except when legally hunting or legally target shooting, an individual may not discharge a firearm on land or waters owned or controlled by the Service.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Firearms shall be unloaded, and arrows kept in a quiver or case, when in a Chesapeake Forest camping area in accordance with <cite path="|08|01|07|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Damage to Public Property.</heading>
    <text>A person may not injure, deface, or vandalize any part of the lands owned or controlled by the Service or any building, sign, gate, equipment, or other public property on those lands.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Disorderly Conduct.</heading>
    <text>An individual may not act in a disorderly manner on Chesapeake Forest Lands by:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Making loud and unseemly noises or profanely cursing, swearing, or using obscene language;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Indecently exposing their person or performing any indecent act;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Throwing missiles, to the annoyance of the public;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Interfering with, encumbering, obstructing, or rendering dangerous any public place;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Engaging in, instigating, or encouraging a confrontation or fight; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Causing a disturbance of the public.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Natural Resources Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|5-209">5-209</cite>(a) and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|10-808">10-808</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-08-02">Effective date: August 2, 2004 (31:15 Md. R. 1184)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-03-23"><cite path="|08|01|07|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective March 23, 2009 (36:6 Md. R. 487)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-03-23"><cite path="|08|01|07|.02|D.">Regulation .02D</cite> amended effective March 23, 2009 (36:6 Md. R. 487); October 29. 2012 (39:21 Md. R. 1377)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-03-23"><cite path="|08|01|07|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite> amended effective March 14, 2005 (32:5 Md. R. 579); March 23, 2009 (36:6 Md. R. 487)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-03-14"><cite path="|08|01|07|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective March 14, 2005 (32:5 Md. R. 579)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-03-14"><cite path="|08|01|07|.13">Regulation .13</cite> adopted effective March 14, 2005 (32:5 Md. R. 579)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-03-11"><cite path="|08|01|07|.13">Regulation .13</cite> amended effective March 11, 2019 (46:5 Md. R. 305)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-03-14"><cite path="|08|01|07|.14">Regulation .14</cite> adopted effective March 14, 2005 (32:5 Md. R. 579)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-03-23"><cite path="|08|01|07|.14">Regulation .14</cite> repealed and new Regulation .14 adopted effective March 23, 2009 (36:6 Md. R. 487)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-03-23"><cite path="|08|01|07|.15">Regulation .15</cite> adopted effective March 23, 2009 (36:6 Md. R. 487)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-03-23"><cite path="|08|01|07|.16">Regulation .16</cite> adopted effective March 23, 2009 (36:6 Md. R. 487)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
