<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Petition for Adoption of Regulations</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>The purpose of these regulations is to enable any interested person to request promulgation of regulations affecting matters under the authority of the Secretary or any constituent officer, commission, or agency, or to request amendment or repeal of any existing regulations.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Form of Petition.</heading>
    <text>The petition shall be submitted in writing to the Secretary, 501 St. Paul Place, Baltimore, Maryland 21202 or to the principal office of the officer, commission, or agency to whom the petition is directed.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Content of Petition—Proposed Regulations.</heading>
    <text>Any request for promulgation of new regulations submitted under these regulations shall include the proposed regulations and the reasons for and effect of the regulations, if adopted.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Content of Petition—Repeal or Amendment.</heading>
    <text>Any request for amendment or repeal submitted under these regulations shall state what regulation the petitioner requests to be amended or repealed and the reasons for an effect of this request.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Review.</heading>
    <text>The Secretary or the officer, commission, or agency to whom the petition is addressed, within 60 days after the petition is submitted, shall either deny the petition in writing, stating the reasons for the denial, or initiate rule-making proceedings. The petitioner shall be advised in writing of any action taken in response to the petition.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|2-105">Business Regulation Article, §2-105</cite>; <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-123">State Government Article, §10-123</cite>; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1983-01-06">Effective date: January 6, 1983 (9:26 Md. R. 2571)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
