<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>09</num>
  <heading>New Home Warranty Security Plans</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Disclosure by Builders Not Participating in New Home Warranty Security Plan.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The disclosure shall be printed in at least 12-point type.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The disclosure shall read as follows:</text>
      <text>Maryland law requires a builder who does not participate in a new home warranty security plan to make the following disclosure as part of the contract for sale or construction of a new home.</text>
      <text>Builders of new homes, in the State of Maryland, are required to be registered with the Consumer Protection Division of the Office of the Attorney General unless they build new homes exclusively in Montgomery County. In that case, they are required to register with the Montgomery County Office of Consumer Affairs.</text>
      <text>I do not participate in a new home warranty security plan. Therefore, the buyer may be afforded only certain limited implied warranties as are provided by law.</text>
      <text>Maryland law requires me to either disclose any actual knowledge that I have of any hazardous or regulated materials which are present on the site of the new home or to state that I am making no representations or warranties as to whether any hazardous or regulated materials are present on the site of the new home.</text>
      <text>I have actual knowledge that the following hazardous or regulated materials are present on the site of the new home.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>__ Asbestos</td>
              <td>__ Lead-Based Paint</td>
              <td>__ Radon</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>__ Methane</td>
              <td>__ Underground Storage Tanks</td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>__ Licensed Landfills</td>
              <td>__ Unlicensed Landfills</td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>__ Licensed Rubble Fills</td>
              <td>__ Unlicensed Rubble Fills</td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
      <text>Other Hazardous or Regulated Materials and Other Environmental Hazards Present on the Site:</text>
      <text>____________________________________________________________________________</text>
      <text>____________________________________________________________________________</text>
      <text>OR</text>
      <text>__ I have no actual knowledge of any hazardous or regulated material present on the site of the new home.</text>
      <text>OR</text>
      <text>__ I am making no representations or warranties as to whether there is any hazardous or regulated material on the site of the new home.</text>
      <text>The buyer has the right to change the buyer's mind and to rescind this contract. If the buyer decides to discontinue this contract, the buyer must notify the builder in writing, within 5 working days from the date the buyer signs the contract. Upon rescission, the buyer is entitled to a refund of any monies paid to the builder for the new home.</text>
      <text>The buyer acknowledges that the builder does not participate in a new home warranty security plan and that the buyer has read and understands the above disclosure.</text>
      <text>______________________________		______________________________</text>
      <text>Signature of Buyer				Date</text>
      <text>______________________________		______________________________</text>
      <text>Signature of Buyer				Date</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Disclosure Required by Builders Participating in New Home Warranty Security Plan.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The disclosure shall be printed in at least 12-point type.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The disclosure shall read as follows:</text>
      <text>Maryland law requires a builder who participates in a new home warranty security plan to make the following disclosure as part of the contract for sale or construction of a new home:</text>
      <text>I am a builder who participates in a Maryland approved new home warranty security plan, and under the terms of that plan, I am required to provide the buyer with a new home warranty which meets the requirements of Maryland law.</text>
      <text>I am a participant, in good standing, with the following plan:</text>
      <text>____________________________		____________________________</text>
      <text>Name of Security Plan				Phone</text>
      <text>The home located at the following address is eligible for and will be enrolled in the new home warranty security plan:</text>
      <text>____________________________________________________</text>
      <text>____________________________________________________</text>
      <text>____________________________________________________</text>
      <text>The plan provides the following coverage:</text>
      <text>Minimum warranty coverage —</text>
      <text>One year—free from any defects in material and workmanship</text>
      <text>Two years—free from any defect in the electrical, plumbing, heating, cooling and ventilating systems, except that the following appliances, fixtures and items of equipment are only covered for the length and scope of the warranty offered by the manufacturer:</text>
      <text>Item						Length of Warranty</text>
      <text>_______________________________________________________</text>
      <text>________________________________________________________________</text>
      <text>Five years—free from any structural defects</text>
      <text>Other express warranties provided:</text>
      <text>_______________________________________________________________</text>
      <text>_______________________________________________________________</text>
      <text>_______________________________________________________________</text>
      <text>Items excluded under this warranty plan:</text>
      <text>Damage to real property that is not part of the home covered by the warranty or that is not included in the purchase price.</text>
      <text>Bodily injury or damage to personal property.</text>
      <text>Any defect in material supplied or work performed by anyone other than the builder or the builder's employees, agents, or subcontractors.</text>
      <text>Any damage that the owner has not taken timely action to minimize or for which the owner has failed to provide timely notice to the builder.</text>
      <text>Normal wear and tear or normal deterioration.</text>
      <text>Insect damage, except where the builder has failed to use proper materials or construction methods designed to prevent insect infestation.</text>
      <text>Any loss or damage that arises while the home is being used primarily for nonresidential purposes.</text>
      <text>Any damage to the extent it is caused or made worse by negligence, improper maintenance, or improper operations by anyone other than the builder or the builder's employees, agents, or subcontractors.</text>
      <text>Any damage to the extent that it is caused or made worse by changes in grading of the ground by anyone other than the builder, the builder's employees, agents, or subcontractors.</text>
      <text>Any loss or damage caused by acts of God.</text>
      <text>I must provide a copy of the warranty plan to the buyer at the time of the contract for sale or construction of the new home. To the extent that the warranty documents provide lesser protection to the buyer than State law, State law prevails.</text>
      <text>Maryland law requires me to either disclose any actual knowledge that I have of any hazardous or regulated materials which are present on the site of the new home or to state that I am making no representations or warranties as to whether any hazardous or regulated materials are present on the site of the new home.</text>
      <text>__ I have actual knowledge that the following hazardous or regulated materials are present on the site of the new home:</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>__ Asbestos</td>
              <td>__ Lead-Based Paint</td>
              <td>__ Radon</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>__ Methane</td>
              <td>__ Underground Storage Tanks</td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>__ Licensed Landfills</td>
              <td>__ Unlicensed Landfills</td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>__ Licensed Rubble Fills</td>
              <td>__ Unlicensed Rubble Fills</td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
      <text>Other Hazardous or Regulated Materials and Other Environmental Hazards Present on the Site:</text>
      <text>_________________________________________________________________________</text>
      <text>OR</text>
      <text>__ I have no actual knowledge of any hazardous or regulated material present on the site of the new home.</text>
      <text>OR</text>
      <text>__ I am making no representations or warranties as to whether there is any hazardous or regulated material on the site of the new home.</text>
      <text>The buyer has read and understands the above disclosure.</text>
      <text>______________________________		______________________________</text>
      <text>Signature of Buyer				Date</text>
      <text>______________________________		______________________________</text>
      <text>Signature of Buyer				Date</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Disclosure Required by Builder Leaving Decision to Participate in New Home Warranty Security Plan to the Buyer.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The disclosure shall be printed in at least 12-point type.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The disclosure shall read as follows:</text>
      <text>Maryland law allows a builder who participates in a new home warranty plan to offer the warranty to the buyer at the buyer's option. A builder who proceeds in this fashion must make the following disclosure as part of the contract for sale or construction of a new home.</text>
      <text>Builders of new homes, in the State of Maryland, are required to be registered with the Consumer Protection Division of the Office of the Attorney General unless they build new homes exclusively in Montgomery County. In that case, they are required to register with the Montgomery County Office of Consumer Affairs.</text>
      <text>I have decided to allow the buyer the option of obtaining a new home warranty. If the buyer decides not to have the builder obtain the new home warranty, the buyer may be afforded only certain limited warranties as provided by law.</text>
      <text>The buyer may decide to waive the right to a warranty, if this decision is solely the decision of the buyer. A builder cannot ask a buyer to sign a waiver of the right to have a warranty. A builder cannot refuse to build a new home for a buyer because the buyer decided to ask for a warranty. If the buyer asks for a new home warranty, the builder must provide the warranty.</text>
      <text>The nature and extent of the warranty that would be provided to the buyer is as follows</text>
      <text>____________________________		____________________________</text>
      <text>Name of Security Plan				Phone</text>
      <text>____________________________</text>
      <text>Cost of Warranty Plan</text>
      <text>The plan provides the following coverage:</text>
      <text>Minimum warranty coverage —</text>
      <text>One year—free from any defects in material and workmanship</text>
      <text>Item						Length of Warranty</text>
      <text>_______________________________________________________</text>
      <text>________________________________________________________________</text>
      <text>Five years—free from any structural defects</text>
      <text>Other express warranties provided:</text>
      <text>____________________________________________________</text>
      <text>____________________________________________________</text>
      <text>Items excluded under this warranty plan:</text>
      <text>Damage to real property that is not part of the home covered by the warranty or that is not included in the purchase price.</text>
      <text>Bodily injury or damage to personal property.</text>
      <text>Any defect in material supplied or work performed by anyone other than the builder or the builder's employees, agents, or subcontractors.</text>
      <text>Any damage that the owner has not taken timely action to minimize or for which the owner has failed to provide timely notice to the builder.</text>
      <text>Normal wear and tear or normal deterioration.</text>
      <text>Insect damage, except where the builder has failed to use proper materials or construction methods designed to prevent insect infestation.</text>
      <text>Any loss or damage that arises while the home is being used primarily for nonresidential purposes.</text>
      <text>Any damage to the extent it is caused or made worse by negligence, improper maintenance, or improper operations by anyone other than the builder or the builder's employees, agents, or subcontractors.</text>
      <text>Any damage to the extent it is caused or made worse by changes in grading of the ground by anyone other than the builder, the builder's employees, agents, or subcontractors.</text>
      <text>Any loss or damage caused by acts of God.</text>
      <text>I must provide a copy of the warranty plan to the buyer at the time of the contract for sale or construction of the new home. To the extent that the warranty documents provide lesser protection to the buyer than State law, State law prevails.</text>
      <text>Maryland law requires me to either disclose any actual knowledge that I have of any hazardous or regulated materials which are present on the site of the new home or to state that I am making no representations or warranties as to whether any hazardous or regulated materials are present on the site of the new home.</text>
      <text>__ I have actual knowledge that the following hazardous or regulated materials are present on the site of the new home:</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>__ Asbestos</td>
              <td>__ Lead-Based Paint</td>
              <td>__ Radon</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>__ Methane</td>
              <td>__ Underground Storage Tanks</td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>__ Licensed Landfills</td>
              <td>__ Unlicensed Landfills</td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>__ Licensed Rubble Fills</td>
              <td>__ Unlicensed Rubble Fills</td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
      <text>Other Hazardous or Regulated Materials and Other Environmental Hazards Present on the Site:</text>
      <text>__________________________________________________________________________</text>
      <text>OR</text>
      <text>__ I have no actual knowledge of any hazardous or regulated material present on the site of the new home.</text>
      <text>OR</text>
      <text>__ I am making no representations or warranties as to whether there is any hazardous or regulated material on the site of the new home.</text>
      <text>The buyer has read and understands the above disclosure.</text>
      <text>______________________________		______________________________</text>
      <text>Signature of Buyer				Date</text>
      <text>______________________________		______________________________</text>
      <text>Acknowledgement of Builder			Date</text>
      <text>Waiver of Warranty Right</text>
      <text>The buyer has read and understands the above information and wishes to waive the right to a new home warranty. The buyer further understands that the buyer can change the buyer's mind and can request a warranty by completing the rescission clause at the end of this notice by delivering it to the builder, within 3 working days from the date the buyer signed this contract.</text>
      <text>______________________________		______________________________</text>
      <text>Signature of Buyer				Date</text>
      <text>Rescission Clause for Waiver of Warranty Right</text>
      <text>The buyer has decided to rescind the waiver or warranty right and to obtain the warranty coverage described in detail in the contract. The buyer understands that the cost to obtain the warranty will be $_________.</text>
      <text>The buyer requests that the builder register the new home located, or to be built, at</text>
      <text>_______________________________________________________________________</text>
      <text>Street Address                                                           City                    Zip Code</text>
      <text>with the builder's new home warranty security plan.</text>
      <text>______________________________		______________________________</text>
      <text>Signature of Buyer				Date</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|01|09|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Notification Required to be Given to Buyer on Warranty Date.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>On the warranty date, if a builder participates in a New Home Warranty Security Plan or if a buyer has elected to have the builder participate in a plan, the builder shall provide the owner with evidence that the new home is covered by a new home warranty that meets the requirements of Maryland law.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Evidence of participation is a letter from the New Home Warranty Security Plan certifying that the new home is covered by the minimum warranty required under Maryland law and specifically setting forth any additional express warranties or any exclusions to the warranty coverage.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The letter in <cite path="09|01|09|.04|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> shall include the address and telephone number of the New Home Warranty Security Plan. The letter shall contain the following statement in bold type:</text>
      <text>The buyer should personally contact the new home warranty security plan to verify the existence of the warranty. Further, the buyer should report any warranty problems which are not promptly resolved by the builder to the new home warranty security plan.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Notice to Buyer Required by Builders Participating in New Home Warranty Security Plan or Electing to Allow Buyer the Option of Participating in New Home Warranty Security Plan.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The notice shall be printed in at least 12-point type.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The notice shall be incorporated into the contract in a conspicuous manner and shall read as follows:</text>
      <text>Notice to Buyer</text>
      <text>Your new home will be covered by a new home warranty that meets the minimum requirements established under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="grp">Title 10, Subtitle 6 of the Real Property Article of the Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>. Before you sign this contract, your builder is required to give you a copy of the warranty coverage you will receive.</text>
      <text>The name of the new home warranty security plan in which your builder is currently a participant is ____________ . You are strongly encouraged to call the new home warranty security plan at ______ to verify(1) that your builder is in good standing with this company, and (2) that your new home will be covered by a warranty from this company.</text>
      <text>If the builder is not a participant in good standing with this company on the date of this contract, or if the new home has not been registered in the plan on or before the warranty date, then it is a material breach of the contract and you are entitled to whatever remedies are provided by law, including, but not limited to, rescission or cancellation of this contract and, except in the case of a construction contract for a new home built on your own property, a refund of any money paid to the builder for your new home.</text>
      <text>On the day that you first occupy the new home, settle on the new home, make the financial payment to the builder on your new home, or obtain an occupancy permit for a new home if the new home is built on your own property, whichever is earlier, you will be provided with evidence that a new home warranty exists for your new home and that coverage begins on that date. You will be provided with a signed new home warranty within 60 days from the date the coverage begins.</text>
      <text>The terms used in this notice shall have the same meanings as provided in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="grp">Title 10, Subtitle 6 of the Real Property Article of the Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      <text>The buyer has read and understands the above disclosure.</text>
      <text>________________________________________________________________</text>
      <text>Signature of Buyer                                    Date</text>
      <text>________________________________________________________________</text>
      <text>Acknowledgment of Builder                     Date</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Financial Security Requirements for New Home Warranty Security Plan.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Approval of a new home warranty security plan shall continue only if the operator of the plan remains financially able to pay all valid claims.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The operator shall demonstrate financial responsibility from time to time to the Secretary in the following manner:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The operator shall maintain and file with the Secretary a surety bond from an authorized insurer or an irrevocable letter of credit from a federally insured financial institution to ensure that the operator is able to meet its contractual obligations under the plan to the buyers. The amount of the bond or letter of credit is $100,000 unless a greater amount is required by the Secretary. The bond or letter of credit is in addition to any insurance or risk retention plan coverage the operator maintains to meet liability claims.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>At such time as it appears to the Secretary that a bond or letter of credit in the amount of $100,000 is not adequate to meet potential new home warranty security plan claims, the Secretary shall require:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A bond or letter of credit in a higher amount;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The establishment by the operator of a reserve fund; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Other measures to ensure financial responsibility.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The operator shall furnish such information and reports, and grant such access to its records, as the Secretary from time to time requires.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Registration and Effective Date of New Home Warranty Security Plan.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If a contract for sale or construction of a new home between a buyer and a builder who participates in a new home warranty security plan provides, either by its terms or by virtue of an option exercised by the buyer, that the home will be registered in the plan, the operator of the plan shall register the home and shall do so at the cost agreed upon between the operator and the builder and disclosed to the buyer at the time the contract for sale or construction of the new home is entered into, unless the buyer is not charged directly or indirectly for the cost of the warranty.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Protection under the new home warranty security plan begins on the warranty date.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The provisions of Real Property Article, Subtitle 6, Annotated Code of Maryland, concerning new home warranties apply to each newly constructed private dwelling unit, the contract for sale or construction of which is entered into on or after January 1, 1991. The provisions of Real Property Article, Subtitle 6, Annotated Code of Maryland, do not apply in Montgomery County, except as provided in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="grp|10-610">Real Property Article, §10-610, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Other Warranties.</heading>
    <text>The warranties provided under a new home warranty security plan are in addition to warranties otherwise provided by law, including those set forth in Real Property Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="grp|10-202">10-202</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="grp|10-203">10-203</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="grp|11-131">11-131</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|01|09|.09">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Notice Requirements for Denial of Coverage.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Notice of Denial.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The operator of a plan shall notify the buyer in writing of a decision to deny warranty coverage for all or part of a claim not later than 90 days after the claim is received by the operator.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The notice of denial shall include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Reference to the specific terms of the plan on which the denial is based; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The procedures which the buyer must follow to appeal the denial, including all time limitations.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the operator is unable to reach a decision on the claim within 90 days, the operator shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Before the end of the 90-day period, notify the buyer in writing of the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Reasons for the inability to meet the deadline, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Date by which the decision will be reached; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When a decision on the claim is reached, notify the buyer of a decision to deny warrant coverage in accordance with <cite path="09|01|09|.09|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The operator shall send copies of all notifications of denial of coverage to the Secretary at the same time that the notice is sent to the buyer.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Real Property Article, Title 10, Subtitle 6, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-05-01">Regulations <cite path="|09|01|09|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|09|01|09|.03">.03</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective January 1, 2000 (26:27 Md. R. 2013); amended permanently effective May 1, 2000 (27:8 Md. R. 798)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-06-25">Regulations <cite path="|09|01|09|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|09|01|09|.03">.03</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective January 1, 2001 (28:2 Md. R. 97); emergency status expired June 1, 2001; amended permanently effective June 25, 2001 (28:12 Md. R. 1105)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1991-01-01">Regulations <cite path="|09|01|09|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|09|01|09|.08">.08</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective January 1, 1991 (18:2 Md. R. 142); emergency status expired July 31, 1991</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-06-08">Regulations <cite path="|09|01|09|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|09|01|09|.08">.08</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective October 29, 1991 (18:23 Md. R. 2481); emergency status expired April 30, 1992;  adopted permanently effective June 8, 1992 (19:11 Md. R. 1013)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-01-24"><cite path="|09|01|09|.09">Regulation .09</cite> adopted effective January 24, 2000 (27:1 Md. R. 74)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
