<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>13</num>
  <heading>Regulation of Units to Prevent Anticompetitive Actions</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Procedures.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The procedures described in this regulation shall apply to a proposed decision or action of a board or commission within the Maryland Department of Labor composed in whole or in part of individuals participating in the occupation or profession regulated by the board or commission if the proposed decision or action:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>May result in an unreasonable anti-competitive action; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Does not further a clearly articulated State policy to displace competition in a regulated market in order to protect the health, safety, and welfare of the citizens of the State.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Before the board or commission makes a decision or takes an action which may result in the outcomes described in this regulation, the board or commission shall notify the Secretary or the Secretary’s designee of the board’s or commission’s proposed action or decision.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Secretary or the Secretary’s designee shall review the proposed action or decision expeditiously and shall notify the board or commission in writing of the decision to approve, disapprove, modify, or remand the proposed decision or action back to the board or commission for further review.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A decision or an action of a board or commission may not constitute a final decision or action of the board or commission until after the Secretary or the Secretary’s designee has conducted a review of the substance of the proposed decision or action by the board or commission to ensure its compliance with an articulated State policy as described in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|8-205">State Government Article, §8-205</cite>.1(b), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A final decision or action of the board or commission shall comply with the written decision made by the Secretary or the Secretary’s designee in accordance with the requirements set forth in this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|8-205">State Government Article, §8-205</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-12-31">Effective date: December 31, 2018 (45:26 Md. R. 1240)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
