<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Certifiable Renewable Energy Facilities</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|61|02|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Application Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A renewable energy facility shall apply for certification as a Tier 1 renewable source or a Tier 2 renewable source provider on a form provided by the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="20|61|02|.01|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>, the renewable energy facility application form shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The name and location of the renewable energy facility;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The legal name of the owner of the renewable energy facility and a copy of a certificate of good standing issued by the state in which the owner's business is formed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The name of the operator of the renewable energy facility, if different than the owner;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A description of the renewable energy facility technology;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The rated renewable generation capacity of the facility or, where Tier 1 renewable source or Tier 2 renewable source fuel is simultaneously cofired with fossil fuels, the proportion of output per fuel type by 1 megawatt-hour (MWh) generated according to the formula on file with GATS;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Documentation indicating that the renewable energy facility meets the resource eligibility criteria for Tier 1 renewable source or Tier 2 renewable source; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Certification that the applicant is substantially in compliance with all applicable environmental and administrative requirements under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-704">Public Utilities Article, §7-704, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In addition to the requirements of <cite path="20|61|02|.01|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, an applicant for certification as a renewable energy facility that consists of a Level 1 or Level 2 photovoltaic solar system, shall file:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A photovoltaic solar system specifications form provided by the Commission; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A copy of the interconnection agreement between the applicant and the applicant's electric company.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An applicant for certification as a renewable energy facility that consists of a Level 1 solar photovoltaic solar system is not required to file the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A copy of a certificate of good standing issued by the state in which the owner's business is formed, provided the owner is not a corporation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Documentation indicating that the renewable energy facility meets the resource eligibility criteria for a Tier 1 renewable source; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Certification that the applicant is substantially in compliance with all applicable environmental and administrative requirements under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-704">Public Utilities Article, §7-704, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>In addition to the requirements of <cite path="20|61|02|.01|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, an owner and operator applicant for certification as a renewable energy facility that consists of glazed liquid-type flat-plate or tubular solar collectors for a solar water heating system installed for residential use, and commissioned on or after June 1, 2011, shall file:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A Project Owner/Installer Affidavit;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A copy of the local building permit final approval; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The system technical documentation:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A copy of the SRCC OG-300 System Specification with annual estimated energy savings; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The system component specifications including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A copy of the SRCC OG-100 Collector Thermal Performance Rating; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The manufacturer and model number of the on-site meter that meets the required performance standards of the International Organization of Legal Metrology and measures the energy savings of a single tank system on the solar loop of the system.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>In addition to the requirements of <cite path="20|61|02|.01|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, an owner and operator applicant for certification as a renewable energy facility that consists of glazed liquid-type flat-plate or tubular solar collectors for a solar water heating system installed for non-residential and commercial use, and commissioned on or after June 1, 2011, shall file:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A Project Owner/Installer Affidavit;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A copy of the local building permit final approval; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The system component specifications including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A copy of the SRCC OG-100 Collector Thermal Performance Rating; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The manufacturer and model number of the on-site meter that meets the required performance standards of the International Organization of Legal Metrology.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>In addition to the requirements of <cite path="20|61|02|.01|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, an owner and operator applicant for certification as a renewable energy facility that consists of a thermal biomass system shall file the manufacturer and model number of the on-site meter that meets the required performance standards of the International Organization of Legal Metrology.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Renewable Energy Facility — REC Account.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as provided under <cite path="20.61.03.03">COMAR 20.61.03.03</cite>, a renewable energy facility or its authorized representative shall apply to PJM Environmental Information Services, Inc. to establish an account with GATS in its name not later than 30 days after Commission certification of the renewable energy facility.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Except as provided under <cite path="20.61.03.03">COMAR 20.61.03.03</cite>, a renewable energy facility shall maintain in good standing an account with GATS in order for a REC to be considered eligible to satisfy the renewable energy portfolio standard in Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|61|02|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Obligation of Certified Renewable Energy Facility.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>After a GATS account is established, the renewable energy facility may record metered electricity generation, or its equivalent, from Tier 1 renewable sources or Tier 2 renewable sources, other than from Level 1 solar facilities, for the purpose of receiving a Maryland-eligible REC.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Level 1 Solar Renewable Energy Facility — Recording Renewable Energy Credits.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A Level 1 solar renewable energy facility owner or designee may record electric generation into its GATS account based on the schedule established by the Commission for the facility.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a Level 1 solar renewable energy facility is unable to meet the electricity generation schedule established by the Commission, the solar facility owner or designee shall notify the Commission within 30 days of the change in status.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Within 30 days of a change in the information contained in its original application or any subsequent amended application, the renewable energy facility shall file a copy of the updated or supplemental information with the Commission, including:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Reference to the original filing and the information contained in it; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A detailed explanation of the proposed change and how the change will affect the original filing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Level 1 and Level 2 Solar  Renewable Energy Credits — Sale or Transfer.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An on-site Level 1 or Level 2 solar renewable energy facility may retain or transfer a REC it creates.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Prior to the sale of a solar REC by a solar renewable energy facility to a person other than a Maryland supplier, the solar renewable energy facility shall offer the solar REC to a Maryland supplier for compliance with the requirements of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-703">Public Utilities Article, §7-703, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A Maryland solar renewable energy facility shall comply with the requirements of <cite path="20|61|02|.03|D.|(2)">§D(2) of this regulation</cite> by posting an offer to sell a solar REC on a publicly accessible website approved by the Commission for 10 business days.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If a solar REC posted on an approved website under this section is not sold to a Maryland supplier 10 business days after posting, the Maryland solar renewable energy facility may sell the REC to any willing buyer.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Decertification.</heading>
    <text>A renewable energy facility may be decertified for any of the following:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Failure to comply with this chapter;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A material change in circumstances that causes the facility to become ineligible for certification under <cite path="|20|61|02|.01">Regulation .01 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Fraud, including participation in events that result in a REC being double-counted; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Good cause as determined by the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Public Utilities Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-121">2-121</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|5-101">5-101</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-701">7-701</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-713">7-713</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-11-24">Regulations <cite path="|20|61|02|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|20|61|02|.04">.04</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective July 1, 2005 (32:18 Md. R. 1517); adopted permanently effective November 24, 2005 (32:23 Md. R. 1829)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-09-20"><cite path="|20|61|02|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective September 20, 2010 (37:19 Md. R. 1285)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-05-05"><cite path="|20|61|02|.01|C.">Regulation .01C</cite>, D adopted as an emergency provision effective April 1, 2008 (35:9 Md. R. 895); adopted permanently effective May 5, 2008 (35:9 Md. R. 899)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-07-10"><cite path="|20|61|02|.01|D.">Regulation .01D</cite> amended effective July 10, 2023 (50:13 Md. R. 514)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-04-02"><cite path="|20|61|02|.01|E.">Regulation .01E</cite>, F adopted as an emergency provision effective January 1, 2012 (39:3 Md. R. 257); adopted permanently effective April 2, 2012 (39:6 Md. R. 410)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-07-08"><cite path="|20|61|02|.01|G.">Regulation .01G</cite> adopted effective July 8, 2013 (40:13 Md. R. 1076)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-05-05"><cite path="|20|61|02|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective April 1, 2008 (35:9 Md. R. 895); amended permanently effective May 5, 2008 (35:9 Md. R. 899)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-09-20"><cite path="|20|61|02|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective September 20, 2010 (37:19 Md. R. 1285)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-05-05"><cite path="|20|61|02|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective April 1, 2008 (35:9 Md. R. 895); amended permanently effective May 5, 2008 (35:9 Md. R. 899)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-09-20"><cite path="|20|61|02|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective September 20, 2010 (37:19 Md. R. 1285)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-07-08"><cite path="|20|61|02|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite> amended effective July 8, 2013 (40:13 Md. R. 1076)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-12-01"><cite path="|20|61|02|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite>, D amended effective December 1, 2008 (35:24 Md. R. 2079)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
