<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>04</num>
  <heading>Specialists</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>Specialists employed in an early childhood, elementary, pre-kindergarten—12 or secondary school program shall hold an appropriate license under COMAR 13A.12.04 or a license in certain areas as otherwise provided in State law.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|12|04|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Licenses for Specialists.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Types of Specialist Licenses.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Temporary Professional.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Temporary Professional License is valid for 2 years and may not be renewed.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A local school system, State-operated school, or nonpublic school approved under COMAR 13A.09.10 may request a Temporary Professional License for an applicant who does not meet the renewal requirements of a professional license.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If an applicant under <cite path="|13A|12|04|.11">Regulation .11 of this chapter</cite> has not completed three semester hours or obtained three State-approved CPD credits in special education coursework, but otherwise meets the requirements for initial licensure, a local school system, State-operated school, or nonpublic school approved under COMAR 13A.09.10 may request a Temporary Professional License for the applicant.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Initial Professional.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Initial Professional License is valid for 5 years and may be renewed should the license holder meet the renewal requirements under <cite path="|13A|12|04|.13">Regulation .13 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An applicant who has met the requirements of one of the pathways to licensure under Regulations <cite path="|13A|12|04|.03">.03</cite>—<cite path="|13A|12|04|.12">.12</cite> of this chapter is eligible for an Initial Professional License.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Professional.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Professional License is valid for 5 years and may be renewed should the license holder meet the renewal requirements under <cite path="|13A|12|04|.13">Regulation .13 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An applicant who has met the requirements of one of the pathways to licensure under Regulations <cite path="|13A|12|04|.03">.03</cite>—<cite path="|13A|12|04|.12">.12</cite> of this chapter is eligible for a Professional License if the applicant submits documentation:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Verifying 3 years of effective performance; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Demonstrating completion of a Maryland induction program, if applicable.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Advanced Professional.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Advanced Professional License is valid for 5 years and may be renewed should the license holder meet the renewal requirements under <cite path="|13A|12|04|.13">Regulation .13 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An applicant who has met the requirements of one of the pathways to licensure under this chapter is eligible for an Advanced Professional License if the applicant meets the requirements for the Professional License under <cite path="13A|12|04|.02|A.|(3)">§A(3) of this regulation</cite> and submits documentation demonstrating that the applicant has:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A master’s degree or higher;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>At least 30 semester hours of post baccalaureate credit; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A National Board Certificate issued by the National Board for Professional Teaching Standards.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Department shall evaluate credits from institutions in other countries for comparability of degree and coursework by an independent agency authorized to analyze foreign credentials and designated by the Department. The evaluation is conclusive for the Department.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation app="2025-10-27" doc="Maryland Register, Volume 52, Issue 21" eff="2025-10-27" path="regulations|final|25-107-F" type="History" display="false"/>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>School Counselor.</heading>
    <text>The requirements for licensure as school counselor are that the applicant shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Complete 3 semester hours or State-approved CPD credits in special education coursework; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Complete one of the following pathways:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Maryland Approved Program. Candidates who possess a master’s degree and complete a program approved under COMAR 13A.07.06 leading to licensure as a school counselor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>National Board of Certified Counselors (NBCC). Candidates who possess a master’s degree in school counseling or school guidance and counseling, a valid National Board of Certified Counselors certificate, and 2 years of effective performance as a teacher or school counselor in a school setting.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>National Board for Professional Teaching Standards (NBPTS). Candidates who possess a master’s degree in school counseling or school guidance and counseling and present a valid National Board Certificate in the area of School Counseling.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Out-of-State Program. Candidates who possess a master’s degree in school counseling or school guidance and counseling from an out-of-State approved program and 2 years of effective performance as a teacher or school counselor or 500 clock hours in a supervised practicum in school counseling.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Council for Accreditation of Counseling and Related Educational Programs (CACREP). Candidates who possess a master’s degree in school counseling or school guidance and counseling from a program approved by the Council for Accreditation of Counseling and Related Educational Programs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Experienced Professional. Candidates who possess a master’s degree and a valid, professional certificate from another state and verification of at least 27 months of effective performance as a school counselor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|12|04|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Library Media Specialist.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definitions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In this regulation, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Terms Defined.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Library media” means a variety of communication and information formats and their accompanying technologies appropriate to learning and instruction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Library media specialist” means an individual who has developed knowledge, understanding of, and competency in the broad range of library media services, with particular emphasis on those competencies related to the development and administration of a comprehensive school library media program.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Pathways to Licensure. To qualify for a Professional Specialist License, a candidate shall complete one of the following pathways:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Maryland Approved Program. Candidates who possess a master’s degree and complete a program approved under COMAR 13A.07.06 leading to licensure as a library media specialist.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Out-of-State Preparation Program. Candidates who possess a master’s degree and complete an approved program leading to licensure as a library media specialist in another state.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Experienced Professional. Candidates who possess a master’s degree, hold a valid professional library media license from another state or country, and submit verification of 3 years of full-time effective experience as a library media specialist.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>National Board Certification. Candidates who possess a master’s degree and a National Board Certificate in the area of Library Media.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Master’s Equivalent.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The applicant shall have a bachelor’s degree or higher from an institution of higher education, to include a program of 36 semester hours of post-baccalaureate credit with 15 semester hours completed at one institution and a minimum of 24 semester hours of graduate credit in the content coursework listed in <cite path="13A|12|04|.04|B.|(5)|(b)">§B(5)(b) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Content coursework shall include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Administration of library media programs, including an understanding of State and national library media standards and technology standards;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Materials for children in all formats, including concepts related to the teaching and learning of reading;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Materials for young adults in all formats, including concepts related to the teaching and learning of reading;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Selection, evaluation, and use of materials in all formats to meet student curriculum and instructional needs;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Access and delivery of information, including reference and bibliographic systems in all formats;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Organization of knowledge, including cataloging and classification, and information retrieval in all formats;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Principles of communication, including dissemination and use of information in all formats; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>The design, creation, and implementation of library media in all formats for instructional use.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Professional education coursework shall include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>History and philosophy of education;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Student developmental levels, learning theory, and strategies for identifying student information and learning needs;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Theory, principles, and methods of instructional design and delivery; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Inclusion of special needs student populations.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The professional education coursework listed in <cite path="13A|12|04|.04|B.|(5)|(b)">§B(5)(b) of this regulation</cite> may be met by course credits earned in addition to, or as part of, the undergraduate degree program. The total number of post-baccalaureate credits needed for licensure may not be reduced for course requirements that are met in the applicant’s bachelor’s degree program. Additional post-baccalaureate or graduate courses may be substituted.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>An applicant shall satisfactorily complete a school library media practicum, 1 year of full-time teaching experience, or 1 year of full-time school library media-related experience.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Special education coursework. In addition to meeting one of the pathways in <cite path="13A|12|04|.04|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, the applicant must present 3 semester hours or State-approved CPD credits in special education coursework.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|12|04|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Pupil Personnel Worker.</heading>
    <text>The requirements for licensure as a pupil personnel worker are that the applicant shall have:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A master’s degree from an institution of higher education in pupil personnel or a related field, such as:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Counseling or guidance services, or both;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Early childhood, elementary, or secondary education;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Human growth and development;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Sociology, social work, or psychology;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Special education; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Administration and supervision;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In addition to or as part of <cite path="13A|12|04|.05|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, 21 semester hours of graduate credit or State-approved CPDs, to include school law and at least 6 of the following seven areas:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Counseling methods;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Early childhood or adolescent psychology, or both;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Multicultural issues;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Family systems/dynamics;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Delivery of pupil personnel services and programs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Abnormal psychology or juvenile delinquency, or both; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Educational assessment interpretation;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>3 years of effective teaching experience, or, at the recommendation of a local superintendent of schools, related experience may be substituted for teaching experience; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>3 semester hours of credit or State-approved CPDs in inclusion of special needs student populations.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|12|04|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Reading Specialist.</heading>
    <text>The requirements for licensure as a reading specialist are that the applicant shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Meet the requirements for licensure in early childhood education, elementary education, special education, or a secondary education area;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Submit verification of 3 years of effective teaching or clinical experience;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Complete 3 semester hours or State-approved CPD credits in special education coursework; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Complete the requirements of one of the following pathways:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Maryland Approved Program. Candidates who possess a master’s degree and complete a program approved under COMAR 13A.07.06 leading to licensure as a reading specialist;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Out-of-State Preparation Program. Candidates who possess a master’s degree and complete an approved program leading to licensure as a reading specialist in another state; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Professional Coursework. Candidates who possess a master’s degree or equivalent of 33 post-baccalaureate credits from an institution of higher education in reading and related areas to include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>15 semester hours of reading coursework with at least one course in each of the following areas:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Foundation or survey course;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Diagnosis and correction of reading difficulties;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Clinical or laboratory practicum;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Assessment or evaluation, or both; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Methods in the teaching of reading to English language learners; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Additional coursework selected from at least four of the following areas:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Emergent literacy;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Literacy Leadership;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Content area literacy;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Writing;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Effective use of technology in the literacy classroom;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Early Childhood, Elementary, or Adolescent literacy;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Literacy research; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Linguistics.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Special Provision.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An applicant who satisfies the requirements of <cite path="13A|12|04|.06|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> by presenting a teaching license in a secondary education area shall demonstrate proficiency in the knowledge and practices of scientific reading instruction, to include phonemic awareness, phonics, fluency, vocabulary, and comprehension.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Demonstration of proficiency may be satisfied by submitting one of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A passing score on a reading instruction test approved by the State Board of Education;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Completion of coursework or professional learning approved by the Department; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Submission of attestation of proficiency through observation completed by a Department-recognized assessor; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Completion of training provided by the Department in the science of reading.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|12|04|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Reading Teacher.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Requirements for Licensure. The requirements for licensure as a reading teacher are that the applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Meet the requirements for licensure in early childhood education, elementary education, special education, or a secondary education area;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Complete 3 semester hours or State-approved CPD credits in special education coursework;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Have 12 semester hours of post-baccalaureate graduate credit from an institution of higher education in reading, including a foundation or survey course and a course in diagnosis and correction of reading difficulties; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Have 2 years of successful teaching experience.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Special Provision.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An applicant who satisfies the requirements of <cite path="13A|12|04|.07|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite> by presenting a teaching license in a secondary education area shall demonstrate proficiency in the knowledge and practices of scientific reading instruction, to include phonemic awareness, phonics, fluency, vocabulary, and comprehension.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Demonstration of proficiency may be satisfied by submitting one of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A passing score on a reading instruction test approved by the State Board of Education;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Completion of coursework or professional learning approved by the Department; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Submission of attestation of proficiency through observation completed by a Department-recognized assessor; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Completion of training provided by the Department in the science of reading.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Psychometrist.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definition.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In this chapter, the following term has the meaning indicated.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Term Defined. “Psychometrist” means an individual who works directly under the professional supervision of a school psychologist or supervisor of school psychological services. The purpose of this position is limited to providing assistance to the school psychologist by administering psychological tests and other related psychometric tasks.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Education. An applicant for licensure as a psychometrist shall have the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A master’s degree from an institution of higher education in psychology or education.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>45 semester hours of graduate and undergraduate coursework from an institution of higher education that shall include the following areas:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Tests and measurements;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Individual intelligence testing of children;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Individual educational assessment of children, reading assessment, curriculum-based assessment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Assessment of personality (including social, emotional, and behavioral assessment of children);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Practicum in psychological testing of children;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Developmental psychology child and adolescent psychology;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Statistics/research methods, research design;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Personality theory;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Learning process/theory;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Abnormal psychology, psychopathology;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Educational psychology;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>Curriculum and instruction;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>Intervention techniques, consultation, counseling;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(n)</num>
          <text>Social bases of behavior, social psychology, multicultural psychology; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(o)</num>
          <text>Physiological and neurological bases of behavior.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Coursework required in §B(2)(a), (h)—(l), and (n) of this regulation may be taken at the undergraduate level.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>3 semester hours or State-approved CPD credits in special education coursework.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Experience. An applicant demonstrating compliance with the experience requirements for licensure as a psychometrist shall comply with the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Option I.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>500 clock hours of field experience in school psychology which is approved by and under the direction of an institution of higher education that has an approved program in psychology.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The applicant shall ensure that field experience includes experience in regular and special education programs and emphasizes assessment.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The applicant shall ensure that field supervision occurs under an individual licensed as a school psychologist.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Option II.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>2 years of successful experience of at least 600 clock hours per year providing psychometric services to children in an educational setting under the supervision of an individual licensed as a school psychologist.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The supervision requirement may be waived if an applicant has previously provided these services as a licensed psychologist.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>School Psychologist.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definition. “School psychologist” means an individual who is licensed to provide psychological services to children in a public or State-approved nonpublic school setting and supervises interns and psychometrists.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Education. An applicant for licensure as a school psychologist shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Complete 3 semester hours or State-approved CPD credits in special education coursework; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Complete one of the following pathways to licensure:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Option I:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Submit a master’s degree or higher in school psychology from a Maryland-approved program; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Qualifying scores on the Maryland-approved test for school psychologist.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Option II:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Submit a master’s degree or higher and complete an out-of-State-approved program in school psychology, culminating a minimum of a 1,200-hour internship in school psychology; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Submit qualifying scores on the Maryland-approved test for school psychologist.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Option III: Submit a valid Nationally Certified School Psychologist certificate issued by the National School Psychology Certification Board.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Option IV:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Submit a master’s degree or higher from an institution of higher education; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Submit a valid professional license in school psychology from another state and verification of at least 27 months of effective performance as a school psychologist during the past 7 years, on the basis of which application is being made for a comparable Maryland license.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Therapists (Occupational Therapists, Physical Therapists, Speech-Language Pathologists, or Audiologists).</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Department shall consider an occupational therapist, physical therapist, speech-language pathologist, or audiologist holding a valid license issued by the State Board of Occupational Therapy Practice, the State Board of Physical Therapy Examiners, or the State Board of Audiologists, Hearing Aid Dispensers, and Speech-Language Pathologists, in accordance with the relevant provisions of the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite> as professionally licensed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This individual does not require an additional educator license.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>School Social Worker.</heading>
    <text>To obtain educator licensure as a school social worker, the applicant shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Be licensed by the Maryland State Board of Social Work Examiners as a:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Masters Social Worker;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Certified Social Worker; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Certified Social Worker — Clinical.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Complete 3 semester hours or State-approved CPD credits in special education coursework</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Gifted and Talented Education Specialist.</heading>
    <text>To be licensed as a Gifted and Talented Education Specialist, an applicant shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Complete one of the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A Department-approved master’s program that leads to licensure in Gifted and Talented Education;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An out-of-State approved master’s program that leads to Gifted and Talented licensure; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Approved coursework.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Complete 15 semester hours of graduate coursework in Gifted and Talented Education from an institution of higher education, which includes a balance of content in the following competencies:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Understanding the foundations of gifted education, including historical perspectives, key philosophies and theories, social, cultural, and economic influences, key issues, and trends;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Understanding the unique cognitive and affective characteristics of gifted and talented students, including the learning differences of gifted and talented students with disabilities and those from diverse backgrounds;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Understanding processes and procedures for the identification of gifted and talented students, including the use of equitable approaches for identifying gifted and talented students from diverse backgrounds and those with disabilities;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Understanding evidence-based instructional strategies for differentiating instruction for gifted and talented students, including strategies that enhance acquisition of knowledge and skills in specific domains, critical and creative thinking, problem solving, and metacognition;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Understanding theories and models for developing and implementing curriculum, instruction, and assessments for gifted and talented students; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Understanding how to create learning environments that foster the social and emotional well-being of gifted and talented students, including the development of self-awareness, coping skills, positive peer relationships, and leadership; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Complete at least 3 semester hours in a clinical/laboratory internship;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Complete 3 semester hours or State-approved CPD credits in special education coursework; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Present verification of 27 months of effective teaching experience or clinical experience</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Renewal and Advancement of a Specialist License.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An applicant who holds a license is responsible for initiating the renewal of the license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An applicant shall ensure renewal requirements are received before the expiration date of the license to be considered continuous.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Failure to Meet Requirements. Failure to meet the requirements of this section results in nonrenewal of the license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Advancement to a New License. An applicant may apply to advance to the next level of licensure by meeting the requirements under §.02A of this chapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Professional Development Requirements. The Initial Professional, Professional, and Advanced Professional License may be renewed for successive 5-year terms upon the successful completion of the requisite number of professional development points (PDPs) as set forth in <cite path="|13A|12|04|.15">Regulation .15 of this chapter</cite> based on an individual professional development plan as set forth in <cite path="|13A|12|04|.14">Regulation .14 of this chapter</cite> that is designed to improve student learning and that is approved, if required, by the educator’s supervisor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Application Process.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Renewal. An educator may renew their existing Initial Professional, Professional, or Advanced Professional License by submitting:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A completed application, in the manner required by the Department;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A statement, signed under the penalty of perjury, that the applicant has completed all requirements for licensure renewal, including the requisite number of Professional Development Points under an Individual Professional Development Plan; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The required fee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Advancement. An educator may request advancement to a new level of licensure by submitting:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A completed application, in the manner required by the Department;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Supporting documentation demonstrating the applicant has met the requirements for the new level of licensure; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The required fee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All documentation submitted is subject to audit by the Department, and the educator shall provide additional documentation to the Department on request.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Individuals employed by a Maryland local school system, State-operated school, or nonpublic school approved under COMAR 13A.09.10, may submit documentation directly to the employer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Individuals who are not employed by a Maryland local school system, State-operated school, or nonpublic school approved under COMAR 13A.09.10 shall submit documentation directly to the Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|12|04|.14">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Individual Professional Development Plans.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Individual Professional Development Plans.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An educator shall have an individual professional development plan in place for each of the 5 years of validity for each Initial Professional, Professional, and Advanced Professional license issued to the educator.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An individual professional development plan shall include a minimum of 90 professional development points, as set forth in <cite path="|13A|12|04|.15">Regulation .15 of this chapter</cite>, to renew the educator’s License.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Educators who are not employed with a local school system, State-operated school, or nonpublic school approved under COMAR 13A.09.10 are responsible for developing their own individual professional development plan.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Approval of an Individual Professional Development Plan.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Educators working in a Maryland local school system, State-operated school, or nonpublic school approved under COMAR 13A.09.10 shall obtain approval of their proposed individual professional development plan from their supervisors.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The educator’s supervisor, or an appropriate designee, shall approve proposed individual professional development plans.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Educators shall obtain initial approval of their individual professional development plan within 6 months of issuance of the license to be renewed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Supervisor Review.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A supervisor shall review the existing individual professional development plan of any educator new to the district or school within 3 months of the educator’s beginning employment in the new position.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A supervisor may require an educator to amend the plan or may withdraw approval for a plan that had been previously approved, but the Department shall approve any professional development points that were earned consistently with an approved plan in the application for license renewal.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Signatures.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Before applying to renew an Initial Professional, Professional, or Advanced Professional license, educators shall obtain a signature from a current supervisor.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A supervisor’s signature shall indicate that the supervisor has reviewed the log of professional development activities maintained by the educator to ensure that the reported activities are consistent with the approved individual professional development plan.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The educator remains responsible for the final accounting of professional development points applied towards license renewal.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>An educator whose supervisor refuses to sign an Individual professional development plan may follow the review procedures set forth in <cite path="13A|12|04|.14|B.|(7)">§B(7) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Approval of an individual professional development plan may not be unreasonably withheld by a supervisor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>If a plan is rejected by a supervisor, an educator may seek review of the denial from:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The superintendent of schools, or designee, if employed with a local school system;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Chief Officer of the Legal Authority, or designee, if employed with a nonpublic school approved under COMAR 13A.09.10; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Executive Director, or comparable position, if employed with a State-operated school.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|12|04|.15">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Professional Development Points.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Professional Development Point (PDP).</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>1 clock hour is equivalent to one PDP.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>1 semester hour is equivalent to 15 PDPs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>One Department-approved continuing professional development credit is equivalent to 15 PDPs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>One continuing education unit is equivalent to ten PDPs.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Educators applying to renew an Initial Professional, Professional, or Advanced Professional License shall complete a minimum of 90 PDPs that shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Content or pedagogy related to an area on the educator’s license;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>English as a Second Language, Sheltered English, or Bilingual Education;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Strategies for teaching students with disabilities, or differentiated instruction for students with diverse learning needs; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Culturally Responsive Teaching or diverse student identities in education.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Additional Requirements for Specific Licensure Areas.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Blind/Visually Impaired. Teachers who hold a license in the area of the Blind/Visually Impaired shall present a minimum of 15 PDPs in braille maintenance.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>School Counselor. An educator who is licensed as a School Counselor shall present 1 semester hour of coursework from an Institution of Higher Education, one Department-approved continuing professional development credit; or an equivalent number of continuing education units that address the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Depression;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Trauma;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Violence;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Youth suicide;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Substance abuse; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The identification of professional resources and best practices for distributing resources to parents or guardians to help students in crisis.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Administrator. If an educator is employed in a local school system, State-operated school, or nonpublic school approved under COMAR 13A.09.10 and assigned in an administrator or supervisor position, the educator shall submit PDPs which include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Strategies for increasing teacher retention; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Strategies for developing and facilitating teacher leadership.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Professional development points may be accrued by the completion of one of more of the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>College credit earned or taught at an accredited institution of higher education.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Continuing professional development (CPD) credits, earned or taught, approved by the Department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Continuing education units (CEUs) from an accredited International Association for Continuing Education and Training provider or approved by another Maryland State agency for purposes of licensure.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Professional conference. A professional conference is a workshop, institute, or seminar of 4 or more hours that contributes to ongoing, sustained, and high-quality professional development.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Curriculum Development.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Curriculum development is a group activity in which the license holder contributes to the improvement of the curriculum of a school, a school division, or an educational institution.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>This includes the alignment of curriculum frameworks, instructional materials, and assessments to provide a system with clear expectations of what is to be taught and learned.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>For each curriculum developed, the Department shall award the educator up to 30 PDPs.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Publication of a Book or Article.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The license holder shall ensure that the book or article contributes to the education profession or to the body of knowledge of the license holder’s teaching area or instructional position.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The educator shall ensure that an article is published in a recognized professional journal.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The educator shall ensure that books are published for purchase.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>For each book published, the Department shall award the educator up to 75 PDPs. For each article published, the Department shall award the educator up to 10 PDPs.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Mentorship.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Mentoring is the process by which an experienced professional who has received mentorship training helps one or more individuals to improve their performance.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Assistance may involve role modeling, direct instruction, demonstration, observation with feedback, developing of plans, and consultation to promote instructional excellence and increased student achievement.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Mentoring may include the supervision of a field experience of a pre-service student teacher or an intern in an approved teacher preparation program, as well as mentoring as part of the induction process for a beginning teacher.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Micro-Credentials.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Micro-credentials are a digital form of certification indicating demonstrated competency/mastery in a specific skill or set of skills.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Educators identify a competency they want to develop, submit evidence that they have mastered the competency, and receive a digital badge once the evidence is approved.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Micro-credentials can be earned by non-profit and for-profit entities approved by the local school system, State-operated school, nonpublic school, or the Department.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>For each micro-credential earned, the Department shall award the educator up to 10 PDPs.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Professional Development Activity.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Department shall accept professional development activities approved by the Department, Maryland local school system, State Agency, a Maryland approved nonpublic school, or another state department of education.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The license holder shall ensure that each activity is a minimum of 1 contact hour.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An educator who earns a National Board Certificate from the National Board of Professional Teaching Standards may present that certificate when subsequently renewing a Maryland Educator License as a substitute for <cite path="13A|12|04|.15|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|2-205">2-205</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|2-303">2-303</cite>(g), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|6-701">6-701</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|6-708">6-708</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-3">8-3</cite>A-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|03">03</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-701">8-701</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-708">8-708</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-01-01">Regulations <cite path="|13A|12|04|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|13A|12|04|.07">.07</cite>, and .09—.15 adopted effective January 1, 1989 (15:26 Md. R. 2996)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-01-20"><cite path="|13A|12|04|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective November 6, 1995 (22:22 Md. R. 1670); January 20, 2003 (30:1 Md. R. 26)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-10-13"><cite path="|13A|12|04|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective October 13, 2014 (41:20 Md. R. 1113)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-10-13"><cite path="|13A|12|04|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective October 13, 2014 (41:20 Md. R. 1113)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-04-08"><cite path="|13A|12|04|.03">Regulation .03</cite> repealed and new Regulation .03 adopted effective April 8, 2019 (46:7 Md. R. 370)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-01-20"><cite path="|13A|12|04|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite> amended effective January 20, 2003 (30:1 Md. R. 26)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-06-22"><cite path="|13A|12|04|.04">Regulation .04</cite> adopted effective June 22, 1992 (19:12 Md. R. 1135)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-08-29"><cite path="|13A|12|04|.04">Regulation .04</cite> repealed and new Regulation .04 adopted effective August 29, 2005 (32:17 Md. R. 1439)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-01-20"><cite path="|13A|12|04|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite>, B amended effective January 20, 2003 (30:1 Md. R. 26)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-03-27"><cite path="|13A|12|04|.04|B.">Regulation .04B</cite> amended effective June 1, 1998 (25:11 Md. R. 822); March 27, 2017 (44:6 Md. R. 327)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-06-01"><cite path="|13A|12|04|.04|D.">Regulation .04D</cite> amended effective April 24, 1995 (22:18 Md. R. 598); June 1, 1998 (25:11 Md. R. 822)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-06-01"><cite path="|13A|12|04|.04|E.">Regulation .04E</cite> amended effective September 12, 1994 (21:8 Md. R. 1512); January 15, 1996 (23:1 Md. R. 29); June 1, 1998 (25:11 Md. R. 822)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-04-06"><cite path="|13A|12|04|.04|F.">Regulation .04F</cite> amended effective September 12, 1994 (21:8 Md. R. 1512); April 6, 1998 (25:7 Md. R. 528)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1991-12-23"><cite path="|13A|12|04|.05">Regulation .05</cite> adopted, and existing Regulation .05 recodified to Regulation .05-1 effective December 23, 1991 (18:25 Md. R. 2758)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-01-20"><cite path="|13A|12|04|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective January 20, 2003 (30:1 Md. R. 26)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-08-29"><cite path="|13A|12|04|.05">Regulation .05</cite> repealed and new Regulation .05 adopted effective August 29, 2005 (32:17 Md. R. 1439)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-08-03"><cite path="|13A|12|04|.05|A.">Regulation .05A</cite> amended effective August 3, 1992 (19:15 Md. R. 1393)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-04-06"><cite path="|13A|12|04|.05|D.">Regulation .05D</cite> adopted effective April 6, 1998 (25:7 Md. R. 528)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-01-20"><cite path="|13A|12|04|.05-1">Regulation .05-1</cite> repealed effective January 20, 2003 (30:1 Md. R. 26)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-08-06"><cite path="|13A|12|04|.06">Regulation .06</cite> repealed and new Regulation .06 adopted effective August 6, 2001 (28:15 Md. R. 1399)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-01-20"><cite path="|13A|12|04|.06|B.">Regulation .06B</cite>, C amended effective January 20, 2003 (30:1 Md. R. 26)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-01-20"><cite path="|13A|12|04|.07|C.">Regulation .07C</cite> amended effective January 20, 2003 (30:1 Md. R. 26)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-04-03"><cite path="|13A|12|04|.08">Regulation .08</cite> adopted effective April 3, 1989 (16:6 Md. R. 729)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-01-20"><cite path="|13A|12|04|.08|A.">Regulation .08A</cite>, D amended effective September 30, 1995 (21:24 Md. R. 1990); January 20, 2003 (30:1 Md. R. 26)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-01-22"><cite path="|13A|12|04|.08|C.">Regulation .08C</cite> amended effective January 22, 2001 (28:1 Md. R. 26)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-01-20"><cite path="|13A|12|04|.09|B.">Regulation .09B</cite> amended effective January 20, 2003 (30:1 Md. R. 26)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-08-02"><cite path="|13A|12|04|.10">Regulation .10</cite> repealed effective August 2, 1993 (20:15 Md. R. 1221)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-04-06">Regulations .11 and .12 repealed effective April 6, 1998 (25:7 Md. R. 528)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-09-12"><cite path="|13A|12|04|.13">Regulation .13</cite> amended effective September 12, 1994 (21:8 Md. R. 1512)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-04-06"><cite path="|13A|12|04|.14|A.">Regulation .14A</cite> amended effective April 6, 1998 (25:7 Md. R. 528)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-01-20"><cite path="|13A|12|04|.15|B.">Regulation .15B</cite> amended effective January 20, 2003 (30:1 Md. R. 26)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-04-09"><cite path="|13A|12|04|.16">Regulation .16</cite> adopted effective April 9, 2007 (34:7 Md. R. 700)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-01-01" discontinuity="true">For a history of certification requirements before January 1, 1989, see the Administrative History for COMAR 13A.07.01.</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-04-01" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|13A|12|04|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|13A|12|04|.16">.16</cite> repealed under Subtitle 12 Certification Chapter 04 Administrators and Supervisors and new Regulations <cite path="|13A|12|04|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|13A|12|04|.15">.15</cite> adopted under Subtitle 12 Educator Licensure Chapter 04 Specialists effective April 1, 2024 (51:5 Md R. 231)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-10-27"><cite path="|13A|12|04|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended effective March 3, 2025 (52:4 Md. R. 220); October 27, 2025 (52:21 Md. R. 1025)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-03-03"><cite path="|13A|12|04|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective March 3, 2025 (52:4 Md. R. 220)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-03-03"><cite path="|13A|12|04|.07|A.">Regulation .07A</cite> amended effective March 3, 2025 (52:4 Md. R. 220)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-03-03"><cite path="|13A|12|04|.13|D.">Regulation .13D</cite> amended effective March 3, 2025 (52:4 Md. R. 220)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-03-03"><cite path="|13A|12|04|.15|C.">Regulation .15C</cite> amended effective March 3, 2025 (52:4 Md. R. 220)</annotation>
    <annotation app="2025-10-27" doc="Maryland Register, Volume 52, Issue 21" eff="2025-10-27" path="regulations|final|25-107-F" type="History" display="false"/>
  </annotations>
</container>
