<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Administrators and Supervisors</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>Administrators and supervisors who have direct contact with students, who have responsibility for curriculum development, or who have responsibility for supervision of instruction shall meet the requirements for a license under COMAR 13A.12.05, as applicable.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|12|05|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Licenses for Administrators and Supervisors.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Types of Administrator/Supervisor Licenses.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Initial Professional.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Initial Professional License is valid for 5 years and may be renewed should the license holder meet the renewal requirements under <cite path="|13A|12|05|.15">Regulation .15 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An applicant who has met the requirements of one of the pathways to licensure under Regulations <cite path="|13A|12|05|.03">.03</cite>—<cite path="|13A|12|05|.12">.12</cite> of this chapter is eligible for an Initial Professional License.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Professional.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Professional License is valid for 5 years and may be renewed should the license holder meet the renewal requirements under <cite path="|13A|12|05|.15">Regulation .15 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An applicant who has met the requirements of one of the pathways to licensure under Regulations <cite path="|13A|12|05|.03">.03</cite>—<cite path="|13A|12|05|.12">.12</cite> of this chapter is eligible for a Professional License if the applicant submits documentation:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Verifying 3 years of effective performance; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Demonstrating completion of a Maryland induction program, if applicable.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Advanced Professional.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Advanced Professional License is valid for 5 years and may be renewed should the license holder meet the renewal requirements under <cite path="|13A|12|05|.13">Regulation .13 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An applicant who has met the requirements of one of the pathways to licensure under this chapter is eligible for an Advanced Professional License if the applicant meets the requirements for the Professional License under <cite path="13A|12|05|.02|A.|(2)">§A(2) of this regulation</cite> and submits documentation that the applicant has:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A master’s degree or higher;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>At least 30 semester hours of post baccalaureate credit; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A National Board Certificate issued by the National Board for Professional Teaching Standards.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Department shall evaluate credits from institutions in other countries for comparability of degree and coursework by an independent agency authorized to analyze foreign credentials and designated by the Department. The evaluation is conclusive for the Department.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation app="2025-10-27" doc="Maryland Register, Volume 52, Issue 21" eff="2025-10-27" path="regulations|final|25-107-F" type="History" display="false"/>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Supportive Services Personnel.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Purpose. The State Superintendent of Schools may license as Supportive Services Personnel a qualified employee of a local school system who is assigned to administrative or supervisory responsibilities not otherwise covered in these regulations, and who has responsibilities comparable to those assigned to individuals who hold specific supervisory licenses.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Education. An applicant for licensure as Supportive Services Personnel shall have a bachelor’s degree or higher appropriate to the area of responsibility from an institution of higher education.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>This license is issued at the request of a local school, State-operated school, or nonpublic school approved under COMAR 13A.09.10.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|12|05|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Superintendents.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Superintendent I.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>This license qualifies an individual to be assigned as a county deputy superintendent, assistant superintendent or associate superintendent through either Traditional or Reciprocal Licensure.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An applicant for Traditional Licensure shall meet the education and experience requirements.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Education Requirements for Traditional Licensure. The applicant shall have:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A master’s degree from an institution of higher education;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Completed one of the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A Department-approved program which leads to licensure as a superintendent;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A program offered by an institution of higher education leading to licensure as a superintendent in the state in which the institution is located; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>45 semester hours of graduate coursework, including a minimum of 15 semester hours in education administration taken at an institution of higher education. Graduate coursework earned under <cite path="13A|12|05|.04|A.|(3)|(a)">§A(3)(a) of this regulation</cite> may be applied toward the 45 required semester hours; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>3 semester hours or State-approved CPD credits in special education coursework.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Experience Requirements for Traditional Licensure. The applicant shall have:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>27 months of effective teaching performance or effective performance as a licensed specialist as defined in COMAR 13A.12.03 in a pre-kindergarten — 12 setting; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>24 months of effective administrative or supervisory experience in a pre-kindergarten—12 setting.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Requirements for Reciprocal Licensure. A deputy, associate, or assistant superintendent who enters Maryland from another state may obtain a Superintendent I license if that individual:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Holds a valid professional state license in a like or comparable area;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Presents verification of at least 36 months of effective performance as a deputy, associate, or assistant superintendent during the past 7 years; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Completes 3 semester hours or State-approved CPD credits in special education coursework.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Superintendent II.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>This license qualifies an individual to be a county superintendent through either Traditional or Reciprocal Licensure.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An applicant for Traditional Licensure shall meet the education and experience requirements.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Education Requirements for Traditional Licensure. The applicant shall have:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A master’s degree from an institution of higher education;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Have completed one of the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A Department-approved program which leads to licensure as a superintendent to include coursework covering public school administration, supervision, and methods of teaching;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A program offered by an institution of higher education leading to licensure as a superintendent in the state in which the institution is located to include coursework covering public school administration, supervision, and methods of teaching; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>60 semester hours of graduate coursework, including a minimum of 24 semester hours in education administration taken at an institution of higher education, to include public school administration, supervision, and methods of teaching. Graduate coursework earned under <cite path="13A|12|05|.04|B.|(3)|(a)">§B(3)(a) of this regulation</cite> may be applied toward the 60 required semester hours; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>3 semester hours or State-approved CPD credits in special education coursework.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Experience Requirements for Traditional Licensure. The applicant shall have:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>27 months of effective teaching performance or effective performance as a licensed specialist as defined in COMAR 13A.12.03 in a pre-kindergarten—12 setting; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>24 months of effective administrative or supervisory experience in a pre-kindergarten—12 setting.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Requirements for Reciprocal Licensure. A superintendent who enters Maryland from another state may obtain a Superintendent II license if that individual:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Holds a valid professional state license in a like or comparable area;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Presents verification of at least 36 months of effective performance as a superintendent during the past 7 years;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Presents verification of 2 years of graduate work at an institution of higher education, to include coursework covering public school administration, supervision, and methods of teaching; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Completes 3 semester hours or State-approved CPD credits in special education coursework.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Supervisors of Instruction, Assistant Principals, and Principals.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Application of Regulation.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>This regulation applies to obtaining licensure as an Administrator.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a principal transfers to become a principal in a special education school, the principal shall hold a Supervisor of Special Education license as set forth in <cite path="|13A|12|05|.10">Regulation .10 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Administrator Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>This license qualifies an individual to be assigned as a supervisor of instruction, assistant principal, or principal.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The applicant shall have:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A master’s degree, or higher, from an accredited institution of higher education;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Twenty-seven months of effective teaching performance or effective performance as a specialist as defined in COMAR 13A.12.04;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Three semester hours or State-approved CPD credits in special education coursework; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The applicant shall meet one of the following pathways:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A Department-approved program which leads to licensure as a supervisor of instruction, assistant principal, or principal;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An approved out-of-State program that leads to licensure as a supervisor of instruction, assistant principal, or principal and includes a supervised clinical practicum;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Eighteen semester hours of graduate coursework taken at an institution of higher education, to include coursework in the following categories:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Curriculum, instruction, and assessment;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Supervision, evaluation, and supporting instructional improvement;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Legal issues and ethical decision-making;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Program/school administration;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Culturally responsive leadership and/or equity in leadership; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Supervised clinical practicum that is a minimum of 240 clock hours; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Holds a valid professional state license in administration from another state or country and has verification of 5 years of effective performance as an administrator in a PK-12 school setting.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Applicants who qualify based on §3(b) or (c) of this regulation must present a qualifying score as established by the State Superintendent of Schools on a school leader licensure assessment approved by the State Board of Education.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation app="2025-09-15" doc="Maryland Register, Volume 52, Issue 18" eff="2025-09-15" path="regulations|final|25-055-F" type="History" display="false"/>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|12|05|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Library Media Administrator.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definition.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In this regulation, the following term has the meaning indicated.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Term Defined. “Library media administrator” means an individual designated by the local superintendent of schools as having responsibility for the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Administration and supervision of the library media program, including the supervision of the library media program in the individual schools; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Development of policies, programs, budgets, and procedures for the library media services of the school system and its schools.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Education and Experience. To be licensed as library media administrator, the applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Meet the requirements for licensure as a library media specialist;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Have a master’s degree from an institution of higher education;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Have 3 years of effective library media program experience;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Complete 3 semester hours or State-approved CPD credits in special education coursework; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Complete one of the options listed under <cite path="|13A|12|05|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite> that would lead to licensure as Administrator I.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Special Provision. An applicant seeking to satisfy the requirements of <cite path="13A|12|05|.06|B.|(3)">§B(3) of this regulation</cite> may, at the recommendation of the local school superintendent, substitute 2 years of related effective experience for 2 years of library media program experience.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Supervisor of School Counseling.</heading>
    <text>The requirements for licensure as a supervisor of school counseling are that the applicant shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Meet the requirements for licensure as a school counselor;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Have 3 years of effective performance as a school counselor;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Complete 3 semester hours or State-approved CPD credits in special education coursework; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Have 12 semester hours of graduate credit from an institution of higher education in any of the following areas, with at least 6 semester hours in school supervision or school administration:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Management;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>School supervision;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>School administration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Program development; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Program evaluation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|12|05|.08">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Supervisor of School Psychological Services.</heading>
    <text>The requirements for licensure as a supervisor of school psychological services are that the applicant shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Meet the requirements for licensure as a school psychologist under COMAR 13A.12.04.09;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Have a doctoral degree:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>From a state or accredited school psychology program, a national educator preparation accreditation organization, National Association of School Psychologists, or American Psychological Association accredited school psychology program; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In psychology or education or human development;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>As part of or in addition to <cite path="13A|12|05|.08|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, have 9 semester hours of graduate credits including 3 semester hours in school law and 6 semester hours in supervision, management, or administration of schools;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Have 3 years of experience as a school psychologist under COMAR 13A.12.04.09; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Complete 3 semester hours or State-approved CPD credits in special education coursework.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|12|05|.09">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Supervisor of Pupil Personnel.</heading>
    <text>The requirements for licensure as a supervisor of pupil personnel are that the applicant shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Meet the requirements for licensure as a pupil personnel worker;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Have a master’s degree from an institution of higher education;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>As part of or in addition to <cite path="13A|12|05|.09|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, have a graduate course in the area of administration and supervision;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Complete 3 semester hours or State-approved CPD credits in special education coursework; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Have 3 years of successful teaching experience. At the recommendation of the local superintendent of schools, related experience may be substituted for teaching experience.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Supervisor of Special Education.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Principal Public Separate School. The requirements for licensure as a principal in a public separate school are that the applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Meet the requirements for licensure in special education; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Meet the requirements for licensure as an Administrator II.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Supervisor of Special Education (Sole Assignment). The requirements for licensure as a supervisor of special education are that the applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Meet the requirements for licensure in special education; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Meet the requirements for licensure as an Administrator I.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Special Provision. Supervisors with multiple area assignments shall meet the requirements set forth in <cite path="|13A|12|05|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Supervisor of Speech Pathologists and Audiologists.</heading>
    <text>The requirements for a license as a supervisor of speech pathology and audiology are that the applicant shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Meet the requirements for certification or licensure as otherwise provided in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|2-301">Health Occupations Article, §2-301, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, as a speech pathologist or audiologist;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Have a master’s degree from an institution with an approved program when graduating with at least one course in administrative and supervisory techniques and one course in the development of school curriculum;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Complete 3 semester hours or State-approved CPD credits in special education coursework; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Have 4 years full-time paid experience or its equivalent as a speech and hearing clinician, 2 years of which shall have been in a school setting.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Supervisor of Teachers of Deaf and Hard of Hearing.</heading>
    <text>The requirements for licensure as a supervisor of teachers of the deaf and hard of hearing are that the applicant shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Meet the requirements for licensure as a teacher of the deaf and hard of hearing;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Have a master’s degree from an institution of higher education, with at least one course in administrative and supervisory techniques and one course in curriculum development;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Complete 3 semester hours or State-approved CPD credits in special education coursework; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Have experience that includes:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>3 years of successful teaching experience with the deaf and hard of hearing; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>4 years paid experience or its equivalent in a school setting with 2 years successful teaching experience with the deaf and hard of hearing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Renewal and Advancement of an Administrator/Supervisor License.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An applicant who holds a license is responsible for initiating the renewal of the license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An applicant shall ensure renewal requirements are received before the expiration date of the license to be considered continuous.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Failure to Meet Requirements. Failure to meet the requirements of this section results in nonrenewal of the license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Advancement to a New License. An applicant may apply to advance to the next level of licensure by meeting the requirements under §.02A of this chapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Professional Development Requirements. The Initial Professional, Professional, and Advanced Professional License may be renewed for successive 5-year terms on the successful completion of the requisite number of professional development points (PDPs) as set forth in <cite path="|13A|12|05|.15">Regulation .15 of this chapter</cite> based on an individual professional development plan as set forth in <cite path="|13A|12|05|.14">Regulation .14 of this chapter</cite> that is designed to improve student learning and that is approved, if required, by the educator’s supervisor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Application Process.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Renewal. An educator may renew their existing Initial Professional, Professional, or Advanced Professional License by submitting:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A completed application, in the manner required by the Department;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The required fee; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A statement, signed under the penalty of perjury, that the applicant has completed all requirements for licensure renewal, including the requisite number of Professional Development Points under an Individual Professional Development Plan.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Advancement. An educator may request advancement to a new level of licensure by submitting:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A completed application, in the manner prescribed by the Department;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Supporting documentation demonstrating the applicant has met the requirements for the new level of licensure; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The required fee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All documentation submitted is subject to audit by the Department, and the educator shall provide additional documentation to the Department on request.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|12|05|.14">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Individual Professional Development Plans.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Individual Professional Development Plans.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An educator shall have an individual professional development plan in place for each of the 5 years of validity for each Initial Professional, Professional, and Advanced Professional license issued to the educator.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An individual professional development plan shall include a minimum of 90 professional development points, as set forth in <cite path="|13A|12|05|.15">Regulation .15 of this chapter</cite>, to renew the educator’s license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Educators who are not employed with a local school system, State-operated school, or nonpublic school approved under COMAR 13A.09.10 are responsible for developing their own individual professional development plan.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Approval of an Individual Professional Development Plan.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Educators working in a Maryland local school system, State-operated school, or nonpublic school approved under COMAR 13A.09.10 shall obtain approval of their proposed individual professional development plan from their supervisors.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The educator’s supervisor, or an appropriate designee, shall approve proposed individual professional development plans.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Educators shall obtain initial approval of their individual professional development plan within 6 months of issuance of the license to be renewed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Supervisor Review.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A supervisor shall review the existing individual professional development plan of any educator new to the district or school within 3 months of the educator’s beginning employment in the new position.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A supervisor may require an educator to amend the plan or may withdraw approval for a plan that had been previously approved, but the Department shall approve any professional development points that were earned consistently with an approved plan in the application for license renewal.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Signatures.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Before applying to renew an Initial Professional or Professional license, educators shall obtain a signature from a current supervisor.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A supervisor’s signature shall indicate that the supervisor has reviewed the log of professional development activities maintained by the educator to ensure that the reported activities are consistent with the approved individual professional development plan.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The educator remains responsible for the final accounting of professional development points applied towards license renewal.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>An educator whose supervisor refuses to sign an individual professional development plan may follow the review procedures set forth in <cite path="13A|12|05|.14|B.|(7)">§B(7) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Approval of an individual professional development plan may not be unreasonably withheld by a supervisor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>If a plan is rejected by a supervisor, an educator may seek review of the denial from:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The superintendent of schools, or designee, if employed with a local school system;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Chief Officer of the Legal Authority, or designee, if employed with a nonpublic school approved under COMAR 13A.09.10; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Executive Director, or comparable position, if employed with a State-operated school.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|12|05|.15">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Professional Development Points.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Professional Development Point (PDP). The Department shall measure professional development activities as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>1 clock hour is equivalent to one PDP.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>1 semester hour is equivalent to 15 PDPs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>One Department-approved continuing professional development credit is equivalent to 15 PDPs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>One continuing education unit is equivalent to ten PDPs.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Educators applying to renew an Initial Professional, Professional, or Advanced Professional License shall complete a minimum of 90 PDPs that shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Content or pedagogy related to an area on the educator’s license;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>English as a Second Language, Sheltered English, or Bilingual Education;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Strategies for teaching students with disabilities, or differentiated instruction for students with diverse learning needs; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Culturally Responsive Teaching or diverse student identities in education.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Additional Requirements for Specific Certification Areas.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Blind/Visually Impaired. Teachers who hold a license in the area of the Blind/Visually Impaired shall present a minimum of 15 PDPs in braille maintenance.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>School Counselor. An educator who is licensed as a School Counselor shall present 1 semester hour of coursework from an institution of higher education, one Department-approved continuing professional development credit; or an equivalent number of continuing education units that address the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Depression;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Trauma;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Violence;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Youth suicide;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Substance abuse; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The identification of professional resources and best practices for distributing resources to parents or guardians to help students in crisis.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Administrator. If an educator is employed in a local school system, State-operated school, or nonpublic school approved under COMAR 13A.09.10 and assigned in an administrator or supervisor position, the educator shall submit PDPs which include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Strategies for increasing teacher retention; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Strategies for developing and facilitating teacher leadership.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Professional development points may be accrued by the completion of one of more of the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>College credit earned or taught at an accredited institution of higher education.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Continuing professional development (CPD) credits, earned or taught, approved by the Department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Continuing education units (CEUs) from an accredited International Association for Continuing Education and Training provider or approved by another Maryland State agency for purposes of licensure.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Professional conference. A professional conference is a workshop, institute, or seminar of 4 or more hours that contributes to ongoing, sustained, and high-quality professional development.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Curriculum Development.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Curriculum development is a group activity in which the license holder contributes to the improvement of the curriculum of a school, a school division, or an educational institution.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>This includes the alignment of curriculum frameworks, instructional materials, and assessments to provide a system with clear expectations of what is to be taught and learned.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>For each curriculum developed, the Department shall award the educator up to 30 PDPs.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Publication of a Book or Article.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The license holder shall ensure that the book or article contributes to the education profession or to the body of knowledge of the license holder’s teaching area or instructional position.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The educator shall ensure that an article is in a recognized professional journal.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The educator shall ensure that books are published for purchase.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>For each book published, the Department shall award the educator up to 75 PDPs. For each article published, the Department shall award the educator up to 10 PDPs.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Mentorship.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Mentoring is the process by which an experienced professional who has received mentorship training helps one or more individuals to improve their performance.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Assistance may involve role modeling, direct instruction, demonstration, observation with feedback, developing of plans, and consultation to promote instructional excellence and increased student achievement.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Mentoring may include the supervision of a field experience of a pre-service student teacher or an intern in an approved teacher preparation program, as well as mentoring as part of the induction process for a beginning teacher.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Micro-Credentials.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Micro-credentials are a digital form of certification indicating demonstrated competency/mastery in a specific skill or set of skills.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Educators identify a competency they want to develop, submit evidence that they have mastered the competency, and receive a digital badge once the evidence is approved.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Micro-credentials can be earned by non-profit and for-profit entities approved by the local school system, State-operated school, nonpublic school, or the Department.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>For each micro-credential earned, the Department shall award the educator up to 10 PDPs.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Professional Development Activity.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Department shall accept professional development activities approved by the Department, Maryland local school system, State Agency, a Maryland approved nonpublic school, or another state department of education.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The license holder shall ensure that each activity is a minimum of 1 contact hour.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An educator who earns a National Board Certificate from the National Board of Professional Teaching Standards may present that certificate when subsequently renewing a Maryland Educator License as a substitute for <cite path="13A|12|05|.15|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|2-205">2-205</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|2-303">2-303</cite>(g), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|6-701">6-701</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|6-708">6-708</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-3">8-3</cite>A-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|03">03</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-701">8-701</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-708">8-708</cite>; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-01-01">Effective date: January 1, 1989 (15:26 Md. R. 2998)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-01-06"><cite path="|13A|12|05|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective December 25, 1989 (16:25 Md. R. 2714); September 17, 1990 (17:18 Md. R. 2201); January 6, 1992 (18:26 Md. R. 2831)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-01-06"><cite path="|13A|12|05|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective December 25, 1989 (16:25 Md. R. 2714); January 6, 1992 (18:26 Md. R. 2831)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-12-25"><cite path="|13A|12|05|.08|A.">Regulation .08A</cite> amended effective December 25, 1989 (16:25 Md. R. 2714)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-11-07" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|13A|12|05|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|13A|12|05|.08">.08</cite> repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|13A|12|05|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|13A|12|05|.08">.08</cite> adopted effective November 7, 1994 (21:22 Md. R. 1879)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-03-05"><cite path="|13A|12|05|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective July 23, 2001 (28:14 Md. R. 1323); March 5, 2012 (39:4 Md. R. 337)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-01-20"><cite path="|13A|12|05|.02|C.">Regulation .02C</cite>, D amended effective September 23, 1996 (23:19 Md. R. 1376); January 20, 2003 (30:1 Md. R. 26)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-03-05"><cite path="|13A|12|05|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite> amended effective March 5, 2012 (39:4 Md. R. 337)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-08-27"><cite path="|13A|12|05|.08">Regulation .08</cite> amended effective August 27, 2007 (34:17 Md. R. 1509)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-01-01" discontinuity="true">For a history of certification requirements before January 1, 1989, see the Administrative History for COMAR 13A.07.01.</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-04-01" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|13A|12|05|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|13A|12|05|.08">.08</cite> repealed under Subtitle 12 Certification Chapter 05 Suspensions and Revocations and new Regulations <cite path="|13A|12|05|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|13A|12|05|.15">.15</cite> adopted under Subtitle 12 Educator Licensure Chapter 05 Administrators and Supervisors effective April 1, 2024 (51:5 Md R. 231)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-10-27"><cite path="|13A|12|05|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended effective October 27, 2025 (52:21 Md. R. 1025)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-15"><cite path="|13A|12|05|.05">Regulation .05</cite> repealed and new Regulation .05 adopted effective September 15, 2025 (52:18 Md. R. 924)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-03-03"><cite path="|13A|12|05|.06|B.">Regulation .06B</cite> amended effective March 3, 2025 (52:4 Md. R. 220)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-03-03"><cite path="|13A|12|05|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective March 3, 2025 (52:4 Md. R. 220)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-03-03"><cite path="|13A|12|05|.08|A.">Regulation .08A</cite> amended effective March 3, 2025 (52:4 Md. R. 220)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-03-03"><cite path="|13A|12|05|.10|A.">Regulation .10A</cite> amended effective March 3, 2025 (52:4 Md. R. 220)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-03-03"><cite path="|13A|12|05|.15|C.">Regulation .15C</cite> amended effective March 3, 2025 (52:4 Md. R. 220)</annotation>
    <annotation app="2025-09-15" doc="Maryland Register, Volume 52, Issue 18" eff="2025-09-15" path="regulations|final|25-055-F" type="History" display="false"/>
    <annotation app="2025-10-27" doc="Maryland Register, Volume 52, Issue 21" eff="2025-10-27" path="regulations|final|25-107-F" type="History" display="false"/>
  </annotations>
</container>
