<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Graduation Requirements for Public High Schools in Maryland</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter sets out the enrollment, credit, student service, and State assessment requirements for graduation from a public high school in Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>It is the expectation of the State Board that each student enrolled in a public school system in Maryland shall earn a Maryland High School Diploma in accordance with the requirements set forth in this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Upon notifying the State Superintendent of Schools, each local school system may establish graduation requirements beyond the minimum requirements established by the State Board.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Credit" means successful demonstration of a specified unit of study.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Department" means the State Department of Education.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“EOC Assessment” means an end-of-course assessment that comprises 20 percent of the student’s grade in that course.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Individualized education program (IEP)" means a written description for a student with a disability that is developed, reviewed, and revised in accordance with 20 U.S.C. §1414 and COMAR 13A.05.01.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Maryland Comprehensive Assessments” means the assessments within the Maryland Comprehensive Assessment Program in algebra, science, English, and government developed or adopted by the Department that are aligned with and measure a student’s skills and knowledge as set forth in the Maryland Standards for those subjects.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Enrollment and Credit Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Beginning with students entering the 9th grade class of 2014—2015 school year, each student shall enroll in a mathematics course in each year of high school that the student attends, up to a maximum of 4 years of attendance, unless in the 5th or 6th year a mathematics course is needed to meet a graduation requirement.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>To be awarded a diploma, a student who entered the 9th grade class in the 2020—2021 school year or earlier shall be enrolled in a Maryland public school system and shall have earned a minimum of 21 credits that include the following specified credits:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>English — four credits of organized instruction in comprehension of literary and informational text, writing, speaking and listening, language, and literacy, of which one credit shall be aligned with the Maryland Comprehensive Assessment for English;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Fine Arts — one credit in dance, media arts, music, theatre, or visual art, or a combination of these;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Mathematics — three credits, including one with instruction in algebra aligned with the Maryland Comprehensive Assessment for algebra or one or more credits in subsequent mathematics courses for which Algebra I is a prerequisite, and one with instruction in geometry aligned with the content standards for geometry;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Physical education — one-half credit;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Health education — one-half credit;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Science — three credits of organized instruction which includes a laboratory component engaging in the application of the science and engineering practices, the crosscutting concepts, and disciplinary core ideas including Earth/space science, life science, physical science (chemistry and physics), engineering, and technology, aligned to the Maryland Comprehensive Assessment for science;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Social studies — three credits including one credit in United States history, one credit in world history, and one credit in local, State, and national government aligned with the Maryland Comprehensive Assessment for government;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Technology education — one credit that includes the application of knowledge, tools, and skills to solve practical problems and extend human capabilities; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>One of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Two credits of world language, which may include American Sign Language;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Two credits of advanced technology education; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Successfully complete a State-approved career and technology program.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Beginning with students entering the 9th grade class in the 2021—2022 school year, to be awarded a diploma, a student shall be enrolled in a Maryland public school system and shall have earned a minimum of 22 credits that include the following specified credits:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>English — four credits of organized instruction in comprehension of literary and informational text, writing, speaking and listening, language, and literacy, of which one credit shall be aligned with the Maryland Comprehensive Assessment for English;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Fine arts — one credit in dance, media arts, music, theatre, or visual art, or a combination of these;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Mathematics — four credits, including one with instruction in algebra aligned with the Maryland Comprehensive Assessment for algebra or one or more credits in subsequent mathematics courses for which Algebra I is a prerequisite, and one with instruction in geometry aligned with the content standards for geometry;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Physical education — one-half credit;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Health education — one credit;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Science — three credits, designed to develop scientific literacy with all courses integrating the application of the science and engineering practices, crosscutting concepts, and each containing a laboratory component, including one credit in life science aligned to the Maryland Comprehensive Assessment for Life Science; one credit in physical science (including chemistry, physics, or integrated physical science); and one credit in Earth/space science or a course with the topics of Earth/space science integrated;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Social studies — three credits including one credit in United States history, one credit in world history, and one credit in local, State, and national government aligned with the Maryland Comprehensive Assessment for government;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Computer science, engineering, or technology education — one credit that includes the study of computers and algorithmic processes or the application of knowledge, tools, and skills to solve practical problems and extend human capabilities; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>One of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Two credits of the same world language, which may include two credits of American Sign Language; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Successful completion of a State-approved career and technical education program.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Elective programs and instruction shall be developed at the discretion of the local school system, open to enrollment for all students, and shall focus on in-depth study in required subject areas, exploration, or application and integration of what has been learned.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>All students must complete a locally designed high school program of environmental literacy as set forth in COMAR 13A.04.17 that is approved by the State Superintendent of Schools.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Other Provisions for Earning Credit.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In addition to earning credits during the regular school day and year, credits may be earned, at the discretion of the local school system, through the means specified in §§B—H of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Summer School.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each local school system may provide summer school programs for original and review credit as determined by the needs of students.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Credit instruction shall meet the aggregate time requirements specified by the local school system.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Consistent with local school system policy and procedure, credit may be given for acceptable summer study offered by approved public and nonpublic institutions in or outside of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Evening School. A local school system may provide evening school programs for credit as an extension of the regular school day as determined by the needs of students.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Online Courses.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Consistent with local school system policy and procedure, credit may be given for Department-approved online courses.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If credit is to be applied toward minimum graduation requirements, the Department-approved online course shall be provided by the local school system or through a Maryland Higher Education Institution as part of dual enrollment, as set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|18-14">Education Article, §18-14</cite>-01, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Work Study Programs, Job Entry Training Programs, or Experience Outside the School.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Consistent with local school system policy and procedure, actual time spent in work study, job entry training, or other experience may be counted for credit when identified as an integrated part of a planned study program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For work or experience outside the school which is approved and supervised by the local school system, not more than nine elective credits toward meeting graduation requirements may be granted to a student.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>College Courses. Consistent with the payment requirement of Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|18-14">18-14</cite>A-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|04">04</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|18-14">18-14</cite>A-05, Annotated Code of Maryland,  credit toward high school graduation shall be given for courses offered by accredited colleges that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Meet the local school system policies and procedures;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Have prior approval of the local superintendent of schools or the superintendent’s designee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Are aligned with the Maryland College and Career Ready Standards or an elective credit for graduation requirements; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Prepare students to earn an industry-recognized credential or college credits.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Independent Study/Internship. Consistent with local school system policy and procedure, credit toward high school graduation may be earned for independent study or internships in which a student successfully demonstrates preestablished curricular objectives.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Credit Through Examination.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Credit toward high school graduation may be earned by passing an examination that assesses student demonstration of local school system curricular objectives, which are based on the Maryland State Standards.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A student who would be eligible to graduate but for attaining credit in English 12 may obtain that credit by taking a State-approved examination and achieving a passing score as defined by the Maryland State Department of Education.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, a county board shall award credit to a middle school student for any course for which a high school student would be awarded credit if the middle school student meets the same requirements as the high school student.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Student Service.</heading>
    <text>To graduate, students shall complete one of the following:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>75 hours of student service that includes preparation, action, and reflection components and that, at the discretion of the local school system, may begin during the middle grades; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A locally designed program in student service that has been approved by the State Superintendent of Schools.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|03|02|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Maryland Comprehensive Assessments.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A student shall take the requisite Maryland Comprehensive Assessment during its next regular administration if the student received credit for taking, by the methods identified in Regulations .03 and .04 of this chapter, any of the following courses aligned with the Maryland Comprehensive Assessment:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Algebra;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Science;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>English; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Government.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>To be awarded the Maryland High School Diploma, all students, including elementary and middle school students who take high school level courses, shall take the Maryland Comprehensive Assessment for algebra, science, English, and government after the student completes the required course or courses.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Reporting Student Performance.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A school system shall state on the student’s performance record card only that the student has or has not met all assessment requirements.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For the purpose of this section, except for students identified in <cite path="13A|03|02|.06|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>, “met all assessment requirements” means taking all Maryland Comprehensive Assessments.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>For the 2020—2021, 2021—2022, and 2022—2023 school years, a student will have met the assessment requirement for Algebra I, English 10, science, and government if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The student has passed the Algebra I course, English 10 course, science course, and government course; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The student takes the Algebra I, English 10, science, and government Maryland Comprehensive Assessment aligned with the course.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Beginning with the 2023—2024 school year:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A student shall take the requisite Maryland Comprehensive Assessment during its regular administration if the student is taking, by the methods identified in Regulations .03 and .04 of this chapter, any of the following courses aligned with the Maryland Comprehensive Assessment:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Algebra;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>English;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Science; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Government; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Students entering the ninth grade, the Maryland Comprehensive Assessment for science and government shall account for 20 percent of the student’s final grade in the respective high school level science and government courses.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Notice to Parents or Guardians and Students.</heading>
    <text>Each principal shall inform all students and their parents or guardians annually at a minimum of the following:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Maryland's graduation requirements;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The student's progress on fulfilling the credit, Maryland Comprehensive Assessment, service, and applicable IEP requirements for graduation;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The results of each Maryland Comprehensive Assessment taken;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Department's schedule for the Maryland Comprehensive Assessment administration; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Beginning with the 2023—2024 school year, the student’s progress on completing the course credit, which includes the end-of-course Maryland Comprehensive Assessment in science and government, service, and applicable IEP requirements for graduation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|03|02|.08">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Grading and Reporting.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each school system in Maryland shall recognize and accept any and all credits a student earned toward graduation in any other public school in Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Each local school system shall develop a written policy on grading and reporting that complies with the student record requirements as set forth in COMAR 13A.08.02 and that includes:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An explanation of the grading scale at the elementary and secondary levels;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An explanation of the calculation of the final grade for a course;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An explanation of weights of honors, Advanced Placement, International Baccalaureate, and dual enrollment courses;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>An explanation of how attendance factors into the student’s grade;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>An explanation of grade changing procedures, including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A timeline for final grade changes that cannot exceed 45 school days following the last day of the grading period. For a change of grade for the fourth marking period, the timeline would begin on the first day of school in the new school year.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The names of personnel at the school and central office level authorized to make final grade changes;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Documentation that authorized personnel are required to maintain to support the final grade changes, including, at a minimum the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Name of teacher requesting grade change;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Reason for the grade change;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Signature of person approving the grade change;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Reason for the approval;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Date of the approval; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Signature of the principal;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>How and when the school system will audit the validity of the grade changes each year; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Appeal procedures.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>On October 1 of each school year, each local school system shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>File its policy on grading and reporting with State Superintendent of Schools; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Submit a copy of the grade change validity audit in accordance with <cite path="13A|03|02|.08|B.|(5)|(d)">§B(5)(d) of this regulation</cite> to the State Superintendent of Schools.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Upon submission of the items contained in <cite path="13A|03|02|.08|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, the Maryland State Department of Education will:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Verify that the local school system has met the requirements of this regulation; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Direct the local school system to develop a corrective action plan to bring it into compliance with this regulation and monitor the school system’s progress in completing its corrective action.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|03|02|.09">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Diplomas and Certificates.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The types of diplomas and certificates specified in §§B—D of this regulation shall be awarded to any student who meets the requirements for award.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Maryland High School Diploma. Except as provided in <cite path="|13A|03|02|.12">Regulation .12 of this chapter</cite>, to be awarded a Maryland high school diploma, a student shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Complete the enrollment, credit, and service requirements as specified in this chapter;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Complete local school system requirements; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Meet the graduation assessment requirements in the following ways:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Take the Maryland Comprehensive Assessments for Algebra I, science, government, and English 10; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Take an approved alternative assessment as established by the Department, such as Maryland Comprehensive Assessment for Algebra II, Advanced Placement examinations, SAT, ACT, or International Baccalaureate examinations.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Exception to Passing Score Requirement.  For the 2020—2021, 2021—2022, and 2022—2023 school years, students taking the Algebra I, English 10, science, and government Maryland Comprehensive Assessment will meet the graduation assessment requirement for Algebra I, English 10, science, and government.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Maryland High School Diploma by Examination.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>General Educational Development Testing Program. A Maryland High School Diploma by Examination may be awarded for satisfactory performance on approved general educational development tests if the student meets those requirements as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gle|11-808">Labor and Employment Article, §11-808, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and <cite path="09.37.01.04">COMAR 09.37.01.04</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Maryland Adult External High School Diploma Program. A Maryland High School Diploma by Examination may be awarded for demonstrating competencies in general life skills and individual skills on applied performance tests if the student meets those requirements as defined in <cite path="09.37.01.20">COMAR 09.37.01.20</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Maryland High School Certificate of Program Completion.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>This certificate shall be awarded only to students with disabilities who cannot meet the requirements for a diploma but who meet the following standards:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The student is enrolled in an education program for at least 4 years beyond grade 8 or its age equivalent, and is determined by an IEP team, with the agreement of the student and the parents of the student, to have developed appropriate skills for the individual to enter the world of work, act responsibly as a citizen, and enjoy a fulfilling life, with the world of work including but not limited to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Gainful employment;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Post-secondary education and training;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Supported employment; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Other services that are integrated in the community; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The student has been enrolled in an education program for 4 years beyond grade 8 or its age equivalent and will have reached age 21 by the end of the student's current school year.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Maryland Summary of Performance that describes the student's skills shall accompany the Maryland High School Certificate of Program Completion.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The final decision to award a student with disabilities a Maryland High School Certificate of Program Completion will not be made until after the beginning of the student's last year in high school.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A student with significant cognitive disability may not meet high school graduation requirements, in accordance with <cite path="13A|03|02|.09|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, if a student:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Participates in an Alternative Assessment based on Alternative Academic Achievement Standards (AA-AAAS); and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Continues to receive instruction based on Alternative Academic Achievement Standards through high school.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If a student participates in a graduation ceremony prior to the completion of the student's education program, at the ceremony the school system shall issue to the student a Certificate of Achievement or other similarly titled certificate in place of a diploma.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Certificate Endorsement.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Beginning with the 2024—2025 school year, students completing a Certificate may earn one or more endorsements.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The endorsements include a Post-Secondary Education endorsement, a Work-Ready/Employment/Career endorsement, and a Community/Citizenship endorsement.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Requirements for the endorsements will be identified by the Department.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Local Endorsements. Consistent with procedures established by the Department, each local school system may add endorsements to the diploma as incentives for students to meet locally established requirements and outcomes in instruction beyond the minimums specified by the State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>At least yearly, through the end of the implementation, the State Board will review and assess updated information on the graduation assessment requirements and scores.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Maryland High School Diploma. Beginning with the 2022—2023 school year, except as provided in <cite path="|13A|03|02|.12">Regulation .12 of this chapter</cite>, to be awarded a Maryland high school diploma, a student shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Complete the enrollment, credit, assessment and service requirements as specified in this chapter; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Complete local school system requirements.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>State Endorsements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Beginning with the 2024—2025 school year, students graduating may earn a College Ready State endorsement, a Career and Technical Education (CTE) State endorsement, or both.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Department will establish the requirements for the endorsements.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|03|02|.09-1">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09-1</num>
    <heading>Appeal of Denial of Diploma for Failure to Meet Maryland Comprehensive Assessment Requirement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A school system shall notify each senior and the senior's parents or guardians on or before the end of February of the senior year if a student may not graduate. The notice shall explain:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The reasons the student may not graduate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The options available to meet all graduation requirements;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>That a waiver of the Maryland Comprehensive Assessment graduation requirement may be one of the options, if the student meets the criteria set forth in §§C and E of this regulation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The waiver process and timeline; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>That parents or guardians may submit information in writing to the principal concerning eligibility of their child for the waiver.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>On or before the end of February, the principal shall report to the local superintendent the name and student identification number of each student identified in the February notice.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>On or before April 1, the school system shall identify each student who may fail to graduate because the student has taken none of the required Maryland Comprehensive Assessments.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>On or before April 1, the principal shall report to the local superintendent the name and student identification number of each student identified as meeting the criteria in <cite path="13A|03|02|.09-1|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>By April 1, for each senior identified in <cite path="13A|03|02|.09-1|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, the school principal shall consider whether to recommend to the local superintendent a waiver of the Maryland Comprehensive Assessment graduation requirements that the student has not fulfilled to date if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The student has or is expected to meet all the other graduation requirements; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The student is prevented from meeting the Maryland Comprehensive Assessment graduation requirements because:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Of a decision made by the local school system concerning the provision of appropriate assistance as required by <cite path="|13A|03|02|.06|C.">Regulation .06C of this chapter</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The student experienced a special, extraordinary, or extenuating circumstance or combination of circumstances preceding the administration of the most recent Maryland Comprehensive Assessment, such as a recent death in the immediate family, a serious or prolonged illness or pregnancy with medical complications, an accident causing serious injury, or a destructive house fire;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The student moved to the United States in the junior or senior year and the student is literate in the student's native language but not literate in English; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The student moved to Maryland in the senior year.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>On or about April 1, the principal shall notify the student and the student's parents or guardians that the student is being considered for a waiver of the Maryland Comprehensive Assessment graduation requirements that the student has not fulfilled to date. The notice shall explain the waiver decision-making process.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>On or before May 1, the principal of the high school shall make a Maryland Comprehensive Assessment waiver recommendation to the local superintendent for each student who meets the criteria set forth in <cite path="13A|03|02|.09-1|E.">§E of this regulation</cite> with the participation of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The student's IEP team, if the student is a student with disabilities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The English Language Learner staff, if the student is an English Language Learner;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Other school personnel; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>One or more of them.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The principal shall explain the reason for each recommendation under <cite path="13A|03|02|.09-1|G.">§G of this regulation</cite>, whether the recommendation is to grant or deny the waiver.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>The local superintendent shall review each recommendation and shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Grant or deny the waiver;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Promptly notify the student and the student's parent or guardian of the decision; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the waiver is granted, include in the notification the local procedures and requirements that must be met for a diploma to be awarded.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>The superintendent's decision in this matter is not appealable to the local board of education, but may be appealed to the State Superintendent of Schools.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>A student or the student's parents or guardians may appeal the waiver denial to the State Superintendent by sending a written appeal letter explaining why the waiver denial was an arbitrary or unreasonable decision. The State Superintendent may affirm or reverse the local superintendent's decision and shall inform the student, the student's parents or guardians, the local superintendent, and the State Board in writing of the decision.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>The decision of the State Superintendent may be appealed to the circuit court pursuant to Maryland Rules 7-201, et seq. On appeal:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If the State Superintendent has reversed the local superintendent's decision to deny the Maryland Comprehensive Assessment waiver and the local school system appeals that decision, the State Superintendent shall defend the decision on appeal; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the State Superintendent has affirmed the local superintendent's decision and the aggrieved student appeals, the local superintendent shall defend the State Superintendent's decision on appeal.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>By August 1, the local superintendent shall send a report to the State Superintendent or the State Superintendent's designee on waiver decisions rendered under this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>Nothing in this regulation is intended to establish any right to participate in the graduation ceremony while an appeal is pending. Participation in the graduation ceremony remains at the discretion of the local superintendent.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Alternatives to 4-year Enrollment Requirement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In recognition of the fact that 4-year enrollment in a public high school may not serve the best interests of some students, the alternatives in §§B and C of this regulation shall be made available.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Early College Admission Program. A student may receive a Maryland High School Diploma through acceptance in the early college admission program, if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The student is accepted for early admission to an accredited college before high school graduation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All Maryland Comprehensive Assessments and student service requirements have been met;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A written request by the student and parent or guardian is made to and approved by the local superintendent of schools certifying the early admission acceptance;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The student's program for the first year of college is approved by the local superintendent of schools if this program is included toward the issuance of a diploma; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>At the conclusion of the program or after 1 year, a written request for a Maryland High School Diploma is submitted to the superintendent together with a transcript or letter from the college to the high school principal indicating that the student has successfully completed a year of college work.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Early Admission to Approved Vocational, Technical, or Other Postsecondary School Program. A student may receive a Maryland High School Diploma through acceptance in an early admission program of an approved vocational, technical, or postsecondary school program if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The student is accepted for early admission by an approved vocational, technical, or postsecondary school program before high school graduation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All Maryland Comprehensive Assessments and student service requirements have been met;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A written request by the student and parent or guardian is made to and approved by the local superintendent of schools certifying the early admission acceptance;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The student's program for the first year of the postsecondary program is approved by the local superintendent of schools if this program is included toward the issuance of a diploma; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>At the conclusion of a full year of study, a written request for a Maryland High School Diploma is submitted to the superintendent together with a transcript or letter from the postsecondary school to the high school principal indicating that the student has successfully completed a year of postsecondary school work.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Alternatives for Structuring Programs.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each local school system shall be permitted to develop alternative ways for individual or groups of students to fulfill graduation requirements.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An alternative plan may include a waiver of the fourth year enrollment requirement if all credit, assessments, and student service requirements are met and if the local superintendent of schools or designee determines that the waiver is in the best interest of the student.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Procedures for implementing these alternative programs leading to high school diplomas are as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Development and approval of a curricular plan which assures that the content of the specified credits is included and the standards for graduation are met pursuant to the requirements of this chapter with the plan containing a program description, performance requirements, and evaluation procedures; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The local superintendent of schools is responsible for approving any plan and shall notify the State Superintendent of Schools once approval has been given.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|03|02|.12">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>General Provisions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Length of School Year. Maryland public high schools shall be open for at least 180 school days and a minimum of 1,170 school hours during a 10-month period in each school year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Graduation Requirements for Transfer Students.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Attendance Requirements.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>To receive a diploma, a student shall be in attendance at a Maryland public high school one full semester immediately preceding graduation in addition to meeting the other diploma requirements.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>In cases where this requirement creates an undue hardship for a student transferring to or from a Maryland nonpublic school or from an out-of-State school and wishing to receive a Maryland high school diploma, the local superintendent of schools may waive the one full semester attendance requirement.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Exception shall be made for a student with disabilities in a State-approved nonpublic program.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Students transferring from one Maryland public high school to another during the second semester of their senior year and meeting all requirements for graduation shall be given the option of graduating from either high school by agreement of the local superintendent of schools or the respective local superintendents when more than one local school system is involved.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Maryland Comprehensive Assessment Exemption Requirements.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A student who transfers from a nonpublic school or a school out of State is exempt from one or more of the Maryland Comprehensive Assessments if, consistent with local school system policy and procedure, the local superintendent determines that the course taken is aligned with the relevant Maryland Comprehensive Assessment and awards the student credit for taking any of the courses aligned with the Maryland Comprehensive Assessments, that is, algebra, science, English, or government, or all of these, in accordance with the principles set forth in <cite path="13A|03|02|.12|B.|(2)|(c)">§B(2)(c) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A student who transfers from a nonpublic school or a school out of State and has not received credit for algebra but has demonstrated mastery of the Maryland College and Career Ready Standards for algebra either through an evaluation or successful completion of subsequent mathematics courses for which algebra is a prerequisite is exempt from the Maryland Comprehensive Assessment for algebra.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>To award credit for taking any of the courses aligned with the Maryland Comprehensive Assessments, that is, algebra, science, English, or government, a principal shall determine through the following considerations whether the transfer student demonstrates subject matter knowledge aligned with the content standards for the subject:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Administration of standardized tests and examinations;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Observation of the student in the classroom;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Use of interviews that are focused around the student's demonstration of course content knowledge and performance levels; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Inspection of transcripts, report cards, and other documentation.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A student who transfers from a nonpublic school or from a school out of State into a local school system after the first semester of their senior year is exempt from the Maryland Comprehensive Assessment Requirements.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The exemption provided in <cite path="13A|03|02|.12|B.|(2)|(d)">§B(2)(d) of this regulation</cite> does not apply to a student with disabilities in a State-approved nonpublic program.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Local Graduation Requirements.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A student who enters a local school system in their senior year shall be granted a waiver from locally established graduation requirements unless the student chooses to fulfill the requirements.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A student in foster care or a homeless student who enters a local school system in their junior year shall be granted a waiver from locally established graduation requirements unless the local school system makes a finding that the student is reasonably able to complete the locally established graduation requirements in time to graduate from high school.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Unavailability of Official Transcript. If the transcript of record is not available, a local superintendent of schools or designee shall determine the appropriate placement of the student within the high school program by an evaluation of the student that shall include one or more of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Administration of standardized tests and examination;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Observation of the student in a classroom setting;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Use of interviews that are focused around the student's demonstration of course content knowledge and performance levels;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Inspection of report cards and other documentation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|2-205">2-205</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|7-203">7-203</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|7-205">7-205</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|7-205">7-205</cite>.1, and 8-404, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1976-04-14">Effective date: April 14, 1976 (3:8 Md. R. 427)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1984-05-21"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective August 11, 1978 (5:16 Md. R. 1259); September 22, 1978 (5:19 Md. R. 1446); May 21, 1984 (11:10 Md. R. 864)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1980-03-21"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.02|C.">Regulation .02C</cite> amended effective March 21, 1980 (7:6 Md. R. 609)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1982-02-10"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.02|D.">Regulation .02D</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective February 10, 1982 (9:5 Md. R. 520); emergency status expired March 12, 1982</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1982-08-02"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.02|D.">Regulation .02D</cite> amended effective August 2, 1982 (9:15 Md. R. 1516)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-07-29" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|13A|03|02|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|13A|03|02|.03">.03</cite> repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|13A|03|02|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|13A|03|02|.07">.07</cite> adopted effective July 29, 1985 (12:15 Md. R. 1524)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-04-14"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective April 14, 1986 (13:9 Md. R. 1021)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-01-15"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.03|F.">Regulation .03F</cite> amended effective January 15, 1989 (15:27 Md. R. 3131)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1988-04-04"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.03|G.">Regulation .03G</cite> amended effective April 4, 1988 (15:7 Md. R. 851)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1988-10-03"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.03|I.">Regulation .03I</cite> amended effective October 3, 1988 (15:20 Md. R. 2334)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-01-15"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.06">Regulation .06</cite> repealed effective January 15, 1989 (15:27 Md. R. 3131)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-08-14">Regulations .07 amended and .08 adopted as an emergency provision effective August 14, 1985 (12:18 Md. R. 1760)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-12-02">Regulations .07 amended and .08 adopted effective December 2, 1985 (12:24 Md. R. 2350)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-01-15"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.07">Regulation .07</cite> recodified to Regulation .06 effective January 15, 1989 (15:27 Md. R. 3131)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-01-15"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.08">Regulation .08</cite> amended and recodified to Regulation .07 effective January 15, 1989 (15:27 Md. R. 3131)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-09-28" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|13A|03|02|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|13A|03|02|.07">.07</cite> repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|13A|03|02|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|13A|03|02|.08">.08</cite> adopted effective September 28, 1992 (19:19 Md. R. 1710)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-03-18"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective August 15, 1994 (21:16 Md. R. 1386); July 29, 1996 (23:15 Md. R. 1089); March 18, 2002 (29:5 Md. R. 504)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-03-18">Regulations <cite path="|13A|03|02|.05">.05</cite>—<cite path="|13A|03|02|.06">.06</cite> repealed effective March 18, 2002 (29:5 Md. R. 504)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-07-19" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|13A|03|02|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|13A|03|02|.08">.08</cite> repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|13A|03|02|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|13A|03|02|.12">.12</cite> adopted effective July 19, 2004 (31:14 Md. R. 1079)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-07-28"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective April 11, 2005 (32:7 Md. R. 682); July 28, 2008 (35:15 Md. R. 1349)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-07-07"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 7, 2012 (39:17 Md. R. 1145); emergency provision expired December 31, 2012</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-03-22"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite> amended effective April 11, 2005 (32:7 Md. R. 682); May 22, 2006 (33:10 Md. R. 882); July 3, 2006 (33:13 Md. R. 1064); March 12, 2007 (34:5 Md. R. 561); March 22, 2010 (37:6 Md. R. 479)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-07-11"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.04|C.">Regulation .04C</cite> adopted effective July 11, 2011 (38:14 Md. R. 790)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-07-07"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.05|D.">Regulation .05D</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 7, 2012 (39:17 Md. R. 1145); emergency provision expired December 31, 2012</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-07-26"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.05|I.">Regulation .05I</cite> amended effective July 26, 2010 (37:15 Md. R. 999)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-07-28"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.05|J.">Regulation .05J</cite> amended effective July 28, 2008 (35:15 Md. R. 1349)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-05-22"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.07|A.">Regulation .07A</cite> amended effective April 11, 2005 (32:7 Md. R. 682); May 22, 2006 (33:10 Md. R. 882)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-05-22"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.07|C.">Regulation .07C</cite> amended effective May 22, 2006 (33:10 Md. R. 882)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-08-28"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.08|B.">Regulation .08B</cite> amended effective April 11, 2005 (32:7 Md. R. 682); May 22, 2006 (33:10 Md. R. 882); August 28, 2006 (33:17 Md. R. 1437)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-02-18"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.09">Regulation .09</cite> amended effective April 21, 2008 (35:8 Md. R. 807); February 18, 2013 (40:3 Md. R. 218)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-05-22"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.09|B.">Regulation .09B</cite> amended effective April 11, 2005 (32:7 Md. R. 682); May 22, 2006 (33:10 Md. R. 882)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-07-22"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.09-1">Regulation .09-1</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective January 23, 2009 (36:4 Md. R. 346); emergency status expired effective July 22, 2009</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-04-19"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.09-1">Regulation .09-1</cite> adopted effective April 19, 2010 (37:8 Md. R. 618)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-07-28"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.12|B.">Regulation .12B</cite> amended effective July 3, 2006 (33:13 Md. R. 1064); July 28, 2008 (35:15 Md. R. 1349)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-09-29" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective September 29, 2014 (41:19 Md. R. 1081)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-02-26"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective February 26, 2018 (45:4 Md. R. 206)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-08-21"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective June 22, 2015 (42:12 Md. R. 763); November 24, 2016 (43:23 Md. R. 1280); February 26, 2018 (45:4 Md. R. 206); June 14, 2021 (48:12 Md. R. 474); August 21, 2023 (50:16 Md. R. 727)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-06-14"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective June 14, 2021 (48:12 Md. R. 474)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-02-26"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite> amended effective February 26, 2018 (45:4 Md. R. 206)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-06-14"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective June 14, 2021 (48:12 Md. R. 474)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-08-21"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.04|F.">Regulation .04F</cite> amended effective August 21, 2023 (50:16 Md. R. 727)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-02-26"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.04|I.">Regulation .04I</cite> amended effective February 26, 2018 (45:4 Md. R. 206)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-08-21"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective February 26, 2018 (45:4 Md. R. 206); June 14, 2021 (48:12 Md. R. 474); August 21, 2023 (50:16 Md. R. 727)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-11-24"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.06|D.">Regulation .06D</cite>, F, G amended effective November 24, 2016 (43:23 Md. R. 1280)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-06-22"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.06|E.">Regulation .06E</cite>, F amended effective June 22, 2015 (42:12 Md. R. 763)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-06-22"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.06|G.">Regulation .06G</cite> adopted effective June 22, 2015 (42:12 Md. R. 763)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-08-21"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective June 14, 2021 (48:12 Md. R. 474); August 21, 2023 (50:16 Md. R. 727)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-02-26"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.07|C.">Regulation .07C</cite>, E amended effective February 26, 2018 (45:4 Md. R. 206)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-12-31"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.08">Regulation .08</cite> amended effective December 31, 2018 (45:26 Md. R. 1248)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-06-14"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.08|B.">Regulation .08B</cite> amended effective June 14, 2021 (48:12 Md. R. 474)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-06-14"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.09">Regulation .09</cite> amended effective June 22, 2015 (42:12 Md. R. 763); June 14, 2021 (48:12 Md. R. 474)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-08-21"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.09|B.">Regulation .09B</cite>, C amended effective November 24, 2016 (43:23 Md. R. 1280); February 26, 2018 (45:4 Md. R. 206); August 21, 2023 (50:16 Md. R. 727)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-08-12"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.09|C.">Regulation .09C</cite> amended effective August 12, 2019 (46:16 Md. R. 689)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-02-26"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.09|E.">Regulation .09E</cite> amended effective February 26, 2018 (45:4 Md. R. 206)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-11-24"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.09|G.">Regulation .09G</cite> adopted effective November 24, 2016 (43:23 Md. R. 1280)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-08-21"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.09|H.">Regulation .09H</cite> amended effective August 21, 2023 (50:16 Md. R. 727)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-06-14"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.09-1">Regulation .09-1</cite> amended effective June 14, 2021 (48:12 Md. R. 474)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-08-21"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.09-1C">Regulation .09-1C</cite>, E amended effective August 21, 2023 (50:16 Md. R. 727)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-02-26"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.09-1O">Regulation .09-1O</cite> repealed effective February 26, 2018 (45:4 Md. R. 206)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-02-26"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.10|B.">Regulation .10B</cite> amended effective February 26, 2018 (45:4 Md. R. 206)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-06-14"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.10|B.">Regulation .10B</cite>, C amended effective June 14, 2021 (48:12 Md. R. 474)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-10-28"><cite path="|13A|03|02|.12|B.">Regulation .12B</cite> amended effective February 26, 2018 (45:4 Md. R. 206); June 14, 2021 (48:12 Md. R. 474); October 28, 2024 (51:21 Md. R. 927)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
