<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Education Programs</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter sets forth additional requirements that a program shall meet as a private or public education program for individuals convicted under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|21-902">Transportation Article, §21-902, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and ordered to attend an education program.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <text>In this chapter, terms have the meanings set forth in <cite path="10.47.01.02">COMAR 10.47.01.02</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Application Process and Evaluation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The applicant shall complete an application on a form approved by the Administration and submit the application and documentation to indicate the applicant is in compliance with the requirements of this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>After the Administration receives the application the Administration shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Return the application if it is incomplete; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Arrange a site visit.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>After the site visit, the Administration shall</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Grant approval;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Grant approval with conditions; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Deny approval.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Program Requirements.</heading>
    <text>The program shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Comply with <cite path="|10.47.01">COMAR 10.47.01</cite> and <cite path="10.47.02.03">10.47.02.03</cite>;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>At minimum, offer six weekly 2-hour sessions for a total of 12 hours;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Have instructors approved by the Administration who are:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Instructors before October 1, 2002; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>At a minimum, certified as a Certified Supervised Counselor-Alcohol and Drug, as defined by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Ensure that staff is appropriately credentialed and privileged to teach the curriculum;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Teach the Administration's curriculum or an equivalent curriculum approved by the Administration, which covers:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Scope of drinking-driver problem;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Drinking driver patterns and characteristics;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The pharmacology of substance abuse;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The process of addiction to drugs and alcohol;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The relationship of substance use to crime, health, family, and other social problems; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Treatment resources; and</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Report to the court or probation agent as specified by the court order.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|47|05|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Denial, Probation, Intermediate Sanctions, Suspension, or Revocation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If an applicant or Program fails to comply with the applicable State and federal laws, rules, or regulations, the Director may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Deny approval to the applicant; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Take disciplinary action, such as:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Placing the program on probation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Suspending or revoking the certification of the program; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Imposing intermediate sanctions on the program.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>For purposes of <cite path="10|47|05|.05|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, intermediate sanctions include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A directed plan of correction, if the program is directed to take a specific action by a certain date;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A mandatory staffing pattern that is stricter than that required under the appropriate level of care in these regulations, if the Administration defines for the program the level of individual supervision;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Mandatory training, if the Administration identifies deficient areas in which training is needed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Expansion ban, if the Administration retains the authority to prohibit the program from obtaining additional sites, admitting individuals, or providing additional services at the site;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Imposition of an intensive monitoring protocol by the Administration; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Imposition of a temporary site monitor, if the Administration maintains an ongoing physical presence for the purpose of providing assistance and evaluating the extent of the program's corrective actions.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the Director proposes to deny approval to an applicant or to take disciplinary action against a program, the Director shall give written notice to the health officer or executive director of the program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>In the written notice under <cite path="10|47|05|.05|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, the Director shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The statutory and regulatory authority upon which the proposed action is based;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The facts supporting the alleged violation of law; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The applicant's or program's right to a hearing before final action under <cite path="10|47|05|.05|F.">§F of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Summary Suspension.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Under the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-226">State Government Article, §10-226(c)(2), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and if appropriate, after a predeprivation hearing, the Director may summarily order the suspension of the approval if the Administration finds that the public health, safety, or welfare imperatively requires emergency action.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Director shall notify the program in writing of the suspension, findings, and reasons that support the findings, and, if appropriate, the opportunity for a predeprivation hearing. The notice shall include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The proposed order for summary suspension which includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The statutory and regulatory authority upon which the order is based;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The facts supporting the alleged violations of law;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The facts supporting the belief that there is an imminent danger to the health, safety, and welfare of individuals; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>The program's right to appeal the summary suspension, if executed by the Director; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A show cause notice providing an opportunity for the program to show cause as to why the order may not be issued if the public health, safety, and welfare permits.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Director may suspend approval without prior notice and the opportunity to be heard if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Director determines that the health, welfare, and safety of the public imperatively requires immediate suspension;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Notice of an opportunity to be heard before the action is not feasible; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Administration provides the program with a post-deprivation hearing opportunity within 15 working days of the suspension.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Procedures for Hearings.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If the Director proposes to deny an approval or take disciplinary action against a program, the Director shall give the program written notice according to <cite path="10|47|05|.05|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Within 10 working days of receipt of the notice, the executive director or health officer may file a written request for a hearing with the Office of Administrative Hearings and send copies of the request to the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Director; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Administrative prosecutor.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the executive director or health officer does not file a request for a hearing within 10 working days of receipt of the notification, the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Program waives its right to request a hearing; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Director may implement the proposed action.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If a timely request for a hearing has been received, the Office of Administrative Hearings shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Notify the Director, the executive director or health officer, and administrative prosecutor of the date, time, and location of the hearing; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>In accordance with <cite path="|28.02.01">COMAR 28.02.01</cite>, hold a hearing and, unless the final decision is delegated to the Office of Administrative Hearings, render a proposed decision to the Director.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>After giving the parties the opportunity to file exceptions under the provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-216">State Government Article, §10-216, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the Director shall issue a final decision and send notice to the governing body or the health officer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A program may appeal any final decision from a contested case by following the provisions of Health-General Article, §2-207, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 10, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>In addition to disposing of a case by a hearing, the Director may dispose of a contested case by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Stipulation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Settlement;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Consent order;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Default;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Withdrawal;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Summary disposition; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Dismissal.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health-General Article, §§8-401 — 8-405 and 19-308, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-06-10">Effective date: June 10, 2002 (29:11 Md. R. 882)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-05-05" discontinuity="true">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|10.47.04">COMAR 10.47.04</cite> to <cite path="|10.47.05">10.47.05</cite> as an emergency provision effective April 1, 2008 (35:9 Md. R. 894); recodified permanently effective May 5, 2008 (35:9 Md. R. 898)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-05-05"><cite path="|10|47|05|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective April 1, 2008 (35:9 Md. R. 894); amended permanently effective May 5, 2008 (35:9 Md. R. 898)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-05-05"><cite path="|10|47|05|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective April 1, 2008 (35:9 Md. R. 894); amended permanently effective May 5, 2008 (35:9 Md. R. 898)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-05-05"><cite path="|10|47|05|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective April 1, 2008 (35:9 Md. R. 894); amended permanently effective May 5, 2008 (35:9 Md. R. 898)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
