<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>06</num>
  <heading>Substance Abuse Treatment Outcomes Partnerships — (S.T.O.P.) Fund</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter specifies the requirements for applying for funding from the Substance Abuse Treatment Outcomes Partnership Fund. This chapter establishes time lines and procedures for requests for partnership funding, guidelines that require programs to bill third-party insurers, and fund management including, but not limited to, authorization of distribution of money.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Department" means the Maryland Department of Health.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Eligible functions” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Transportation to and from treatment services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Treatment, prevention, or coordination staff;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Data sharing services among counties and other appropriate treatment providers;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Education or outreach programs and materials;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>In-community emergency behavioral health services or crisis stabilization units; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Behavioral health programs in schools.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Eligible population" means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Mothers of drug-addicted infants;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Parents of children in need of assistance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Hospital emergency room admittees;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Needy families receiving temporary cash assistance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Foster care children and parents;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Children in after-school programs and their parents, including children and parents in programs supported by the Maryland After-School Opportunity Fund;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Adolescents;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Parents subject to arrearages in child support payments;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Drug offenders under the supervision of the Division of Parole and Probation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Pretrial correctional inmates;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Prerelease correctional inmates;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>The general inmate population within county-managed correctional facilities;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>Parents of children entering out-of-home placements or at risk of entering out-of-home placements; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(n)</num>
          <text>Drug offenders under the supervision of the problem solving courts.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Jurisdiction" means Baltimore City or one of the 23 counties in Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Partnership funding" means money granted from the Substance Abuse Treatment Outcomes Partnership Fund.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Proposal" means a plan under this chapter to provide new or expanded substance abuse treatment services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Request for partnership funding” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A proposal, submitted by the governing bodies of one or more jurisdictions, to provide substance-related disorder treatment services to one or more eligible populations; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>To provide funding for eligible functions within the requesting jurisdiction or jurisdictions.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Task Force" means the Task Force to Study Increasing the Availability of Substance Abuse Programs.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Requests for Partnership Funding and Criteria for Awarding Funding.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Requests for partnership funding may be submitted to the Department by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The governing body of a jurisdiction or its designee; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The governing bodies of more than one jurisdiction or their designee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Proposals shall include the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Identification of one or more eligible populations per jurisdiction;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Eligible functions that will be funded under the plan;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A description of the plan to provide substance-related disorder services;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Identification of local providers able to provide these services;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A plan to reach the eligible populations using relevant means of contact;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Performance and outcome indicators to evaluate the program effectiveness including a description of the expected schedule and methods for measuring performance and outcome;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>A plan to bill third-party insurers;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>A prepared annual expenditure plan which reflects all anticipated income including partnership funding, local, third party, and cash revenue to the partnership program; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>A statement of the local cash match or local in-kind match, including but not limited to provision of space, staff, or services, that the applicant intends to commit to the effort.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Time Line. Requests for partnership funding shall be received by the Department by April 1 for the following fiscal year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Department shall consider the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Performance and outcome indicators specified;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The degree to which the proposal may reduce the need for other State or local public services or programs intended for the populations targeted by the proposal;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The extent to which the proposal incorporates the use of excess or otherwise available medical-related facilities, including vacant hospital beds;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>How the proposal fits into a balanced approach to the State’s variety of substance-related disorder needs and populations that serve different geographic areas of the State with partnership funding;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The extent to which the proposal is part of or consistent with a regional strategy for substance-related disorder treatment programs affecting adjoining jurisdictions; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Other factors consistent with Health-General Article, §8-6C-04, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Department may specify in a request for proposals the types of treatment services that are eligible for funding awards.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Fiscal Responsibility by Jurisdiction.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Department may award partnership funding that results in a county being responsible for less than 1/2 of the cost of the approved partnership funding after considering:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The financial hardship of the participating county;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Prior and current contributions of funds for substance abuse treatment programs made by the participating county; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Other relevant considerations considered appropriate by the Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A participating jurisdiction shall use partnership funding only to supplement levels of spending by the participating jurisdiction on drug treatment programs.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A participating jurisdiction may not use partnership funding to supplant spending by the participating jurisdiction on drug treatment programs.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A participating jurisdiction may use partnership funding to continue or expand funding for eligible functions if the participating jurisdiction began spending funds on eligible functions after October 1, 2010.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health-General Article, §§8-6C-01 — 8-6C-04, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-04-30">Regulations <cite path="|10|47|06|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|47|06|.04">.04</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective January 30, 2001 (28:3 Md. R. 203); adopted permanently effective April 30, 2001 (28:8 Md. R. 762)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-06-10" discontinuity="true">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|10.47.03">COMAR 10.47.03</cite> to <cite path="|10.47.05">10.47.05</cite> effective June 10, 2002 (29:11 Md. R. 882)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-05-05" discontinuity="true">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|10.47.05">10.47.05</cite> to <cite path="|10.47.06">10.47.06</cite> as an emergency provision effective April 1, 2008 (35:9 Md. R. 894); recodified permanently effective May 5, 2008 (35:9 Md. R. 898)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-08-15"><cite path="|10|47|06|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective August 15, 2016 (43:16 Md. R. 901)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-08-15"><cite path="|10|47|06|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective August 15, 2016 (43:16 Md. R. 901)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-08-15"><cite path="|10|47|06|.04|D.">Regulation .04D</cite> adopted effective August 15, 2016 (43:16 Md. R. 901)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
