<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>04</num>
  <heading>Hazardous Substances</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose and Scope — Products That Contain Mercury.</heading>
    <text>This chapter establishes limitations on the sale of specified products that contain mercury.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions — Products That Contain Mercury.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Manufacturer" means a person that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Produces a product;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For a multicomponent product, produces or assembles the final product; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Serves as an importer or domestic distributor of a product produced outside of the United States.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Marketer" means a person who manufactures, assembles, sells, distributes, affixes a brand name or private label to, or licenses the use of a brand name on a fever thermometer containing mercury.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Mercury-added product" means any of the following products if containing elemental mercury or a mercury compound that has been added to the product for any reason:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Dyes or pigments;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Electric switches;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Fluorescent lamps; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Thermostats.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Motor vehicle" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|11-135">Transportation Article, §11-135, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="26|02|04|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Prohibition on the Sale of Certain Products.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Fever Thermometers Containing Mercury.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="26|02|04|.03|A.|(2)">§A(2) of this regulation</cite>, a marketer may not sell or provide a fever thermometer containing mercury to a consumer except by prescription.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The prohibition of <cite path="26|02|04|.03|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite> does not apply to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A fever thermometer sold or provided to be used in hospitals or other places where medical services are provided by medical service professionals; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A digital thermometer using mercury-added button cell batteries.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Mercury-Added Products.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>This regulation does not apply to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Prescription drugs;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Any substance regulated by the federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Biological products regulated by the federal Food and Drug Administration under the federal Public Health Service Act;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Medical equipment not intended for use by nonmedical personnel; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Products that contain mercury-added products that are labeled in accordance with this regulation, except as provided in <cite path="|26|02|04|.04|B.|(4)|(b)">Regulation .04B(4)(b) of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Unlabeled Mercury-Added Products. Beginning April 1, 2006:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A manufacturer or wholesaler may not sell a mercury-added product at retail in Maryland or to a retailer in Maryland unless the product is labeled in accordance with <cite path="|26|02|04|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A retailer may not knowingly sell a new mercury-added product in Maryland unless the product is labeled in accordance with <cite path="|26|02|04|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The manufacturer of a mercury-added product manufactured on or after January 1, 2006 is responsible for affixing the label required by <cite path="26|02|04|.03|B.|(2)">§B(2) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Motor Vehicles.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The manufacturer of a motor vehicle may meet the labeling requirements of <cite path="26|02|04|.03|B.|(2)">§B(2) of this regulation</cite> by placing the label on the doorpost of a new vehicle.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A person who, in servicing a motor vehicle, adds a mercury-added product to the vehicle, shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Make any necessary revisions to the label on the doorpost of the vehicle provided by the manufacturer under <cite path="26|02|04|.03|B.|(4)|(a)">§B(4)(a) of this regulation</cite>; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Add a label meeting the requirements of <cite path="26|02|04|.03|B.|(2)">§B(2) of this regulation</cite> to the doorpost of the vehicle if the vehicle did not previously have such a label.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="26|02|04|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Labeling Standards for Mercury-Added Products.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A mercury-added product required to be labeled under <cite path="|26|02|04|.03|B.">Regulation .03B of this chapter</cite> shall either:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Have a label that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Clearly informs the purchaser or consumer that:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Mercury is present in the product; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The product shall be managed in accordance with federal and State environmental laws to minimize the release of mercury to the environment; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Meets another state's label requirements for mercury-added products; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Satisfy the conditions for an exemption under <cite path="26|02|04|.04|B.|(2)|(a)">§B(2)(a) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Label Standards.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The text of a label required under <cite path="26|02|04|.04|A.|(1)|(a)">§A(1)(a) of this regulation</cite>:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Shall be legible and clearly presented;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>May be any single, clear, easy-to-read type style;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Shall have not more than 39 characters per inch;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Shall have at least 0.5 point leading, that is, space between 2 lines of text;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>May not have letters that touch; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Shall use a type size not smaller than 8-point type for the notice that mercury is present in the product, and not smaller than 6-point type for the remainder of the message.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Location of the Label.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A label required under <cite path="26|02|04|.04|A.|(1)|(a)">§A(1)(a) of this regulation</cite> shall be affixed on the surface of the mercury-added product, unless:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The physical form of the product prevents it from being directly labeled;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The size of the product's surface is too small to accommodate the label, taking into account other requirements concerning the use of the product's surface, such as other required labels;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Attachment of the label to the surface of the product would interfere with the function of the product; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>The person required to affix the label demonstrates, to the Secretary's satisfaction, that it is not otherwise feasible to affix the label to the surface of the product.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If, as provided in <cite path="26|02|04|.04|B.|(2)|(a)">§B(2)(a) of this regulation</cite>, the label is not attached to the surface of the mercury-added product, the label shall be:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Attached to packaging of the product that will be seen by the product's purchaser or user; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Provided as a package insert if the label would cover more than 60 percent of the total surface area of the product's packaging available to carry labeling.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Size of the Label. A label under <cite path="26|02|04|.04|A.|(1)|(a)">§A(1)(a) of this regulation</cite> shall be of sufficient size to present the information required by <cite path="26|02|04|.04|A.|(1)|(a)">§A(1)(a) of this regulation</cite> while meeting the standards of <cite path="26|02|04|.04|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Requirements for Additional Labels.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If a label attached to the surface of a mercury-added product is not visible to a prospective purchaser, and the mercury-added product is not contained within another product, a second label meeting the requirements of §§A and B(1) of this regulation shall be:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Attached to packaging of the product that will be seen by the product's purchaser; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Provided as a package insert if the label would cover more than 60 percent of the total surface area of the product's packaging available to carry labeling.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If, as provided in <cite path="26|02|04|.04|B.|(2)|(a)">§B(2)(a) of this regulation</cite>, the label is not attached to the surface of the mercury-added product, and the mercury-added product is used as a component in the manufacture of another product, the product that contains the mercury-added product as a component shall be labeled in accordance with <cite path="26|02|04|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Environmental Article, §§6-905, 6-905.1, and 6-905.3, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-01-01">Effective date: January 1, 2007 (33:26 Md. R. 1999)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
