<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>04</num>
  <heading>Rules Compliance Violations</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>State Safety Oversight Agency Investigative Authority.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>To carry out this title the MDOT Deputy Secretary of Operations or designee, may administer an oath, certify an official act, take or cause to be taken a deposition of a witness, or issue a subpoena for the attendance of a witness to testify and/or produce papers, books, documents, records, and testimony.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If a person fails to comply with a lawfully issued subpoena, on application of the MDOT Deputy Secretary of Operations or designee in a contempt proceeding, a court of competent jurisdiction may compel the person to comply.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Event/Threshold.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The SSOA will investigate and take actions in accordance with <cite path="11.24.02.03">COMAR 11.24.02.03</cite> to compel compliance by the RTA with any Corrective Action Plan or order stemming from the investigation of accidents, incidents, and occurrences as listed in Appendix A to 49 CFR 674 — Notification and Reporting of Accidents, Incidents, and Occurrences.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Nothing in this regulation shall be deemed to alter a rail transit vehicle or high-rail vehicle operator’s or any safety-sensitive employee’s duty to comply with any other provisions of the RTA concerning rail safety.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Suspension of Safety-Sensitive Certification.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An employee may have his or her safety-sensitive certification suspended by the SSOA in accordance with to the following standards:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In the case of a single incident (as defined in 49 CFR §674.7) that is deemed to be a safety violation, the employee may have his or her safety-sensitive certification suspended for up to 1 month.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In the case of two separate incidents that occurred within 24 months of each other, the employee may have his or her safety-sensitive certification suspended for up to 6 months.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>In the case of three separate incidents that occurred within 36 months of each other, the employee may have his or her safety-sensitive certification suspended for up to 1 year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>In the case of four separate incidents that occurred within 36 months of each other, the employee may have his or her safety-sensitive certification suspended indefinitely.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If a safety violation is egregious or results in bodily injury or death, the suspension period may be raised to a higher level.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>If an employee is not on full duty at the time a suspension is to be issued, the suspension period will commence the first day the employee would otherwise return to full duty.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The actions described in this section do not replace or otherwise affect any disciplinary action that may be taken against an employee by the RTA about a safety violation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Reinstatement of Safety-Sensitive Eligibility.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An employee whose safety-sensitive certification has been suspended may be eligible for reinstatement prior to the expiration of the initial period of suspension if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The suspension imposed is for a period of 1 year or less;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The suspension was for reasons other than noncompliance with the drug and alcohol policy;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The employee has been evaluated by a qualified supervisor of the specific safety-sensitive position and determined to have received adequate remedial training;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The employee has successfully completed any mandatory training program or retraining, deemed necessary by the RTA prior to return to service; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>At least one half of the imposed period of suspension has elapsed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An employee requesting reinstatement, must do so formally in writing to the MDOT Deputy Secretary of Operations, or designee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Deputy Secretary of Operations or designee will conduct an evaluation and advise the employee of the determination within 30 calendar days.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Administrative Hearing.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An employee wishing to file an appeal must notify the SSOA within 15 calendar days of receiving the notice of the suspension, to request an administrative hearing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>When a suspension is contested, the SSOA will forward the matter to Maryland Office of Administrative Hearings (OAH) to set in for a hearing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The hearing will be conducted in accordance with Title 28 of the Code of Maryland Regulations (<cite path="|28.02.01">COMAR 28.02.01</cite>).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The administrative law judge’s decision is the final order of the MDOT Deputy Secretary of Policy, Planning, and Enterprise Services.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|2-102">2-102</cite>(c)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|5">5</cite>) and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|7-203">7-203</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland;<br/>49 U.S.C. §5329 and 49 CFR Part 674</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-03-26">Effective date: March 26, 2018 (45:6 Md. R. 321)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
