<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Breast Implantation</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Breast implantation" means both:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Breast augmentation, the procedure of surgically inserting breast implants beneath a woman's natural breasts; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The type of breast reconstruction that involves surgically inserting a breast implant in the chest area of a woman who has had a mastectomy.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Department" means the Maryland Department of Health.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Physician" means an individual who is authorized under the Medical Practice Act to practice medicine in Maryland and who performs breast implantation surgery in Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Requirements for the Maryland Department of Health.</heading>
    <text>The Department shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Provide a standardized written summary in layperson's language that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Contains the information on breast implantation generally contained in the package inserts for breast implants, and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Discloses side effects, warnings, and cautions for a breast implantation operation;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Update as necessary the standardized written summary;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Provide a statement indicating acknowledgment of receipt of the standardized written summary to be signed by the patient;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Provide a waiver form describing the conditions under which the usual time requirements of the summary distribution may be waived; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Distribute copies of the standardized written summary, the acknowledgment of receipt statement, and the 5-day waiver form to all hospitals, clinics, other facilities, and physicians' offices where breast implantation is performed.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Requirements for Physicians.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The standardized written summary provided by the Department shall be provided to the woman by the physician as soon as possible but not later than 5 days before a physician performs a breast implantation operation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The physician may provide the standardized written summary less than 5 days before performing breast reconstruction with breast implants only when the following conditions have been met:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The woman's breast cancer surgery is scheduled to take place within 5 days of the time she initially consults with a breast cancer surgeon;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The woman decides to have breast implant reconstruction at the same time as the breast cancer surgery;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>At the time of the woman's initial visit with the physician who will perform the breast implant reconstruction, that physician:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Gives the woman the Department's standardized written summary;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has the patient sign the statement provided by the Department acknowledging receipt of the summary; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Informs the woman of the relative advantages and disadvantages of having breast implant reconstruction at the same time as cancer treatment;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The woman decides to waive the 5-day minimum waiting period and signs the waiver provided by the Department; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A copy of this signed waiver, along with a copy of the signed acknowledgment of receipt form, is placed in the patient's medical record which is used by the physician.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A physician may not perform breast implantation until a patient has been given the standardized written summary described in <cite path="|10|12|05|.02|A.">Regulation .02A of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A physician who provides a patient with the written summary required under these regulations shall have:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The patient sign a statement provided by the Department acknowledging receipt of the summary; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A copy of the signed acknowledgment pursuant to §D(1), of this regulation, placed in the patient's medical record which is used by the physician.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>This regulation is supplemental and additional to any other requirements established by other laws upon a physician and may not be regarded as in derogation or substitution of any requirements now existing upon a physician, such as the need to obtain informed consent for treatment.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health-General Article, §20-114, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-09-03">Effective date: September 3, 1990 (17:17 Md. R. 2080)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
