<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>07</num>
  <heading>Alcohol and Drug Counselors — Requirements for Certification and Licensure</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter applies to alcohol and drug counselors and alcohol and drug trainees in Maryland.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Accredited educational institution" means a Board-approved college or university that is accredited by a national or regional accrediting body recognized by the Council on Post-Secondary Accreditation or through one of the following bodies recognized by the U.S. Department of Education:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools — the Commission on Higher Education;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The New England Association of Schools and Colleges;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The North Central Association of Schools and Colleges;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Northwest Association of Schools and of Colleges and Universities;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The Southern Association of Colleges and Schools; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The Western Association of Colleges and Schools.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Appraisal" means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Selecting, administering, scoring, and interpreting instruments designed to assess an individual’s aptitudes, attitudes, abilities, achievements, interests, and personal characteristics; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Using nonstandardized methods and techniques for understanding human behavior in relation to coping with, adapting to, or changing life situations.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Approved alcohol and drug counselor supervisor" means a Board-approved:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Licensed clinical alcohol and drug counselor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Health-care provider:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Licensed under the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>With 3 years of documented experience in alcohol and drug counseling;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Certified professional counselor-alcohol and drug;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Certified associate counselor-alcohol and drug with 3 years of documented experience in alcohol and drug counseling;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Licensed clinical professional counselor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Licensed clinical marriage and family therapist; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Licensed clinical professional art therapist.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Biopsychosocial evaluation" means a comprehensive assessment of the patient addressing the following areas:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Physical health;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Employment or financial support;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Drug and alcohol use;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Treatment history;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Legal history;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Familial and social relationships;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Educational background; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Mental health.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Case management" means the provision of services which assist participants in gaining access to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The full range of substance abuse services; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Any additional needed medical, social, financial assistance, counseling, educational, housing services.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Clinical supervision" means that the supervisor:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Controls the supervisees’ work, and provides face-to-face or immediately available supervision;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Evaluates completed work for technical soundness, appropriateness, and conformity to policy and requirements; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Confirms that all diagnoses are clinically supported by appropriate criteria, as:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Defined in the current editions of the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM) or the International Classification of Diseases and Related Health Problems (ICD); and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Documented by signature and credentials.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Close supervision" means that the supervisor:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Closely controls the supervisees’ work, and provides direct, face-to-face, or on-site supervision;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Maintains control through review of case management and progress notes, treatment plan reviews, and other documentation as appropriate;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Evaluates completed work for accuracy, detail, and adherence to instructions and established procedures; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Reviews and approves content for all diagnostic impressions and new treatment plans, as documented by signature and credentials.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Co-occurring disorders (CODs)" means the occurrence in any individual, simultaneously or sequentially, of two or more somatic or behavioral health disorders which may imply an interaction between the disorders that affect the course and prognosis of each diagnosis.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Diagnosis" means the identification of psychological problems, emotional, or mental disorders by a licensed clinician, using specified terms and criteria identified in the current editions of the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM); or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>International Classification of Diseases and Related Health Problems (ICD).</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Direct clinical counseling services" means the provision of face-to-face clinical professional counseling services to clients and their significant others that include, but are not limited to the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Individual counseling;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Group counseling;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Family counseling;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Couples counseling;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Evaluation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Intake or Assessment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Diagnosis;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Treatment planning with a client; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Crisis management or intervention.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Direct supervision" means supervision provided by a supervisor who is present on the premises where services are provided, and is available for consultation within the treatment area.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Face-to-Face.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Face-to-face" means in the physical presence of an individual or using video conferencing which allows individuals to hear and see each other in synchronous points of time.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Face-to-face" does not include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Telephone supervision; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Internet communication that does not involve synchronous video conferencing, such as instant messaging services and social networking sites.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>"Health and human services counseling field" means a specific degree program with a counseling emphasis, including but not limited to the following areas:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Addictions counseling, including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Alcohol and drug counseling;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Substance abuse counseling; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Chemical dependence counseling;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Counseling practiced under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Professional counseling;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Marriage and family therapy; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Art therapy;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Practice areas of other mental health care providers, including, but not limited to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Psychiatry;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Psychology;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Social work; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Psychiatric nursing;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Other academic concentrations in the health and human services field, including, but not limited to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Human services;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Behavioral health or behavioral sciences;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Rehabilitation counseling;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Counselor education;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Counseling psychology; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Human development.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>"Immediately available supervision" means supervision provided by a supervisor who is instantly available:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In person;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>By telephone or other electronic means; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>By designation of one or more supervisors in the absence of the supervisor of record.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>"Indirect clinical counseling services" means all case management and professional development activities related to the provision of clinical professional counseling services to a client that include but are not limited to the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Referral;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Intake or assessment by telephone or other means when client is not face-to-face;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Receiving individual and group supervision on-site or at a university;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Consultation with other professionals;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Treatment planning with other professionals;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Case staffing;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Staff meetings;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Related trainings and seminars;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Record keeping;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Report writing;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Case note taking;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>Providing clinical training;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>Telephone triage;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(n)</num>
          <text>Case management;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(o)</num>
          <text>Program development; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(p)</num>
          <text>Other clinical professional counselor administrative duties as required by the setting in which the clinical hours are accrued.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>"Licensed graduate alcohol and drug counselor" means an individual approved by the Board to practice graduate alcohol and drug counseling under the supervision of an approved alcohol and drug counselor supervisor while fulfilling the supervised clinical experience for licensure under:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-302">Health Occupations Article, §17-302(e), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text><cite path="|10|58|07|.04">Regulation .04</cite> of this chapter.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>"Moderate supervision" means that the supervisor:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Controls the supervisee’s work and provides face-to-face or immediately available supervision;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Ensures that completed work and methods used are technically accurate and in compliance with instructions or established procedures;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Provides more intense review for difficult assignments, if the supervisee has not previously performed similar assignments; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Reviews and approves content for all diagnostic impressions and new treatment plans, as documented by signature and credentials.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>Ongoing Process of Supervision.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Ongoing process of supervision" means that the supervisor is available to provide support for the supervisee’s day-to-day practice of alcohol and drug counseling, throughout the course of the supervisee’s scheduled work hours;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Ongoing process of supervision" includes close, moderate, or clinical supervision of an individual or a group.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>"On-site supervision" means supervision provided by a supervisor who is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Physically present in the facility where patient or client services are rendered; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Able to respond in person without delay.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>Participating in the development of diagnostic impressions.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Participating in the development of diagnostic impressions" means gathering information to support a diagnosis through:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Screening and assessment activities;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Observations of signs and symptoms;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Reports of behaviors;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Collateral information acquired with the appropriate release; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>The identification of specific disorders to be ruled out by the diagnosing clinician.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Participating in the development of diagnostic impressions" does not include diagnosis.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>"Practice clinical alcohol and drug counseling" means to engage professionally and for compensation in alcohol and drug counseling and appraisal activities by providing services for individuals, couples, families and groups involving:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The application of counseling principles; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Methods in the diagnosis, prevention, treatment, and amelioration of psychological problems, emotional conditions, or mental conditions.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>"Psychotherapy" means providing clinical services which involve:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The professional application of psychotherapy and counseling theories and methods, including but not limited to psychodynamic, cognitive, behavioral, humanistic, systems theories, or trauma informed care to assist the client in:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Improving functioning;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Obtaining symptom relief;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Preventing psychosocial dysfunction;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Changing personality; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Maintaining improved functioning; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Situations in which the principal discourse involves, but is not limited to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Diagnosis of psychopathology based on standard diagnostic criteria;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Psychotherapeutic treatment of mental disorders, emotional disorders, and adjustment reactions utilizing clinically appropriate treatment modalities;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Childhood trauma and abuse;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Identifying and changing self-defeating patterns of behaving, thinking, feeling, believing, or interacting with others in systems;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Developmental issues;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Personality development; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Problems related to disorders of thinking, emotional suffering, addictions, behavior, or interpersonal dysfunctions.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>"Relative" means an individual connected to another by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Blood;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Marriage;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Guardianship; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Domestic partnership.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(24)</num>
        <text>"SBIRT" means Screening, Brief Intervention, and Referral to Treatment, including the following practices:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Screening which quickly assesses the severity of substance use and identifies the appropriate level of treatment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Brief intervention which focuses on increasing insight and awareness regarding substance use and motivation toward behavioral change; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Referral to treatment which provides individuals identified as needing more extensive treatment with access to specialty care.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(25)</num>
        <text>"Scope of competence" means that area within which the individual is proficient to practice based on:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Education;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Training;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Supervised clinical experience; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Professional credentials.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(26)</num>
        <text>"Substance use disorders (SUDs)" means any problematic pattern of substance use leading to clinically significant impairment or distress, which is diagnosed using specified terms and criteria identified in the current editions of the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM); or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>International Classification of Diseases and Related Health Problems (ICD).</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(27)</num>
        <text>"Supervised clinical experience in alcohol and drug counseling" means alcohol and drug counseling services provided under the close or moderate supervision of an approved licensed or certified alcohol and drug counselor supervisor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(28)</num>
        <text>"Supervisee" means any of the following who obtains the supervised clinical experience required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-302">Health Occupations Article, §17-302, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A licensed graduate alcohol and drug counselor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A certified associate counselor-alcohol and drug;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A certified supervised counselor-alcohol and drug; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>An alcohol and drug trainee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(29)</num>
        <text>Supervision.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Supervision" means a formalized professional relationship between a supervisor and supervisee that involves:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Directing, guiding, monitoring, instructing, and evaluating the supervisee’s alcohol and drug counseling practice throughout an ongoing process of supervision; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Utilizes close, moderate, or clinical levels of supervision.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Supervision" includes an acceptance of direct responsibility for the patient services rendered by the supervisee, including continuous availability to the supervisee:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>In person;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Through written instructions;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>By telephone or other electronic means; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>By designation of one or more supervisors in the absence of the supervisor of record as defined in Regulations <cite path="|10|58|07|.13">.13</cite>—<cite path="|10|58|07|.16">.16</cite> of this chapter.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(30)</num>
        <text>"Trauma informed care" means including in treatment an approach that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Engages people with histories of physical, sexual, emotional, or mental trauma in a manner that recognizes the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Presence of a trauma history;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Consequences of the trauma; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Neurological, biological, psychological, and social effects of trauma for the affected individual; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Addresses the vulnerabilities or triggers for these individuals while minimizing any harm.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(31)</num>
        <text>"Under the supervision of an approved alcohol and drug counselor supervisor" means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Engaging in an ongoing process that includes direct, on-site, face-to-face individual or group meetings focused on quality of delivery of alcohol and drug counseling services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Monitoring the performance of a:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Licensed graduate alcohol and drug counselor</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Certified associate counselor-alcohol and drug;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Certified supervised counselor-alcohol and drug; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Alcohol and drug trainee;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Providing documented and direct consultation, guidance, and instruction with respect to clinical skill and competency; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Improving counseling skills for a minimum of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>1 documented hour for each 40-hour work week; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Not less than 2 documented hours per month for less than a 40-hour work week.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(32)</num>
        <text>"Written contract for supervision" means a Board-approved agreement between the supervisee and approved alcohol and drug supervisor that is initiated before beginning supervision and that details the scope of supervision and includes at a minimum the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Name and credentials of the supervisor and the supervisee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Primary purpose, goals, and objectives of the supervision process;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Details of provisions, including frequency, format, and case or chart review;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Methods of documentation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Duties and responsibilities of the supervisor and the supervisee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Procedural considerations in the case of the supervisor’s absence; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Information regarding the supervisor’s scope of competence.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|58|07|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Application Process for Certification, Licensure, and Trainee Status.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In order to obtain a certificate or license or to be eligible for trainee status, an applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Complete and return the Board-approved application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Submit an official transcript from an accredited educational institution indicating the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Completion of the highest degree attained; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Course work required for:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Licensure;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Certification; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Trainee status;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Pay all applicable fees set forth in <cite path="|10.58.02">COMAR 10.58.02</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Submit to a criminal history background check in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-501">Health Occupations Article, §17-501</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Be of good moral character; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Be at least 18 years old.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Applications shall be acted upon as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within 30 days after receipt of an application, the Board shall determine whether the application is complete;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the Board determines that the application is not complete, the Board shall send a notice of deficiency to the applicant;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Upon receipt of the notice, the applicant shall correct the deficiency within 90 days, or other period specified in the notice;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the applicant fails to correct the deficiency within the required period, the application may lapse and the applicant shall be required to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Submit a new application; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Pay the nonrefundable fee set forth in <cite path="|10.58.02">COMAR 10.58.02</cite>;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If the Board determines that an applicant is eligible to take the required examinations, the Board shall send a notice of approval to the applicant;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Upon receipt of the approval notice, the applicant shall have 1 year from the date of the notice to take the examinations; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>If the applicant fails to take the examinations within 1 year from the date of the approval notice, the requirements set forth under <cite path="10|58|07|.03|B.|(4)">§B(4) of this regulation</cite> shall apply.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|58|07|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Licensed Graduate Alcohol and Drug Counselors.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Scope of Practice. The scope of practice for a licensed graduate alcohol and drug counselor includes the following activities to be performed under the clinical supervision of an approved alcohol and drug counselor supervisor:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Clinical evaluation, including screening, assessment, and diagnosis for mental health disorders;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Treatment planning for mental health disorders, including initial, ongoing, continuity of care, discharge, and planning for relapse prevention;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Referral;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Service coordination and case management;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Counseling, therapy, and trauma informed care with individuals, couples, families and groups;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Client, family, and community education;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Documentation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Professional and ethical responsibilities.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Licensure. To qualify for licensure as a graduate alcohol and drug counselor, an applicant shall have:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Completed one of the following from an accredited educational institution:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A master’s degree in a health and human services counseling field with:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A minimum of 60 graduate semester credit hours; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>90 graduate quarter credit hours;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A doctoral degree in a health and human services counseling field with:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A minimum of 90 graduate semester credit hours; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>135 graduate quarter credit hours; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A master’s degree and have completed a program of studies determined by the Board to be substantially equivalent in subject matter with a minimum of 60 credit hours in counseling, including the required alcohol and drug course work for the license, as specified in §B(2) and (4) of this regulation;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Completed a minimum of 39 semester credit hours or 65 quarter credit hours in alcohol and drug counselor training from an accredited educational institution including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>3 semester credit hours or 5 quarter credit hours of course work in each of the following course content areas:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Pharmacology;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Group counseling;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Individual counseling;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Addictions treatment delivery;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Ethics that include alcohol and drug counseling issues; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Abnormal psychology; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Any three of the following 3 semester credit hours or 5 quarter credit hours of course work in each of the following course content areas:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Human development;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Theories of counseling;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Treatment of co-occurring disorders;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Topics in substance-related and addictive disorders; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Family counseling;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Completed one of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An internship in alcohol and drug counseling that totals 6 semester credit hours or 10 quarter credit hours; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A minimum of 1,000 hours of alcohol and drug counseling work completed as a certified associate counselor-alcohol and drug, a certified supervised counselor-alcohol and drug, or an alcohol and drug trainee under and verified by an approved alcohol and drug counselor supervisor;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Completed a minimum of 3 graduate semester credit hours or 5 quarter credit hours in each of the following course content areas:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Diagnosis and psychopathology; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Psychotherapy and treatment of mental and emotional disorders;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Achieved a passing score on:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A national alcohol and drug counselor examination approved by the Board;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An examination of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text><cite path="|10.58">COMAR 10.58</cite>;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Met all of the requirements set forth under <cite path="|10|58|07|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Complied with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The code of ethics as set forth in <cite path="|10.58.03">COMAR 10.58.03</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Licensed graduate alcohol and drug counselors shall have available for inspection a professional disclosure statement, as described in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-507">Health Occupations Article, §17-507, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Clearly states that the counseling services are provided under supervision; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provides the name, title, and credentials of the supervisor of record, including the supervisor’s address and contact information.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Reexamination. An applicant who fails an examination for licensure:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>May retake the exam if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>It is within the time frame set by the applicable testing authority; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A waiver is approved by the Board to extend the testing deadline upon proof of exceptional circumstances; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shall be required to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Submit a new application; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Pay the nonrefundable fee set forth in <cite path="|10.58.02">COMAR 10.58.02</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Board shall act upon applications as set forth under <cite path="|10|58|07|.03|B.">Regulation .03B of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A licensed graduate alcohol and drug counselor may not:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Practice independently; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide supervision.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Expiration and Extension.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The graduate alcohol and drug counselor license expires 2 years after the date issued.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the graduate alcohol and drug counselor licensee is unable to accumulate the required clinical hours for licensure as a clinical alcohol and drug counselor in 2 years, the graduate alcohol and drug counselor may apply on a Board-approved form for a 2-year extension before the current license as a graduate alcohol and drug counselor expires, up to a maximum of 6 years, except as provided in <cite path="10|58|07|.04|G.|(4)">§G(4) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>For the graduate alcohol and drug counselor who has been granted a 2-year extension, CEUs are not required for the first 2-year extension. Subsequent extensions approved by the Board shall be subject to the continuing education requirements in <cite path="|10.58.05">COMAR 10.58.05</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A graduate alcohol and drug counselor shall submit a written request for an extension beyond the 6-year maximum, which the Board may grant in certain circumstances.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Reinstatement.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within 5 calendar years after the license renewal date, the Board may reinstate the license of a licensed graduate alcohol and drug counselor otherwise entitled to reinstatement under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-505">Health Occupations Article, §17-505(b), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, whose license was not renewed for any reason, if the licensee:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Completes the required CEUs as set forth under <cite path="|10.58.05">COMAR 10.58.05</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Meets the current licensure requirements; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Pays the reinstatement fee as set forth under <cite path="|10.58.02">COMAR 10.58.02</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>CEUs which are acquired in order to reinstate under <cite path="10.58.05.05">COMAR 10.58.05.05</cite> and .06 may be credited only once and may not be credited for any future renewals.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>For any licensed graduate alcohol and drug counselor whose license has expired more than 5 calendar years before the request for reinstatement, a new application for licensure shall be completed and the current licensure requirements shall be met.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>An individual who fails to reinstate licensure is not authorized to and may not practice clinical alcohol and drug counseling.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Inactive Status.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-505">Health Occupations Article, §17-505, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, a request to transfer a license to inactive status shall be granted upon receipt of the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Completed Board-approved application; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Payment of all applicable fees set forth in <cite path="|10.58.02">COMAR 10.58.02</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An individual may apply for inactive status only if the individual’s license is still active at the time application for inactive status is made.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An individual on inactive status is not authorized to practice graduate alcohol and drug counseling.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Within 5 calendar years after being placed on inactive status, an individual on inactive status seeking to be reinstated to active status shall be required, as a condition of reinstatement, to submit proof of having completed the CEU requirements as set forth under <cite path="|10.58.05">COMAR 10.58.05</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If an individual on inactive status seeks to be reinstated beyond the required 5-year period and the conditions set forth under <cite path="10|58|07|.04|I.|(4)">§I(4) of this regulation</cite>, the individual shall be required to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Submit a new application;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Meet the current licensure requirements; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Pay the nonrefundable fee set forth in <cite path="|10.58.02">COMAR 10.58.02</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Licensed Clinical Alcohol and Drug Counselors.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Scope of Practice. The scope of practice of a licensed clinical alcohol and drug counselor includes the following activities:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Clinical evaluation, including screening, assessment, and diagnosis for mental health disorders;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Treatment planning for mental health and substance use disorders, including initial, ongoing, continuity of care, discharge, and planning for relapse prevention;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Referral;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Service coordination and case management;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Counseling, therapy, and trauma-informed care with individuals, couples, families, and groups;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Client, family, and community education;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Documentation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Professional and ethical responsibilities; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Supervisory responsibilities for all categories of licensed and certified alcohol and drug counselors or trainees.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Licensure. To qualify for licensure as a clinical alcohol and drug counselor, the applicant shall have:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Completed one of the following from an accredited educational institution:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A master’s degree in a health and human services counseling field with:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A minimum of 60 graduate semester credit hours; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>90 quarter credit hours;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A doctoral degree in a health and human services counseling field with:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A minimum of 90 graduate semester credit hours; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>135 graduate quarter credit hours; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A master’s degree and have completed a program of studies determined by the Board to be substantially equivalent in subject matter with a minimum of 60 credit hours in counseling, including the required alcohol and drug course work for the license, as specified in §B(2) and (4) of this regulation;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Completed a minimum of 39 semester credit hours or 65 quarter credit hours in alcohol and drug counselor training from an accredited educational institution with at least 3 semester credit hours or 5 quarter credit hours of course work in each of the following course content areas:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Pharmacology;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Group counseling;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Individual counseling;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Addictions treatment delivery;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Ethics that include alcohol and drug counseling issues;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Human development;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Abnormal psychology;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Theories of counseling;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Treatment of co-occurring disorders;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Topics in substance-related and addictive disorders; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Family counseling;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Completed one of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An internship in alcohol and drug counseling that totals 6 semester credit hours or 10 quarter credit hours; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A minimum of 1,000 hours of alcohol and drug counseling work completed as a licensed graduate alcohol and drug counselor, a certified associate counselor-alcohol and drug, a certified supervised counselor-alcohol and drug, or an alcohol and drug trainee under and verified by an approved alcohol and drug counselor supervisor;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Completed a minimum of 3 graduate semester credit hours or 5 quarter credit hours in each of the following content areas:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Diagnosis and psychopathology; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Psychotherapy and treatment of mental and emotional disorders;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Completed a minimum of 2 years and 2,000 hours of supervised clinical experience in alcohol and drug counseling:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Obtained  after the awarding of a master’s or doctoral degree;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>As a supervisee, as defined under <cite path="|10|58|07|.02|B.">Regulation .02B of this chapter</cite>, under an approved alcohol and drug counselor supervisor; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Of which a minimum of 1,500 hours shall be direct clinical counseling services, including 100 hours of clinical supervision, of which:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A minimum of 50 hours shall be individual face-to-face clinical supervision; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A maximum of 50 hours may be face-to-face group clinical supervision;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Achieved a passing score on:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A national alcohol and drug counselor examination approved by the Board; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An examination of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text><cite path="|10.58">COMAR 10.58</cite>;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Met all of the requirements set forth under <cite path="|10|58|07|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Complied with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The code of ethics as set forth in <cite path="|10.58.03">COMAR 10.58.03</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Renewal.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To renew clinical alcohol and drug counselor licensure, the applicant, before the current license expiration, shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Complete a Board-approved renewal application;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Pay all applicable fees set forth in <cite path="|10.58.02">COMAR 10.58.02</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Attest to completion of continuing education activities as specified in <cite path="10.58.05.05">COMAR 10.58.05.05</cite> and .06.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A licensed clinical alcohol and drug counselor shall comply with the renewal requirements as provided in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17">Health Occupations Article, §17</cite>–504, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An individual who fails to renew licensure is not authorized to and may not practice clinical alcohol and drug counseling.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Reinstatement. The Board may reinstate the license of a licensed clinical alcohol and drug counselor as set forth under <cite path="|10|58|07|.04|H.">Regulation .04H of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Inactive Status. A licensed clinical alcohol and drug counselor may request inactive status as set forth under <cite path="|10|58|07|.04|I.">Regulation .04I of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Certified Professional Counselor-Alcohol and Drug.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The scope of practice for a certified professional counselor-alcohol and drug consists of the following activities:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Biopsychosocial evaluation, including screening, assessment, and participating in the development of diagnostic impressions for SUDs and CODs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Treatment planning for SUDs and CODs, including initial, ongoing, continuity of care, discharge, and planning for relapse prevention;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Referral;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Service coordination and case management in the areas of SUDs and CODs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Counseling, therapy, and trauma-informed care with individuals, families, and groups in the areas of SUDs and CODs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Client, family, and community education;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Documentation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Professional and ethical responsibilities; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Supervisory responsibilities for all categories of certified alcohol and drug counselors or trainees in the certification track.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Renewal.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To renew certified professional counselor-alcohol and drug certification, the applicant, before the current certificate expiration, shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Complete an application on a form approved by the Board;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Pay the required application fee set forth in <cite path="|10.58.02">COMAR 10.58.02</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Attest to completion of continuing education activities as specified in <cite path="10.58.05.05">COMAR 10.58.05.05</cite> and .06.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Board may not renew the certification of any certified professional counselor-alcohol and drug who fails to complete all requirements for renewal before the expiration date of the current certification.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Board may not reinstate the certification of a certified professional counselor-alcohol and drug who has failed to renew for any reason.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|58|07|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Certified Associate Counselor-Alcohol and Drug.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Scope of Practice. The scope of practice of a certified associate counselor-alcohol and drug consists of the following activities, performed in accordance with <cite path="10|58|07|.07|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Biopsychosocial evaluation, including participating in the development of diagnostic impressions for SUDs or Screening, Brief Intervention, and Referral to Treatment (SBIRT);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Treatment planning for SUDs and CODs, including initial, ongoing, continuity of care, discharge, and planning for relapse prevention;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Referral;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Service coordination and case management for SUDs and CODs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Counseling, therapy, and trauma informed care, with individuals, couples, families, and groups;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Client, family, and community education;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Documentation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Complying with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Professional and ethical responsibilities; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Supervisory responsibilities for a certified associate counselor-alcohol and drug, certified supervised counselor-alcohol and drug, or a trainee seeking certification, provided that the certified associate counselor-alcohol and drug has been approved as a supervisor by the Board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A certified associate counselor-alcohol and drug:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall provide alcohol and drug counseling:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>As an employee of an agency or facility that is certified or licensed by the State; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Under the moderate supervision of an approved alcohol and drug counselor supervisor as specified in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17">Health Occupations Article, §17</cite>–403, Annotated Code of Maryland;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>May provide supervision with approval by the Board; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>May not practice independently.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>To qualify for certification as a certified associate counselor-alcohol and drug (CAC-AD) an applicant shall have:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At a minimum:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A bachelor’s degree from an accredited educational institution in a health and human services counseling field; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A bachelor’s degree and have completed a program of studies determined by the Board to be substantially equivalent in subject matter with a minimum of 45 credit hours in counseling, including the required alcohol and drug course work for the level of certification sought, as specified in <cite path="10|58|07|.07|C.|(2)">§C(2) of this regulation</cite>;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Completed a minimum of 33 semester credit hours or 50 quarter credit hours in alcohol and drug counselor training from an accredited educational institution including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>3 semester credit hours or 5 quarter credit hours of course work in each of the following course content areas:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Pharmacology;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Group counseling;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Individual counseling;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Addictions treatment delivery;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Ethics that includes alcohol and drug counseling issues; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Abnormal psychology; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Any three of the following 3 semester credit hours or 5 quarter credit hours of course work in each of the following course content areas:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Human development;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Theories of counseling;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Treatment of co-occurring disorders;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Topics in substance-related and addictive disorders; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Family counseling;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Completed one of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An internship in alcohol and drug counseling that totals 6 semester credit hours or 10 quarter credit hours; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A minimum of 1,000 hours of alcohol and drug counseling work completed as a certified associate counselor-alcohol and drug, a certified supervised counselor-alcohol and drug, or an alcohol and drug trainee under and verified by an approved alcohol and drug counselor supervisor;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Completed not less than 1 year with a minimum of 1,000 hours of clinically supervised experience in alcohol and drug counseling completed as a certified supervised counselor-alcohol and drug or an alcohol and drug trainee under and verified by an approved alcohol and drug counselor supervisor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Achieved a passing score on:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A national alcohol and drug counselor examination as approved by the Board; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An examination of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>This subtitle;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Met all of the requirements set forth under <cite path="|10|58|07|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Complied with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The code of ethics as set forth in <cite path="|10.58.03">COMAR 10.58.03</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Certified associate counselors-alcohol and drug shall have available for inspection a professional disclosure statement, as described in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-507">Health Occupations Article, §17-507, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Clearly states that the counseling services are provided under supervision; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provides the name, title, and credentials of the supervisor of record, including the supervisor’s address and contact information.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Reexamination. An applicant who fails an examination for certification:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>May retake the exam if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>It is within the time frame set by the applicable testing authority; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A waiver is approved by the Board to extend the testing deadline upon proof of exceptional circumstances; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shall be required to submit a new application and pay the nonrefundable fee set forth in <cite path="|10.58.02">COMAR 10.58.02</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Board shall act upon applications as set forth under <cite path="|10|58|07|.03|B.">Regulation .03B of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Renewal.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To renew the certification of a certified associate counselor-alcohol and drug, the applicant, before the current certificate expiration, shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Complete a Board-approved renewal application;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Pay all applicable fees set forth in <cite path="|10.58.02">COMAR 10.58.02</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Attest to completion of continuing education activities as specified in <cite path="10.58.05.05">COMAR 10.58.05.05</cite> and .06.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Board may not renew the certification of any certified associate counselor — alcohol and drug who fails to complete all requirements for renewal before the expiration date of the current certification.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An individual who fails to renew certification is not authorized to and may not practice alcohol and drug counseling.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Reinstatement.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within 5 calendar years after the certificate renewal date, the Board may reinstate the certificate of a certified associate counselor-alcohol and drug otherwise entitled to reinstatement under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-505">Health Occupations Article, §17-505(b), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, whose certificate was not renewed for any reason, if the certificate holder:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Completes the required CEUs as set forth under <cite path="|10.58.05">COMAR 10.58.05</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Meets the current certification requirements; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Pays the reinstatement fee as set forth under <cite path="|10.58.02">COMAR 10.58.02</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>CEUs which are acquired in order to reinstate under <cite path="10.58.05.05">COMAR 10.58.05.05</cite> and .06 may be credited only once and may not be credited for any future renewals.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>For any certified associate counselor-alcohol and drug whose certificate has expired more than 5 calendar years before the request for reinstatement, a new application for certification shall be completed and the current certification requirements shall be met.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Inactive Status.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-505">Health Occupations Article, §17-505, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, a request to transfer a certificate to inactive status shall be granted upon receipt of the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Completed Board-approved application; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Payment of all applicable fees set forth in <cite path="|10.58.02">COMAR 10.58.02</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An individual may apply for inactive status only if the individual’s certificate is active at the time application for inactive status is made.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An individual on inactive status is not authorized to practice alcohol and drug counseling.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Within 5 calendar years after being placed on inactive status, an individual on inactive status seeking to be reinstated to active status shall be required, as a condition of reinstatement, to submit proof of having completed the CEU requirements as set forth under <cite path="|10.58.05">COMAR 10.58.05</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If an individual on inactive status seeks to be reinstated beyond the required 5-year period and conditions set forth under <cite path="10|58|07|.07|I.|(4)">§I(4) of this regulation</cite>, the individual shall be required to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Submit a new application;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Meet the current certification requirements; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Pay the nonrefundable fee set forth in <cite path="|10.58.02">COMAR 10.58.02</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|58|07|.08">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Certified Supervised Counselor-Alcohol and Drug.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Scope of Practice. The scope of practice for a certified supervised counselor-alcohol and drug consists of the following activities, performed in accordance with <cite path="10|58|07|.08|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Participating in the development of diagnostic impressions for SUDs and CODs, as:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Confirmed by an approved alcohol and drug counselor supervisor; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Documented by signature and credentials;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Biopsychosocial evaluation, as permitted by the Board-approved supervisor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Screening, Brief Intervention, and Referral to Treatment (SBIRT);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Treatment planning for SUDs and CODs, including initial, ongoing, continuity of care, discharge, and planning for relapse prevention, as confirmed by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An approved alcohol and drug counselor supervisor; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Documentation by signature and credentials;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Referral;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Participating in service coordination, case coordination, and case management for SUDs and CODs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Counseling of individuals and groups for SUDs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Client, family, and community education for SUDs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Documentation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Complying with the professional and ethical responsibilities set forth in <cite path="|10.58.03">COMAR 10.58.03</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A certified supervised counselor-alcohol and drug:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall practice under the close supervision of an approved alcohol and drug counselor supervisor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shall provide alcohol and drug counseling as an employee of an agency or facility that is certified or licensed by the State; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>May not:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Provide supervision; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Practice independently.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>To qualify for certification as a supervised counselor-alcohol and drug, an applicant shall have:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At a minimum:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An associate’s degree from an accredited educational institution in a health and human services counseling field; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An associate’s degree and have completed a program of studies determined by the Board to be substantially equivalent in subject matter with a minimum of 30 credit hours in counseling, including the required alcohol and drug course work for the level of certification sought, as specified in <cite path="10|58|07|.08|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Completed a minimum of 24 semester credit hours or 37 quarter credit hours in alcohol and drug counselor training from an accredited educational institution including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>3 semester credit hours or 5 quarter credit hours of course work in each of the following course content areas:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Pharmacology;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Addictions treatment delivery; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Ethics that includes alcohol and drug counseling issues; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Any three of the following 3 semester credit hours or 5 quarter credit hours of course work in each of the following course content areas:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Human development;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Theories of counseling;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Treatment of co-occurring disorders;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Family counseling;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Individual counseling;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Group counseling;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Abnormal psychology; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Topics in substance-related and addictive disorders;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Completed one of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An internship in alcohol and drug counseling that totals 6 semester credit hours or 10 quarter credit hours; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A minimum of 1,000 hours of alcohol and drug counseling work completed as an alcohol and drug trainee under and verified by an approved alcohol and drug counselor supervisor;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Achieved a passing score on:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A national alcohol and drug counselor examination as approved by the Board; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An examination of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>This subtitle;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Met all of the requirements set forth under <cite path="|10|58|07|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Complied with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The code of ethics as set forth in <cite path="|10.58.03">COMAR 10.58.03</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Certified supervised counselors-alcohol and drug shall have available for inspection a professional disclosure statement, as described in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-507">Health Occupations Article, §17-507, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Clearly states that the counseling services are provided under supervision; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provides the name, title, and credentials of the supervisor of record, including the supervisor’s address and contact information.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Reexamination. An applicant who fails an examination for certification:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>May retake the exam if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>It is within the time frame set by the applicable testing authority; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A waiver is approved by the Board to extend the testing deadline upon proof of exceptional circumstances; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shall be required to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Submit a new application; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Pay the nonrefundable fee set forth in <cite path="|10.58.02">COMAR 10.58.02</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Board shall act upon applications as set forth under <cite path="|10|58|07|.03|B.">Regulation .03B of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Renewal. The Board may renew the certificate of a certified supervised counselor-alcohol and drug as set forth under Regulation .07G in this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Reinstatement. The Board may reinstate the certificate of a certified supervised counselor-alcohol and drug as set forth under Regulation .07H in this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Inactive Status. A certified supervised counselor-alcohol and drug may request inactive status as set forth under <cite path="|10|58|07|.07|I.">Regulation .07I of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|58|07|.09">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Alcohol and Drug Trainees.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Scope of Practice. The scope of practice of an alcohol and drug trainee shall be limited to the following activities under an approved alcohol and drug counselor supervisor:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Biopsychosocial evaluation, including screening, assessment, and diagnostic impressions for SUDs and CODs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Treatment planning for SUDs and CODs, including initial, ongoing, continuity of care, discharge, and planning for relapse prevention;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Referral;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Service coordination and case management in the areas of SUDs and CODs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Counseling, therapy, and trauma informed care with individuals, couples, families and groups in the areas of SUDs and CODs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Client, family, group, and community education;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Documentation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Compliance with professional and ethical responsibilities.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A trainee may not perform supervision.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Qualifications. To qualify as an alcohol and drug trainee, an applicant shall meet one of the following requirements:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Hold an associate’s degree or higher from an accredited educational institution:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In a health and human services counseling field; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Hold an associate’s degree and a completed program of studies determined by the Board to be substantially equivalent in subject matter, which includes 1 semester credit hour or 2 quarter credit hours in the ethics of alcohol and drug counseling; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Have completed 15 semester credit hours or 25 quarter credit hours from among the topic areas specified in <cite path="|10|58|07|.05|B.">Regulation .05B of this chapter</cite> including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>15 continuing education units (CEUs) in the ethics of alcohol and drug counseling; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>1 semester credit hour or 2 quarter credit hours in the ethics of alcohol and drug counseling from an accredited educational institution.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An alcohol and drug trainee shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Practice under the supervision of a Board-approved alcohol and drug supervisor as specified under §§E—H of this regulation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Have available for inspection a professional disclosure statement, as described in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-507">Health Occupations Article, §17-507, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Clearly states that the counseling services are provided under supervision; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Provides the name, title, and credentials of the supervisor of record, including the supervisor’s address and contact information.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A trainee holding a master’s degree shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Practice under the clinical supervision of an approved alcohol and drug counselor supervisor as defined under <cite path="|10|58|07|.02|B.">Regulation .02B of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide alcohol and drug counseling as an employee of an agency or facility that is certified or licensed by the State; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Provide documentation satisfactory to the Board every 2 years of progress towards the fulfillment of the experiential and course of study requirements under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-302">Health Occupations Article, §17-302, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A trainee holding a bachelor’s degree shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Practice under the moderate supervision of an approved alcohol and drug counselor supervisor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide alcohol and drug counseling as an employee of an agency or facility that is certified or licensed by the State; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Provide documentation satisfactory to the Board every 2 years of progress towards the fulfillment of the experiential and course of study requirements under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-403">Health Occupations Article, §17-403 </cite>or 17-404, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A trainee holding an associate’s degree shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Practice under the close supervision of an approved alcohol and drug counselor supervisor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide alcohol and drug counseling as an employee of an agency or facility that is certified or licensed by the State; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Provide documentation satisfactory to the Board every 2 years of progress towards the fulfillment of the experiential and course of study requirements under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-403">Health Occupations Article, §17-403 </cite>or 17-404, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>A trainee holding a high school diploma shall meet all guidelines set forth under <cite path="10|58|07|.09|G.">§G of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Application Process.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To qualify for alcohol and drug trainee status, an applicant shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Complete and return the Board-approved application that includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Information and supporting documentation regarding the applicant’s current educational level at the start of the trainee period; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>An attestation specifying the certification or licensure level being sought at the end of the trainee period;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Meet all of the requirements set forth under <cite path="|10|58|07|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Provide the name and credentials of the applicant’s prospective supervisor before beginning practice; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Comply with:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The code of ethics as set forth in <cite path="|10.58.03">COMAR 10.58.03</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The trainee shall notify the Board in writing within 30 days of any changes in employment and supervision.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An individual licensed as a clinical mental healthcare provider under the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, may not apply as a trainee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Trainee Practice of Alcohol and Drug Counseling.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An individual may practice alcohol and drug counseling as a trainee for a maximum of 6 years.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>After fulfilling the experiential and course of study requirements under Regulations .04, .05, .07, or .08 of this chapter, the alcohol and drug trainee may be eligible to apply for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Licensed clinical alcohol and drug counselor (LCADC);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Licensed graduate alcohol and drug counselor (LGADC);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Certified associate counselor-alcohol and drug (CAC—AD); or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Certified supervised counselor-alcohol and drug (CSC—AD).</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Renewal.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board shall issue a letter to the individual authorizing the individual to practice alcohol and drug counseling as a trainee for 2 years, renewable in 2-year increments up to a total of 6 years.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In each 2-year renewal application, before the expiration of the current trainee period, the trainee shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Document progress made during the current 2-year period towards the stated educational and supervised clinical experience required for the licensure or certification sought at the end of the trainee period, including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A verification from the approved alcohol and drug supervisor documenting the number of hours of supervised clinical experience obtained during the 2-year period; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A copy of an official transcript from an educational institution approved by the Board documenting progress made in completing the required education;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Submit a completed Board-approved trainee renewal application;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Pay the required renewal fee set forth in <cite path="|10.58.02">COMAR 10.58.02</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Provide documentation, satisfactory to the Board, every 2 years of the applicant’s progress towards fulfilling the experiential and course of study requirements under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-403">Health Occupations Article, §17-403 </cite>or 17-404, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Board may deny renewal if the applicant fails to document sufficient progress as determined by the Board.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A trainee who fails to renew their trainee status is not authorized to practice alcohol and drug counseling.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|58|07|.10">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Licensure Eligibility: Out-of-State Applicants.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant licensed as a clinical alcohol and drug counselor or its equivalent, as established by the Board, in another state, territory, or jurisdiction is eligible for licensure if the applicant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provides:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A completed Board-approved application;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Documentation or transcripts confirming completion of one of the following from an accredited educational institution:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A master’s or doctoral degree in a health and human services counseling field; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A master’s degree and confirmation of the completion of a program of studies determined by the Board to be substantially equivalent in subject matter with a minimum of 60 credit hours in counseling, including the required alcohol and drug course work for the license, as specified in <cite path="|10|58|07|.04|B.">Regulation .04B of this chapter</cite>;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A copy of a current license from each state, territory, or jurisdiction in which the applicant has been licensed, registered, or otherwise authorized to practice alcohol and drug counseling;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Documentation, satisfactory to the Board, that the applicant is currently licensed in good standing to practice alcohol and drug counseling in another state, territory, or jurisdiction; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Verification that the applicant has:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>No history of disciplinary action, past or pending, in a state, territory, or jurisdiction in which the applicant holds a license to practice clinical alcohol and drug counseling; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Not committed any act or omission that would be grounds for discipline or denial of licensure under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-509">Health Occupations Article, §17-509, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Pays the application fee set forth in the <cite path="|10.58.02">COMAR 10.58.02</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Has achieved a passing score on:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A national alcohol and drug counselor examination approved by the Board; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An examination of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>This subtitle;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Meets all of the requirements set forth under <cite path="|10|58|07|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Complies with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The code of ethics as set forth in <cite path="|10.58.03">COMAR 10.58.03</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Waiver of Examination. The Board may waive any examination requirements for an applicant who satisfies the Board that the applicant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Obtained licensure in a state or country that grants a similar endorsement to license holders of this State;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Became licensed in another state or country after passing an examination approved by the Board; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Meets the qualifications otherwise required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and this chapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Educational Requirements. The educational requirements for licensure in this State as a clinical alcohol and drug counselor shall be met:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>As established in <cite path="|10|58|07|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>By providing documentation of the substitute educational and experience requirements outlined in §§D and E of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Waiver of Course Requirements. The Board may waive one or more course requirements specified in <cite path="|10|58|07|.04|B.">Regulation .04B of this chapter</cite>, except for documentation or transcripts showing completion of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>3 graduate semester credit hours or 5 graduate quarter credit hours covering the following primary topics or content areas:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Psychotherapy and treatment of mental and emotional disorders, as described in <cite path="|10|58|07|.02|B.">Regulation .02B of this chapter</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Diagnosis and psychopathology; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Professional, legal, and ethical responsibilities; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>3 undergraduate semester credit hours or 5 undergraduate quarter credit hours in:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The ethics of alcohol and drug counseling; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Pharmacology.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Equivalent Experience Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The applicant shall provide documentation, satisfactory to the Board, of one of the following for an applicant with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A master’s degree consisting of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A minimum of 60 graduate credit hours; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Not less than 3 years, with a minimum of 2,000 hours, of supervised clinical experience in alcohol and drug counseling, 2 years of which shall be completed after the award of the master’s degree;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A master’s degree consisting of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Less than 60 graduate credit hours; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Not less than 3 years of experience practicing as a clinical alcohol and drug counselor, with a minimum of 2,000 hours of clinical alcohol and drug counseling experience; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A doctoral degree consisting of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Not less than 2 years practicing as a clinical alcohol and drug counselor; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A minimum of 2,000 hours of clinical alcohol and drug counseling experience.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The applicant shall provide verification, on a Board-approved form, from employers, supervisors, or colleagues that the applicant has practiced clinical alcohol and drug counseling for the length of time stated in <cite path="10|58|07|.10|E.|(1)">§E(1) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|58|07|.11">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Certification Eligibility — CAC-AD — Out-of-State Applicants.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant certified as a certified associate counselor-alcohol and drug or its equivalent, as established by the Board, in another state, territory, or jurisdiction is eligible for certification if the applicant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provides:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A completed Board-approved application;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Documentation or transcripts confirming completion of one of the following from an accredited educational institution:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A bachelor’s degree in a health and human services counseling field; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A bachelor’s degree and confirmation of the completion of a program of studies determined by the Board to be substantially equivalent in subject matter with a minimum of 45 credit hours in counseling, including the required alcohol and drug course work for the certificate, as specified in Regulations .07 and .08 of this chapter;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A copy of a current certification from each state, territory, or jurisdiction, in which the applicant has been certified or otherwise authorized to practice alcohol and drug counseling;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Documentation, satisfactory to the Board, that the applicant is currently certified in good standing to practice alcohol and drug counseling in another state, territory, or jurisdiction; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Verification that the applicant has:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>No history of disciplinary action, past or pending, in a state, territory, or jurisdiction in which the applicant holds a certificate to practice alcohol and drug counseling; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Not committed any act or omission that would be grounds for discipline or denial of certification under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-509">Health Occupations Article, §17-509, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Pays the application fee set forth in the <cite path="|10.58.02">COMAR 10.58.02</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Has achieved a passing score on:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A national alcohol and drug counselor examination approved by the Board; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An examination of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>This subtitle;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Meets all of the requirements set forth under <cite path="|10|58|07|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Complies with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The code of ethics as set forth in <cite path="|10.58.03">COMAR 10.58.03</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Waiver of Examination. The Board may waive any examination requirements for an applicant who satisfies the Board that the applicant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Obtained certification in a state or country that grants a similar endorsement to certificate holders of this State;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Became certified in another state or country after passing an examination approved by the Board;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Meets the qualifications otherwise required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and this chapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Educational Requirements. The educational requirements for certification in this State as a certified associate counselor-alcohol and drug shall be met:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>As established in <cite path="|10|58|07|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>By providing documentation of the substitute educational and experience requirements outlined in §§D and E of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Waiver of Course Requirements. The Board may waive one or more course requirements specified in Regulations .04B and .05B of this chapter, except for documentation showing completion of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>12 continuing education units (CEUs) in the ethics of alcohol and drug counseling; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>1 semester credit hour or 2 quarter credit hours in the ethics of alcohol and drug counseling.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Equivalent Experience Requirements. The applicant shall provide:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Documentation, satisfactory to the Board, of not less than 2 years of supervised clinical experience in alcohol and drug counseling with a minimum of 2,000 hours experience; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Verification, on a Board-approved form, from employers, supervisors, or colleagues that the applicant has practiced alcohol and drug counseling for the length of time stated in <cite path="10|58|07|.11|E.|(1)">§E(1) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|58|07|.12">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Certification Eligibility — CSC-AD — Out-of-State Applicants.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant certified as a certified supervised counselor-alcohol and drug or its equivalent, as established by the Board, in another state, territory, or jurisdiction is eligible for certification if the applicant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provides:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A completed Board-approved application;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Documentation or transcripts confirming completion of one of the following from an accredited educational institution:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>An associate’s degree in a health and human services counseling field; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>An associate’s degree and confirmation of the completion of a program of studies determined by the Board to be substantially equivalent in subject matter with a minimum of 30 credit hours in counseling, including the required alcohol and drug course work for the certificate, as specified in Regulations .07 and .08 of this chapter;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A copy of a current certification from each state, territory, or jurisdiction in which the applicant has been certified or otherwise authorized to practice alcohol and drug counseling;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Documentation, satisfactory to the Board, that the applicant is currently certified in good standing to practice alcohol and drug counseling in another state, territory, or jurisdiction;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Verification that the applicant has:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>No history of disciplinary action, past or pending, in a state, territory, or jurisdiction in which the applicant holds a certificate to practice alcohol and drug counseling; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Not committed any act or omission that would be grounds for discipline or denial of certification under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-509">Health Occupations Article, §17-509, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Pays the application fee set forth in the <cite path="|10.58.02">COMAR 10.58.02</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Has achieved a passing score on:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A national alcohol and drug counselor examination approved by the Board; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An examination of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>This subtitle;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Meets all of the requirements set forth under <cite path="|10|58|07|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Complies with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The code of ethics as set forth in <cite path="|10.58.03">COMAR 10.58.03</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Waiver of Examination. The Board may waive any examination requirements for an applicant as set forth under <cite path="|10|58|07|.11|B.">Regulation .11B of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Educational Requirements. The educational requirements for certification in this State as a certified supervised counselor-alcohol and drug shall be met:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>As established in <cite path="|10|58|07|.08">Regulation .08 of this chapter</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>By providing documentation of the substitute educational and experience requirements outlined in §§D and E of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Waiver of Course Requirements. The Board may waive one or more course requirements specified in Regulations .07C and .08C of this chapter, except for documentation from an accredited educational institution showing completion of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>12 continuing education units (CEUs) in the ethics of alcohol and drug counseling; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>1 semester credit hour or 2 quarter credit hours in the ethics of alcohol and drug counseling.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Equivalent Experience Requirements. The applicant shall provide:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Documentation, satisfactory to the Board, of not less than 2 years of supervised clinical experience in alcohol and drug counseling with a minimum of 2,000 hours experience; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Verification, on a Board-approved form, from employers, supervisors, or colleagues that the applicant has practiced alcohol and drug counseling for the length of time stated in <cite path="10|58|07|.12|E.|(1)">§E(1) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|58|07|.13">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Standards for Supervision.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as otherwise specified in this chapter, this chapter does not apply to personnel or management practices associated with contractual relationships or employment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A supervisor shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Supervise only in those areas within the supervisor’s competence, as determined by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Education;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Training; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Experience;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide supervision appropriate to the particular level of licensure or certification being applied for or maintained;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Provide supervision in the general content areas established in Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-302">17-302</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-403">17-403</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-404">17-404</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-406">17-406</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Ensure that a supervisee has read and is knowledgeable about:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>This subtitle, with special emphasis on the code of ethics chapter, <cite path="|10.58.03">COMAR 10.58.03</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In addition to the requirements of <cite path="10|58|07|.13|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, the supervisor shall specifically instruct and provide guidance relating to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The supervisee’s scope of practice of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Clinical alcohol and drug counseling under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-101">Health Occupations Article, §17-101(s), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Alcohol and drug counseling under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-101">Health Occupations Article, §17-101(p), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Activities specified under Regulations .04A, .07A, .08A, and .09A, of this chapter;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Appropriate billing practices, if applicable to the practice site, including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Financial record keeping and disclosure; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Establishment and disclosure to clients of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Fees for services;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Payment arrangements;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Payment plans;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Financial services; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Terms and conditions of service;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Professional and ethical responsibilities, including a working knowledge of the Board’s code of ethics, as set forth in <cite path="|10.58.03">COMAR 10.58.03</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The provision of services involving the application of counseling principles and methods in the diagnosis, prevention, treatment, and amelioration of psychological problems, emotional conditions, or mental conditions of individuals or groups, as required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-308">Health Occupations Article, §17-308, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Appropriate maintenance and destruction of clinical and financial records.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The following supervisees shall practice alcohol and drug counseling under the supervision of an approved alcohol and drug counselor supervisor as defined under <cite path="|10|58|07|.02|B.">Regulation .02B of this chapter</cite>:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A licensed graduate alcohol and drug counselor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A certified associate counselor-alcohol and drug;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A certified supervised counselor-alcohol and drug; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>An alcohol and drug trainee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|58|07|.14">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Supervisor Qualifications.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An individual providing supervision shall be Board-approved and:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Licensed by the Board as a clinical alcohol and drug counselor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Licensed by the Board as:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A clinical professional counselor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A clinical marriage and family therapist; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A clinical professional art therapist;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A licensed mental health care provider as defined in <cite path="|10|58|07|.02|B.">Regulation .02B of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Certified by the Board as a certified professional counselor-alcohol and drug; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Certified by the Board as a certified associate counselor-alcohol and drug for at least 2 years.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Experience, Education, and Training.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A supervisor licensed or certified by the Board, or any Board-approved mental health care provider licensed under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, with 3 years of documented experience in alcohol and drug counseling, including 3,000 hours of direct client contact, shall complete any of the following options:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>For a certified professional counselor-alcohol and drug or a certified associate counselor-alcohol and drug, at least 3 semester credit hours or 5 quarter credit hours of undergraduate or graduate-level academic course work that includes counseling supervision;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For a licensed clinical alcohol and drug counselor or other board-approved mental health care provider, at least 3 semester credit hours or 5 quarter credit hours of graduate-level academic course work that includes counseling supervision;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A Board-approved continuing education program in counseling supervision that includes a minimum of 18 CEUs with a sponsor approved by the Board to provide Category A CEUs as defined under <cite path="10.58.05.05">COMAR 10.58.05.05</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Hold the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>National Association of Alcohol and Drug Abuse Counselors Approved Clinical Supervisor credential; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>International Certification and Reciprocity Consortium Clinical Supervisor credential.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Supervision training required by <cite path="10|58|07|.14|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite> may be obtained in a graduate or undergraduate course as provided in §B(1)(a) or (b) of this regulation, or continuing education as listed in <cite path="10|58|07|.14|B.|(1)|(c)">§B(1)(c) of this regulation</cite>, and may include, but is not limited to, training in:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The role and responsibilities of the supervisor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The needs of the supervisee, the supervisor, and the agency setting while:</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The role of the supervisor as gatekeeper to the profession;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Methods for building effective and appropriate relationships with clients;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Methods for group supervision; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Models and modalities for practice intervention.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Pre-Supervision Responsibilities of a Supervisor. In addition to meeting the requirements of this regulation, the supervisor shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>File with the Board the approved alcohol and drug supervisor application form;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide each supervisee with a copy of the Board’s authorization of approved alcohol and drug supervisor status;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Have a license or certification that is in good standing; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Be an approved alcohol and drug supervisor as defined under <cite path="|10|58|07|.02|B.">Regulation .02B of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|58|07|.15">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Supervisor Responsibilities.</heading>
    <text>A supervisor shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Agree to and sign a written contract for supervision before initiating supervision;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Ensure that the supervisee is practicing within the scope of the supervisee’s credentialing;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Determine the skill level at which the supervisee may practice;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Focus on primary data from the supervisee’s practice;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Maintain documentation for at least 7 years of supervisory sessions, including:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Dates;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Duration; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Focus of the supervisory sessions;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Ensure that a supervisee has read and is knowledgeable about:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>This subtitle, with special emphasis on the code of ethics chapter, <cite path="|10.58.03">COMAR 10.58.03</cite>;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Within a reasonable period of time before termination of supervision, provide the supervisee and employer with a written notice of termination to avoid or minimize any harmful effect on the supervisee’s clients or patients;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Be responsible for the professional practices of supervisees;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Provide:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For emergency supervision of and direction to a supervisee by a Board-approved alcohol and drug supervisor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A written evaluation of progress to the supervisee on a regular basis or as needed; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A copy of the documentation required by <cite path="10|58|07|.15|E.">§E of this regulation</cite> on request by the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Supervisee; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Board or its authorized agent; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Comply with a Board audit of a supervisor’s compliance with regard to the supervisory requirements and responsibilities.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Supervisee Responsibilities.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A supervisee shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Verify that the supervisor has been approved by the Board;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Agree to and sign a Board-approved contract before initiating supervision;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Attend and participate in supervision as agreed to in the supervision contract;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Prepare for supervision using case materials related to the supervisee’s alcohol and drug counseling practice;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Maintain documentation of supervisory sessions for at least 7 years, to be available for verification to the Board or its authorized agent, including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Dates;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Duration; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Focus of the supervision; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Follow all terms of the written contract for supervision.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A supervisee may not engage in the practice of alcohol and drug counseling independently.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A supervisee shall provide each client with a copy of the supervisee’s professional disclosure statement, as required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-507">Health Occupations Article, §17-507, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, stating:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>That the supervisee’s alcohol and drug counseling services are provided under supervision; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The name of the supervisor, including the supervisor’s address and contact information.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A supervisee shall obtain from each client a signed informed consent for treatment form which indicates that the client:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is aware that counseling services are being provided under supervision; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Consents to the recording of counseling sessions, and the sharing of client information, acknowledging that all of these materials may be shared with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The approved alcohol and drug supervisor of record; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The instructor supervising an education-related practicum.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-101">17-101</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-102">17-102</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-205">17-205</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-301">17-301</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-302">17-302</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-305">17-305</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-308">17-308</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-309">17-309</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-401">17-401</cite>(b), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-403">17-403</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-407">17-407</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-501">17-501</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-509">17-509</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-01-21">Regulations <cite path="|10|58|07|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|58|07|.06">.06</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective October 1, 2001 (28:22 Md. R. 1932); adopted permanently effective January 21, 2002 (29:1 Md. R. 23)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-03-03"><cite path="|10|58|07|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective October 1, 2002 (29:25 Md. R. 1979); amended permanently effective March 3, 2003 (30:4 Md. R. 317)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-11-23"><cite path="|10|58|07|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective November 23, 2006 (33:23 Md. R. 1796)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-06-24">Regulations .07 and .08 adopted as an emergency provision effective October 1, 2001 (28:22 Md. R. 1932); amended as an emergency provision effective March 30, 2002 (29:7 Md. R. 617); adopted permanently effective June 24, 2002 (29:12 Md. R. 929)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-11-25"><cite path="|10|58|07|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective August 15, 2002 (29:18 Md. R. 1439); amended permanently effective November 25, 2002 (29:23 Md. R. 1811)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-01-21">Regulations <cite path="|10|58|07|.09">.09</cite>—<cite path="|10|58|07|.12">.12</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective October 1, 2001 (28:22 Md. R. 1932); adopted permanently effective January 21, 2002 (29:1 Md. R. 23)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-11-23"><cite path="|10|58|07|.12">Regulation .12</cite> amended effective November 23, 2006 (33:23 Md. R. 1796)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-03-03"><cite path="|10|58|07|.13">Regulation .13</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective October 1, 2002 (29:25 Md. R. 1979); adopted permanently effective March 3, 2003 (30:4 Md. R. 317)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-05-17"><cite path="|10|58|07|.14">Regulation .14</cite> adopted effective May 17, 2010 (37:10 Md. R. 723)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-05-17"><cite path="|10|58|07|.15">Regulation .15</cite> adopted effective May 17, 2010 (37:10 Md. R. 723)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-05-17"><cite path="|10|58|07|.16">Regulation .16</cite> adopted effective May 17, 2010 (37:10 Md. R. 723)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-05-17"><cite path="|10|58|07|.17">Regulation .17</cite> adopted effective May 17, 2010 (37:10 Md. R. 723)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-07-22" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective July 22, 2013 (40:14 Md. R. 1176)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-11-09"><cite path="|10|58|07|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite>, D amended effective November 9, 2015 (42:22 Md. R. 1379)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-11-09"><cite path="|10|58|07|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective November 9, 2015 (42:22 Md. R. 1379)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-11-09"><cite path="|10|58|07|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective November 9, 2015 (42:22 Md. R. 1379)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-11-09"><cite path="|10|58|07|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective November 9, 2015 (42:22 Md. R. 1379)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-11-09"><cite path="|10|58|07|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective November 9, 2015 (42:22 Md. R. 1379)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-12-31" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective December 31, 2018 (45:26 Md. R. 1247)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-06-28" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective June 28, 2021 (48:13 Md. R. 508)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
