<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>08</num>
  <heading>Marriage and Family Therapists — Requirements for Licensure</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Establishes the requirements for an individual to practice clinical marriage and family therapy;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Establishes standards of supervision and the responsibilities of supervisors and supervisees in the practice of clinical marriage and family therapy;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Applies to licensees who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Practice clinical marriage and family therapy; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide supervision for licensed graduate marriage and family therapists; and</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Applies to licensed graduate marriage and family therapists who are in the process of obtaining the supervised clinical experience required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-303">Health Occupations Article, §17-303, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Accredited educational institution” means a Board-approved college or university that is accredited by a national or regional accrediting body recognized by the Council on Post-Secondary Accreditation or through one of the following bodies recognized by the U.S. Department of Education:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools — the Commission on Higher Education;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The New England Association of Schools and Colleges;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The North Central Association of Schools and Colleges;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Northwest Association of Schools and of Colleges and Universities;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The Southern Association of Colleges and Schools; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The Western Association of Colleges and Schools.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Appraisal" means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Selecting, administering, scoring, and interpreting instruments designed to assess an individual's aptitudes, attitudes, abilities, achievements, interests, and personal characteristics; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Using nonstandardized methods and techniques for understanding human behavior in relation to coping with, adapting to, or changing life situations.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Board-approved marriage and family therapy supervisor" means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An American Association for Marriage and Family Therapy approved and Board-approved:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Supervisor;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Supervisor in training; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Supervisor candidate;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A licensed clinical marriage and family therapist who:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Meets the requirements for licensure under this chapter; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Has been approved by the Board;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A licensed clinical professional counselor, licensed clinical marriage and family therapist, licensed clinical professional art therapist, or licensed clinical alcohol and drug counselor who meets the requirements for licensure under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and has been approved by the Board; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>An individual who is authorized by law to practice a health occupation which includes the diagnosis, prevention, treatment, and amelioration of psychological problems and emotional or mental conditions of individuals or groups, and has been approved by the Board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Client contact hour” means at least 45 minutes of direct session time with a client present.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Clinical supervision hour" means at least 45 minutes of direct supervision time with the supervisee present.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Direct clinical marriage and family therapy services” means the provision of face-to-face clinical marriage and family therapy services to clients and their significant others that includes, but is not limited, to the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Individual counseling;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Group counseling;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Family counseling;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Couples counseling;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Evaluation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Intake or assessment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Diagnosis;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Treatment planning with a client; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Crisis management or intervention.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Face-to-Face.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Face-to-face” means in the physical presence of an individual or using video conferencing which allows individuals to hear and see each other in synchronous points of time.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Face-to-face” does not include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Telephone communication; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Internet communication that does not involve synchronous video conferencing, such as instant messaging services and social networking sites.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Indirect clinical marriage and family therapy services” means all case management and professional development activities related to the provision of clinical marriage and family therapy services to a client that include, but are not limited to, the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Referral;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Intake or assessment by telephone or other means when the client is not face-to-face;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Receiving individual and group supervision at site or at the university;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Consultation with other professionals;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Treatment planning with other professionals;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Case staffing;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Staff meetings;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Related trainings and seminars;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Record keeping;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Report writing;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Case notes;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>Providing clinical training;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>Telephone triage;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(n)</num>
          <text>Case management;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(o)</num>
          <text>Program development; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(p)</num>
          <text>Other clinical marriage and family therapy administrative duties as required by the setting in which the clinical hours are accrued.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“Licensed clinical marriage and family therapist” means an individual approved by the Board to practice clinical marriage and family therapy.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Licensed graduate marriage and family therapist" means an individual approved by the Board to practice graduate marriage and family therapy under the supervision of a Board-approved marriage and family therapy supervisor while fulfilling the supervised clinical experience for licensure under Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-303">17-303</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-309">17-309</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland, and <cite path="|10|58|08|.04|B.">Regulation .04B of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>“Licensed mental health care provider” means a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Licensed clinical marriage and family therapist; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Licensed clinical professional counselor, licensed clinical alcohol and drug counselor, licensed clinical professional art therapist, licensed certified social worker-clinical, psychiatrist, psychologist, or psychiatric nurse practitioner who is authorized by law to practice a health occupation that includes the diagnosis, prevention, treatment, and amelioration of psychological problems and emotional or mental conditions of individuals or groups.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>“Marriage and family therapy field” means a specific degree program with a marriage and family therapy emphasis, including, but not limited to, the following areas:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Marriage and family therapy, including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Marriage and family counseling;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Couple and family therapy;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Couple and family counseling;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Family and systems therapy;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Family therapy; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Family counseling;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Counseling practice under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Practice areas of other mental health providers, including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Psychiatry;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Psychology;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Social Work;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Psychiatric nursing; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Any other program of study approved by the Board.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>"Practice clinical marriage and family therapy" means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>To engage professionally and for compensation in marriage and family therapy and appraisal activities by providing services involving the application of therapy principles and methods in the diagnosis, crisis management, prevention, treatment, and amelioration of psychological problems, emotional conditions, or mental conditions of individuals or groups, including couples and families; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The use of instruments that require specialized psychological training for administration and interpretation as described in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-310">Health Occupations Article, §17-310, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>“Practice graduate marriage and family therapy” means to practice marriage and family therapy:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Under the supervision of a Board-approved marriage and family therapy supervisor; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>While fulfilling the requirements for supervised experience under:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-303">Health Occupations Article, §17-303, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text><cite path="|10|58|08|.04">Regulation .04</cite> of this chapter.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>"Psychotherapy" means providing clinical services that involve:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The professional application of psychotherapy and counseling theories and methods, including, but not limited to, psychodynamic, cognitive, behavioral, humanistic, systems theories, or trauma informed care to assist the client in:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Improving functioning;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Obtaining symptom relief;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Preventing psychosocial dysfunction;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Changing personality; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Maintaining improved functioning; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Situations in which the principal discourse involves, but is not limited to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Diagnosis of psychopathology based on standard diagnostic criteria;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Psychotherapeutic treatment of mental disorders, emotional disorders, and adjustment reactions utilizing clinically appropriate treatment modalities;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Childhood trauma and abuse;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Identifying and changing self-defeating patterns of behaving, thinking, feeling, believing, or interacting with others in systems;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Developmental issues;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Personality development; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Problems related to disorders of thinking, emotional suffering, addictions, behavior, or interpersonal dysfunctions.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>"Related field" means a profession using counseling whose academic requirements include degree programs from an accredited college or university that has curricula in areas such as expressive therapy, gerontology, human services, marriage and family therapy, mental health, pastoral counseling, psychology, psychotherapy, social work, and other areas approved by the Board.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>“Relative” means an individual connected to another by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Blood;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Marriage;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Guardianship; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Domestic partnership.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>“Scope of competence” means that area within which the individual is proficient to practice, based on education, training, supervised experience, and professional credentials.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>“Substantially equivalent” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A degree in a program of studies determined by the Board to have:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Substantial marriage and family therapy emphasis in the subject matter; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The extent of training required for the specified level of licensure; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The applicant meets the relevant qualifications stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17">Health Occupations Article, §17</cite>–303, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>"Supervised clinical experience in marriage and family therapy" means the provision of marriage and family therapy services conducted under the supervision of a Board-approved marriage and family therapy supervisor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>“Supervisee” means a licensed graduate marriage and family therapist obtaining the supervised experience required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-303">Health Occupations Article, §17-303, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>“Supervision” means a formalized professional relationship between a supervisor and supervisee in which the supervisor directs, guides, monitors, instructs, and evaluates the supervisee’s clinical marriage and family therapy practice while promoting development of the supervisee’s knowledge, skills, and abilities to provide clinical marriage and family therapy services in an ethical and competent manner and includes an acceptance of direct responsibility for the client services rendered by the supervisee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>Supervision Training.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Supervision training” means a course or program designed to provide information regarding the supervision process utilized by licensed clinical marriage and family therapists in a variety of settings.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Supervision training” includes training obtained through:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Graduate-level course work;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Continuing education units (CEUs); or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Other training hours approved by the Board.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(24)</num>
        <text>"Under the supervision of a Board-approved marriage and family therapy supervisor" means engaging in an ongoing process of receiving direction from a Board-approved supervisor that includes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Monitoring the performance of a supervisee; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Providing documented and direct consultation, guidance, and instruction with respect to clinical skill and competency.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(25)</num>
        <text>“Written contract for supervision” means an agreement between the supervisee and Board-approved supervisor that is initiated before beginning supervision and that details the scope of supervision and includes at a minimum the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Name and credentials of the supervisor and the supervisee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Primary purpose, goals, and objectives of the supervision process;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Details of provisions, including frequency, format, and case or chart review;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Methods of documentation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Duties and responsibilities of the supervisor and the supervisee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Procedural considerations in the case of the supervisor’s absence; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Information regarding the supervisor’s scope of competence.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|58|08|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Application Process for Licensure.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In order to obtain a license, an applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Complete and return the Board-approved application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Submit an official transcript from an accredited educational institution awarding the highest degree attained in clinical marriage and family therapy or a related field;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Pay all applicable fees set forth in <cite path="|10.58.02">COMAR 10.58.02</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Submit to a criminal history background check in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-501">Health Occupations Article, §17-501</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Be of good moral character; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Be at least 18 years old.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Applications shall be acted upon as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within 30 days after receipt of an application, the Board shall determine whether the application is complete;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the Board determines that the application is not complete, the Board shall send a notice of deficiency to the applicant;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Upon receipt of the notice, the applicant shall correct the deficiency within 90 days, or other period specified in the notice;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the applicant fails to correct the deficiency within the required period, the application may lapse and the applicant shall be required to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Submit a new application; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Pay the nonrefundable fee set forth in <cite path="|10.58.02">COMAR 10.58.02</cite>;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If the Board determines that an applicant is eligible to take the required examinations, the Board shall send a notice of approval to the applicant;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Upon receipt of the approval notice, the applicant shall have 1 year from the date of the notice to take the examinations; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>If the applicant fails to take the examinations within 1 year from the date of the approval notice, the requirements set forth under <cite path="10|58|08|.03|B.|(4)">§B(4) of this regulation</cite> shall apply.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|58|08|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Licensed Graduate Marriage and Family Therapists.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>To qualify for licensure as a graduate marriage and family therapist, an applicant shall have:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>One of the following from an accredited educational institution approved by the Board:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>For an applicant holding a master’s degree in marriage and family therapy, or a substantially equivalent program, completed a minimum of 60 semester credit hours or 90 graduate quarter credit hours; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For an applicant holding a doctoral degree in marriage and family therapy, or a substantially equivalent program, completed a minimum of 90 graduate semester credit hours or 135 graduate quarter credit hours;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Completed a minimum of 45 graduate semester credit hours or 68 graduate quarter credit hours as required by <cite path="|10|58|08|.05|B.">Regulation .05B of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Of the graduate credit hours required by §A(1) and (2) of this regulation, completed a minimum of 45 credit hours in each of the following areas:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A supervised clinical internship or practicum that includes at least 60 hours completed under the supervision of a Board-approved supervisor and 300 hours of direct client contact with couples, families, and individuals, at least 100 hours of which are relational therapy;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Normal and abnormal personality development which includes individual development across the life span and the family life cycle;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Psychopathology with emphasis on standard diagnostic manuals, as well as family systems models;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Diagnosis and treatment of mental and emotional disorders in family systems;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>A comprehensive survey of the extant major models of family therapy;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>At least two courses which focus on a minimum of three marriage and family therapy models;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>A comprehensive survey of the extant, major models of couples therapy;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>An intensive study of at least three different models of couples therapy:</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>One course covering gender and ethnicity as they relate to marriage and family theory and practice, or two separate courses with one focusing on gender issues and the other one on ethnicity as they relate to marriage and family therapy;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Sexual issues in marriage and family therapy, including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Sexual normality;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Sexual dysfunction;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Sexual orientation; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Sexual identity; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Ethical, legal, and professional issues in marriage and family therapy;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Met all of the requirements set forth under <cite path="|10|58|08|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Achieved a passing score on:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A national certification exam approved by the Board; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An examination of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>This subtitle; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Complied with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The code of ethics as set forth in <cite path="|10.58.03">COMAR 10.58.03</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An applicant who fails an examination for licensure:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>May retake the exam if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>It is within the time frame set by the applicable testing authority; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A waiver is approved by the Board to extend the testing deadline upon proof of exceptional circumstances; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shall be required to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Submit a new application; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Pay the nonrefundable fee set forth in <cite path="|10.58.02">COMAR 10.58.02</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Board shall act upon applications as set forth under <cite path="|10|58|08|.03|B.">Regulation .03B of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A licensed graduate marriage and family therapist shall practice clinical marriage and family therapy under the supervision of a Board-approved marriage and family therapy supervisor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A licensed graduate marriage and family therapist may not:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Practice independent of supervision; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide supervision.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Expiration and Extension.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The graduate marriage and family therapist license expires 2 years after the date issued.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a licensed graduate marriage and family therapist is unable to accumulate the required clinical hours for licensure as a clinical marriage and family therapist within 2 years, the licensed graduate marriage and family therapist may apply on a Board-approved form for a 2-year extension before the current license expires, up to a maximum of 6 years, except as provided in <cite path="10|58|08|.04|F.|(4)">§F(4) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>For a licensed graduate marriage and family therapist who has been granted a 2-year extension, CEUs are not required for the first 2-year extension. Subsequent extensions approved by the Board shall be subject to the continuing education requirements in <cite path="|10.58.05">COMAR 10.58.05</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If a licensed graduate marriage and family therapist notifies the Board in writing, the Board may grant, in certain circumstances, a license extension beyond the 6-year maximum as set forth in <cite path="10|58|08|.04|F.|(2)">§F(2) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Reinstatement.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within 5 calendar years after the license renewal date, the Board may reinstate the license of a licensed graduate marriage and family therapist otherwise entitled to reinstatement under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-505">Health Occupations Article, §17-505(b), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, whose license was not renewed for any reason, if the licensee:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Completes within that 5-year period the minimum of 20 CEUs required for each year; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Pays the reinstatement fee set by the Board in <cite path="|10.58.02">COMAR 10.58.02</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>CEUs which are acquired in order to reinstate under <cite path="10.58.05.05">COMAR 10.58.05.05</cite> and .06 may be credited only once and may not be credited for any future renewals.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>For any licensed graduate marriage and family therapist whose license has expired more than 5 calendar years before the request for reinstatement, a new application for licensure shall be completed and the current licensure requirements shall be met.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>An individual who fails to reinstate licensure is not authorized to and may not practice graduate marriage and family therapy.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|58|08|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Licensed Clinical Marriage and Family Therapists.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>To qualify for licensure as a clinical marriage and family therapist, an applicant shall have:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A graduate marriage and family therapist license or other credential approved by the Board;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Completed the course work requirements set forth under <cite path="|10|58|08|.04|B.">Regulation .04B of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Completed a minimum of 2 years and 2,000 hours of clinical experience in marriage and family therapy, of which:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A minimum of the 1,000 hours shall be direct clinical therapy services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A maximum of 1,000 hours may consist of indirect clinical therapy services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A minimum of 2,000 hours of supervised clinical experience as a licensed graduate marriage and family therapist shall be completed after the awarding of the master's degree under a Board-approved supervisor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>At least 80 percent of the requisite direct and indirect hours included as supervised clinical experience hours shall be completed under the supervision of a Board-approved marriage and family therapy supervisor who is a licensed clinical marriage and family therapist; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>No more than 20 percent of the requisite direct and indirect hours included as supervised clinical experience hours shall be completed under the supervision of a Board-approved marriage and family therapy supervisor, as defined in <cite path="|10|58|08|.02|B.">Regulation .02B of this chapter</cite>, who is one of the following, provided the supervisor can document a minimum of 5 years’ experience delivering marriage and family therapy services:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A licensed clinical alcohol and drug counselor;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A licensed clinical professional counselor;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A licensed clinical professional art therapist: or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Another licensed mental health care provider as defined under <cite path="|10|58|08|.02|B.">Regulation .02B of this chapter</cite> and approved by the Board; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>100 hours of face-to-face clinical supervision hours shall be completed within 2 years of the awarding of the master’s degree, including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A minimum of 50 hours shall be individual face-to-face clinical supervision; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A maximum of 50 hours may be face-to-face group clinical supervision;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Achieved a passing score on:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A national certification exam approved by the Board; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An examination of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>This subtitle;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Met all of the requirements set forth under <cite path="|10|58|08|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Complied with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The code of ethics as set forth in <cite path="|10.58.03">COMAR 10.58.03</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An applicant who fails an examination for licensure:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>May retake the exam if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>It is within the time frame set by the applicable testing authority; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A waiver is approved by the Board to extend the testing deadline upon proof of exceptional circumstances; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shall be required to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Submit a new application; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Pay the nonrefundable fee set forth in <cite path="|10.58.02">COMAR 10.58.02</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Board shall act upon applications as set forth under <cite path="|10|58|08|.03|B.">Regulation .03B of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Board may include hours of clinical supervised experience obtained in another jurisdiction toward the total 2,000 required hours of supervised experience required for the licensed clinical marriage and family therapist, if the clinical experience hours:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Were obtained in accordance with the rules and regulations of that jurisdiction; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Included the course work requirements set forth under <cite path="|10|58|08|.06|D.">Regulation .06D of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Renewal.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To renew a clinical marriage and family therapist license, the applicant shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Submit a completed Board-approved application;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Pay the required application fee set forth in <cite path="|10.58.02">COMAR 10.58.02</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Attest to completion of continuing education activities as specified in <cite path="10.58.05.05">COMAR 10.58.05.05</cite> and .06.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A licensed clinical marriage and family therapist shall comply with the renewal requirements as provided in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17">Health Occupations Article, §17</cite>–504, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An individual who fails to renew licensure:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is not authorized to and may not practice clinical marriage and family therapy; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>May be subject to sanctions pursuant to Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-513">17-513</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-604">17-604</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Reinstatement.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within 5 calendar years after the license renewal date, the Board may reinstate the license of a licensed clinical marriage and family therapist otherwise entitled to reinstatement under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-505">Health Occupations Article, §17-505(b), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, whose license was not renewed for any reason, if the licensee:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Completes within that 5-year period the minimum of 20 CEUs required for each year; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Pays the reinstatement fee set by the Board in <cite path="|10.58.02">COMAR 10.58.02</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>CEUs which are acquired in order to reinstate under <cite path="10.58.05.05">COMAR 10.58.05.05</cite> and.06 may be credited only once and may not be credited for any future renewals.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>For any licensed clinical marriage and family therapist whose license has expired more than 5 calendar years before the request for reinstatement, a new application for licensure shall be completed and the current licensure requirements shall be met.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>An individual who fails to reinstate licensure is not authorized to and may not practice clinical marriage and family therapy.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Inactive Status.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-505">Health Occupations Article, §17-505, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, a request to transfer a license to inactive status shall be granted upon receipt of the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Completed Board-approved application; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Payment of the required, nonrefundable, annual fee set forth in <cite path="|10.58.02">COMAR 10.58.02</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An individual may apply for inactive status only if the individual’s license is still active at the time application for inactive status is made.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An individual on inactive status is not authorized to and may not practice clinical marriage and family therapy.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Within 5 calendar years after being placed on inactive status, an individual seeking to be reinstated to active status shall be required, as a condition of reinstatement, to submit proof of having completed 20 CEUs for each year of inactive status, at least 40 of which shall have been obtained within the 2-year period immediately preceding the application for reinstatement.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If an individual on inactive status seeks to be reinstated beyond the required 5-year period and conditions set forth under <cite path="10|58|08|.05|G.|(4)">§G(4) of this regulation</cite>, the individual shall be required to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Submit a new application; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Pay the nonrefundable fee set forth in <cite path="|10.58.02">COMAR 10.58.02</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Licensure Eligibility: Out-of-State Applicants.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant licensed as a clinical marriage and family therapist or its equivalent, as established by the Board, in another state, territory, or jurisdiction is eligible for licensure if the applicant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provides:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A completed Board-approved application;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An official transcript from the educational institution which awarded the master’s or doctoral degree;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A copy of a current license from each state, territory, or jurisdiction in which the applicant has been licensed, registered, or otherwise authorized to practice clinical marriage and family therapy;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Documentation, satisfactory to the Board, that the applicant is currently licensed in good standing to practice clinical marriage and family therapy in another state, territory, or jurisdiction; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Verification that the applicant has:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>No history of disciplinary action, past or pending, in a state, territory, or jurisdiction in which the applicant holds a license to practice clinical marriage and family therapy; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Not committed any act or omission that would be grounds for discipline or denial of licensure under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-509">Health Occupations Article, §17-509, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Pays the application fee set forth in <cite path="|10.58.02">COMAR 10.58.02</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Has achieved a passing score on:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An examination of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>This subtitle; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A national certification exam approved by the Board;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Submits to a criminal history background check in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-501">Health Occupations Article, §17-501</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Meets the educational requirements for licensure in this State as a clinical marriage and family therapist:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>As established in <cite path="|10|58|08|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>By providing documentation of the substitute educational and experience requirements outlined in §§B—E of this regulation;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Is of good moral character; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Complies with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The code of ethics as set forth in <cite path="|10.58.03">COMAR 10.58.03</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Waiver of Examination. The Board may waive any examination requirements for an applicant who satisfies the Board that the applicant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Obtained licensure in a state or country that grants a similar endorsement to licensees of this State;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Became licensed in another state or country after passing an examination approved by the Board; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Meets the qualifications otherwise required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and this chapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Equivalent Educational Requirements. The applicant shall provide documentation or transcripts confirming completion of a master's or doctoral degree in a marriage and family therapy field from an accredited educational institution.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Waiver of Course Requirements. The Board may waive one or more course requirements specified in <cite path="|10|58|08|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>, except for documentation showing completion of a minimum of 3 graduate semester credit hours or 5 graduate quarter credit hours covering each of the following primary topics or content areas:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Diagnosis and psychopathology;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Sexual issues in marriage and family therapy;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Couples therapy, theory, and techniques; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Professional, legal, and ethical responsibilities in marriage and family therapy.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Equivalent Experience Requirements. The Board may waive the clinical experience requirements specified in <cite path="|10|58|08|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite> as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The applicant shall provide documentation, satisfactory to the Board, of one of the following for an applicant with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A master’s or doctoral degree in a marriage and family therapy field from an accredited educational institution as approved by the Board, as specified in <cite path="|10|58|08|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Program of studies judged by the Board to be substantially equivalent in subject matter and extent of training; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The applicant shall provide verification on a Board-approved form, from employers, supervisors, or colleagues that the applicant has practiced clinical marriage and family therapy for the length of time specified as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A master's or doctoral degree consisting of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A minimum of 60 graduate credit hours or 90 graduate quarter credit hours; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Not less than 2 years, with a minimum of 2,000 hours, of supervised clinical experience in marriage and family therapy, completed after the award of the master's degree; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A master's or doctoral degree consisting of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Less than 60 graduate credit hours or 90 graduate quarter credit hours; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Not less than 2 years’ experience practicing as a licensed clinical marriage and family therapist, with a minimum of 2,000 hours of clinical marriage and family therapy experience.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|58|08|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Standards for Supervision.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as otherwise specified in this chapter, this chapter does not apply to personnel or management practices associated with contractual relationships or employment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A supervisor shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Supervise only in those areas within the supervisor’s competence, as determined by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Education;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Training; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Experience;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide supervision appropriate to the particular level of licensure being applied for or maintained;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Provide supervision in the general content areas established in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-303">Health Occupations Article, §17-303, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Ensure that a supervisee has read and is knowledgeable about:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>: and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>This subtitle, with special emphasis on the code of ethics under <cite path="|10.58.03">COMAR 10.58.03</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In addition to the requirements of <cite path="10|58|08|.07|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, the supervisor shall specifically instruct and provide guidance relating to the supervisee’s scope of practice of clinical marriage and family therapy under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-101">Health Occupations Article, §17-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The supervisor shall also instruct and provide guidance to supervisees in:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Appropriate billing practices if applicable to the practice site, including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Financial record keeping and disclosure; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Establishment and disclosure to clients of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Fees for services;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Payment arrangements;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Payment plans;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Financial services; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Terms and conditions of service;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Providing services involving the application of therapy principles and methods in the diagnosis, prevention, treatment, and amelioration of psychological problems, emotional conditions, or mental conditions of individuals, families, couples, or groups, as stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-308">Health Occupations Article, §17-308, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Appropriate maintenance and destruction of clinical and financial records.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The following individuals may not provide clinical supervision for a licensed graduate marriage and family therapy supervisee:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A relative;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A licensed graduate marriage and family therapist, licensed graduate alcohol and drug counselor, a certified alcohol and drug counselor, licensed graduate professional counselor, licensed graduate professional art therapist, or any other graduate-level health care provider licensed under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An individual with whom there could be a conflict of interest, including, but not limited to, an employee supervising their own employer or a student supervising their own teacher.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|58|08|.08">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Supervisor Qualifications.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Licensure. An individual providing supervision shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Licensed by the Board as a clinical:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Marriage and family therapist;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Professional counselor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Alcohol and drug counselor; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Professional art therapist; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A licensed mental health care provider as defined in <cite path="|10|58|08|.02|B.">Regulation .02B of this chapter</cite> and approved by the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Education, Training, or Supervision Experience.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A Board-approved supervisor, or any licensed mental health care provider as defined in <cite path="|10|58|08|.02|B.">Regulation .02B of this chapter</cite> who is approved by the Board and has completed 3 years of documented experience in clinical marriage and family therapy shall complete at least one of the following education and training experiences:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>2 years of documented experience providing clinical supervision for marriage and family therapists working with families from a systemic perspective and conceptualizing family cases using a recognized family theoretical model;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>At least 3 graduate semester credit hours or 5 quarter credit hours of academic course work in clinical supervision;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A graduate-level course in marriage and family therapy supervision;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The American Association for Marriage and Family Therapy Approved Supervisor designation; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The American Association for Marriage and Family Therapy Supervisor in Training or Supervisor Candidate designation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In addition to the requirements of <cite path="10|58|08|.08|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite>, a supervisor shall complete at least 6 semester credit hours or 10 quarter credit hours of graduate-level academic training in Theories of Couples and Family Therapy.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Supervision training required by this section may be obtained in a graduate course as listed in <cite path="10|58|08|.08|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite> and may include, but not be limited to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The role and responsibilities of the supervisor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The needs of the supervisee, supervisor, and the agency setting while maintaining a clear ethical perspective, including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The maintenance of appropriate boundaries; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Making clinically appropriate diagnoses;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The role of the supervisor as gatekeeper to the profession;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Methods for building effective and appropriate relationships with clients;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Models for group supervision; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Models and modalities for practice intervention.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Pre-Supervision Responsibilities of a Supervisor. In addition to meeting the requirements of this regulation, before beginning supervision, the Board-approved supervisor shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>File the completed Board-approved supervisor application form;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide the supervisee with a copy of the Board’s licensed clinical marriage and family therapy approved supervisor letter; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Have an active license that is without restrictions or conditions due to disciplinary action for the 2 years preceding an application for licensed clinical marriage and family therapy Board-approved supervisor status.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A supervisor may be an:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Agency-designated supervisor; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Independent supervisor in private practice.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|58|08|.09">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Supervisor Responsibilities.</heading>
    <text>A supervisor shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Agree to and sign a written contract for supervision before initiating supervision;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Ensure that the supervisee is practicing within the scope of the supervisee’s license;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Determine the skill level at which the supervisee may practice;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Focus on primary data from the supervisee’s practice;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Maintain documentation, for at least 7 years, of supervisory sessions, including:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Dates;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Duration; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Focus of the supervisory sessions;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Ensure that a supervisee has read and is knowledgeable about:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>This subtitle with special emphasis on the code of ethics under <cite path="|10.58.03">COMAR 10.58.03</cite>;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Within a reasonable period of time before termination of supervision, provide the supervisee and employer with a written notice of termination to avoid or minimize any harmful effect on the supervisee’s clients or patients;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Be responsible for the clinical marriage and family therapy practices of supervisees;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Provide:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For emergency supervision and direction to a supervisee by a Board-approved supervisor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A written evaluation of progress to the supervisee on a regular basis or as needed; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A copy of the documentation required by <cite path="10|58|08|.09|E.">§E of this regulation</cite> on request by the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Supervisee; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Board or its authorized agent; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Comply with a Board audit of a Board-approved supervisor’s compliance with regard to the supervisory requirements and responsibilities.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Supervisee Responsibilities.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A supervisee shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Verify that the supervisee's supervisor has been approved by the Board;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Agree to and sign a written contract for supervision before initiating supervision;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Attend and participate in supervision as agreed to in the supervision contract;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Prepare for supervision using case materials related to the supervisee’s clinical marriage and family therapy practice;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Maintain documentation of supervisory sessions for at least 7 years, to be available for verification to the Board or its authorized agent, including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Dates;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Duration; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Focus of the supervision; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Follow all terms of the written contract for supervision.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A supervisee may not engage in the practice of clinical marriage and family therapy independent of supervision.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A supervisee shall provide the client with a copy of a professional disclosure statement as required under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-507">Health Occupations Article, §17-507, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Clearly states the marriage and family therapy services are provided under clinical supervision; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provides the name of the supervisor with address and contact information.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A supervisee shall obtain a signed informed consent for treatment form from the client which indicates that the client:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is aware that marriage and family therapy services are being provided under clinical supervision; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Consents to the recording of therapy sessions and the sharing of client information and, acknowledges that all these materials may be shared with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Board-approved supervisor of record; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The instructor supervising an education-related practicum.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-101">17-101</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-205">17-205</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-301">17-301</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-303">17-303</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-306">17-306</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-308">17-308</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-309">17-309</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-507">17-507</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-509">17-509</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-01-21">Regulations <cite path="|10|58|08|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|58|08|.05">.05</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective October 1, 2001 (28:22 Md. R. 1932); adopted permanently effective January 21, 2002 (29:1 Md. R. 24)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-03-03"><cite path="|10|58|08|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective October 1, 2002 (29:25 Md. R. 1979); amended permanently effective March 3, 2003 (30:4 Md. R. 317)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-03-03"><cite path="|10|58|08|.06">Regulation .06</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective October 1, 2002 (29:25 Md. R. 1979); adopted permanently effective March 3, 2003 (30:4 Md. R. 317)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-06-06"><cite path="|10|58|08|.07">Regulation .07</cite> adopted effective June 6, 2005 (32:11 Md. R. 983)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-05-17"><cite path="|10|58|08|.07">Regulation .07</cite> repealed and new Regulation .07 adopted effective May 17, 2010 (37:10 Md. R. 723)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-04-28" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective April 28, 2014 (41:8 Md. R. 473)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-04-04" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective April 4, 2022 (49:7 Md. R. 467)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
