<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>11</num>
  <heading>Advanced Assessment Activities</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter applies to licensees who practice clinical professional counseling, clinical marriage and family therapy, and clinical alcohol and drug counseling in this State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This chapter establishes standards for engaging in advanced assessment activities using instruments that require specialized psychological training for administration and interpretation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Advanced assessment” means to use instruments that require specialized psychological training for administration and interpretation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Face-to-Face Supervision.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Face-to-face supervision” means in the physical presence of the individuals involved in the supervisory relationship during supervision.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Face-to-face supervision” does not include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Telephone supervision; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Video conferencing.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Internet communication.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Supervisor who is proficient in the use of advanced assessment tests” means a licensed mental health professional approved by the Board, who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Under Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-302">17-302</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-303">17-303</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-304">17-304</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Is qualified to practice clinical alcohol and drug counseling, clinical marriage and family therapy, or clinical professional counseling;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Has completed the courses and supervised experience required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-310">Health Occupations Article, §17-310(1) </cite>and (2), Annotated Code of Maryland;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Has passed the National Counselors Examination (NCE) or another examination, as determined by the Board, that includes a comparable number of items assessing knowledge of advanced assessment procedures; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Has 2 years experience practicing as a licensed clinical professional counselor, a licensed clinical marriage and family therapist, or a licensed clinical alcohol and drug counselor; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has 2 years of documented, professional experience in psychological testing or advanced assessment, as approved by the Board, using the modalities, principles, and procedures of advanced assessment, including, but not limited to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Teaching;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Counseling;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Clinical practice; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Research modalities.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Qualifications.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>License. To engage in advanced assessment activities under this chapter, a licensee shall hold an active license in this State as a:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Licensed clinical professional counselor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Licensed clinical marriage and family therapist;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Licensed clinical alcohol and drug counselor; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Licensed clinical professional art therapist.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Education and Training.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A licensee may engage in advanced assessment activities as defined in this chapter if the licensee has obtained a doctoral or master’s degree in counseling or a related field that includes a minimum of nine graduate courses of at least 3 semester hours or 5 quarter credit hours in each of the following courses listed in §B(2)—(10) of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Psychopathology. Studies in this area shall include, but are not limited to, the scientific study of mental disorders and principles of abnormal psychology.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Biological Bases of Behavior. Studies in this area shall include, but are not limited to, the biological, physiological, and neurological aspects of behavioral and mental disorders.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Research Methods. Studies in this area shall include, but are not limited to, research methods for and principles of performing qualitative and quantitative research in the social sciences.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Advanced Statistics. Studies in this area shall include, but are not limited to, the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Parametric and nonparametric statistics;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Multivariate statistical methods, correlation, regression, factor analysis, and discriminate analysis; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Use of computers for data management and analysis.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Tests and Measures. Studies in this area shall include, but are not limited to, the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Test construction;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Evaluation and documentation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Fairness in testing; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Testing applications.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Intellectual Assessment. Studies in this area shall include, but are not limited to, the construction, standardization, administration, scoring, and interpretation of intelligence tests.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Personality Assessment. Studies in this area shall include, but are not limited to, the construction, standardization, scoring, and interpretation of personality tests.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Ethics. Studies in this area shall include, but are not limited to the ethical, legal, and professional standards related to assessment and the practice of professional counseling or therapy.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Practicum in Advanced Assessment. Studies in this area shall include, but are not limited to the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Practice with clients in the use of advanced assessment tests;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Practice in the scoring, interpretation, and reporting of results; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Practice in the integration of advanced assessment results with other sources of client information.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Supervision. In order to engage in advanced assessment activities as defined in this chapter, a licensee shall also complete 500 hours of supervised, direct, client-related, advanced assessment testing that is fulfilled in not less than 2 years and after the award of the master’s degree, of which a minimum of 100 hours shall include face-to-face supervision by a supervisor who is proficient in the use of advanced assessment tests.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Examination. In addition to meeting the requirements in §§A—C of this regulation, the licensee shall pass the National Counselors Examination (NCE) or another examination, as determined by the Board, that includes a comparable number of items assessing knowledge of advanced assessment procedures.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Complaint. In the event the Board receives a complaint regarding a licensee’s engagement in the practice of advanced assessment or the use of instruments that require specialized psychological training for administration and interpretation, a licensee shall demonstrate compliance with the education, supervision, and examination requirements set forth in this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|17-310">Health Occupations Article, §17-310, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-11-15">Effective date: November 15, 2010 (37:23 Md. R. 1611)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-12-31"><cite path="|10|58|11|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite> amended effective December 31, 2018 (45:26 Md. R. 1246)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
