<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Schools</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Public and Private Beauty Schools—General.</heading>
    <text>The Board's inspectors may conduct inspections of those schools of beauty culture approved by the State Board of Education or the Maryland Higher Education Commission.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Prohibitions — Schools.</heading>
    <text>The following activities are prohibited in a beauty school approved by the State Board of Education or the Maryland Higher Education Commission:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The performance of services of any kind on a client who has an infectious or contagious disease that presents a hazard to others;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The performance of services of any kind by a student who has an infectious or contagious disease that presents a hazard to clients;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The performance of services of any kind upon the surface of a client's skin, scalp, or nail where the skin, scalp, or nail is inflamed or where a skin infection or eruption is present, unless authorized by a physician;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The removal of corns, calluses, or other growths of the skin, such as warts, by cutting;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The use of electrical muscle stimulator devices purported to produce nonsurgical face or body lifts;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Cosmetic tatooing;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The presence of a dog, cat, bird, or any kind of animal on the school premises with the exception of a designated service animal;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The sale of any hairpieces which previously have been worn including, but not limited to, wigs, toupees, wiglets, falls, and switches;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>The use or possession of a Credo blade or a similar razor-type implement used to cut growths on the skin;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>The use or possession of lasers, microdermabrasion equipment, or any other mechanical device used to remove one or more layers of skin; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>The use of any product or method that causes tissue destruction or penetrates the blood fluid barrier, including:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Chemical peels; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Glycolic acids.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|22|03|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Sanitation Requirements—General.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A cosmetology school approved by the State Board of Education or the Maryland Higher Education Commission shall comply with the sanitation provisions in <cite path="09|22|03|.03|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Sanitary Provisions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Every school shall be well lighted, heated, and ventilated, and shall be kept in a clean and sanitary condition.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The walls, curtains, and floor coverings in a school shall be washed and kept clean.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All schools shall be supplied with hot and cold running water.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The premises shall be kept free from rodents, vermin, flies, or similar insects.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The school may not be used for sleeping or living quarters.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>All hair, nail service debris, cotton, or other waste material shall be removed from the floor without delay and deposited in a closed container and removed from the premises frequently.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Rest rooms shall be kept in a sanitary condition and have a soap dispenser and disposable towels.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>All students shall be attired in clean, washable garments.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>The hands of a student shall be washed before attending each client.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Surgical latex gloves shall be worn if a student has a cut or open wound.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Implements used in direct contact with a client shall be washed in hot, soapy water before being immersed in a disinfectant solution as specified in <cite path="09|22|03|.03|B.|(12)">§B(12) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Implements shall be disinfected in a wet sanitizer containing an EPA-registered disinfectant effective against HIV and hepatitis viruses, or a hospital-grade tuberculocidal disinfectant in a quantity sufficient to cover those portions of the implements that come in direct contact with a client.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>For each work station being used by a student, a school shall have:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>At least one wet sanitizer containing a disinfectant solution as specified in <cite path="09|22|03|.03|B.|(12)">§B(12) of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>At least one closed, dry drawer or cabinet which contains no other objects or substances.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>Cleaned and disinfected implements and equipment shall be stored in a closed, dry cabinet or drawer which contains no other objects or substances.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>The use of neck dusters, powder puffs, sponges, styptic pencil, and lump alum or any other equipment or implement which cannot be sanitized and disinfected may not be used on more than one client.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>Lotions, oils, and any other type liquid shall be poured into a disinfected container or disinfected hand. Any excess remaining after application shall be discarded immediately and not returned to the original container or applied to another client.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>Lotions, ointments, creams, and powders shall be kept in clean closed containers. All cosmetic containers shall be recovered.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>Every head rest and foot rest shall be covered with a new clean towel or disposable paper for each client.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>A school shall have a closed cabinet in which laundered towels are stored and a separate bin or hamper for the disposal of soiled towels. If the school does its own laundering, the school shall have both an automatic washer and dryer on the premises.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>Creams shall be dipped from a container with a clean spatula, and this instrument may not come in contact with the patron. Creams may not be removed with the fingers.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>An instrument that caused a skin abrasion or a cut to the skin shall be cleansed and disinfected immediately. If bleeding occurs, a tissue or cotton shall be used to collect the blood. Blood-contaminated materials shall be disposed of immediately in a sealed, double-plastic bag.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>A student whose hands come in contact with blood shall wash and disinfect them immediately.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>Pressing combs shall be kept clean and free of carbon, and a hot soda solution or similar cleansing agent shall be used for this purpose. Between clients, pressing combs shall be scrubbed with a stiff brush, rinsed, disinfected, and dried.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(24)</num>
        <text>Curling irons shall be wiped with a clean cloth after use on each client. They shall be cleansed in a soap solution containing a portion of ammonia or similar cleansing agent and wiped dry each day to keep them clean and free from rust, grease, and dirt.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(25)</num>
        <text>Hot combs and curling irons shall be used in a well ventilated area and wiped free of grease and hair with a paper towel or cloth before their placement in the heater.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(26)</num>
        <text>A minimum of eight combs and four brushes shall be available for each student.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(27)</num>
        <text>Protective neck strips or similar covering shall be used on each client.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(28)</num>
        <text>Shampoo bowls shall be washed after each shampoo and sanitized frequently with a disinfectant to assure cleanliness.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(29)</num>
        <text>Permanent waving retention rods shall be cleansed and sanitized after each use. End papers shall be discarded immediately after use.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(30)</num>
        <text>Soiled combs, brushes, towels, or other used material shall be removed from the tops of work stations immediately after use.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(31)</num>
        <text>Hair clips, hairpins, bobby pins, or similar implements may not be placed in the mouth.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(32)</num>
        <text>Objects dropped on the floor may not be used until they are cleansed and disinfected.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(33)</num>
        <text>Scissors, trimmers, clippers, and other implements which cannot be immersed in a disinfectant shall be cleaned and sprayed with an EPA-registered antimicrobial spray after each use.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|22|03|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Sanitation Requirements—Estheticians.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In addition to the sanitation requirements in <cite path="|09|22|03|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>, a cosmetology school approved by the State Board of Education or the Maryland Higher Education Commission that offers cosmetology services normally performed by an esthetician shall comply with the sanitation requirements in <cite path="09|22|03|.04|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Sanitation Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Creams, lotions, powders, and other cosmetics shall be removed from the patron by means of disposable absorbent cotton, cleansing tissue, cotton swab, pledget, or other similar material.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Lip and eyebrow pencils shall be sharpened after each use.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Lip color, eye color, shadows, or other cosmetics shall be removed from the container by a spatula and applied to the client with a disposable or cleansed and sanitized applicator.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Disposable lip, makeup, eyelash, or other cosmetic applicator shall be discarded immediately after use.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Hair removal waxes may not be used for more than one client. Any excess wax left after client service shall be discarded immediately.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Blood lancets shall be wrapped and discarded immediately after use.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>An EPA-registered disinfectant effective against HIV and hepatitis viruses or a hospital-grade tuberculocidal disinfectant shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Kept on the esthetician tray for contact disinfection of implements that may come in contact with blood; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Changed every 1 to 2 hours, or immediately upon becoming dirty, cloudy, or contaminated with blood.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Nondisposable drapings shall be laundered after each client.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|22|03|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Sanitation Requirements—Nail Technician Services.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In addition to the sanitation requirements in <cite path="|09|22|03|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>, a cosmetology school approved by the State Board of Education or the Maryland Higher Education Commission that offers cosmetology services normally performed by a nail technician shall comply with the requirements of <cite path="09|22|03|.05|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Sanitation Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Finger bowls, manicure bowls, pedicure spas, and foot bath basins shall be disinfected after each client with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An EPA-registered disinfectant effective against HIV and hepatitis viruses; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A hospital-grade tuberculocidal disinfectant.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Oils used in a nail technology procedure shall be dropped onto a properly disinfected hand with a glass or plastic dropper, and any excess remaining after application shall be immediately discarded.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The manicure table and surrounding areas shall be maintained in a sanitary condition at all times.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Table tops, armrests, footrests, and any other surface that the client has physical contact with shall be disinfected after each client with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An EPA-registered disinfectant effective against HIV and hepatitis viruses; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A hospital-grade tuberculocidal disinfectant.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A clean towel or disposable paper cover shall be placed over the manicure cushion and footrest, and changed before each client.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>An emery board or disposable file shall be discarded after its use on a client.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="|09|22|03|.03|B.|(33)">Regulation .03B(33) of this chapter</cite>, all implements used by a nail technician student shall be cleansed in hot, soapy water and then immersed in a disinfecting solution as specified in <cite path="|09|22|03|.03|B.|(12)">Regulation .03B(12) of this chapter</cite> before reuse.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>An EPA-registered disinfectant effective against HIV and hepatitis viruses or a hospital-grade tuberculocidal disinfectant in a quantity sufficient to cover those portions of the implements that come in direct contact with the client shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Kept on the student's table for contact disinfection of implements that may come in contact with blood; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Changed immediately upon becoming dirty, cloudy, or contaminated with blood.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>A complete set of manicuring implements shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Properly cleansed and disinfected, as specified in <cite path="|09|22|03|.03|B.|(12)">Regulation .03B(12) of this chapter</cite>, after use on a client; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Stored in an air-tight container or a wet sanitizer containing a disinfectant as specified in <cite path="|09|22|03|.03|B.|(12)">Regulation .03B(12) of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>A sanitizable or washable file shall be properly disinfected, as specified in <cite path="|09|22|03|.03|B.|(12)">Regulation .03B(12) of this chapter</cite>, after each use.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>When paraffin wax is used:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The client shall be free of broken skin or any skin disorder;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The hands or feet of the client shall be properly disinfected before being dipped into paraffin wax;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Hands or feet shall be covered with disposable plastic coverings after being dipped into the wax and before covering with cloth mitts, boots, or towels;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Cloth mitts or towels used in paraffin wax services shall be kept in a closed container;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Paraffin wax that has been removed from the client's hands or feet shall be discarded after each use; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Paraffin wax shall be kept free of any debris and in a sanitary manner at all times.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Sanding bands used on electric file mandrels are for single use purposes and shall be disposed of after each use.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Electric Files.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Only electric files specifically manufactured for use in the nail technology industry shall be used during the performance of nail technology services.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Modified craft and hobby drills may not be used during the performance of nail technology services.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>Metal bits for electric files shall be properly disinfected after each client with an approved disinfectant as specified in <cite path="|09|22|03|.03|B.|(12)">Regulation .03B(12) of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>Only bits which are specifically manufactured for use on the nail plate itself shall be used on the natural nail.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>Metal bits and sanding bands shall be used only on the surface of artificial nail enhancement products.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>During acrylic nail services, both the technician and client shall wear protective eye glasses or goggles when acrylic is being clipped, filed, or shaped.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>Artificial nail products:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Shall be removed by using a solvent; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>May not be pulled off the nail plate by the nail technician student.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Complaints and Violations in Beauty Schools.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This regulation applies whenever a complaint is made to the Board by an inspector, member of the Board, or any other person in regard to the sanitary condition of a cosmetology school or the sanitary practice of cosmetology performed at a cosmetology school.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Upon receipt of a complaint, in compliance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|5-509">Business Occupations and Professions Article, §5-509, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, an inspector shall investigate the complaint, and the Board shall determine if the complaint alleges grounds adequate to warrant action by the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the Board determines that the complaint does not allege grounds adequate to warrant action by the Board, the Board shall dismiss the complaint.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the Board determines that the complaint does allege grounds adequate to warrant action by the Board, the Board shall notify the owner of the school, or an authorized representative of the school, in writing, and provide the owner of the school with an opportunity to correct the violation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If the owner corrects each alleged violation within 10 days of the written notification, the Board shall dismiss the complaint and notify the owner.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If the owner fails to correct each alleged violation within 10 days of the written notification, the Board shall institute and conduct a hearing as provided in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 10, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>If the Board conducts a hearing and concludes that the owner has violated one or more sanitation regulations, the Board may impose a fine not to exceed $300 for each violation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The Board shall report the sanitation violation and the amount of fine imposed to the Department of Education in regard to a public school or to the Maryland Higher Education Commission in regard to a private career school.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Citations to Schools.</heading>
    <text>Unless otherwise indicated, the following civil penalties are applicable to the following violations of the laws and regulations of the Board of Cosmetologists discovered by a Board inspector during an inspection of a school:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Sanitation:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Improper disinfection:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Failure to wash implements before disinfection — $150;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Failure to properly disinfect implements, bowls, basins, or other areas — $150;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Failure to properly store disinfected implements — $150;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Failure to keep clean disinfectant on esthetician tray or nail technician table — $150;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Improper procedures for cut or blood-related incidents — formal hearing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Other:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Poor lighting, heating, or ventilation — $50;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Unclean walls, curtains, or floor coverings — $50;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Absence of hot or cold running water — $50;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Presence of rodents or insects — $50;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Use of salon (shop) for sleeping or living — $100;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Failure to promptly remove hair or debris — $50;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Unsanitary restroom — $50;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>No soap dispenser and disposable towels — $50;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Unclean operator's garments — $50;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Failure to wash hands before each client — $50;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>No wet sanitizer at station — $50;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>No closed drawer or cabinet for disinfected implements at station — $100;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>Use of neck duster, powder puff, sponge, septic pencil, or lump alum on more than one client — $100;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(n)</num>
          <text>Improper application, removal, or discarding of lotions, oils, and other liquids — $100;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(o)</num>
          <text>Improper application of creams — $100;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(p)</num>
          <text>Improper maintenance of lotions, oils, and other liquids — $100;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(q)</num>
          <text>Failure to properly cover head, foot rest, or manicuring cushion — $100;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(r)</num>
          <text>Improper storage or disposal of towels — $50;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(s)</num>
          <text>Improper sanitation of pressing combs or curling irons — $100;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(t)</num>
          <text>Insufficient number of combs or brushes — $50;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(u)</num>
          <text>Failure to use protective neck strip — $50;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(v)</num>
          <text>Improperly washed or sanitized shampoo bowl — $50;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(w)</num>
          <text>Improper cleansing or sanitation of retention rods — $100;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(x)</num>
          <text>Failure to remove soiled items from top of work station after use — $50;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(y)</num>
          <text>Placement of pins or clips in mouth — $50;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(z)</num>
          <text>Use of implements dropped on floor without cleaning and disinfecting — $100;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(aa)</num>
          <text>Failure to sharpen lip or eyebrow pencil after each use — $100;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(bb)</num>
          <text>Failure to discard disposable implement or cosmetic after use — $100;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(cc)</num>
          <text>Use of hair removal wax for more than one client — $300;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(dd)</num>
          <text>Failure to launder nondisposable draping after each client — $50;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(ee)</num>
          <text>Unsanitary manicuring table or surrounding area — $100;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(ff)</num>
          <text>Improper paraffin wax procedures — $100;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(gg)</num>
          <text>Improper use of electric files, bits, or sanding bands — $100;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(hh)</num>
          <text>Improper procedures when working on acrylic nails — $100;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Prohibited Practices:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Services on client with infectious or contagious disease — formal hearing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Operator with infectious or contagious disease performing services — formal hearing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Services on inflamed skin or scalp without physician authorization — formal hearing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Removal of corns, calluses, or other growths of skin by cutting — $300;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Use of electrical muscle stimulator devices — $300;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Cosmetic tattooing — formal hearing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Presence of an animal other than a designated service animal — $100;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Sale of used hairpieces — $300;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Methyl methacrylate liquid monomer (MMA) — formal hearing;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Interference with inspector — formal hearing.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Business Occupations and Professions Article, Title 5, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-05-23"><cite path="|09|22|03|.01">Regulation .01</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective May 23, 1986 (13:12 Md. R. 1371) (Emergency provisions are temporary and not printed in COMAR)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-11-03"><cite path="|09|22|03|.01">Regulation .01</cite> adopted effective November 3, 1986 (13:22 Md. R. 2397)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-06-22">Chapter repealed effective June 22, 1992 (19:12 Md. R. 1133)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-06-22" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|09|22|03|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|09|22|03|.06">.06</cite> adopted effective June 22, 1992 (19:12 Md. R. 1133)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-03-23"><cite path="|09|22|03|.02|G.">Regulation .02G</cite> amended effective March 23, 2020 (47:6 Md. R. 342)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-09-12"><cite path="|09|22|03|.02|H.">Regulation .02H</cite> amended and I—K adopted effective September 12, 2005 (32:18 Md. R. 1519)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-04-29"><cite path="|09|22|03|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite> amended effective April 29, 2002 (29:8 Md. R. 699)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-04-29"><cite path="|09|22|03|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite> amended effective March 9, 1998 (25:5 Md. R. 368); April 29, 2002 (29:8 Md. R. 699)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-04-29"><cite path="|09|22|03|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective April 29, 2002 (29:8 Md. R. 699)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-09-04"><cite path="|09|22|03|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective September 4, 2000 (27:17 Md. R. 1618)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-04-29"><cite path="|09|22|03|.05">Regulation .05</cite> repealed and new Regulation .05 adopted effective April 29, 2002 (29:8 Md. R. 699)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-07-31"><cite path="|09|22|03|.07">Regulation .07</cite> adopted effective July 31, 2006 (33:15 Md. R. 1280)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-03-23"><cite path="|09|22|03|.07|B.">Regulation .07B</cite> amended effective March 23, 2020 (47:6 Md. R. 342)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
