<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>04</num>
  <heading>Continuing Education</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>The State legislature has determined that it is in the best interest of the public to require licensed cosmetologists to comply with the continuing professional competency requirements as a prerequisite for the renewal of a license.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Approved continuing education course” means a course approved by the Maryland Board of Cosmetologists.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Board” means the Maryland Board of Cosmetologists.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Classroom instruction” means the art or science of teaching in a space:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>That is exclusively used for teaching during periods of instruction;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>That is conducive to learning; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Where an assigned instructor is present.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Contact Hour</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Contact hour” means a period of 60 minutes in which actual learning takes place.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Contact hour” does not include</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A portion of the program devoted to registration, breaks, or meals; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Fractions of an hour.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Continuing education course” means the basic measurement for a licensee’s direct participation in continuing education, consisting of 6 contact hours.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Continuing education course related to cosmetology” means a course that covers one or more of the following topics:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Board Laws and Regulations (1 to 2 hours);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Elective topics (1 to 4 hours);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Health (1 to 2 hours);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Safety (1 to 2 hours); or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Welfare (1 to 2 hours).</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Course” means classroom or distance learning instruction of 1 clock hour, but not more than 6 clock hours.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Course provider” means someone who is qualified to conduct continuing education courses in accordance with Business Occupations and Professional Article, §5-205(c)(2), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Distance Learning Instruction.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Distance learning instruction” means the art or science of teaching where:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The instructor and student may be separated by distance and time;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Equipment may be needed to communicate the content; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The content is specifically developed for this form of instruction.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Distance learning instruction” includes any other delivery system approved by the Board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>“Instructor” means an individual engaged by a course provider to teach a continuing education course.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>“License” means, unless the context requires otherwise, a license issued by the Board.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>“Licensee” means an individual awarded a license by the Board and includes a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Cosmetologist;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Limited Blow Dry Stylist;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Limited Esthetician;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Limited Hair Stylist;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Limited Nail Technician; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Senior Cosmetologist.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Licensee Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A licensee shall complete, as a condition for a license renewal, a minimum 6 credit hours of approved continuing education.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A licensee shall provide proof of completion of continuing education courses by uploading the documentation to the Board’s website as provided by the Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Course Provider Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A course provider shall get approval from the Maryland Board of Cosmetologists’ designee or Education Coordinator.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The course provider shall submit grades for continuing education courses by uploading the documentation to the Board’s website as provided by the Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Course Provider Fees.</heading>
    <text>Fees charged by the Board are as follows:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Course providers shall pay a nonrefundable fee for each continuing education provider application.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Providers shall pay a nonrefundable fee for each continuing education course approval application.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Course Content.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board may approve continuing education courses that include, but are not limited to, the following topics:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Business;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Communicable and infectious disease control;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The practice of cosmetology, esthetics, and nail techniques;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Ethics and standards of professional practice;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Occupational health and safety;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Product knowledge;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Sanitation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>State of Maryland laws and regulations.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The subject matter of the course shall meet the following requirements:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Address the protection of health and safety of the general public;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Enable the licensee to serve the objectives of the consumer in a cosmetology transaction; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Enable the licensee to develop competency and professionalism in a changing marketplace.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The course shall meet the following criteria:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Cover the topic area cited in the applications;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Have an outline detailing the sequence of topics and the amount of time allotted to each topic;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Content may not be materially changed without prior written approval of the Board; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Consist of at least 1 clock hour.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Facilities.</heading>
    <text>Each classroom in which courses are given shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Meet all fire, safety, zoning, and Americans with Disabilities Act (ADA) requirements;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Be of sufficient size to comfortably accommodate all enrolled students;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Provide an appropriate learning environment; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Be free of distractions that would disrupt class sessions.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Conduct of Courses.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Scheduling.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The maximum permissible class session without a break is 90 minutes.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A course scheduled for more than 4 hours in a single day shall include a meal break of at least 30 minutes, but not more than 90 minutes.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A course shall begin promptly at the scheduled time.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Records.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The course provider shall require each licensee to show photo identification in order to be admitted to a class for which the licensee has enrolled.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The course provider shall maintain a sign-in sheet containing:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The printed names and the signatures of all enrolled licensees on their arrival; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Notation by the instructor or monitor of the beginning and end times of any absences of the licensee from the class during the instructional period.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The course provider shall give each student at check-in a copy of the continuing education student information sheet furnished to the provider by the Board unless the sheet has previously been made available to students electronically.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Monitors.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A monitor is not required if the class consists of 25 or fewer pre-registered students.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Monitors are required under the following conditions:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>26 to 50 preregistered students — 1 monitor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>51 to 100 preregistered students — 2 monitors; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>More than 100 preregistered students — 1 additional monitor for each additional 100 students.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The instructor shall teach the course in substantially the same manner as that set forth in the outline submitted to the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|22|04|.08">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Distance Learning.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The course provider of a distance learning course shall obtain approval of the technical aspects of a course from an entity recognized by the Board in the field of technical expertise before submitting the course to the Board for review of its substance and subject matter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Technical staff:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The course provider’s technical staff may answer student questions about technical support and delivery method;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The course provider’s technical staff may not answer questions about content; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The assigned instructor shall respond to questions from students about course content within 2 business days.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The course provider shall be responsible for establishing guidelines for the completion of a distance learning course and any specific components of the course.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A distance learning instruction course shall include the following requirements:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The student shall complete the instructional module or modules and receive a passing grade on a final examination administered and graded by the approved provider;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The passing grade shall be 75 percent or higher; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If a student fails initially to achieve a passing score on a final exam, the student shall successfully pass the examination within the period set by the course provider in order to use the course for credit toward the continuing education requirement.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Student Affirmation.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The course provider shall be responsible for obtaining from each student who has completed a distance learning course an affirmation that states, “I (name of student) affirm that I have personally completed every requirement of the course and that I have not provided any aspect of the course to others.”</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The course provider may obtain the affirmation described in <cite path="09|22|04|.08|E.|(1)">§E(1) of this regulation</cite> by electronic means.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Audit.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board shall conduct random audits of licensees in conjunction with license renewal requirements.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board shall send an audit letter at the close of the renewal period to licensees subject to audit.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Penalties.</heading>
    <text>A licensee who submits false continuing education documentation at the time of license renewal shall be subject to any and all available disciplinary action available pursuant to Business Occupations and Professional Article, §5-314, Annotated Code of Maryland</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Business Occupations and Professions Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|5-205">5-205</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|5-311">5-311</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-05-01">Effective date: Effective date: May 1, 2023 (50:8 Md. R. 337)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
