<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Maryland Boat Act Advisory Committee</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Maryland Boat Act Advisory Committee.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A committee, to be known as the Maryland Boat Act Advisory Committee, is hereby created. The members shall represent groups or organizations concerned with boating activities, and shall be selected by the Secretary of Natural Resources in consideration of expert knowledge of, and demonstrated interest in, the operation and equipage of boats.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Procedures for Appointing Members.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The terms of the members may be 3 years and shall begin on January 1 of the year of appointment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Members are eligible for reappointment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Committee shall consist of not more than 21 members.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Each year 1/3 of the membership may be eligible for reappointment by the Secretary to a new 3-year term.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Solicitation of candidates shall be established by the Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Maryland Boat Act Advisory Committee shall elect from its membership a chairman, vice-chairman, and an alternate officer. The committee shall have the assistance of a designated member of the staff of the Department of Natural Resources in preparation of agenda, minutes, and other clerical assistance as may reasonably be necessary.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Maryland Boat Act Advisory Committee shall meet in January, March, May, and October of each year, and at other times as requested by the chairman or by a majority of the members.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The advice and opinions of the Maryland Boat Act Advisory Committee shall be sought by the Secretary of Natural Resources on all proposed regulations affecting the equipment and operation of vessels in Maryland waters, and may be sought by the Secretary of Natural Resources on any other matters considered appropriate.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Active members of the Maryland Boat Act Advisory Committee shall be entitled to display on vessels they are aboard a distinguishing flag or pennant, of a design approved by the Secretary of Natural Resources.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The Secretary may release an appointee at any time during a term.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Natural Resources Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|8-704">8-704</cite>(b) and (b-1), and 8-712, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1974-08-10">Effective date: August 10, 1974 (1:1 Md. R. 23)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1976-06-23">Chapter renumbered effective June 23, 1976 (3:13 Md. R. 721)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1991-04-29"><cite path="|08|04|02|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective April 29, 1991 (18:8 Md. R. 863)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
