<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>12</num>
  <heading>Security Interest Recordation</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Security Interest Recordation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A secured party shall perfect a security interest in a vessel by submitting the filing fee and completing:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The spaces provided for security interests in a vessel on the application for Maryland Certificates of Title and Boat Numbers for a vessel required to be numbered and never titled in Maryland;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The spaces provided for security interests in a vessel on the application for transfer of a Maryland titled vessel; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Security Interest Filing Statement and submitting the Statement, the owner's Certificate of Title, and the appropriate fee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Department may record the security interest only if the filing fee is paid.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>To record a subsequent security interest in a vessel:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Second or subsequent secured party shall submit the Security Interest Filing Statement to the first secured party with the appropriate fee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>First secured party shall transmit the Security Interest Filing Statement and appropriate fee to the Department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Department shall deliver the new Security Interest Filing Statement to the first secured party.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Department shall deliver a validated copy of the Security Interest Filing Statement showing the date of recordation to the second or subsequent secured party.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>When a second or subsequent secured party interest is discharged, that party shall forward the original Discharge of Security Interest to the Department and a copy to the first secured party and to the vessel owner.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Department record shall be available for inspection by the public during normal working hours in the Annapolis office only.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Natural Resources Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|8-704">8-704</cite>(c) and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|8-733">8-733</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1975-10-29">Effective date: October 29, 1975 (2:24 Md. R. 1480)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1976-06-23">Chapter renumbered effective June 23, 1976 (3:13 Md. R. 721)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-11-14"><cite path="|08|04|12|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective November 14, 2011 (38:23 Md. R. 1419)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
