<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Credit Life and Credit Health Reinsurance</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>In connection with credit life and credit health insurance written in Maryland by an authorized insurer, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|13-116">Insurance Article, §13-116, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, permits a fronting agreement between the authorized insurer writing the business and an otherwise unauthorized insurer if the unauthorized insurer maintains certain deposits with the Commissioner. The purpose of these regulations is to establish rules with regard to the deposits which are to be held by the Commissioner for the protection of affected authorized insurers, policyholders, certificate holders, and creditors in Maryland.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Acceptable securities" means any one of or a combination of the following, provided the securities are not in default as to payment of principal or interest at the time of deposit with the Commissioner:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Cash;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>General obligations of, or obligations guaranteed by, the federal government;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>General obligations of, or obligations guaranteed by this State or any of its political subdivisions; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>General obligations of the District of Columbia or of any state of the United States.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Commissioner" means the Insurance Commissioner of the State of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Fronting agreement" means an agreement by reinsurance or otherwise under which an authorized insurer transfers to one or more unauthorized insurers substantially the entire risk of loss under substantially:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All of the insurance written by the authorized insurer in this State;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>All of one or more kinds, lines, types, or classes of insurance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>All of the business produced through one or more agents or agencies;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>All of the business in a designated geographical area; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>All of the business written on one or more policy forms.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Insurer", unless the context indicates otherwise, means an insurer not licensed to do life and health insurance business in Maryland and not an accredited reinsurer but qualified or proposing to qualify as a fronting reinsurer under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|13-116">Insurance Article, §13-116, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|13|02|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Deposit.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Securities on Deposit with the Commissioner.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In order to qualify as an insurer in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|13-116">Insurance Article, §13-116, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the insurer at all times shall keep on deposit with the Commissioner acceptable securities with a total value at least equal to the sum of §A(1)(a) and (b) of this regulation:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>$500,000 reduced by the amount of the insurer's actual capital; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>$750,000 at the time of initial qualification and, after that, $500,000, in either case reduced by the amount of the insurer's actual surplus.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the insurer's actual capital exceeds $500,000, the excess may be used by the insurer to reduce the amount required by <cite path="31|13|02|.03|A.|(1)|(b)">§A(1)(b) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the insurer's actual surplus exceeds the amount required under <cite path="31|13|02|.03|A.|(1)|(b)">§A(1)(b) of this regulation</cite>, the excess may not be used to reduce the amount required by §A(1)(a), of this regulation, except as provided in <cite path="31|13|02|.03|A.|(4)">§A(4) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If, after deducting investments which qualify under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|5-510">Insurance Article, §5-510(a) </cite>and (b), Annotated Code of Maryland, in the amount of the insurer's actual capital, the insurer's remaining investments which qualify under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|5-511">Insurance Article, §5-511, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, exceed the amount of the insurer's liabilities as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|5-103">Insurance Article, §5-103, </cite>that part of the excess assets which also qualifies under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|5-510">Insurance Article, §5-510(a) </cite>and (b), Annotated Code of Maryland, may be used, at the insurer's option, as a credit against either §A(1)(a) or A(1)(b) of this regulation, but not both.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In determining the amount of the insurer's actual capital, only the type of investments listed in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|5-510">Insurance Article, §5-510(a) </cite>and (b), Annotated Code of Maryland, shall be considered.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The requirements of Insurance Article, Title 5, Subtitle 5, shall be used to determine the amount of the insurer's actual surplus.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>In determining the value of the deposit, securities shall be valued at market but not in excess of par value.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>In order to ascertain that the value of the securities on deposit is sufficient to meet the requirements of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|13-116">Insurance Article, §13-116, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and of this regulation, the insurer shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>File with the Commissioner not later than March 1 in each calendar year a certified copy of its NAIC Convention Blank form of Annual Statement as of the preceding December 31; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Require the custodian to supply the Commissioner not later than January 31 in each calendar year with a proper accounting of the securities on deposit as of the preceding December 31. This accounting shall include a listing of the securities on deposit showing the par value and the market value of each, together with a statement as to whether any are in default.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If an insurer which has previously qualified under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|13-116">Insurance Article, §13-116, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, no longer meets the requirements of that section, the Commissioner shall notify the insurer in writing of the additional amount of deposit required to restore the insurer's qualification. If the insurer does not satisfy the requirements by making the additional deposit within 30 days after the date of the Commissioner's notice, the insurer shall forthwith cease to accept any reinsurance under any fronting agreement to which <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|13-116">Insurance Article, §13-116, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, applies.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Unless the Commissioner liquidates a deposit for the purpose of paying claims to Maryland policyholders, certificate holders, authorized insurers, or creditors and for providing for the expenses incurred in connection with the payment of these claims, a deposit made by an insurer for the purpose of qualifying under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|13-116">Insurance Article, §13-116, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, shall remain on deposit with the Commissioner until:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The insurer notifies the Commissioner that it no longer wishes to qualify; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All policies issued in Maryland and reinsured by the insurer are terminated.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>If the insurer is adjudged insolvent, or, if for any reason the Commissioner, after a hearing, determines that the rights of authorized insurers, policyholders, certificate holders, or creditors may be in jeopardy, the Commissioner may direct the custodian to immediately deliver to him the securities then held on deposit, or at the Commissioner's option, he may direct the custodian to sell the securities and remit the proceeds of the sale to the Commissioner.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>An authorized insurer desiring to make a fronting agreement shall first ascertain that the reinsurer is appropriately licensed in Maryland, or is an accredited reinsurer, or is qualified as a fronting reinsurer under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|13-116">Insurance Article, §13-116, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>. An authorized insurer shall be subject to the penalties provided in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|4-113">Insurance Article, §4-113, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, as well as any other applicable penalties if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The authorized insurer makes a fronting agreement with a reinsurer which is not licensed, or is not an accredited reinsurer, or has not qualified in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|13-116">Insurance Article, §13-116, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The authorized insurer continues in a fronting agreement after having been notified by the Commissioner that the reinsurer has ceased to be qualified as a fronting reinsurer.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>The deposit required by these regulations may be made either by the insurer, or by another person on behalf of the insurer. If the deposit is made by another person, the custodian agreement shall provide the Commissioner all the rights of access to the deposit which these regulations require. If any agreement with reference to the deposit is made between the insurer and the person making the deposit, the insurer shall submit the agreement to the Commissioner for his approval at the time the insurer requests the Commissioner to accept the custodian agreement under which the deposit is kept.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Custodian Agreement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The deposit of acceptable securities shall be maintained under a custodian agreement acceptable to the Commissioner. If the deposit is made by a person other than the insurer, the Commissioner will require that person to also become a party to the custodian agreement.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The custodian shall be a bank located in Maryland, which has deposits insured by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation, and which is not affiliated with the insurer.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Not later than January 31 in each calendar year, the custodian shall give the accounting referred to in <cite path="|31|13|02|.03|E.|(2)">Regulation .03E(2) of this chapter</cite> to the Commissioner and to the insurer. At the Commissioner's request at any other time, the custodian also shall give an accounting to the Commissioner and to the insurer within 15 days of the Commissioner's request.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The expense of maintaining the deposit under the custodian agreement and of making the reports required of the custodian shall be borne by the insurer.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The custodian agreement shall provide that the custodian shall promptly return the deposit to the Commissioner at the Commissioner's request, or at the Commissioner's option the custodian shall sell all or a portion of the deposit and remit the net proceeds of the sale to the Commissioner.</text>
      <text>Agency Note: A specimen acceptable form of custodian agreement is attached to these regulations as Exhibit A. Appropriate changes in this form will be required if the deposit is made on behalf of the insurer by another person.</text>
      <text class="center">
        <strong>Exhibit A</strong>
      </text>
      <text>This agreement is made and executed this ____ day of  _____________ 20___, by and between the Insurance Commissioner of the State of Maryland (Commissioner), the XYZ Life Insurance Company, a Minnesota Corporation (Insurer), and the ABC Bank, a Maryland Corporation (Custodian).</text>
      <text>In this agreement the term "securities" means only any one of, or a combination of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Cash,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>General obligations of, or obligations guaranteed by, the federal government,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>General obligations of, or obligations guaranteed by this State or any of its political subdivisions, or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>General obligations of the District of Columbia or of any state of the United States, provided in any case that the obligations are not in default as to payment of principal or interest at the time of deposit with the Commissioner.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <aftertext>WHEREAS the reinsurance of credit life and credit health insurance written in Maryland is prohibited unless the reinsurer is an authorized insurer or is an accredited reinsurer, or unless the reinsurer makes a deposit of securities with the Commissioner in accordance with Insurance Article, §13-116, Annotated Code of Maryland,</aftertext>
    <aftertext>NOW, THEREFORE, in consideration of these covenants, the parties agree as follows:</aftertext>
    <para>
      <num>1.</num>
      <text>The Insurer agrees to pledge securities and deliver them to the custodian as directed by the Commissioner in accordance with the provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin">Insurance Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <aftertext>The total value of the securities shall be not less than required by Insurance Article, §13-116, Annotated Code of Maryland, and by regulations under COMAR 31.13.02.</aftertext>
    <aftertext>The insurer has assigned, transferred, and delivered to the Commissioner, and the Commissioner has received securities which have been accepted and approved by the Commissioner to the aggregate amount in value prescribed by the Commissioner, which are to be held by the custodian for the Commissioner in accordance with Insurance Article, Annotated Code of Maryland, the securities being as follows:</aftertext>
    <aftertext>_________________________________________________________________</aftertext>
    <aftertext>______________________________________________________________________________</aftertext>
    <aftertext>______________________________________________________________________________</aftertext>
    <para>
      <num>2.</num>
      <text>The custodian agrees, at the expense of the insurer, to hold all of the securities received by it from the insurer in accordance with the terms of this agreement. The custodian also agrees not later than January 31 in each calendar year to give a proper accounting of the securities as of the preceding December 31 to the Commissioner and to the insurer, and to give an<br/><br/>accounting to the Commissioner and to the insurer at other times at the Commissioner's request within 15 days of the request. The accounting shall include a listing of the securities on deposit, showing the par value and the market value of each, together with a statement as to whether any are in default.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>3.</num>
      <text>The custodian assumes no responsibility for the character of the securities held by it under this agreement nor for the sufficiency of the value of the securities.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>4.</num>
      <text>The insurer shall have the right, from time to time, to deliver to the custodian additional securities as prescribed by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|13-116">Insurance Article, §13-116, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and by regulations under <cite path="|31.13.02">COMAR 31.13.02</cite> to be held by the custodian, subject to the terms of this agreement and to substitute other securities in the place and stead of the securities then held by the custodian, provided that every addition, substitution, or withdrawal shall first be approved in writing by the Commissioner.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>5.</num>
      <text>The insurer shall be entitled to all interest which may become due and payable on the securities, and the custodian shall permit the insurer to remove and withdraw the interest unless otherwise directed by the Commissioner.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>6.</num>
      <text>If the insurer becomes insolvent, or, if for any reason the Commissioner determines that the rights of policyholders, certificate holders, authorized insurers, or creditors may be in jeopardy, the Commissioner may issue a written order briefly stating his determination and directing the custodian immediately to deliver to the Commissioner the securities then held by the custodian under the terms of this agreement. This order shall be effective upon delivery to the custodian. A copy of the order shall also be delivered to the insurer. Upon receipt of the order, the custodian shall promptly deliver to the Commissioner the securities then held by the custodian under the terms of this agreement.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>7.</num>
      <text>Instead of requesting that the securities be delivered to him, the Commissioner may direct the custodian to sell, assign and deliver all or any portion of the securities at any public or private sale within or without the State of Maryland. If the custodian is directed by the Commissioner to sell securities, the custodian is authorized to deduct from the proceeds of the sale the amount necessary for the payment of costs and expenses incident to the sale. The custodian shall promptly pay the balance of the proceeds of the sale to the Commissioner.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>8.</num>
      <text>This agreement may be terminated by either the insurer or the custodian 60 days following delivery of written notice of intention to terminate to each of the other parties, including the Commissioner, provided, however, that the custodian may not release or return to the insurer any of the securities held by it under this agreement without first having received written authority from the Commissioner to do so.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>9.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner may at any time terminate this agreement by written notice to each of the other parties. Upon receipt of the notice, the custodian shall immediately deliver all securities held under this agreement to the Commissioner.</text>
    </para>
    <aftertext>IN WITNESS WHEREOF, the Insurance Commissioner of the State of Maryland has affixed his hand and seal, and XYZ Life Insurance Company and ABC Bank have caused this agreement to be executed on their behalf by their president or vice president and have caused their corporate seals to be affixed, and duly attested, all as of the day and year first above written.</aftertext>
    <aftertext>ATTEST:</aftertext>
    <aftertext>________________________________________________ 	______________________________________________________</aftertext>
    <aftertext>Secretary	Insurer</aftertext>
    <aftertext>Corporate Seal 	By:___________________________________________________</aftertext>
    <aftertext>President-Vice President</aftertext>
    <aftertext>________________________________________________ 	______________________________________________________</aftertext>
    <aftertext>Secretary	Custodian</aftertext>
    <aftertext>Corporate Seal 	By:___________________________________________________</aftertext>
    <aftertext>President-Vice President</aftertext>
    <aftertext>(SEAL) 	______________________________________________________</aftertext>
    <aftertext>Insurance Commissioner</aftertext>
    <aftertext>State of Maryland</aftertext>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Letter of Credit.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>To the extent that the securities on deposit with the Commissioner and the other assets of the fronting reinsurer are insufficient to qualify in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|13-116">Insurance Article, §13-116, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and these regulations, the insurer may provide the Commissioner with an irrevocable letter of credit in an amount at least equal to the shortfall.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In order to be acceptable for the purpose of this regulation, the letter of credit shall be issued by a bank located in Maryland, which has deposits insured by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation, and which is not affiliated with the insurer.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The letter of credit shall be automatically renewable from time to time, and may only be terminated by the issuing bank upon 30 days' written notice sent to the Commissioner by certified or registered mail.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Insurance Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|2-109">2-109</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|4-105">4-105</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|4-116">4-116</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|13-116">13-116</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1980-12-12">Effective date: December 12, 1980 (7:25 Md. R. 2334)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-10-29"><cite path="|31|13|02|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite> amended effective October 29, 1990 (17:21 Md. R. 2527)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-10-29"><cite path="|31|13|02|.03|E.">Regulation .03E</cite> amended effective October 29, 1990 (17:21 Md. R. 2527)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-10-29"><cite path="|31|13|02|.05">Regulation .05</cite> adopted effective October 29, 1990 (17:21 Md. R. 2527)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-09-07" discontinuity="true">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|09.30.52">COMAR 09.30.52</cite> to <cite path="|31.13.02">COMAR 31.13.02</cite> effective September 7, 1998 (25:18 Md. R. 1439)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-11-07"><cite path="|31|13|02|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective November 7, 2016 (43:22 Md. R. 1223)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-11-07"><cite path="|31|13|02|.03|I.">Regulation .03I</cite> amended effective November 7, 2016 (43:22 Md. R. 1223)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-11-07"><cite path="|31|13|02|.04">Regulation .04</cite> Exhibit A amended effective November 7, 2016 (43:22 Md. R. 1223)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
