<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Standards for Credit Involuntary Unemployment Benefit Insurance</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>The purpose of this chapter is to promote the public welfare by regulating credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance and to establish standards for premium rates.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Regulation of Commissions.</heading>
    <text>The Commissioner finds it necessary to establish maximum rates of commission that may be paid to insurance producers and maximum benefits payable to creditor group policyholders in the form of dividends, retrospective rate credits, or any other form, to ensure that credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance operations of insurers do not:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Result in rates that are excessive in relation to benefits;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Endanger the solvency of insurers rendering their transaction of business hazardous to policyholders or the public; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Adversely affect other classes of business of insurers.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Applicability.</heading>
    <text>This chapter applies to all authorized insurers delivering, issuing for delivery, or proposing to deliver or issue for delivery, credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance in Maryland under individual policies, group policies, or group certificates that are required to be filed under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|13-110">Insurance Article, §13-110, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Account" means the coverage for a single plan of benefits for credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance under one premium payment method offered to a single class of business in Maryland by one creditor, whether written on a group or individual basis, or both.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Advance loan payment" means the payment of a scheduled loan installment before the installment's scheduled due date on a loan repayable in substantially equal installments.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Balloon loan" means an indebtedness, the initial amount of which includes both:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An amount that decreases by substantially equal periodic payments; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A final installment amount that is larger than any one of the periodic payments.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Case" means an account or, at the option of the insurer, a combination of some or all of the insurer's accounts written under an identical plan of benefits in which the gross premiums before refunds and at prima facie rates, whether consisting of one or more accounts, exceed or may reasonably be expected to exceed $50,000 in a policy year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Case method" means the filing and rate requirements stated in this chapter for business that meets the definition of a case.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Class of business" includes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Cash loans not secured by real estate and made by banks;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Cash loans made by credit unions;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Cash loans not secured by real estate and made by creditors other than banks and credit unions;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Cash loans secured by real estate and made by banks;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Cash loans secured by real estate and made by creditors other than banks and credit unions;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Production credit association and other agricultural loans;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Installment sales finance contracts; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Revolving charge agreements, credit card accounts, and open-end credit other than credit union accounts.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Commission.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Commission" means all forms of compensation or remuneration including dividends, retrospective rating credits, or any other form of benefit.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Commission" includes, but is not limited to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Commissions as a percentage of, or otherwise based on, premiums or amounts of insurance sold;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Retrospective or refund rate credits, except credits on creditor paid insurance;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Dividends, except dividends on creditor paid insurance;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Commissions or any other form of compensation or remuneration for reinsurance ceded or assumed;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Service fees or administrative fees;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Consulting fees;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Expense allowances;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Gifts;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ix)</num>
            <text>Expense for vacations or travel other than travel for training purposes or attendance at conventions;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(x)</num>
            <text>Value of electronic data-processing equipment or services furnished;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xi)</num>
            <text>Allowances or subsidies for rent, payroll, advertising, telephone, or other purposes;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xii)</num>
            <text>Advertising provided by the insurer;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xiii)</num>
            <text>Supplies, excluding application, reporting and claim forms, envelopes for transmitting the forms, and brochures, rate books, and rate charts related to the insurer's credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xiv)</num>
            <text>Dividends, profits, capital gains, commissions, or other benefits that may be reasonably anticipated under reinsurance agreements with any unauthorized reinsurer affiliated with or controlled by a licensed insurance producer, a creditor, or an affiliate, corporate parent, subsidiary, associate, director, officer, active or retired employee, or other representative of the creditor or the licensed insurance producer;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xv)</num>
            <text>Services, including an amount paid to an employee of the insurer specifically for services provided to a creditor or affiliate of the creditor if the services are normally performed outside the home office of the insurer, but not including services performed by account executives or liaison personnel of the insurer who visit the offices of the creditor at occasional intervals, are regular salaried officers or employees of the insurer, and receive no commission or other compensation directly dependent upon the amount of business obtained;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xvi)</num>
            <text>Value of training programs for employees of the creditor or insurance producer, excluding training of employees provided solely in connection with a program of credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance for the purpose of acquainting the creditor's employees with administrative procedures of the insurer when the salary of the employees during the training period is paid by the creditor;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xvii)</num>
            <text>Rental by the insurer of space or equipment from the insurance producer or creditor, excluding rentals not related to any insurance transaction on terms approved by the Commissioner;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xviii)</num>
            <text>Commission or some other form of compensation or remuneration in excess of what otherwise would be payable in connection with the sale of allied lines of insurance or other business, such as credit property insurance and maintenance warranties;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xix)</num>
            <text>Profit sharing plans;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xx)</num>
            <text>Bonuses;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xxi)</num>
            <text>Finders' fees; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xxii)</num>
            <text>Offers of share ownership in an agency or corporation at less than the fair market value.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>"Commission" does not include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The cost to the insurer of conducting a review performed under <cite path="|31|13|03|.21">Regulation .21 of this chapter</cite>; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Services performed by account executives or liaison personnel of the insurer who visit the offices of the creditor at occasional intervals, are regular salaried officers or employees of the insurer, and receive no commission or other compensation directly dependent upon the amount of business obtained.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Commissioner" means the Maryland Insurance Commissioner.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Consumer loans" means loans issued by lenders licensed under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfi">Financial Institutions Article, Title 11, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and made under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcl">Commercial Law Article, Title 12, Subtitle 3, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance" means insurance on a debtor that provides indemnity for payments that are due on a specific loan or other credit transaction while the debtor is involuntarily unemployed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Creditor-Paid Insurance.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Creditor-paid insurance" means insurance in which the creditor pays the insurance premium without separate charge to the debtor.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Creditor-paid insurance" does not include a transaction if:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The debtor is required to pay an identifiable charge or premium for credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>There is a differential in finance, interest, carrying, service, or other similar charge made to debtors who are in similar circumstances except for their insured or noninsured status.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>"Earned premiums at prima facie" means the premiums that would have been earned if all earned premiums had been written at prima facie rates.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>"Enroller" means a person:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Who enrolls individuals or issues certificates under group credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Who does not receive any form of commission, compensation, remuneration, or other benefit based on this activity; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Whose salary scale is not dependent on the volume of insurance.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>"Experience period" means 2 consecutive calendar years or, at the option of the insurer, 2 consecutive policy years under a group policy issued to one creditor or under one case.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>"Family leave" means an employer-approved temporary leave of absence due to one of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The birth of a child;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The placement of a child for adoption or foster care;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The need to care for a spouse, child, or parent, if the spouse, child, or parent has a serious health condition; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Any other event as may be defined in the policy and approved by the Commissioner.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>"Full time" means working for wages or salary for at least 30 hours per week.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>Insurance Producer.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Insurance producer" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|1-101">Insurance Article, §1-101(u), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Insurance producer" includes a person who:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Sells a group or individual policy of credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Receives any form of commission, compensation, remuneration, or other benefit based on enrolling individuals or issuing certificates under group credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>Involuntary Unemployment.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Involuntary unemployment" means involuntary loss of employment.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Involuntary unemployment" includes a loss of employment as a result of individual or mass layoff, termination by employer, organized labor dispute including general strike and lockout, or any other event defined by the policy.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>"Joint involuntary unemployment insurance" means credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance issued to two codebtors if both are jointly and severally liable for the debt which pays a full benefit as defined in the policy if either or both of the codebtors becomes eligible for benefits under the policy.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>"Loss ratio" means the ratio of incurred claims to premiums earned during a specified period.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>"New case" means an account in which the gross premiums before refunds and at prima facie premium rates exceed or may reasonably be expected to exceed $50,000 in the most recent policy year, but did not exceed $50,000 in the prior policy year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>"Monthly premium insurance" means insurance for which a separately identifiable insurance premium is paid each month.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>Plan of Benefits.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Plan of benefits" means credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance that provides benefits after either a 30-day elimination period or a 30-day retroactive waiting period, on either a single premium or monthly premium basis, and provides a maximum number of 6, 9, 12, 18, or 24 monthly benefits.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Plan of benefits" includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Each possible combination of waiting period, premium method, and maximum number of benefits; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Any other plan of benefits approved by the Commissioner.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(24)</num>
        <text>Policy Year.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Policy year" means, in the case of a group policy, the period between a policy anniversary and the next succeeding policy anniversary.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Policy year" means, in the case of an individual policy, a calendar year or a period of 12 consecutive months beginning from an anniversary of the opening of an account, as the insurer may elect.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(25)</num>
        <text>"Prima facie loss ratio" means the ratio of incurred claims to earned premiums at prima facie during a specified period.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(26)</num>
        <text>"Prima facie premium rates" means maximum applicable premium rates as authorized and promulgated by the Commissioner from time to time under <cite path="|31|13|03|.10">Regulation .10 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(27)</num>
        <text>Single Premium Insurance.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Single premium insurance" means insurance for which the debtor pays or finances the entire required premium in advance.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Single premium insurance" includes insurance if:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The creditor adds identifiable insurance charges or premiums for credit insurance to the indebtedness; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A direct or indirect finance, carrying, credit, or service charge is made to the debtor on the insurance charges or premiums.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(28)</num>
        <text>Unauthorized Reinsurer.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Unauthorized reinsurer" means any insurer meeting the qualifications of a nonadmitted accredited reinsurer.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Unauthorized reinsurer" does not include any insurer authorized to do business in this State or any insurer qualified under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|13-116">Insurance Article, §13-116, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|13|03|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Loss Ratio.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Benefits for policies issued under these regulations shall be deemed reasonable in relation to premiums if claims incurred under the policies result in, or may reasonably be expected to result in, a loss ratio of not less than 55 percent when premiums do not exceed prima facie premium rates.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>When the prima facie loss ratio exceeds 58 percent, the premiums shall be determined in accordance with the methods of <cite path="|31|13|03|.12">Regulation .12 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Rate Reduction.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>When the prima facie loss ratio is less than 52 percent:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A reduced premium rate shall be used that is calculated by dividing the prima facie loss ratio by 0.55 and multiplying the result by the prima facie premium rate; but</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Except as provided in <cite path="31|13|03|.05|C.|(2)">§C(2) of this regulation</cite>, the reduced premium rate may not be less than 40 percent of the prima facie premium rate.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>At the option of the insurer, a premium rate less than 40 percent of the prima facie premium rate may be used.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|13|03|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Statistics and Reporting Forms.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General Requirements. To permit the Commissioner to review the basis of prima facie premium rates and the basis of premium rates being charged on the case method, each insurer writing credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Maintain statistics relating to the insurer's Maryland business; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>File the statistics with the Commissioner in the form required by the Commissioner.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Case Filing Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An insurer shall file with the Commissioner the statistics:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>For each account that has qualified as a case for the 2 most recent policy years, not later than 120 days after the end of the second calendar year to which the statistics relate; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For all other business, including new cases, not later than June 30 following the close of the calendar year to which the statistics relate.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Each insurer writing credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance also shall file with the Commissioner:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Notice of each account that is a new case;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The identity of the creditor for each new case, including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The corporate name of the creditor;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Any "trading as" name used by the creditor;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The address and phone number of the creditor; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>The name of a contact person for insurance matters at the creditor; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The statistics for the most recent calendar year, certified by a responsible officer of the insurer, that would have been required under this regulation if the new case had been a case for each of the 2 most recent policy years.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An insurer shall file the information on a new case with the Commissioner not later than the June 30 following the close of the calendar year in which the account became a new case.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Use of Code Numbers.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In filing the information required by this section, an insurer may use a code number instead of the name and address of a creditor.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If an insurer uses a code number instead of the name and address of a creditor, the insurer shall submit a separate list that identifies the name and address of each creditor with the creditor's code number.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The list that identifies the name and address of each creditor with the creditor's code number is confidential commercial information under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-617">State Government Article, §10-617(d), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Reports required under <cite path="31|13|03|.06|B.|(1)|(b)">§B(1)(b) of this regulation</cite> shall be submitted on a calendar year basis.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>All reports, both those on a calendar year basis and those on the case method, shall be submitted separately for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each class of business;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Each premium payment method, single premium or monthly premium;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Each plan of benefits;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Single credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance and joint credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Family leave.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Every report filed with the Commissioner shall contain the following information:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Gross premiums written;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Refunds of premiums on terminated insurance;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Net premiums written;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Unearned premium reserve at beginning of period;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Unearned premium reserve at end of period;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Earned premiums, which equal <cite path="31|13|03|.06|E.|(1)">§E(1) of this regulation</cite> minus <cite path="31|13|03|.06|E.|(2)">§E(2) of this regulation</cite>, minus the result of <cite path="31|13|03|.06|E.|(5)">§E(5) of this regulation</cite> minus <cite path="31|13|03|.06|E.|(4)">§E(4) of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Earned premiums at prima facie;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Claims paid;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Claim reserve at beginning of period;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Claim reserve at end of period;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Claims incurred, which equal <cite path="31|13|03|.06|E.|(8)">§E(8) of this regulation</cite> plus the result of <cite path="31|13|03|.06|E.|(10)">§E(10) of this regulation</cite> minus <cite path="31|13|03|.06|E.|(9)">§E(9) of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Loss ratio, which equals <cite path="31|13|03|.06|E.|(11)">§E(11) of this regulation</cite> divided by <cite path="31|13|03|.06|E.|(6)">§E(6) of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Prima facie loss ratio, which equals <cite path="31|13|03|.06|E.|(11)">§E(11) of this regulation</cite> divided by <cite path="31|13|03|.06|E.|(7)">§E(7) of this regulation</cite>, rounded to two decimal places;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>Dividends and experience rating refunds;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>All other commissions, compensation, and remuneration to creditors or insurance producers;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>Total of §E(14) and (15) of this regulation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>Ratio of <cite path="31|13|03|.06|E.|(16)">§E(16) of this regulation</cite> divided by <cite path="31|13|03|.06|E.|(3)">§E(3) of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>Combined ratio, which equals the sum of <cite path="31|13|03|.06|E.|(12)">§E(12) of this regulation</cite> and <cite path="31|13|03|.06|E.|(17)">§E(17) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Every statistical report shall be certified by a responsible officer of the insurer and shall be accompanied by a statement certified by the president or other responsible officer of the insurer that the insurer has not paid or credited or provided commission as defined in this chapter in excess of the applicable maximum amounts specified in <cite path="|31|13|03|.15">Regulation .15 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|13|03|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Rate Changes and Creditor-Paid Insurance.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Premium rates under a group policy of credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance may not be increased more than once during the first policy year, and a subsequent increased rate may not be charged within 12 months of any prior change in rates.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Monthly Premium Insurance.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In a policy of monthly premium insurance, a change in rates may not be made effective until 31 days after all existing debtors in the group have been notified of any increased charge that they will be required to pay as a result of the change in rates.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The notice required by <cite path="31|13|03|.07|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite> shall be deemed to be satisfied if the insurer:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Notifies the creditor of the increased charge;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Provides the creditor with the necessary forms to be mailed by the creditor to the debtors advising them of the increased charge; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Verifies that the creditor has mailed the notices to the debtors.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An insurer may file for approval of policy forms and premium rates for creditor-paid insurance on a basis other than that established by these regulations upon a showing satisfactory to the Commissioner that the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Forms and rates meet the requirements of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin">Insurance Article, Title 13, Subtitle 1, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Rates are actuarially consistent with rates prescribed by this chapter for other forms of credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|13|03|.08">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Premium Rates by Case Method.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Case Comprising Two or More Accounts.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If an insurer has combined two or more accounts to establish a case, it may not add additional accounts or remove accounts from that case except with the permission of the Commissioner and under conditions that the Commissioner may specify.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When submitting an experience report for a case comprising two or more accounts, the insurer shall include a list of the names of each account included in the case.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Premium rates for each case shall be established by the insurer to afford a loss ratio of at least 55 percent if the resulting rates do not exceed prima facie premium rates, and may be established in accordance with the methods of <cite path="|31|13|03|.12">Regulation .12 of this chapter</cite> if the substitution of prima facie premium rates would result in a loss ratio in excess of 55 percent.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Existing Account with Rate Established by Case Method.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If an insurer acquires an existing account for which rates were established by another insurer by the case method, the new insurer shall use the same rates or rates not greater than those which were approved for use by the former insurer until the end of the existing experience period established by the former insurer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In reporting this account at the end of the experience period, the new insurer shall combine the experience of the former insurer with its own experience for the term of the experience period in order to determine subsequent rates for the account.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Reports.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Reports for each case shall be submitted by the insurer at the end of each experience period, together with a statement of the then-applicable premium rates proposed by the insurer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the premium rates proposed by the insurer for the case do not meet the loss ratio standards of <cite path="31|13|03|.08|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, the insurer shall make an appropriate premium reduction, to be effective on or before the 45th day after the date of filing of the experience report, unless, for good cause shown, the Commissioner approves a higher premium rate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the insurer does not propose to reduce premium rates in accordance with these regulations, the Commissioner shall notify the insurer and afford it a hearing to show cause to the Commissioner why the premium rate should not be reduced.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Commissioner shall notify the insurer in writing within 60 days after the filing of the experience report of the Commissioner's findings in regard to the premium rate which the Commissioner determines should be charged.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The insurer shall implement the rates determined by the Commissioner not later than 45 days after receipt of the Commissioner's notice of the rates that the Commissioner authorizes for the case.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Credit Involuntary Unemployment Benefit Insurance Case Experience and Application of Rate Adjustment Factor.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a plan of benefits for credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance qualifies as a case, whether consisting of accounts of one or more creditors, the case experience submitted by the insurer at the end of the experience period shall include the experience of all plans of benefits for credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance written by creditors comprising the case.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the experience of the case results in a downward rate adjustment, the insurer shall apply the rate adjustment factor to all plans of benefits for credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance written by the creditors comprising the case.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the experience of the case results in an upward rate adjustment, the insurer may apply the rate adjustment factor to all plans of benefits for credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance written by the creditors comprising the case.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Rounding Rate Calculations. Premium rates for credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance determined under this regulation shall be rounded to three decimal places per $10 of monthly benefit payable.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>General Premium Rate Standards and Increased Rates.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>With respect to all premium rates not eligible for filing in accordance with the case method, the Commissioner shall accept as meeting the standards of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|13-110">Insurance Article, §13-110(b)(1), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, those premium rate filings that do not exceed prima facie premium rates stated in <cite path="|31|13|03|.10">Regulation .10 of this chapter</cite> for the several categories of insurance described in <cite path="|31|13|03|.10">Regulation .10 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The prima facie premium rates in <cite path="|31|13|03|.10">Regulation .10 of this chapter</cite> are based on the assumption that a policy fee, policy issue fee, certificate fee, or other additional charge will not be made.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Premium rates for use with forms that have less restrictive provisions than those described in this chapter may not exceed the prima facie rates specified in <cite path="|31|13|03|.10">Regulation .10 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>All prima facie premium rates and standards and formulas for increased rates refer to individual policies and group certificates insuring single lives.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Joint Credit Involuntary Unemployment Benefit Insurance. For credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance issued to cover two debtors jointly, the premium for the involuntary unemployment insurance benefits may not exceed 1.80 times the premium that would be charged if one debtor alone were insured.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Application for Approval of Higher Rates.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>With respect to premium rates not eligible for filing in accordance with the case method, an insurer may file with the Commissioner an application for approval of rates higher than the prima facie premium rates for a single creditor or for one or more classes of business.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The application shall specify the basis for the increased rate requested and shall be accompanied and supported by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Credible statistics applicable to the business under consideration; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A demonstration that the requested rates are in conformity with, or less than, rates that would meet the guidelines for increased rates set forth in <cite path="|31|13|03|.12">Regulation .12 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Notice of Increased Rate.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Commissioner may grant approval of an increased rate for a stated period.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a period is not specified in the Commissioner's notice of approval, an approval by the Commissioner of an increased rate shall be effective for a period of 1 year.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|13|03|.10">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Prima Facie Premium Rates for Credit Involuntary Unemployment Insurance.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Prima Facie Single Premium Rates. The premiums charged for credit involuntary unemployment insurance policies having all policy provisions not less favorable to the insured debtor than those required by Regulation .l1 of this chapter may not exceed, on policies of credit involuntary unemployment insurance for which a single premium is charged in advance for the entire duration of the insurance and the indebtedness is repayable in equal installments, the amount shown in the table below for each $10 of the monthly benefit insured:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Prima Facie Single Premium Rates per $10 of Monthly Benefit Payable</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th>Number of Months in Which<br/>Indebtedness is Repayable</th>
                <th colspan="5">Benefits Retroactive 30 Day Waiting Period Maximum Number of Benefits Per Occurrence</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">6</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">9</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">12</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">18</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">24</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">9</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$ 1.276</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">12</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">1.816</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">2.185</td>
                <td/>
                <td/>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">24</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">3.926</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">4.862</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">5.466</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">6.216</td>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">36</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">5.964</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">7.447</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">8.443</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">9.687</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">10.584</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">48</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">7.933</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">9.943</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">11.318</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">13.039</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">14.307</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">60</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">9.833</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">12.353</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">14.095</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">16.276</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">17.902</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">72</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">11.668</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">14.680</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">16.776</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">19.401</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">21.373</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">84</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">13.441</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">16.928</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">19.364</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">22.420</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">24.725</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">96</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">15.152</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">19.098</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">21.864</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">25.334</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">27.962</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">108</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">16.805</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">21.194</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">24.279</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">28.149</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">31.088</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">120</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">18.401</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">23.218</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">26.610</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">30.864</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">34.107</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Prima Facie Single Premium Rates per $10 of Monthly Benefit Payable</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th>Number of Months in Which <br/>Indebtedness Is Repayable</th>
                <th colspan="5">Benefits not Retroactive 30 Day Elimination Period Maximum Number of Benefits per Occurrence</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">6</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">9</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">12</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">18</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">24</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">9</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$ 0.950</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">12</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">1.352</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">1.566</td>
                <td/>
                <td/>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">24</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">2.923</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">3.485</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">3.834</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">4.303</td>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">36</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">4.441</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">5.337</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">5.923</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">6.706</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">7.311</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">48</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">5.906</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">7.126</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">7.940</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">9.027</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">9.882</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">60</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">7.321</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">8.854</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">9.887</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">11.268</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">12.366</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">72</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">8.688</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">10.522</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">11.768</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">13.432</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">14.763</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">84</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">10.008</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">12.113</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">13.584</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">15.521</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">17.079</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">96</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">11.282</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">13.688</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">15.338</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">17.539</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">19.315</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">108</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">12.512</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">15.191</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">17.032</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">19.488</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">21.474</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">120</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">13.700</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">16.641</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">18.667</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">21.369</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">23.559</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Prima Facie Monthly Premium Rates.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>On policies of group credit involuntary unemployment insurance issued as monthly premium insurance, a monthly premium rate shall be used instead of the rates referred to in <cite path="31|13|03|.10|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The rates under this plan may not exceed those shown in the schedule immediately below.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The rate shall be applied to the amount of the monthly payment insured in that month regardless of the duration of the loan.</text>
      </para>
      <aftertext>Prima Facie Monthly Premium Rates per $10 of Monthly Benefit Payable</aftertext>
      <aftertext>
        <table>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Maximum Number of Monthly<br/> Benefits  per Occurrence</th>
              <th>Benefits Retroactive<br/> 30 Day Waiting Period</th>
              <th>Benefits not Retroactive<br/> 30 Day Elimination</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">6</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$0.184</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$0.137</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">9</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">0.233</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">0.167</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">12</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">0.268</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">0.188</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">18</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">0.312</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">0.216</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">24</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">0.346</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">0.239</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </aftertext>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If a credit involuntary unemployment policy, otherwise meeting the requirements of <cite path="|31|13|03|.11">Regulation .11 of this chapter</cite>, provides for payment of benefits in the event of family leave as defined in <cite path="|31|13|03|.04|B.|(15)">Regulation .04B(15) of this chapter</cite>, the insurer may charge a rate not to exceed 4 percent more than the rates in Regulations .09E, .10A or B, or .12B of this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The prima facie premium rates for credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance in this regulation apply to all premiums charged on or after the effective date of this chapter, for every class of business.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Rates Per $100 Outstanding Balance Per Month.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Rates stated as $0.xx per $100 outstanding balance per month shall be consistent with the above rates.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For example, if a credit card requires a minimum payment of 5 percent of the balance, a rate of $0.40 per $10 of monthly benefit may also be stated as $0.20 per $100 of outstanding balance because $10 is 5 percent of $200.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>As another example, if the minimum required payment is 3 percent of the outstanding balance, the $0.40 per $10 of monthly benefit rates translates to $0.12 per $100 of outstanding balance.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>For purposes of this section, the following formula may be used:</text>
        <text>M = R × 10 × P</text>
      </para>
      <aftertext>If: M = monthly rate per $100 of outstanding balance,</aftertext>
      <aftertext>R = rate per $10 of payment of term,</aftertext>
      <aftertext>P = the percent of the outstanding balance required by the creditor as the minimum monthly payment, but not less than 3 percent.</aftertext>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Underwriting Requirements for Insurance Prima Facie Premium Rates.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The prima facie premium rates in <cite path="|31|13|03|.10">Regulation .10 of this chapter</cite> assume that contracts providing credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance do not require evidence of individual insurability from any eligible debtor electing to purchase coverage except:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A requirement that the debtor has been employed full-time for not more than 30 days before the effective date of coverage;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A requirement that the debtor has not received notice of impending termination or layoff within 60 days before the effective date of coverage; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>That there are no age restrictions, except that coverage may be restricted based on age if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>There is credit health insurance coverage or credit life insurance coverage on the same debt;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The credit health insurance coverage or credit life insurance coverage is subject to an age restriction; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance is:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Subject to the same age restriction that applies to the credit health insurance coverage; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>If no age restriction applies to the credit health insurance, subject to the same age restriction that applies to the credit life insurance.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Regardless of individual policy or certificate amounts, for underwriting purposes it is assumed that the policy contains no exclusions except the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Voluntary forfeiture of salary, wages, or employment income;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Resignation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Retirement;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Loss of employment as a result of willful or criminal misconduct;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Loss of employment as a result of seasonal employment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Loss of employment as a result of disability;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Discharge from military; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Loss of self-employment without a declaration of bankruptcy, either of the debtor or of the debtor's business.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Acquisition of Existing Account.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If an insurer acquires an existing account providing involuntary unemployment benefits on a monthly premium basis or on another basis for which the debtor is charged monthly, the new insurer shall honor all claims for periods of involuntary unemployment commencing on or after the date of takeover and all claims after that which would have been paid under the former policy.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The original insurer shall honor all claims for periods of involuntary unemployment commencing before the date of takeover.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Guidelines for Increased Rates.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Applications to the Commissioner for higher than prima facie premium rates shall be accompanied and supported by credible statistics.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Approval of applications for increased rates shall depend on whether the requested rates are not greater than rates based on the standards in this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>On policies of credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance for which the prima facie loss ratio exceeds 58 percent, the rate shall be determined by the formula:</text>
      <text>((Prima Facie Loss Ratio - 0.55) (1.41) + 1)(Prima Facie Rate).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Premium rates for credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance determined under this regulation shall be rounded to three decimal places per $10 of monthly benefit payable.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Remittance of Premiums to Insurer.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Premiums shall be remitted to the insurer within 60 days of their due dates.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>For purposes of this chapter, the deposit of premiums to any demand deposit account with the creditor or affiliate and the continued retention of the premiums in the deposit account for more than 60 days may not be deemed remittance to the insurer.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|13|03|.14">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Refunds.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In event of termination of the insurance before the scheduled maturity date of the indebtedness, the insurer promptly shall refund or credit to the person entitled to it the appropriate portion of any premiums paid for the insurance.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In the case of monthly premium credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance, the amount of the refund or credit may not be less than the pro rata gross unearned premium.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Single Premium Credit Insurance.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In the case of single premium credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance, the amount of the refund or credit may not be less than the refund computed by the sum of the digits method commonly known as the Rule of 78.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The insurer may not reduce the amount of the refund based on the amounts of benefit paid.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Calculation.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At the option of the insurer, refunds under <cite path="31|13|03|.14|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> may be calculated on a daily or on a monthly basis, as may be elected in the filing made by the insurer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Refunds may be calculated on an approximate daily basis by interpolating pro rata between the values at the beginning and at the end of the month.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>For a calculation under <cite path="31|13|03|.14|D.|(2)">§D(2) of this regulation</cite>, the insurer shall assume that every month has 30 days.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If refunds are calculated on a monthly basis, a charge may not be made for a period less than 15 days elapsing since the last monthly installment due date. If the period elapsing since the last monthly installment due date is 15 days or more, a charge may be made for the full month.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A premium refund is not required under <cite path="31|13|03|.14|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> if the sum of the refunds on all insurance issued to the debtor by an insurer in connection with the loan would be less than $1.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If a refund or credit is due to the debtor in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|13-107">Insurance Article, §13-107(c)(3) </cite>or 13-112(b), Annotated Code of Maryland, the amount of refund or credit may not be less than the amount paid by the debtor, less the amount payable under any substituted or delayed coverage issued to the debtor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Death of Debtor. In the event of the death of a debtor who is covered for credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance may not be deemed to have terminated by the performance of the insurance contract by reason of the debtor's death; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The insurer shall make the appropriate refund for the credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance coverage that terminated at the date of death.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|13|03|.15">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Commission to Insurance Producers and Creditors.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>On all loans originating in Maryland, an insurer may not directly or indirectly pay, allow, or offer to pay any form of commission, as defined in <cite path="|31|13|03|.04|B.|(7)">Regulation .04B(7) of this chapter</cite>, in excess of the limits stated in this chapter on a form of credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance, regardless of whether the payment is made to a licensed insurance producer, a creditor, or an affiliate, corporate parent, subsidiary, associate, director, officer, active or retired employee, or other representative of the creditor or the licensed insurance producer.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The maximum commission payable to all payees on each policy of credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance may not exceed a total of 36 percent of prima facie premium rates.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A commission paid to a creditor, or an affiliate, corporate parent, subsidiary, associate, director, officer, active or retired employee, or other representative of the creditor, regardless of whether the payee is a licensed insurance producer, may not exceed 32 percent of prima facie premium rates.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Payment as described in <cite path="31|13|03|.15|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> does not preclude payment of commission to a licensed insurance producer not listed in <cite path="31|13|03|.15|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, if the total commission paid under <cite path="31|13|03|.15|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> and under this section does not exceed the maximum rate allowed in <cite path="31|13|03|.15|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Payment of Commission by Insurance Producer.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A licensed insurance producer proposing to pay commission to any payee listed in <cite path="31|13|03|.15|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> shall first inquire of the insurer whether any commission is being paid by the insurer to that payee on the same business.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The insurance producer may not pay that payee an amount which, if added to the amount paid by the insurer for the same business, would cause the payment to exceed the maximum rate allowed in <cite path="31|13|03|.15|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The insurer shall cooperate with the insurance producer in providing the information called for by this section.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Reinsurance Treaties.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>To permit the Commissioner to enforce the provisions of <cite path="|31|13|03|.15">Regulation .15 of this chapter</cite> with respect to that portion of commission defined by <cite path="|31|13|03|.04|B.|(7)|(a)|(xiv)">Regulation .04B(7)(a)(xiv) of this chapter</cite> and to permit the Commissioner to ascertain that there are no violations of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin">Insurance Article, Title 27, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and other applicable sections of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin">Insurance Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, a contract of reinsurance of credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance on loans originating in Maryland may not be entered into, or continued, after the effective date of this chapter unless approved by the Commissioner and unless the reinsurer is licensed in Maryland, qualifies under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|13-116">Insurance Article, §13-116, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or is an accredited reinsurer.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A person proposing to enter into a reinsurance treaty as described in this regulation or a person proposing to continue a treaty entered into before the effective date of this chapter shall submit the treaty to the Commissioner for the Commissioner's approval.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the Commissioner does not approve or disapprove the proposed or existing reinsurance treaty within 90 days after the date it is filed with the Commissioner, the treaty shall be deemed to be approved.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner may withdraw approval of a reinsurance treaty after a hearing held not less than 20 days after written notice to the insurer and the reinsurer.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.17</num>
    <heading>Prohibited Transactions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A person may not solicit, sell, or negotiate a group or individual policy of credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance unless the person is licensed as an insurance producer in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin">Insurance Article, Title 10, Subtitle 1, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Enroller.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An enroller may not receive any form of commission, compensation, remuneration, or other benefit based on the enroller's activity in enrolling persons in group policies of credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An enroller who is not also licensed as an insurance producer may not engage in soliciting, selling, or negotiating, or assist in soliciting, selling, or negotiating, an individual policy of credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Unfair Trade Practices.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An insurer or insurance producer may not engage in any of the following practices in connection with the solicitation, sale, or negotiation of credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance as an inducement to the sale of the insurance, and each of these practices is an unfair trade practice under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin">Insurance Article, Title 27, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Offering or granting to a creditor or to a person connected or affiliated with the creditor any special advantage or service not specified in the insurance contract;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Agreeing to deposit with a bank or financial institution money or securities of the insurer or the insurance producer with the design or intent that the deposit reduce or take the place of a deposit of money or securities that otherwise would be required of the creditor or an affiliate of the creditor by the bank or financial institution as a compensating balance or offsetting deposit for a loan or other advance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Allowing the creditor to retain premiums on credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance on policies issued to the creditor or on policies sold or collected by the creditor for more than 60 days after the due date of the premiums; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Depositing with the creditor or an affiliate of the creditor money or securities without interest or at a lesser rate of interest than is generally being paid by the creditor bank or financial institution to other depositors of like amounts.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Section C(1)(d) of this regulation may not be construed to prohibit the maintenance by an insurer or insurance producer of demand deposits or premium deposit accounts that are reasonably necessary for use in the ordinary course of the insurer's or the insurance producer's business.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If advance loan payments are made before the date of involuntary unemployment of the debtor on a loan covered by single premium credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance, or if the debtor, the beneficiary, or any other person makes payments on a loan after the date the debtor is first entitled to receive a benefit for involuntary unemployment, the insurer may not reduce the amount of payments that were scheduled to be paid under the provisions of the credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance policy because of these loan payments.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Benefit Eligibility Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Benefit eligibility requirements may not include a requirement that as of the date of loss of employment the insured debtor had been employed for a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Set number of hours per week; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Set period of time.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The insurer may require only that the insured debtor had been employed and that separation from employment was the result of involuntary unemployment as defined in Regulation .04B(18) this chapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance may not be permitted in a package sold to any individual who is not eligible for coverage on the date of the application for coverage.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Reeligibility Conditions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance policy may impose conditions upon which an insured debtor becomes reeligible for credit unemployment benefits after a period of receiving benefits.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If reeligibility conditions are required for full benefits for a subsequent period of unemployment, the conditions may not:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be more stringent than the initial eligibility conditions; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Require that the insured be actively at work for more than 30 consecutive days.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If an insured debtor has not satisfied the reeligibility requirement at the time of a subsequent unemployment, the unemployment shall be considered a continuation of the prior unemployment with no waiting period, with the maximum benefit period equal to the unused portion of the maximum benefit period for the prior unemployment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Return To Work.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a debtor was working full time on the date of involuntary unemployment and returns to work less than full time, the insurer shall consider the debtor to be involuntarily unemployed until the debtor returns to full-time employment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a debtor was working less than full time on the date of involuntary unemployment and returns to work less than full time, the insurer may consider the debtor to be no longer involuntarily unemployed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.18</num>
    <heading>Combinations of Coverages.</heading>
    <text>If an individual policy form or group policy form of credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance or a certificate form of group credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance is used to provide both single and joint coverage, the coverage in effect shall clearly and prominently be indicated in the schedule of benefits.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|13|03|.19">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.19</num>
    <heading>Notice to Debtors.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Notice of Termination.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a debtor is covered by a group credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance policy providing for payment of premiums to the insurer on a monthly premium basis, the policy shall provide that in the event of termination of the policy for any reason:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The insured debtor shall be given written notice of termination; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Except if replacement of the coverage by the same or another insurer in the same or greater amount takes place without interruption of coverage and a new certificate reflecting the replacement coverage is delivered to the insured debtor, coverage will continue for at least 31 days from the date of notice.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The notice of termination required by this section shall be given by the insurer unless the insurer is unable to identify the debtors, in which case it shall be given by the creditor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>There shall be a prominent notice printed or stamped close to the schedule of benefits in the certificate form that the insurance coverage will terminate if the group policy terminates.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>An insurer also may include notice of additional events that would lead to termination of insurance coverage if the events are approved by the Commissioner.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Notice that Benefit May Not Cover Installments.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance policy is issued under which the monthly benefit might not cover payment of the entire scheduled monthly loan installment or the total benefit might not cover payment of all of the unpaid scheduled installments under the loan even if the loan account and the insurance premiums are paid on a current basis, then there shall be a notice to this effect in the individual policy or in certificates of insurance issued under a group policy.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The notice under <cite path="31|13|03|.19|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite> shall be prominently printed or stamped close to the schedule of benefits in the policy and in the certificate form.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Other Notices. A policy or certificate of credit involuntary benefit insurance shall include a notice printed in or close to the schedule of benefits that clearly calls attention to any of the following limitations or requirements that are applicable to the policy or certificate:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Any evidence of insurability required for advances of credit;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Any limit on the number of monthly benefit payments that the insurance will provide per occurrence of involuntary unemployment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any limit on the number of monthly benefit payments that the insurance will provide over the term of the insurance;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The right of the insured to cancel credit involuntary unemployment benefit coverage that has been issued without canceling any other coverage that has been issued covering the same debt;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Any limit on the term of coverage;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Any limit on the amount of any monthly benefit payment that the insurance will provide over the term of the insurance;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Any limit on the aggregate of any monthly benefit payments that the insurance will provide over the term of the insurance; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Any requirement that the insured register with the Office of Unemployment Insurance or a recognized employment agency to be eligible for benefits.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.20</num>
    <heading>Benefits.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If a debtor has filed in accordance with the policy provisions a claim for benefits for which the insurer is liable under a credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance policy, the insurer shall pay any late charges accruing on the amount payable under the claim after the date the claim has been filed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>For monthly premium credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The amount of the monthly benefit payable on a revolving, open end, account shall be the greater of the minimum payment required by the creditor or 3 percent of the debt at the time of involuntary unemployment, subject to any policy maximum; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If involuntary unemployment occurs prior to the date of termination of the policy or prior to the date of termination of coverage of an insured debtor and if benefits would otherwise have been payable, benefits shall be paid as if coverage continued.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>For single premium and nonrevolving, closed end, monthly outstanding balance credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance, the amount of the monthly benefit payable shall be the scheduled payment required by the creditor, subject to any policy maximum.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>For purposes of this chapter, a claim shall be deemed filed if it is transmitted to the creditor, the insurer, or an insurance producer of the insurer.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Amount Due in Excess of Amount Due to Creditor.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An amount due under a credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance policy in excess of the payment due at the time of involuntary unemployment shall be paid by the insurer directly to the debtor, the designated second beneficiary, or the estate of the debtor, whichever is entitled to the payment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the insurer does not have the address of the person entitled to the excess amount, the insurer shall send a check payable to that person to the creditor for transmittal.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Claims shall be paid either by a check of the insurer, by a draft drawn upon the insurer, or by electronic transmission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The creditor may not be authorized to settle or adjust claims or to act as a claim representative for the insurer.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Benefits for a covered period of unemployment less than a full month shall be paid at a rate of 1/30 of a full monthly benefit for each day of unemployment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>The benefit payable under a joint credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance policy if only one debtor is receiving benefits may not be less than the benefit that would have been paid if both were eligible for benefits.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>If a policy requires registration with the Office of Unemployment Insurance or a recognized employment agency within a stated time period in order to be eligible for benefits:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The time period may not be less than 15 days; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the debtor registers after the stated time period has expired, benefits otherwise payable may not be denied for periods of unemployment after the registration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|13|03|.21">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.21</num>
    <heading>Review of Credit Operations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Review Required.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Every insurer transacting credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance business in Maryland shall conduct a review of each of its creditor accounts with respect to the credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance business of the creditor to ensure compliance with the insurance laws and regulations of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Unless a satisfactory review has been made within 2 years before the effective date of this chapter, the first review shall be made not later than 15 months after the effective date of this chapter or of the date of the initial credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance transaction between the creditor and the insurer, whichever is later.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>After review under <cite path="31|13|03|.21|A.|(2)">§A(2) of this regulation</cite>, a review shall be made not later than 36 months after the last preceding review.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The review shall include but need not be limited to a determination that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The proper premium charges to debtors are made by the creditor and remitted in a timely manner to the insurer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The proper refunds are being accurately calculated and promptly made by the creditor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All claims are being filed promptly and properly handled;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Amounts of insurance payable in excess of the amounts necessary to extinguish the indebtedness are properly calculated and reported to the insurer in proofs of loss; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The creditor is promptly and fairly processing complaints concerning its credit insurance operations and is maintaining proper procedures for, and records of, the complaints processed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Insurers shall retain copies of the reviews in their home offices for at least 5 years.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An insurer may retain copies of the reviews in paper, photographic, microprocessed, magnetic, mechanical, electronic, digital, or any other medium if the copies of the reviews are maintained in a manner that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is clear and legible;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Accurately represents the original document in its entirety, including any attachment to the document;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Is capable of producing a clean and legible hard copy of the original document; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Preserves evidence of any signature contained in the original document.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.22</num>
    <heading>Effective Date.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An individual policy, group policy, or group certificate of credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance not in conformity with this chapter may not be issued or continued to be used in connection with any loan made on or after the effective date of this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A premium in excess of that permitted by these regulations may not be charged for credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance, and a commission or other form of benefit may not be paid to insurance producers or creditors in excess of the premium and commission rates permitted under this chapter for credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance which is issued in connection with any loan made on or after the effective date of this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.23</num>
    <heading>Clerical Errors.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Excess Insurance.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a policy of credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance limits the involuntary unemployment benefits to stated policy maximums, the policy and certificates of insurance issued under a group policy shall provide that if the insured has been charged premiums for insurance in excess of the stated maximums, the insurer may terminate the excess insurance and refund all premiums paid by the debtor for the excess insurance.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The notice of termination of the excess insurance shall state that the premium paid by the debtor for the excess coverage shall be refunded to the person entitled to it.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A single premium credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance policy and certificate shall further provide that excess insurance shall remain in force if the insurer does not terminate the excess insurance within 60 days after the effective date of coverage or if the debtor suffers a covered loss within the 60-day period but before notification by the insurer of termination of the excess coverage.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A monthly premium credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance policy and certificate shall further provide that the excess insurance shall be in force for the period for which a premium was charged unless the excess insurance is cancelled before the occurrence of a loss.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Ineligible Debtor.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Misstatement of Age.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If a policy of credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance or certificate of credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance issued under a group policy contains an age restriction, the policy or certificate may allow the insurer to terminate the coverage and refund all premiums paid by the debtor if:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The debtor has misstated the debtor's age; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The debtor's true age is greater than the limiting age stated in the policy.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If a policy of credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance or certificate of credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance issued under a group policy contains an age restriction, the policy or certificate may not provide for an adjustment of premiums or benefits if:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The debtor misstates the debtor's age; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The debtor's true age is not greater than the limiting age stated in the policy or certificate.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a debtor's eligibility for credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance is subject to restrictions based on employment or other factors, the policy and certificates of insurance issued under a group policy shall provide that if insurance is issued to an ineligible debtor who has truthfully answered all eligibility questions, the insurer may terminate the insurance and refund all premiums paid by the debtor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The notice of termination of the insurance shall state that the premium paid by the debtor shall be refunded to the person entitled to it.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A single premium credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance policy and certificate shall also provide that the insurance shall remain in force if the insurer does not terminate the coverage within 60 days after the effective date of coverage or if the debtor suffers a covered loss within the 60-day period but before notification by the insurer of termination of the insurance.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A monthly premium credit involuntary unemployment benefit policy and certificate shall provide that the insurance shall be in force for the period for which a premium was charged unless the insurance is cancelled with not less than 31 days notice before the occurrence of a loss.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|13|03|.24">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.24</num>
    <heading>Change of Insurers Reporting Requirements Coverage and Rates.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Insurers That Cease to Offer Credit Involuntary Unemployment Benefit Insurance. Within 90 days after an insurer ceases to offer credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance through a case, the insurer shall notify the Commissioner of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The name or code number of the creditor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Each coverage no longer offered;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The date on which the coverage ceased to be offered; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The current approved premium rate applicable to each coverage no longer offered.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Insurers That Begin to Offer Credit Insurance.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At the end of a calendar year in which an insurer has begun to offer credit involuntary unemployment benefit insurance for which premium rates have not yet been established by the case method but for which a prior insurer submitted notification of a new case required by Regulation .06B(2) and (3) of this chapter, the insurer shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>File the report for the case required by <cite path="|31|13|03|.06|B.|(1)">Regulation .06B(1) of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Submit the insurer's experience and the experience of the prior insurer for the experience period even if the account did not qualify as a case for the most recent policy year.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An insurer that is required to submit its experience and the experience of a prior insurer under <cite path="31|13|03|.24|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite> shall submit the experience of each insurer:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Separately by year; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>As a total for a 2-year period.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Commissioner shall notify an insurer if a report for a case is required to be filed under <cite path="31|13|03|.24|B.|(2)">§B(2) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If an insurer begins to offer credit insurance through a case during an experience period for which premium rates were established for a prior insurer by the case method, the insurer shall certify to the Commissioner that the insurer will not charge premium rates that exceed the rates permitted under <cite path="|31|13|03|.08|E.">Regulation .08E of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If an insurer begins to offer credit insurance for a case after the end of a previously established experience period but before the effective date of new premium rates approved by the Commissioner based on that experience period, the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Commissioner shall, when new premium rates are established, send written notice of the new premium rates to the insurer, stating an effective date that provides the insurer at least 30 days notice; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Insurer shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Beginning not later than the effective date established by the Commissioner, use premium rates not greater than the new premium rates approved by the Commissioner; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>At the end of the experience period stated by the Commissioner, file the report for the case required by <cite path="|31|13|03|.06|B.|(1)">Regulation .06B(1) of this chapter</cite>, submitting the experience of the former insurer and the insurer's own experience for the term of the experience period in order to determine subsequent rates for the account.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>An insurer required to submit its experience and the experience of a former insurer under <cite path="31|13|03|.24|B.|(5)|(b)|(ii)">§B(5)(b)(ii) of this regulation</cite> shall submit the experience of each insurer:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Separately by year; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>As a total for a 2-year period.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>On the request of a succeeding insurer, a prior insurer promptly shall provide the succeeding insurer with any experience information of the prior insurer that the succeeding insurer needs to meet the requirements of this section.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|2-109">Insurance Article, §2-109 </cite>and Title 13, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-01-01">Effective date: January 1, 2003 (29:12 Md. R. 934)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-11-07"><cite path="|31|13|03|.04|B.">Regulation .04B</cite> amended effective November 7, 2016 (43:22 Md. R. 1223)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-11-07"><cite path="|31|13|03|.16|A.">Regulation .16A</cite> amended effective November 7, 2016 (43:22 Md. R. 1223)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
