<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Unorthodox Vehicles</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Constructed vehicle" means any vehicle which has been assembled by anyone other than a manufacturer of vehicles, and the chassis of another vehicle which has been assembled by a bona fide manufacturer was not used during the course of construction.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Reconstructed vehicle" means any vehicle which has been assembled from the chassis and other parts of vehicles which were originally constructed by bona fide manufacturers of vehicles.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Unorthodox Vehicle.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Unorthodox vehicle" means a vehicle which is unusual in design and which deviates from the types of vehicles required to be titled and registered under the provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr">Transportation Article, Title 13, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, regardless if the vehicle was assembled by a bona fide vehicle manufacturer or by any other person.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Unorthodox vehicle" includes motorized wheel chairs, minibikes, trail machines, beach buggies, dune buggies, and any other similar type of vehicle.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01-1</num>
    <heading>Incorporation by Reference.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following document is incorporated by reference.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Document Incorporated. 49 CFR §§571.101—571.302 (1993).</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Vehicles to be Registered as Class A Passenger Vehicles.</heading>
    <text>Constructed, reconstructed, or unorthodox vehicles to be registered as Class A passenger vehicles shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Be inspected and approved by an authorized Maryland inspection station before applying for title and registration;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Be equipped with the equipment and mechanisms required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr">Transportation Article, Title 22, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, which shall be inspected and approved by an authorized Maryland inspection station; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Comply with the provisions of 49 CFR §§571.101—571.302, which are incorporated by reference.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|15|05|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Vehicles to be Registered as Class D Motorcycles.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Constructed, reconstructed, or unorthodox vehicles to be registered as Class D motorcycles shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be equipped with the equipment and mechanisms required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr">Transportation Article, Title 22, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Comply with the provisions of 49 CFR §§571.101—571.302, which are incorporated by reference.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The owners of constructed, reconstructed, or unorthodox vehicles to be registered as Class D motorcycles shall certify that the vehicle complies with the provisions of <cite path="11|15|05|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Vehicles to be Registered as Class E Trucks.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Constructed, reconstructed, or unorthodox vehicles to be registered as Class E trucks shall meet the requirements in §§B—D of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The original design of the vehicle shall be for the purpose of transporting freight or merchandise and the use of the vehicle shall be restricted to that purpose.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Hauling Compartment.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A vehicle shall be built in such a manner as to provide a hauling compartment which shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be permanently attached to the vehicle;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Be separated from the passenger compartment; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Have a capacity of at least 12 cubic feet.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The trunk of a passenger vehicle or the rear portion of a station wagon, when the seats are folded down or removed, is not considered a hauling compartment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A vehicle shall be equipped with equipment and mechanisms which comply with the provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr">Transportation Article, Title 22, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and 49 CFR §§571.101—571.302, which are incorporated by reference.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-104">Transportation Article, §12-104(b), </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1973-02-15">Effective date: February 15, 1973</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1996-06-17">Chapter revised effective June 17, 1996 (23:12 Md. R. 872)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
