<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>14</num>
  <heading>Certificates of Title</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>The purpose of this chapter is to specify the documents and information needed for the Administration to issue a certificate of title for a vehicle and to clarify the Administration's policy regarding the refusal to issue a certificate of title for a vehicle if an applicant fails to furnish certain information or documents required by statute or regulation for the following title transaction types:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>New vehicles;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Used vehicles sold by a dealer;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Used vehicles sold or transferred from someone other than a dealer;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Used vehicles titled in the applicant's name in another jurisdiction and now being titled in Maryland;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Vehicles being titled as a result of a repossession;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Vehicles being titled as a result of a mechanic's lien;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Vehicles being titled as the result of a sheriff's sale;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Vehicles being titled by a court order;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Reconstructed vehicles;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Glider kits and kit cars;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Homemade trailers; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Kit trailers.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Administration" means the Motor Vehicle Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Applicant" means the person requesting a certificate of title for a vehicle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"ASED" means the Automotive Safety Enforcement Division of the Department of State Police.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Bill of sale" means a written statement certifying the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Ownership of something has been transferred; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Exchange of property for an agreed sum of money or other valuable consideration.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Certificate of Title.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Certificate of title" means a document evidencing ownership and commonly associated with motor vehicles.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Certificate of title does not include a salvage certificate.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Dealer" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|11-111">Transportation Article, §11-111, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Vehicle" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|11-176">Transportation Article, §11-176, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Vehicle identification number (VIN)” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|11-177">Transportation Article, §11-177, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>New Vehicles.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant for a certificate of title for a new vehicle shall provide the Administration with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A certificate of origin;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A completed application for a certificate of title;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A dealer's reassignment or reassignments;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A dealer's bill of sale; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>An odometer disclosure certification as required by <cite path="|11.13.06">COMAR 11.13.06</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Instead of a dealer's bill of sale, Maryland dealers may complete the purchase price certification on an application for a certificate of title or a dealer's reassignment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall refuse to issue a certificate of title if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The required documents are not furnished or the information is incomplete;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The seller's or applicant's signature is signed by an individual to whom power of attorney is granted and the writing granting the power of attorney is not furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The applicant is a trust and the trust agreement naming the trust and designating the trustee or trustees is not furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A transaction involves a bankruptcy and a copy of the court appointment for the bankruptcy trustee is not furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A transaction involves a legal dependent and a copy of a court appointment for the legal guardian is not furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>An error or alteration in the documents furnished has occurred and a letter of explanation or certified statement does not clarify the error or alteration to the satisfaction of the Administration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The lien holder to be recorded is someone other than a dealer or bona fide lending institution and a lien contract is not furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The vehicle is an unrecovered stolen vehicle and a letter from the insurance company requesting issuance of a title in order to satisfy the claim is not furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Certain documents are lost or omitted and the applicant fails to furnish:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A letter of indemnification which is subject to the approval of the Administration; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Photocopies of lost documents;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>The owner or purchaser is deceased and the personal representative, legatee, distributee, legal heir, or surviving spouse has not provided as required:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Letters of administration/testamentary;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A legal heir form; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A death certificate;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>For a mobile home, a receipt from the Compliance Division of the Comptroller of the Treasury, which shows that the retail sales tax has been paid on a mobile home, is not furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>The vehicle is an import and the following documents are not furnished:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>One of the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Appropriate U.S. Customs forms; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>If imported by a member of the U.S. military, Form DD788 or DD1252, and a copy of military orders or a Maryland driver's license; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the vehicle does not comply with U.S. Department of Transportation or U.S. Environmental Protection Agency requirements:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Receipts for conversion work, or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A bond release letter;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>The applicant has requested a replacement VIN but has not:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Furnished an application for an assigned VIN; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Had a VIN inspection completed by an authorized police officer in this State;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>The vehicle is a two-stage vehicle and both certificates of origin are not presented; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>The vehicle is purchased directly from a manufacturer and an invoice is not presented.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|15|14|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Used Vehicles Sold by a Dealer.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant for a certificate of title to be issued for a used vehicle sold by a dealer shall provide the Administration with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A properly assigned certificate of title or other acceptable ownership document from the jurisdiction in which the vehicle was last registered;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A completed application for a certificate of title;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A dealer's reassignment or reassignments;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A dealer's bill of sale;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Except for <cite path="11|15|14|.04|C.|(14)">§C(14) of this regulation</cite>, a Maryland safety inspection certificate; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>An odometer disclosure certification as required by <cite path="|11.13.06">COMAR 11.13.06</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Instead of a dealer's bill of sale, Maryland dealers may complete the purchase price certification on the application for a certificate of title or dealer's reassignment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall refuse to issue a certificate of title if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The required documents are not furnished or the information is incomplete;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The seller's or applicant's signature is signed by an individual to whom power of attorney is granted and the writing granting the power of attorney is not furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The applicant is a trust and the trust agreement naming the trust and designating the trustee or trustees is not furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A transaction involves a bankruptcy and a copy of the court appointment for the bankruptcy trustee is not furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A transaction involves a legal dependent and a copy of a court appointment for the legal guardian is not furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>An error or alteration in the documents furnished has occurred and a letter of explanation or certified statement does not clarify the error or  alteration to the satisfaction of the Administration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The lien holder to be recorded is someone other than a dealer or bona fide lending institution and a lien contract is not furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The vehicle is an unrecovered stolen vehicle and a letter from the insurance company requesting issuance of a title in order to satisfy the claim is not furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Certain documents are lost or omitted and the applicant fails to furnish:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A letter of indemnification which is subject to the approval of the Administration; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Photocopies of the lost documents;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>The owner or purchaser is deceased and the personal representative, legatee, distributee, legal heir, or surviving spouse has not provided:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Letters of administration/testamentary;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A legal heir form; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A death certificate;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>For a mobile home, a receipt from the Compliance Division of the Comptroller of the Treasury, which shows that the retail sales tax has been paid on a mobile home sold before January 1, 1989, is not furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>The vehicle is an import and the following documents are not furnished:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>One of the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Appropriate U.S. Customs forms; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>If imported by a member of the U.S. military, Form DD788 or DD1252, and a copy of military orders or a Maryland driver's license; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the vehicle does not comply with U.S. Department of Transportation or U.S. Environmental Protection Agency requirements:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Receipts for conversion work; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A bond release letter;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>The vehicle was subject to a security interest and a proper termination statement is not furnished:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>On a Maryland Notice of Security Interest Filing form;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>On a title;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>On a letter on the lien holder's letterhead; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>By electronic transmission from an approved vendor;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>Except for trucks with a gross vehicle weight of 1 ton or more, truck tractors, and freight trailers, which Maryland dealers may sell without an inspection, the vehicle was sold by a Maryland dealer and the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Vehicle's most current safety inspection is over 6 months old;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Vehicle has traveled more than 1,000 miles since the inspection certificate was issued; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Vehicle was sold uninspected for dismantling or rebuilding and the dealer has not furnished a statement to indicate that the vehicle was sold for dismantling or rebuilding;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>The ownership document is a salvage certificate from this State or another state and the inspection by a police officer in this State who is authorized to inspect salvage vehicles has not been furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>The applicant has requested a replacement VIN but has not:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Furnished an application for an assigned VIN; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Had a VIN inspection completed by an authorized police officer in this State; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>The ownership document is a salvage certificate branded "Not Rebuildable — Parts Only — Not To Be Retitled".</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Used Vehicles Sold or Transferred from Someone Other Than a Dealer.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant for a certificate of title for a used vehicle transferred from someone other than a dealer shall provide the Administration with a:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Properly assigned certificate of title or other ownership documentation acceptable to the Administration from the jurisdiction in which the vehicle was last registered; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Completed application for a certificate of title.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall refuse to issue a certificate of title if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The required documents are not furnished or the information is incomplete;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The seller's or applicant's signature is signed by an individual to whom power of attorney is granted and the writing granting the power of attorney is not furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The applicant is a trust and the trust agreement naming the trust and designating the trustee or trustees is not furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A transaction involves a bankruptcy and a copy of the court appointment for the bankruptcy trustee is not furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A transaction involves a legal dependent and a copy of a court appointment for the legal guardian is not furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>An error or alteration in the documents furnished has occurred and a letter of explanation or certified statements does not clarify the error or alteration to the satisfaction of the Administration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The lien holder to be recorded is someone other than a dealer or bona fide lending institution and a lien contract is not furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The vehicle is an unrecovered stolen vehicle and a letter from the insurance company requesting issuance of a title in order to satisfy the claim is not furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Certain documents are lost or omitted and the applicant fails to furnish:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A letter of indemnification which is subject to the approval of the Administration; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Photocopies of lost documents;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>The owner or purchaser is deceased and the personal representative, legatee, distributee, legal heir, or surviving spouse has not provided as required:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Letters of administration/testamentary;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A legal heir form; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A death certificate;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>For a mobile home, a receipt from the Compliance Division of the Comptroller of the Treasury, which shows that the retail sales tax has been paid on a mobile home sold before January 1, 1989, is not furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>The vehicle is an import and the following documents are not furnished:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>One of the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Appropriate U.S. Customs forms; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>If imported by a member of the U.S. military, Form DD788 or DD1252, and a copy of military orders or a Maryland driver's license; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the vehicle does not comply with U.S. Department of Transportation or U.S. Environmental Protection Agency requirements:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Receipts for conversion work, or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A bond release letter;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>The vehicle was subject to a security interest and a proper termination statement is not furnished:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>On a Maryland Notice of Security Interest Filing form;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>On a title;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>On a letter on the lien holder's letterhead; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>By electronic transmission from an approved vendor;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>The ownership document is a salvage certificate from this State or another state and the inspection by a police officer in this State who is authorized to inspect salvage vehicles has not been furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>The applicant has requested a replacement VIN but has not:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Furnished an application for an assigned VIN; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Had a VIN inspection completed by an authorized police officer in this State;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>The ownership document is a salvage certificate branded "Not Rebuildable — Parts Only — Not To Be Retitled";</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>The vehicle is less than 7 years old and the applicant:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Did not furnish a notarized bill of sale; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Refuses to pay excise tax based on the greater of the purchase price or the book value of the vehicle;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>The purchase price on the title is left blank and the applicant fails to produce a bill of sale;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>The assignment of ownership is signed by the seller, but:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The space provided for the purchaser's name is left blank; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A bill of sale is not furnished;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>A Maryland titled vehicle is transferred as a gift between family members and the applicant fails to furnish a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Gift certification form; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Proof of relationship certification;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>A vehicle with an open lien is transferred as a gift between a parent and child, and the transferor and transferee fail to furnish a statement signed by both parties, identifying the individual who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Paid the down payment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Paid the taxes;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Made all previous payments; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Incurred the obligation for continued payment; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>The vehicle is transferred as a result of a divorce and the divorce decree is not furnished.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Used Vehicles Transferred from Another Jurisdiction to Maryland.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant for a certificate of title for a used vehicle presently titled in the applicant's name in another jurisdiction and who is now applying for a Maryland certificate of title shall provide the Administration with an:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Out-of-State title or other acceptable ownership document from the jurisdiction where the vehicle was last registered; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Application for a Maryland certificate of title.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall refuse to issue a certificate of title if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The required documents and information are not submitted or are not complete;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The out-of-State title or other acceptable ownership document is held by a lien holder and the lien holder refuses to relinquish the title or other ownership document to the Administration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The ownership document presented to the Administration is a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Nonnegotiable title; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Memorandum title;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The application for a certificate of title is signed by an individual to whom power of attorney is granted and the writing granting the power of attorney is not furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The application is signed by a legal guardian and the court appointment is not furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The applicant's name has changed through marriage, divorce, court order, or other method and a change of name and address notice and proof of the name change such as a marriage certificate, divorce decree, or court order is not furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The vehicle previously had a salvage certificate issued in this State or another state and a VIN inspection has not been completed by a police officer of this State authorized to inspect salvage vehicles;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The vehicle was previously salvaged in this State or another state and has been branded "Parts Only — Not Rebuildable";</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>The vehicle is an import and the following documents are not furnished:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>One of the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Appropriate U.S. Customs forms; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>If imported by a member of the U.S. military, Form DD788 or DD1252, and a copy of military orders or a Maryland driver's license; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the vehicle does not comply with U.S. Department of Transportation or U.S. Environmental Protection Agency requirements:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Receipts for conversion work, or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A bond release letter;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>The applicant has requested a replacement VIN but has not:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Furnished an application for an assigned VIN number; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Had a VIN inspection completed by an authorized police officer in this State;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>An error or alteration in the documents furnished has occurred and a letter of explanation or certified statement does not clarify the error to the satisfaction of the Administration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Certain documents are lost or omitted and the applicant fails to furnish:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A letter of indemnification subject to the approval of the Administration; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Photocopies of lost documents; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>The ownership document is a salvage certificate branded "Not Rebuildable — Parts Only — Not to be Retitled", or with an equivalent term.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Vehicles Being Titled Because of Repossessions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant for a certificate of title for a vehicle which has been repossessed shall provide the Administration with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A Notice of Security Interest Filing form;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An out-of-State title or other ownership document acceptable to the Administration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A certification of repossession;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>An assignment of ownership or bill of sale;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>An odometer disclosure certification as required by <cite path="|11.13.06">COMAR 11.13.06</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A condition report; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>An application for a certificate of title.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall refuse to issue a certificate of title if the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Required documents are not furnished or information is incomplete;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Lien holder was a dealer or someone other than a bona fide lending institution and a clear copy of the lien contract is not furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Lien holder was not holding first position and a previous lien holder has not been released;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Vehicle was not titled in the debtor's name and the lien holder cannot furnish a copy of the contract;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Vehicle is titled in Maryland, but the security interest has not been perfected and the applicant cannot furnish a copy of a contract;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Applicant is not the secured party shown on the title and cannot furnish an assignment of lien;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Applicant is a dealer but the lien contract does not state that the dealer has full recourse for the secured party named in the contract;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Vehicle was titled out of State and the forms required by that state for repossession have not been furnished; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Lien contract does not contain:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The signature of all vehicle owners;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A full description of the vehicle; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A notation of the security interest.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|15|14|.08">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Vehicles Being Titled Because of Mechanic's Lien.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant for a certificate of title for a vehicle being titled due to a mechanic's lien shall provide the Administration with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A completed application for a certificate of title;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A certification by the garage owner or the person having the lien, and the auctioneer, including the odometer disclosure as required by <cite path="|11.13.06">COMAR 11.13.06</cite>, on a form provided by the Administration, that the auction was held in compliance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcl">Commercial Law Article, Title 16, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A digital photograph of the VIN;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A certification that a newspaper advertisement has run once a week for the 2 consecutive weeks immediately preceding the sale, in a newspaper of general circulation in the county or city where the vehicle was repaired or originally stored, with the last advertisement appearing the week immediately preceding the sale;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A copy of the newspaper advertisement required by <cite path="11|15|14|.08|A.|(4)">§A(4) of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A storage or repair order as specified in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcl|14-1008">Commercial Law Article, §14-1008, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, containing an affirmative request by the vehicle owner for the repair services or storage services requested or, if applicable, a written statement from the lienor that the lienor stored the vehicle in accordance with an agreement with an insurer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Signed receipts for a certified or registered letter in a format prescribed by the Administration sent to the individual who left the vehicle for repairs, the vehicle owner, the lien holder, and the MVA or the unopened, undeliverable certified or registered letter or letters; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The national vehicle history report.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall refuse to issue a certificate of title if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The required documents or information are not furnished or are incomplete;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The address on the returned, unopened certified or registered letter or letters sent to the vehicle owner, individual who left the vehicle for repairs, or lien holder is different from the Administration's most current records;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The receipt for the certified or registered letter sent to the owner, lien holder, or individual who left the vehicle for repairs was signed by someone other than the person to whom the letter was addressed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The provided national vehicle history report shows that the vehicle was stolen and the reporting police agency has not issued a recover report;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>There is a discrepancy or alteration in the paperwork and the letter of explanation or certified statements do not clarify the discrepancy to the satisfaction of the Administration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The signatures on the submitted documents or the application are signed by an individual to whom power of attorney is granted and the writing granting the power of attorney is not furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>A notarized bill of sale is not submitted and the customer refuses to pay the excise tax on the greater of the book value or the purchase price;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The digital photograph VIN is illegible;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>The vehicle was not advertised in a newspaper as specified in <cite path="11|15|14|.08|A.|(4)">§A(4) of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>The vehicle description by year, make, and VIN in the newspaper advertisement is different than in the supporting documents furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>The newspaper advertisement does not contain the time, date, place of auction, and description of the vehicle by year, make, and VIN;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>The vehicle was previously salvaged in this State or another state and the applicant fails to furnish a certification by a police officer in this State who is authorized to inspect salvage vehicles;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>The vehicle was previously salvaged in this State or another state, with a brand reflecting "Not Rebuildable — Parts Only — Not To Be Retitled" or an equivalent brand; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>The Administration has been notified that action in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcl|16-206">Commercial Law Article, §16-206, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, is being taken and that the Administration has received notification of the action before the close of the business day following the action.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Vehicles Being Titled Due to a Sheriff's Sale.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant for a title for a vehicle being titled due to a sheriff's sale shall provide the Administration with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A court order or writ directing the sale;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An application for a certificate of title;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A copy of the required newspaper advertisement; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A bill of sale from a sheriff.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall refuse to issue a certificate of title if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The required documents are not furnished or the information is incomplete;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The application for certificate of title is signed by an individual to whom power of attorney is granted and the writing granting the power of attorney is not furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The applicant is a trust and the trust agreement naming the trust and designating the trustee or trustees is not furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A transaction involves a bankruptcy and a copy of the court appointment for the bankruptcy trustee is not furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A transaction involves a legal dependent and a copy of a court appointment for the legal guardian is not furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The documents furnished contain an error or alteration and letters of explanation or certified statements do not clarify the errors or alterations to the satisfaction of the Administration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The lien holder to be recorded is someone other than a dealer or bona fide lending institution and a lien contract is not furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The vehicle is an unrecovered stolen vehicle and a letter from the insurance company requesting issuance of a title in order to satisfy the claim is not furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Certain documents are lost or omitted and the applicant fails to furnish:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A letter of indemnification which is subject to the approval of the Administration; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Photocopies of lost documents;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>The owner or purchaser is deceased and the personal representative, legatee, distributee, legal heir, or surviving spouse has not provided as required:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Letters of administration/testamentary;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A legal heir form; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A death certificate;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>For a mobile home, a receipt from the Compliance Division of the Comptroller of the Treasury, which shows that the retail sales tax has been paid on a used mobile home sold before January 1, 1989, is not furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>The applicant has requested a replacement VIN but has not:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Furnished an application for an assigned VIN; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Had a VIN inspection completed by an authorized police officer in this State;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>The previous ownership document was a salvage certificate and the inspection by a police officer in this State who is authorized to inspect salvage vehicles is not furnished; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>A security interest termination statement for liens on the previous Maryland title record is not furnished.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Vehicles Being Titled Because of Court Orders.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant for a title for a vehicle being titled as a result of a court order shall provide the Administration with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An application for a certificate of title; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A writ of mandamus or show cause order.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall refuse to issue a certificate of title if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The court order does not clearly indicate that the Administration is to take the ordered action;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A lien shows on the previous Maryland record and a security interest termination statement for each lien is not furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The vehicle is not fully described by year, make, and VIN;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A salvage certificate has been previously issued in this State or another state and an inspection from a police officer in this State authorized to inspect salvage vehicles is not furnished; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A salvage certificate had been previously issued containing the brand "Not Rebuildable — Parts Only — Not To Be Retitled" or an equivalent term.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Reconstructed Vehicles.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant for a certificate of title for a reconstructed vehicle shall provide the Administration with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An application for a certificate of title;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An application for an assigned VIN;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A certificate of title for the frame;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A bill of sale or a copy of the title for the body;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Receipts for parts and labor used to reconstruct the vehicle; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A garage inspection by an authorized police officer in this State.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall refuse to issue a certificate of title if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The required documents are not furnished or the information is incomplete;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A title for a vehicle less than 7 years old is being assigned to the applicant and the applicant:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Does not furnish a notarized bill of sale; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Refuses to pay excise tax on the book value of the vehicle;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An individual bringing the vehicle to the Administration for a garage inspection by the ASED does not furnish a power of attorney authorizing the individual to sign for the applicant;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The garage inspection reveals stolen parts; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A security interest termination statement has not been furnished for each lien shown on the Administration's records.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Glider Kits and Kit Cars.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant for a certificate of title for a vehicle constructed from a glider kit or a car kit shall provide the Administration with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An application for a certificate of title;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A certificate of origin for the kit;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A bill of sale for the kit;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A title for the frame;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Bills of sale or receipts for all parts and labor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>An application for an assigned VIN; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>A garage inspection at the Administration or, in the case of a glider kit, a certified statement that the vehicle was assembled by a Maryland licensed dealer or repair shop.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall refuse to issue a certificate of title if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The required documents are not furnished or the information is incomplete;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The individual bringing the vehicle to the Administration garage is not the applicant and cannot furnish a power of attorney authorizing the individual to sign for the applicant;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The garage inspection reveals stolen parts;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The application is being processed at a branch office of the Administration, and a statement certifying that the glider kit has been assembled by a Maryland licensed dealer or repair shop is not furnished;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A security interest termination statement has not been furnished for each lien shown on record; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A title for a vehicle less than 7 years old is being assigned to the applicant and the applicant:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Does not furnish a notarized bill of sale; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Refuses to pay excise tax on the greater of the book value or the purchase price of the vehicle.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Homemade Trailers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant for a certificate of title for a homemade trailer shall provide the Administration with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A rear view and a side view photograph of the trailer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Receipts for the parts used to build the trailer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A certified statement listing the parts used to construct the trailer and the total value of the trailer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>An application for an assigned VIN; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>An application for a certificate of title.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall refuse to issue a certificate of title if the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Required documents or information are not furnished or are incomplete;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Trailer is other than a boat, utility, or camping trailer which:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Weighs 10,000 pounds or less; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has not had an inspection completed by an authorized police officer in this State; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Homemade trailer was previously issued a Maryland-assigned VIN, and the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Maryland-assigned VIN has been lost; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Owner refuses to have the vehicle inspected by an authorized police officer in this State.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Kit Trailer.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant for a certificate of title for a kit trailer shall provide the Administration with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A certificate of origin;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An application for a certificate of title; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A bill of sale or receipt.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall refuse to issue a title if the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Required documents and information are not furnished or are incomplete; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Applicant's signature is signed by an individual to whom power of attorney is granted and the power of attorney is not furnished.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Vehicle Titled by Survivor When Co-owner is Deceased.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A joint tenant or joint tenants applying for a certificate of title by right of survivorship shall provide the Administration with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If the Maryland Department of Health has not made electronic notification to the Administration of the deceased, a certified death certificate for the deceased co-owner;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A completed application for certificate of title; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The title from the Administration bearing the names of the decedent and the applicant or applicants as co-owners.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall refuse to issue a title if the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Required documents and information are not furnished or are incomplete; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Applicant's signature is signed by an individual to whom power of attorney is granted and the power of attorney is not furnished.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-104">12-104</cite>(b), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-106">13-106</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-110">13-110</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1996-03-11">Effective date: March 11, 1996 (23:5 Md. R. 380)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-12-21"><cite path="|11|15|14|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective December 21, 2015 (42:25 Md. R. 1545)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-12-21"><cite path="|11|15|14|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite>, C amended effective December 21, 2015 (42:25 Md. R. 1545)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-12-21"><cite path="|11|15|14|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite>, C amended effective December 21, 2015 (42:25 Md. R. 1545)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-12-21"><cite path="|11|15|14|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective December 21, 2015 (42:25 Md. R. 1545)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-12-21"><cite path="|11|15|14|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective December 21, 2015 (42:25 Md. R. 1545)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-12-21"><cite path="|11|15|14|.07|A.">Regulation .07A</cite> amended effective December 21, 2015 (42:25 Md. R. 1545)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-12-21"><cite path="|11|15|14|.08">Regulation .08</cite> amended effective December 21, 2015 (42:25 Md. R. 1545)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-12-21"><cite path="|11|15|14|.09|B.">Regulation .09B</cite> amended effective December 21, 2015 (42:25 Md. R. 1545)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-12-21"><cite path="|11|15|14|.10|B.">Regulation .10B</cite> amended effective December 21, 2015 (42:25 Md. R. 1545)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-12-21"><cite path="|11|15|14|.11|A.">Regulation .11A</cite> amended effective December 21, 2015 (42:25 Md. R. 1545)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-12-21"><cite path="|11|15|14|.12|A.">Regulation .12A</cite> amended effective December 21, 2015 (42:25 Md. R. 1545)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-12-21"><cite path="|11|15|14|.13|A.">Regulation .13A</cite> amended effective December 21, 2015 (42:25 Md. R. 1545)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-12-21"><cite path="|11|15|14|.14|A.">Regulation .14A</cite> amended effective December 21, 2015 (42:25 Md. R. 1545)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-07-23"><cite path="|11|15|14|.15">Regulation .15</cite> adopted effective July 23, 2001 (28:14 Md. R. 1322)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-12-21"><cite path="|11|15|14|.15">Regulation .15</cite> amended effective December 21, 2015 (42:25 Md. R. 1545)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
