<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>18</num>
  <heading>Vehicle Registration Issuance by State Agencies or Political Subdivisions Acting as Agent for Motor Vehicle Administration</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>State Agency or Political Subdivision as Agent for Administration.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A State agency or political subdivision may act as the agent of the Administration in the registration of vehicles and in the issuance of registration plates, registration cards, and validation stickers.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A State agency or political subdivision shall adhere to the regulations contained in this chapter while acting as agent for the Administration in the issuance of registration plates, registration cards, and validation stickers.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Location Approval.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each State agency or political subdivision who acts as an agent for the Administration shall request prior approval of the location from which the issuance of registration plates, registration cards, and validation stickers shall be made.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Administration shall review and approve the location selected in order to ensure the ability to serve the public efficiently and effectively and to contain automated equipment for processing transactions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The State agency or political subdivision shall provide the Administration with the name of the supervisor in charge of the location or the name of the manager in charge of the program and update the names as necessary.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Issuance of Validation Stickers, Registration Cards, and Registration Plates.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall provide procedures for the issuance of registration plates, registration cards, and validation stickers by State agencies or political subdivisions to each State agency or political subdivision acting as an agent of the Administration. These procedures shall contain detailed processing and accounting requirements to be followed by each State agency or political subdivision.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="|11|15|18|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>, all fees collected from the issuance of registration plates, registration cards, and validation stickers shall be transmitted to the Administration.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Fees.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each State agency or political subdivision shall collect the fee specified on the registration application and an additional $1 fee for each transaction issued by it, of which 50 cents of each $1 collected shall be submitted to the Administration to offset administrative expenses incurred by the Administration. The remaining 50 cents of each $1 fee collected shall be retained by the State agency or political subdivision.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Each State agency or political subdivision may collect and retain an additional fee not to exceed $1 for each transaction issued by it to offset expenses incurred by the State agency or political subdivision in administering the program.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-104">12-104</cite>(b) and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-404">13-404</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-01-01">Regulations <cite path="|11|15|18|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|11|15|18|.03">.03</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective September 11, 1985 (12:20 Md. R. 1921); adopted permanently effective January 1, 1986 (12:26 Md. R. 2545)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1997-09-22"><cite path="|11|15|18|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective September 22, 1997 (24:19 Md. R. 1341)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1997-09-22"><cite path="|11|15|18|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective September 22, 1997 (24:19 Md. R. 1341)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1997-09-22"><cite path="|11|15|18|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective September 22, 1997 (24:19 Md. R. 1341)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
