<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>23</num>
  <heading>Special Registration Plates for Recipients of Combat-Related Armed Forces Medals and Honorably Discharged Veterans</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Administration, in cooperation with the U.S. Department of Defense, the Maryland Department of Veterans Affairs, and appropriate representatives of the various branches of the armed forces, shall maintain a list of combat-related medals which, when awarded to an individual who registers a vehicle in this State, qualify that individual for special registration under this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An individual who was honorably discharged from a branch of the armed forces of the United States may apply for special registration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An individual who is the surviving spouse, parent, child, or sibling of a person who served in the Armed Forces of the United States and lost their life may apply for special registration plates depicting the Gold Star.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Eligible Classes of Vehicles — Repealed.</heading>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Fees.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In addition to the annual registration fee required for a vehicle, a nonrefundable fee as set forth in <cite path="|11.11.05">COMAR 11.11.05</cite> shall be paid for special registration plates under this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The nonrefundable fee shall be assessed each time new or substitute special registration plates are issued.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Special Registration Number and Plates.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A special registration number as specified by the Administration and assigned under this chapter consists of a logo depicting the medal, the alpha characters CR, five numeric characters, and the name, initials, or abbreviation of the name of the medal awarded on the bottom of the special registration plates, unless otherwise specified in this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Individuals awarded the Medal of Honor or the Purple Heart or who are honorably discharged veterans shall be assigned special registration plates depicting the Medal of Honor and the alpha characters MH or a Purple Heart Medal and the alpha characters PH. The bottom of the special registration plates shall reflect the Medal of Honor or Purple Heart respectively.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Individuals who are honorably discharged veterans of the Armed Forces of the United States shall be assigned special registration plates depicting the American flag, the alpha characters HDV, and the words Honorably Discharged Veteran on the bottom of the plates.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Individuals awarded the Combat Infantry Badge shall be assigned special registration plates depicting the Combat Infantry Insignia, the alpha characters CIB, and the words Combat Infantry on the bottom of the plates.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Individuals who are veterans of World Ward II shall be assigned special registration plates depicting the World War II Victory Medal, the alpha characters WWV, and the words World War II Veteran on the bottom of the plates.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Special registration plates depicting the Gold Star shall have the alpha characters GS, and the words Gold Star on the bottom of the plates.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A special registration plate issued for a Class D motorcycle may not have the words describing the medal printed across the bottom of the plate.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Upon receipt of the special registration plates, the individual shall return previously issued registration plates to any Administration office for cancellation of the previous registration.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Certification of Combat-Related Medal.</heading>
    <text>The owner, co-owner, or lessee of the vehicle to be registered under this chapter shall provide proof that is satisfactory to the Administration with the application for registration as follows:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>For a combat-related registration, proof shall be one of the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Copy of military discharge record (Form DD 214);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Copy of permanent combat-related award certificate; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Written proof from the National Personnel Records Center that the owner, co-owner, or lessee of the vehicle has been awarded the combat-related medal or qualifies for other combat-related plates under this chapter;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>For an honorably discharged veteran registration, proof shall be a copy of the military record (Form DD 214) evidencing an honorable discharge; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>For a Gold Star registration, proof shall be one of the following;</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Copy of the application for a Gold Star Lapel Button (Form DD-3) approved by the Department of Defense;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Copy of the casualty report issued by the military indicating the name and date of death;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Copy of an overseas death certificate issued by the military indicating the name and date of death; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Self-certification by the applicant for a casualty that occurred in World War I, World War II, or the Korean War.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Cancellation of Registration.</heading>
    <text>The Administration has the right to suspend a registration granted under this chapter if the applicant for registration is found, after hearing, to have perpetrated a fraud against the Administration in obtaining the special registration.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Retention of Special Registration Plates.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A family member of the deceased owner of special registration plates issued under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-619">Transportation Article, §13-619</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland, may retain the special registration plate displayed on the front of the deceased owner's vehicle as a keepsake after providing satisfactory proof that the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Owner of the special registration plates is deceased;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Special registration plates have been cancelled or are expired; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Special registration plate with the validation tabs displayed on the rear of the deceased owner's vehicle has been surrendered to the Administration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A special registration plate retained under the provisions of this regulation may not be displayed on any vehicle.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-104">12-104</cite>(b) and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-619">13-619</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-07-09">Effective date: July 9, 1990 (17:13 Md. R. 1612)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-01-01"><cite path="|11|15|23|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended effective January 1, 1992 (18:25 Md. R. 2755)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-06-20" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|11|15|23|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|11|15|23|.04">.04</cite>, Special Registration Plates for Recipients of the Purple Heart, repealed, and new Regulations <cite path="|11|15|23|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|11|15|23|.06">.06</cite>, Special Registration Plates for Recipients of Combat-Related Armed Forces Medals, adopted effective June 20, 1994 (21:12 Md. R. 1061)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1997-12-29"><cite path="|11|15|23|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective December 29, 1997 (24:26 Md. R. 1759)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-01-09" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective January 9, 2000 (26:27 Md. R. 2015)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-07-30"><cite path="|11|15|23|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective July 30, 2018 (45:15 Md. R. 725)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-10-20"><cite path="|11|15|23|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective May 23, 2005 (32:10 Md. R. 925); October 20, 2008 (35:21 Md. R. 1825)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-10-20"><cite path="|11|15|23|.01|D.">Regulation .01D</cite> adopted effective October 20, 2008 (35:21 Md. R. 1825)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-07-30"><cite path="|11|15|23|.02">Regulation .02</cite> repealed effective July 30, 2018 (45:15 Md. R. 725)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-05-23"><cite path="|11|15|23|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective May 23, 2005 (32:10 Md. R. 925)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-10-20"><cite path="|11|15|23|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective May 23, 2005 (32:10 Md. R. 925); October 20, 2008 (35:21 Md. R. 1825)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-07-30"><cite path="|11|15|23|.04|H.">Regulation .04H</cite> repealed effective July 30, 2018 (45:15 Md. R. 725)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-10-20"><cite path="|11|15|23|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective May 23, 2005 (32:10 Md. R. 925); October 20, 2008 (35:21 Md. R. 1825)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-12-07"><cite path="|11|15|23|.07">Regulation .07</cite> adopted effective December 7, 2006 (33:24 Md. R. 1906)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
