<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>33</num>
  <heading>Vehicle Trade-In Allowance</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Applicability.</heading>
    <text>This chapter applies to the use of a dealer trade-in allowance to determine the total purchase price of a vehicle that is used to calculate the excise tax remitted when purchasing another vehicle.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>The purpose of this chapter is to establish the requirements and guidelines for calculating the total purchase price of a vehicle when there is a dealer trade-in allowance, as set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-809">Transportation Article, §13-809, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Administration" means the Motor Vehicle Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Certified selling price" means the full price of the vehicle purchased before the trade-in allowance is deducted.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Dealer" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|11-111">Transportation Article, §11-111, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Lease.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Lease" means a signed contract or agreement for the rental or leasing of a vehicle for more than 180 consecutive days.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Lease" includes a lease where the vehicle is intended or not intended as security as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|11-127">Transportation Article, §11-127</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Leased vehicle" means a vehicle acquired from a dealer, by the lessor, for lease of the vehicle to a lessee for payment under the terms and conditions of a lease.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Lessee" means a person or entity who, under the terms and conditions of a lease made at the time of acquisition from a dealer, has possession of the leased vehicle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Lessor" means a person or entity who, at the time of acquisition from a dealer, relinquished possession of the vehicle to a lessee under the terms and conditions of the lease.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Nonleased vehicle" means a vehicle in which a person or business entity holds both title to, and possession of, the vehicle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Taxable price" means the total purchase price as stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-809">Transportation Article, §13-809, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Trade-in" means a vehicle assigned to a dealer for the purpose of receiving a deduction in value that is applied to the purchase price of another vehicle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Trade-in allowance" means the amount determined by the dealer that is deducted from the purchase price of another vehicle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Total Purchase Price.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The total purchase price or taxable price of a vehicle is determined by the certified selling price agreed on by the buyer and the seller, including any dealer processing charges as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|15-311">Transportation Article, §15-311</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland, less an allowance for the trade-in. There is no other nonmonetary consideration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The taxable price of the vehicle shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The retail purchase price;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The shipping or freight charges;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>After manufacture items included with the vehicle at time of purchase; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Manufacturer rebates.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A dealer may not include the cost for any nontaxable items when determining the taxable price of the vehicle. Nontaxable items include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Dealer trade-in allowance;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Dealer discounts or rebates;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Extended warranties;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Mechanical repair contracts;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Federal excise tax;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Electronic registration fee; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Equipment installed to accommodate a disabled person.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|15|33|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Trade-in Allowance.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A dealer determines the trade-in allowance that is deducted from the purchase price of another vehicle.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A trade-in allowance may not be divided or deducted from the purchase price of more than one vehicle.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Only one traded-in vehicle can be applied to a sales transaction for purposes of the trade-in allowance deduction.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A vehicle titled in Maryland or out-of-State may be used as a trade-in.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If the vehicle traded-in is subject to a lien, the owner or co-owners of the vehicle are entitled to the full trade-in allowance, as stated in <cite path="11|15|33|.05|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, and deducted from the total purchase price. The trade-in allowance is not limited to the amount of equity the owner has in the vehicle.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If the trade-in allowance exceeds the trade-in value indicated in a national publication of used car values adopted for use by the Administration, the dealer shall provide documentation that satisfies the Administration that the higher trade-in value is justified. Documentation includes:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Evidence of the amount required to release the lien on the trade-in vehicle;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Evidence of the vehicle customization that increases the vehicle value;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A current valuation from an alternative national publication; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the traded-in vehicle has already been sold, the actual resale price of the trade-in vehicle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|15|33|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Applying the Trade-in Allowance.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>When applying a trade-in allowance to the certified selling price to determine the taxable price of the vehicle purchased, the dealer shall complete one of the following forms:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Application for Certificate of Title (VR-5);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Maryland Dealers Reassignment (VR-182);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Dealers Reassignment on the reverse side of the Maryland Certificate of Title (VR-2);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Dealer's or Auto Wreckers Re-Assignment on the reverse side of the Maryland Salvage Certificate (VR-108); or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Dealer's Reassignment on the reverse side of the Maryland Notice of Security Interest Filing (VR-2), if the dealer is selling a repossessed vehicle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>When applying a trade-in allowance, a dealer shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Complete the Maryland Dealer's Certification portion of the application for title; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide an original bill of sale showing the certified selling price and amount of the trade-in allowance.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The dealer shall determine and enter on the Maryland Dealer's Certification portion of the application for title:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The certified selling price;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The trade-in allowance;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The taxable price of the vehicle by deducting the amount of the trade-in allowance from the certified selling price;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The gross tax remitted by calculating the applicable excise tax rate times the taxable price; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>For licensed Maryland dealers, the net tax remitted by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Multiplying 0.6 percent times the gross tax remitted up to $12; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Subtracting the result from the gross tax collected.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>When the trade-in allowance is equal to, or higher than, the total purchase price, the excise tax shall be $0.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>When the excise tax is exempt under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-810">Transportation Article, §13-810, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or calculated as $0 as set forth in <cite path="11|15|33|.06|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>, no additional allowance or refund shall be given to the purchaser of the vehicle.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>When a certificate of title or a dealer reassignment is submitted without the required Maryland Dealer's Certification showing the trade-in allowance information on the form, a dealer shall submit with the certificate of title or a dealer reassignment:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A completed Application for Certificate of Title (VR-5) containing the required certification; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An original bill of sale showing the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Purchase price and the amount of trade-in allowance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Vehicle identification number of the trade-in vehicle; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>State in which the trade-in vehicle was last titled.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|15|33|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Qualifications for Trade-in Allowance.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A trade-in allowance under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-809">Transportation Article, §13-809(a)(3)(i), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, shall only apply when:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The owner or co-owner of the trade-in vehicle is the owner or co-owner of the vehicle being purchased; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The owner or co-owner of the trade-in vehicle is a relative as defined in <cite path="11|15|33|.07|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> of the owner or co-owner of the vehicle being purchased.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In this regulation, a relative means a spouse, son, daughter, grandchild, parent, sister, brother, grandparent, father-in-law, mother-in-law, son-in-law, or daughter-in-law of the owner or co-owner of the trade-in vehicle and is the owner or co-owner of the vehicle being purchased.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>For a relative who qualifies for a trade-in allowance, the dealer shall submit an application for a certificate of title to the Administration with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A completed application for Maryland Gift Certification (VR-103) certifying the relationship to the owner or co-owner of the trade-in vehicle and vehicle being purchased; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Proof of the relationship if the last names of the relatives are different.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A trade-in allowance may be applied when the owner of the trade-in vehicle is the primary beneficiary of an inter-vivos trust and the purchased vehicle is in the name of the inter-vivos trust.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Trade-in Allowance for Leased Vehicles.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A trade-in allowance under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-809">Transportation Article, §13-809(a)(3)(ii), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, may be applied to the purchase price of a leased vehicle if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The trade-in is in the same owner's name as the name of the lessee on the purchased vehicle; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The vehicle is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Owned by the same leasing company purchasing the vehicle;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Being assigned to the dealer; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Becoming a part of the dealers inventory for resale.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A trade-in does not include a vehicle acquired by a dealer but not assigned to a dealer.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-104">12-104</cite>(b), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-809">13-809</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-812">13-812</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-04-06">Effective date: April 6, 2009 (36:7 Md. R. 526)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-11-24"><cite path="|11|15|33|.05|A.">Regulation .05A</cite>, C amended effective November 24, 2014 (41:23 Md. R. 1374)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-11-24"><cite path="|11|15|33|.05|F.">Regulation .05F</cite> adopted effective November 24, 2014 (41:23 Md. R. 1374)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-11-14"><cite path="|11|15|33|.06|C.">Regulation .06C</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective August 18, 2011 (38:19 Md. R. 1146); amended permanently effective November 14, 2011 (38:23 Md. R. 1422)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
