<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>37</num>
  <heading>Temporary In-Transit Registration</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>This chapter establishes the criteria necessary for a nonresident of the State to apply for, and receive, a temporary in-transit registration for purposes of transporting a vehicle purchased in Maryland to the nonresident purchaser’s state of residence for titling and registration.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Application for Temporary In-Transit Registration.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A nonresident of the State who purchases a vehicle in the State and who wishes to transport the purchased vehicle to a jurisdiction outside the State for titling and registration shall apply for a temporary in-transit registration in a format prescribed by the Administration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An applicant for a temporary in-transit registration shall provide the Administration with a completed application, the required fee as set forth in <cite path="|11.11.05">COMAR 11.11.05</cite>, and proof of the following, as described in <cite path="|11|15|37|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Identity;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Residency;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Vehicle ownership; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Insurance.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Application for a temporary in-transit registration may be submitted through:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Administration; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A licensed title service agent.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Period of Validity.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A temporary in-transit registration shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be valid for a period of 14 days; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Indicate the expiration date.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration or a licensed title service agent may not issue more than one temporary in-transit registration for each vehicle sales transaction.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Required Proofs.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>As proof of identity, an applicant for a temporary in-transit registration shall furnish a valid driver’s license.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>As proof of residency, an applicant for a temporary in-transit registration shall complete a Verification of Residency form furnished by the Administration. The address reflected on the Verification of Residency form shall match the address reflected on the applicant’s driver’s license.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>As proof of vehicle ownership, an applicant for a temporary in-transit registration shall provide a properly assigned certificate of title or other ownership documentation acceptable to the Administration, as well as a bill of sale. If the vehicle is less than 7 years old, the bill of sale shall be notarized.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>As proof of insurance, an applicant for a temporary in-transit registration shall provide proof that the vehicle for which the temporary in-transit registration is to be issued is covered by the minimum amount of vehicle liability insurance required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|17-103">Transportation Article, §17-103, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-104">12-104</cite>(b) and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-405">13-405</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-07-01">Effective date: July 1, 2020 (47:13 Md. R. 641)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
