<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>06</num>
  <heading>Speedometer and Odometer on Passenger Cars and Light Trucks</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Components.</heading>
    <text>Speedometers and odometers, when inspected, shall have legible dials and calibrations and register speed and distance traveled in miles or kilometers, or both, and be connected and operable. When the odometer is calibrated only in kilometers, a written notice shall be posted on the instrument panel in full view of the driver, and the notice shall contain the formula for converting kilometers to miles. Example: “Kilometers” divided by 1.609 equals “miles”.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Service, Repair, or Replacement of an Odometer.</heading>
    <text>Nothing in this title prevents the service, repair, or replacement of an odometer, whether calibrated in miles or kilometers, provided the distance traveled that is indicated on the odometer remains the same as before the service, repair, or replacement. If the odometer is incapable of registering the same distance traveled before the service, repair, or replacement, the odometer shall be adjusted to read zero, and a notice in writing shall be attached to the left door frame of the vehicle by the owner, his agent, or the person performing the service, repair, or replacement specifying the distance traveled before repair or replacement of the odometer and the date on which it was repaired or replaced. Any removal or alteration of the notice shall be a violation of this regulation.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Odometer Disclosure Certification.</heading>
    <text>At the time of sale of a vehicle, the seller or transferor shall furnish the buyer an odometer disclosure certification which shall include the vehicle’s odometer reading and any reading which has been attached to the vehicle’s door frame in accordance with <cite path="|11|13|06|.02">Regulation .02 of this chapter</cite>. The odometer disclosure certification shall be presented to the Motor Vehicle Administration upon application for title.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Verification of Odometer Disclosure Certification.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Motor Vehicle Administration, upon receipt of the odometer disclosure certification, shall verify that the vehicle’s odometer reading included in the certification corresponds with the odometer reading on the application for title accompanying the certification.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If a vehicle has been repossessed, the Motor Vehicle Administration shall verify that any odometer reading on any documents submitted to the Motor Vehicle Administration corresponds with the odometer readings on both the application for title and the odometer disclosure certification.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Filing Odometer Disclosure Certification.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Upon verification that all odometer readings correspond, the mileage indicated on the odometer disclosure certification shall be assumed correct and made a part of the permanent record of the Motor Vehicle Administration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>As part of the permanent record, the Motor Vehicle Administration may not change the mileage reflected on the original title or any duplicate titles issued unless the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Ownership of the vehicle changes and a new odometer disclosure certification is submitted as required by <cite path="|11|13|06|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Motor Vehicle Administration determines that the actual mileage is greater than the mileage reflected in the original title or any duplicate titles, and the owner requests a change to the known actual mileage.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-104">12-104</cite>(b) and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|22-415">22-415</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland; 49CFR 580</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1975-12-24">Effective date: December 24, 1975 (2:29 Md. R. 1741)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-10-27"><cite path="|11|13|06|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective October 27, 2014 (41:21 Md. R. 1260)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-10-27"><cite path="|11|13|06|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective December 23, 1991 (18:25 Md. R. 2752); October 27, 2014 (41:21 Md. R. 1260)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1991-12-23"><cite path="|11|13|06|.04">Regulation .04</cite> adopted effective December 23, 1991 (18:25 Md. R. 2752)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-10-27"><cite path="|11|13|06|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective October 27, 2014 (41:21 Md. R. 1260)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1991-12-23"><cite path="|11|13|06|.05">Regulation .05</cite> adopted effective December 23, 1991 (18:25 Md. R. 2752)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-10-27"><cite path="|11|13|06|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective October 27, 2014 (41:21 Md. R. 1260)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
