<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>11</num>
  <heading>Load Covers</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope and Applicability.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>These regulations do not limit or supersede any other law or regulation concerning vehicle equipment or means of enforcing laws or regulations relating to vehicle equipment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>These regulations apply to a vehicle carrying loose material which is not otherwise exempted under <cite path="|11|13|11|.02">Regulation .02 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Exemptions.</heading>
    <text>A vehicle meeting the requirements of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|24-106">Transportation Article, §24-106</cite>.1(e)(1), Annotated Code of Maryland, and <cite path="|11|13|11|.04|A.">Regulation .04A of this chapter</cite> is exempt from the load cover requirements of these regulations.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Bed" means the load-carrying part temporarily or permanently attached to a vehicle and separated from the passenger compartment and fully enclosed on both sides by side boards or side panels, on the front, by a board or panel or by the cab of the vehicle and, on the rear, by a tailgate, board, or panel.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Enclosures” means the front, rear, and sides of a vehicle bed as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|24-106">Transportation Article, §24-106</cite>.1(d), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Load cover" means a device made of canvas or other type material authorized under Regulation .05 and used to enclose the open top of a vehicle bed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Loose material" means loose material as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|24-106">Transportation Article, §24-106</cite>.1(a), Annotated Code of Maryland, and <cite path="11.15.20.01">COMAR 11.15.20.01</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Safety equipment repair order” means a safety equipment repair order as defined in <cite path="11.14.01.01|B.|(30)">COMAR 11.14.01.01B(30)</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Securement hardware" means any device or equipment used to attach or secure a load cover on a vehicle bed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Vehicle" means a vehicle as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|11-176">Transportation Article, §11-176, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Load Covers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Load covers are not required on:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Any Class K (farm area) vehicle as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-935">Transportation Article, §13-935, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Any Class E (truck) vehicle registered or capable of being registered under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-917">Transportation Article, §13-917, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, regardless of the date of manufacture or how the vehicle is loaded provided the vehicle manufacturer's original design specifications for bed enclosures have not been altered to increase the vehicle's load carrying capacity;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any Class G (trailer) vehicle registered or capable of being registered under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-927">Transportation Article, §13-927, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, carrying loose material if the top of the load is not within 6 inches of the top of any enclosure it touches;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Any construction vehicle working within the confines of a public works construction work project site as outlined in the construction project's plans and specifications, provided the distance travelled does not exceed 1 mile or the distance specified in an extension granted by the Maryland Department of Transportation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Any construction vehicle or mining equipment while crossing a highway between construction or mining sites; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Within the Port of Baltimore for a distance not to exceed 1 mile, any vehicle carrying a load of loose material between a stockpile or storage facility and a vessel docked at the port.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Load covers are required when carrying loose material on a:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Class E (truck) vehicle registered or capable of being registered under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-917">Transportation Article, §13-917, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, on which the manufacturer's original design specifications for bed enclosures have been altered to increase the vehicle's load carrying capacity;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Class G (trailer) vehicle registered or capable of being registered under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-927">Transportation Article, §13-927, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, regardless of the date of manufacture, and carrying loose material if the top of the load of loose material is within 6 inches of the top of any enclosure it touches;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Vehicle not otherwise exempted after January 1, 1992 regardless of how the vehicle is loaded.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Covers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The cover shall be constructed of material which will prevent any part of the load from blowing, falling, or spilling out of the vehicle.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The cover shall be of sufficient size to fully cover the top of the vehicle bed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The cover shall be maintained in a manner to ensure the cover functions as designed. It shall be free of holes, rips, tears, or broken mesh which would permit any part of the load being hauled to blow, fall, or spill from the bed.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Cover Securement Equipment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A cover shall be secured to the vehicle bed in a manner to prevent:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Part of the vehicle load from blowing, falling, or spilling out of the vehicle;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The cover from blowing off the vehicle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Securement hardware shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Of sufficient strength to prevent the cover from blowing off the vehicle or permitting any part of the load from blowing, falling, or spilling out of the bed of the vehicle;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Maintained in a good state of repair.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Enforcement.</heading>
    <text>These regulations may be enforced in the same manner as the enforcement of other provisions of law or regulation relating to vehicle equipment. A safety equipment repair order may only be issued to a Maryland-registered vehicle.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Effective Dates.</heading>
    <text>This chapter applies to any vehicle after January 1, 1992, regardless of the date of manufacture, when carrying a load of loose material and the vehicle is not otherwise exempted under <cite path="|11|13|11|.02">Regulation .02 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-104">12-104</cite>(b), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|23-104">23-104</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|23-105">23-105</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|24-106">24-106</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1991-04-01">Effective date: April 1, 1991 (18:6 Md. R. 685)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-10-27"><cite path="|11|13|11|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective October 27, 2014 (41:21 Md. R. 1260)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-10-27"><cite path="|11|13|11|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective October 27, 2014 (41:21 Md. R. 1260)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-10-27"><cite path="|11|13|11|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite> amended effective October 27, 2014 (41:21 Md. R. 1260)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-10-27"><cite path="|11|13|11|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective October 27, 2014 (41:21 Md. R. 1260)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-10-27"><cite path="|11|13|11|.08">Regulation .08</cite> amended effective October 27, 2014 (41:21 Md. R. 1260)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
