<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Meningococcal Vaccination Requirements for Students in Institutions of Higher Education</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter applies to meningococcal vaccination of individuals enrolled in institutions of higher education who are living in on-campus student housing.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Enrolled" means having registered for a credit or noncredit course.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Institution of higher education" means a school of post-secondary education that generally limits enrollment to graduates of secondary schools and awards degrees at the associate, baccalaureate, or graduate level.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Meningococcal vaccination" means receipt of the vaccine protecting against at least the four serogroups of A, C, Y, and W-135 of meningococcal disease within the preceding 5 years before the individual moves into on-campus student housing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"On-campus student housing" means housing provided to individuals, regardless of the fee, that is owned, rented, or contracted for and operated by an institution of higher education, or through written agreement, with an agent of the institution of higher education.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Required Meningococcal Vaccination.</heading>
    <text>Except as provided in <cite path="|10|06|05|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>, an individual enrolled in an institution of higher education living in on-campus student housing shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Obtain a meningococcal vaccination; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Submit written documentation to the institution of higher education from a health care professional or clinic of receipt of a meningococcal vaccination.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Notification of Required Meningococcal Vaccination.</heading>
    <text>An institution of higher education shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Inform an individual or the parent or guardian of an individual younger than 18 years old of the requirement for meningococcal vaccination at the time the individual:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is accepted for admission to an institution of higher education; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Registers for classes, if the individual is not required to apply for admission before registering for courses;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Include notice of the requirement for meningococcal vaccination in:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Admission acceptance information;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Student health-related information and materials;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Resident life information and materials;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The student handbook; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The college catalog; and</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Provide detailed information to an individual who resides or may reside in on-campus student housing or the parent or guardian of an individual younger than 18 years old who resides or may reside in on-campus student housing concerning:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The risks associated with meningococcal disease; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The availability and effectiveness of meningococcal vaccine.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Exemption from Meningococcal Vaccination Requirement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An individual 18 years old or older is exempt from the meningococcal vaccination requirement set forth at <cite path="|10|06|05|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite> if the individual presents to the institution of higher education a signed written waiver as set forth in <cite path="|10|06|05|.06|A.">Regulation .06A of this chapter</cite> stating that the individual has:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Received and reviewed the information specified in <cite path="|10|06|05|.04|C.">Regulation .04C of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Chosen not to obtain the meningococcal vaccination.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An individual younger than 18 years old is exempt from the meningococcal vaccination requirement set forth at <cite path="|10|06|05|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite> if a signed written waiver as set forth in <cite path="|10|06|05|.06|B.">Regulation .06B of this chapter</cite> is presented to the institution of higher education on behalf of the individual stating that a parent or guardian of the individual has:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Received and reviewed the information specified in <cite path="|10|06|05|.04|C.">Regulation .04C of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Chosen not to have the individual obtain the meningococcal vaccination.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Waiver Form.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A waiver form for an individual 18 years old or older shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>State that the individual:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is 18 years old or older;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has received and reviewed the information provided by the institution of higher education on the risk of meningococcal disease and the availability and effectiveness of meningococcal vaccine; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Chooses to waive the receipt of meningococcal vaccine; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide spaces for the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Printed name of the individual;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Signature of the individual; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Date.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A waiver form for an individual younger than 18 years old shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>State that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The individual is younger than 18 years old;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The parent or guardian of the individual has received and reviewed the information provided by the institution of higher education on the risk of meningococcal disease and the availability and effectiveness of meningococcal vaccine; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The parent or guardian of the individual chooses to waive the receipt of meningococcal vaccine for the individual; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide spaces for the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Printed name of the individual;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Printed name of the parent or guardian;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Signature of the parent or guardian; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Date.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Payment for Meningococcal Vaccination.</heading>
    <text>Nothing in this chapter shall be construed to require an institution of higher education or a local public health agency to provide or pay for a meningococcal vaccination.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health-General Article, §18-102(b), Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-11-12">Effective date: November 12, 2001 (28:22 Md. R. 1937)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
