<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>09</num>
  <heading>Maryland Equity Investment Fund</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>These regulations prescribe the objectives and investment policy of the Maryland Equity Investment Fund, and the eligibility requirements, criteria, procedures, and guidelines for investment by the Maryland Equity Investment Fund.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Objective.</heading>
    <text>Through the Maryland Equity Investment Fund, TEDCO seeks to invest in qualified businesses with a goal to increase private equity and venture capital in the State that will have the potential to:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Generate financial returns to the benefit of the participants of the several pension systems managed by the State Retirement and Pension System; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Foster economic growth throughout the State.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Definitions</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Maryland Equity Investment Fund” means the investment program established by §10-487 of the Act.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Qualified business” has the meaning stated in §10-487(a)(4) of the Act..</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Investment Philosophy and Types of Qualified Businesses.</heading>
    <text>TEDCO seeks to invest in businesses that have demonstrated financial success and continued growth potential appropriate for subsequent venture investments or a public offering.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Eligibility.</heading>
    <text>TEDCO shall be satisfied that the applicant is a qualified business and meets the requirements under <cite path="14.04.02.04">COMAR 14.04.02.04</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Investment Criteria.</heading>
    <text>In General. In addition to the investment criteria set forth in <cite path="14.04.02.05">COMAR 14.04.02.05</cite>, TEDCO shall consider the following investment criteria:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Whether the market opportunity is appropriate for venture capital;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Whether the applicant, at the time it submits an application to TEDCO, is raising a minimum investment round of $2,000,000;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Whether the investment has the potential to generate returns of two times the amount of TEDCO’s invested capital not more than 8 years from the date of the investment;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Whether the applicant presents a plausible exit strategy for investors; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Whether the management team has the skills and ability to effectively secure an institutional venture investment concurrent with the investment of the Maryland Equity Investment Fund.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Procedures and Guidelines for Investment Decisions.</heading>
    <text>TEDCO shall select businesses for investment by the Maryland Equity Investment Fund in accordance with the application process set forth in <cite path="|14.04.02">COMAR 14.04.02</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gec|10-409">Economic Development Article, §10-409, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-09-18">Effective date: <strong>September 18, 2023 (50:18 Md. R. 800)</strong></annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
