<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>07</num>
  <heading>Testing of Equipment on School Vehicles</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Pilot Testing Program.</heading>
    <text>Notwithstanding the requirements of <cite path="|11.19.02">COMAR 11.19.02</cite> and <cite path="|11.19.03">11.19.03</cite>, the Administration may authorize the testing of equipment that would otherwise not meet the requirements of those chapters.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Administration" means the Motor Vehicle Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Equipment" means those furnishings or apparatus which improve vehicle safety or passenger comfort when installed on a school vehicle after manufacture.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Section" means the School Vehicle Safety Section, Division of Driver Licensing and School Vehicle Safety, Motor Vehicle Administration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Testing Requests.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A school bus owner, board of education, or manufacturer shall submit a written request to the Administration for equipment to be tested. The request shall contain:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The name, manufacturer, and model number of the equipment to be tested;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The vehicle identification number and name of the owner of the vehicle in which the equipment will be installed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A complete set of instructions and diagrams showing how the equipment shall be installed; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A list of persons outside the State who may be testing or using the equipment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Approval or Rejection of Testing Request. The Administration shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Issue a written approval or rejection for each test request; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Specify a time period for each approved testing request.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Testing of Equipment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Equipment that is prohibited by federal or State law may not be tested.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Equipment that may pose a danger to the public may not be tested.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Equipment may not be tested on vehicles that are mechanically unfit and unsafe to be operated on the highway.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Administration may place further restrictions on certain equipment, if necessary.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Approvals. Equipment may not be installed on a vehicle without the written approval of the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Administration; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Director of transportation, if the vehicle is operating for a public school system.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Testing Conditions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Vehicles.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A vehicle being used to test equipment shall be inspected and approved by the Section before the test period begins.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Testing is limited to the vehicle or vehicles specified in the approval.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration may limit the number of units of the same type and manufacturer to be tested.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Test Period.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Administration may specify test periods of different lengths for different types of equipment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The test period shall start immediately after installation of the equipment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>At or before the end of the test period, the Administration may:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Extend the test period;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Approve the equipment being tested for use on school vehicles operating in the State;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Reject the equipment being tested for use on school vehicles operating in the State;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Require the owner to remove the equipment being tested from the school vehicle for safety reasons; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Allow the equipment being tested to remain on the school vehicle or vehicles approved for the test without approval, as long as the equipment does not pose a danger to the public.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Approval.</heading>
    <text>If the Administration approves the equipment being tested, the Administration shall propose regulations to authorize the installation of the equipment on school vehicles in the State.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|19|07|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Reports.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The school bus owner, board of education, or manufacturer shall submit detailed reports on the performance of the equipment to the Section every 3 months, and shall include in the reports the manufacturer, model, and date of installation of the equipment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In addition to the reports required in <cite path="11|19|07|.07|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, the Administration may require other reports the Administration may consider necessary.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the vehicle is sold, the seller shall give copies of all reports, certifications, and correspondence concerning the equipment to the purchaser or purchasers of the vehicle.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-104">12-104</cite>(b) and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|25-110">25-110</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-02-15">Effective date: February 15, 1993 (20:3 Md. R. 260)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1996-09-09"><cite path="|11|19|07|.01">Regulation .01</cite> repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|11|19|07|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|11|19|07|.07">.07</cite> adopted effective September 9, 1996 (23:18 Md. R. 1318)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
