<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>08</num>
  <heading>Certified School Vehicle Inspection Facilities for Vehicles 12 Years Old or Older</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Administration" means the Motor Vehicle Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Certification" means a statement made under penalty of perjury, on a form provided by the Administration, which is evidence that a school bus complies with the standards established by the Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Certified facility" means a facility which has been certified by the Administration to perform inspections and issue certificates.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Certified inspector" means an inspector who is certified by the Administration to perform school bus inspections and sign certifications.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Immediate family" means mother, father, brother, sister, son, daughter, and spouse, including relationships established by adoption or marriage.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Owner of a certified facility" means an individual who owns or controls more than 5 percent of the facility.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"School bus" means a bus over 12 years old which is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>National school bus yellow;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Registered as a school bus; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Equipped with a warning light system.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Type A inspection" means an inspection of a school vehicle that includes the inspection of the items set forth in <cite path="|11.14.02">COMAR 11.14.02</cite> and <cite path="|11.14.04">11.14.04</cite> for Type I and Type II school vehicles.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Type B inspection" means an inspection of school vehicles which includes all items in a Type A inspection, except those which require pulling of wheels of the school vehicles.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Scope of Duties.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A certified facility may conduct a Type A or Type B inspection of a school bus.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A certified facility may not conduct an inspection of its own school vehicles.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A certified facility may not conduct an inspection of buses owned by members of the owner of the certified facility's immediate family.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Certifying Requirements for a Facility.</heading>
    <text>Before the Administration certifies a school bus inspection station to conduct inspections of school vehicles, the owner of the facility shall submit a written request for certification and the facility shall be inspected by the Administration before the issuance of certification.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Certification of Inspectors.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant seeking certification to conduct inspections in a certified facility shall submit an application to the Administration on a form required by the Administration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The application shall indicate the background of the applicant, including the education and experience of the applicant.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provide evidence of a minimum of 2 years experience in vehicle mechanics;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Pass the written test for inspector of school vehicles administered by the Administration or the Maryland State Police;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Pass a practical test administered by the Administration; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Pass a law test in which the inspector shall demonstrate familiarity with the regulations governing the inspection of school vehicles.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Facility Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A certified facility shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Have a garage with a concrete floor and a minimum dimension of 15 feet wide and 45 feet long; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Be equipped with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A wheel dolly for removing wheels from a bus,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A minimum of four heavy-duty jack stands and one 12-ton hydraulic jack or air jack, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The proper tools for removing wheels, drums, and rotors from the bus, including drum and disc micrometers.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A certified facility's inspection area shall be free of work benches, displays, machines, shelves, stairways, or other obstructions which could create a hazard.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Responsibilities of Owner.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An owner of a certified facility is responsible for the activities of certified inspectors and other persons employed by the certified facility.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A certified inspector may conduct inspections of school buses only at the station which employs the certified inspector.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Responsibilities of Certified Facilities.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A certified facility shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Maintain the following records for all school buses inspected:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Owner's name, address, telephone number,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Year and make of bus, including make of body,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>VIN number,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Bus number,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Tag number, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Odometer reading;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Permit only certified inspectors to perform inspections and sign certifications;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Notify the Administration if any changes to the inspection area have been made;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Issue certificates only after a complete inspection has been performed; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Notify the Administration if a certified inspector's employment with the certified facility ends.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A certified facility shall use only those forms provided by the Administration for school vehicle inspections.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>When a school vehicle fails an inspection, and the vehicle is removed from the inspection station, the certified facility shall notify the Administration.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Causes for Revocation of Certification.</heading>
    <text>A certification may be suspended or revoked if:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The owner of the certified facility or a certified inspector or other individual employed by the owner of a certified facility fails to comply with any requirements of this chapter or <cite path="|11.19.04">COMAR 11.19.04</cite>;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An applicant for certification misrepresents any material fact in an application submitted to the Administration;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The owner of the certified facility or a certified inspector misrepresents any material fact in a certificate submitted to the Administration;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The owner of the certified facility or a certified inspector fails to perform an inspection for which a certificate has been submitted; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A school vehicle is certified which does not meet the standards established in <cite path="|11.14.02">COMAR 11.14.02</cite> and <cite path="|11.14.04">11.14.04</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-104">12-104</cite>(b) and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|25-110">25-110</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-03-14">Effective date: March 14, 1994 (21:5 Md. R. 404)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
