<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>04</num>
  <heading>Evaluation of Professionally Certificated Personnel</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Evaluation" means a written appraisal of professional performance for a school year based on written criteria and procedures.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Professionally certificated personnel" means individuals holding a professional certificate as defined in COMAR 13A.12.01.02B.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Minimum Requirements for Evaluation of Professionally Certificated Personnel.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General Standards.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An evaluation shall be based on written criteria established by the local board of education, including but not limited to scholarship, instructional effectiveness, management skills, professional ethics, and interpersonal relationships.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An evaluation shall provide, at a minimum, for an overall rating.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An overall rating that is not satisfactory or better is considered unsatisfactory.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>An evaluation shall be based on at least two observations during the school year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>An unsatisfactory evaluation shall include at least one observation by an individual other than the immediate supervisor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The written evaluation report shall be shared with the certificated individual who is the subject of the evaluation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The certificated individual shall receive a copy of and sign the evaluation report.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The signature of the certificated individual does not necessarily indicate agreement with the evaluation report.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>An evaluation shall provide for written comments and reactions by the individual being evaluated, which shall be attached to the evaluation report.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Frequency of Evaluations.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Standard Professional Certificate. An individual holding a Standard Professional Certificate shall be evaluated at least once annually.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Advanced Professional Certificate.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An individual holding an Advanced Professional Certificate shall receive an evaluation at least twice during the validity period of each certificate. The first evaluation shall occur during the initial year of the certificate.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An individual holding an Advanced Professional Certificate who receives an unsatisfactory overall rating shall be evaluated at least once annually until receiving a satisfactory rating.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If an individual holding an Advanced Professional Certificate receives an overall rating of satisfactory or better, subsequent annual performance shall be considered satisfactory in the absence of an annual evaluation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Minimum Requirements for Observation of Professionally Certificated Personnel.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An observation, announced or unannounced, shall be conducted with full knowledge of the certificated individual.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A written observation report shall be shared with the certificated individual within a reasonable period of time.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An observation shall provide for written comments and reactions by the individual being observed, which shall be attached to the observation report.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Appeal of an Evaluation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In the event of an overall rating of unsatisfactory, the local school system shall, at a minimum, provide certificated individuals with a meaningful appeal in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|4-205">Education Article, §4-205(c)(4), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If an observation report is a component of an unsatisfactory evaluation, the observation report may be appealed along with the unsatisfactory evaluation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The burden of proof is on the certificated individual appealing an overall rating of unsatisfactory.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|2-205">2-205</cite>(b), (e), and (g), 4-205(c), and 6-202; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date: March, 1969</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-01-15"><cite path="|13A|07|04|.01">Regulation .01</cite>, Professional Employees Organizations, repealed effective January 15, 1989 (15:27 Md. R. 3136)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-12-05" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|13A|07|04|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|13A|07|04|.04">.04</cite> adopted effective December 5, 1994 (21:24 Md. R. 1989)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
