<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>07</num>
  <heading>Tuition Reimbursement for Retraining Teachers in Mathematics or Science</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Eligibility Criteria and Standards for Reimbursement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Eligibility Criteria. To be eligible for the program of tuition reimbursement for retraining, an applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be currently employed as a teacher in a Maryland public school system;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Be presently certified in a field other than mathematics or science;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Declare an interest in being certified in mathematics or science in a Maryland public school system; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Agree, with the consent of the local board of education, as specified in §C, of this regulation, to teach mathematics or science in a Maryland public school system for at least 2 years following certification in mathematics or science.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Standards for Reimbursement. An individual accepted in the tuition reimbursement program shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Obtain from the State Department of Education an evaluation of the individual's credentials to determine what requirements the applicant shall complete to become certified in mathematics or one of the five certification fields of science;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide this evaluation to the State Scholarship Board for use in determining when the individual has completed the certification requirements and is eligible for reimbursement; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Complete either the courses remaining for certification or not less than 12 semester hours per year toward the certification field.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Consent of the Local Board of Education. Before acceptance into the program by the State Scholarship Board, the applicant's local board of education shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>File a letter of consent with the State Scholarship Board indicating approval for the individual to participate in the program; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Assure in the letter of consent that the funds for this program may not be used to supplant funds of any other program.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Surety Bond. Before reimbursement by the State Scholarship Board, a teacher shall execute a surety bond to this State which shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be in the total amount of tuition reimbursement;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Guarantee to the satisfaction of the State Scholarship Board that the teacher will teach in a Maryland public school for at least 2 years after certification; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Provide a basis for reimbursement in the case of default.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|18-1501">Education Article, §18-1501, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-01-27"><cite path="|13A|07|07|.01">Regulation .01</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective May 31, 1985 (12:13 Md. R. 1275); emergency status expired November 1, 1985; adopted permanently effective January 27, 1986 (13:2 Md. R. 138)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
