<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>10</num>
  <heading>Comprehensive Principal Induction Program</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter applies to a comprehensive induction program for new principals. The purpose of this regulation is to provide guidance for local school systems to establish a high quality induction program that addresses critical professional learning needs of new principals, improves instructional quality, and helps inductees achieve success in their initial assignments, resulting in improved student learning and higher retention in the profession. The induction program that each local school system designs shall reflect coherence in structure and consistency in focus to ensure an integrated, seamless system of support. Recognizing that "one-size-fits-all" induction programs do not meet the needs of new principals, these regulations establish the components of an induction program, allowing local school systems to build on their current programs.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Incorporation by Reference.</heading>
    <text>In this chapter, the following document is incorporated by reference:</text>
    <text>Maryland Instructional Leadership Framework, 2005, which has been incorporated by reference in COMAR 13A.07.09.03.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Mentee" means a public school principal who is the recipient of the services of a mentor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Mentor" means an individual who possesses the attributes set forth in <cite path="|13A|07|10|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"New principal" means a principal who is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>New to the position; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A veteran who is new to the local school system.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Executive officer” means a principal's supervisor who evaluates the principal in accordance with COMAR 13A.01.04.02.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>General Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each local school system shall have a comprehensive induction program for new principals. Such programs should be differentiated based on the needs of the principal and should include such components as:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A locally designed orientation program for all principals new to the principalship and/or local school system;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Ongoing support from a mentor; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Appropriate levels of staffing to plan and coordinate all induction activities.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>All principals new to the position or to the local school system shall participate in induction activities in year one. Beyond year one, participation in induction activities will be a local decision.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>To the extent practicable given staffing and fiscal concerns, local school systems shall consider minimizing system-wide responsibilities in the new principal’s first year.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Mentoring Component of the Comprehensive Induction Program.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A local school system shall identify full-time or part-time mentors to support principals during their comprehensive induction period.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In collaboration with the mentor, the new principal shall identify areas for focus of his/her professional growth.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Mentors shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Demonstrate a knowledge base and skills to address the performance evaluation criteria and outcomes to be met by each mentee; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Have been a principal and have been rated as satisfactory or effective or be a retiree from a local school system and have been rated as a satisfactory or effective principal.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Local school systems shall provide ongoing training for mentors as appropriate.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Evaluation of the Comprehensive Induction Program.</heading>
    <text>Local school systems shall evaluate the effectiveness of the comprehensive induction program.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Date of Compliance.</heading>
    <text>Local school systems shall be in full compliance with this chapter by July 1, 2014.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Reporting Requirements.</heading>
    <text>By September 1, 2014, and each 5 years after, each local school system superintendent shall certify to the State Superintendent of Schools that the Comprehensive Principal Induction Program meets the minimum requirements set forth in this chapter.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|2-205">2-205</cite>(b), (c), and (g) and 6-202(b), Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-04-01">Effective date: April 1, 2013 (40:6 Md. R. 475)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
