<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Executive Orders</prefix>
  <num>2025</num>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Governor’s Office of Community Initiatives</heading>
    <text class="center">(Rescinds Executive Orders <cite path="01.01.2004.57">01.01.2004.57</cite>, <cite path="01.01.2007.18">01.01.2007.18</cite>, <cite path="01.01.2007.19">01.01.2007.19</cite>, <cite path="01.01.2007.21">01.01.2007.21</cite>, <cite path="01.01.2007.22">01.01.2007.22</cite>, <cite path="01.01.2007.25">01.01.2007.25</cite>, <cite path="01.01.2009.07">01.01.2009.07</cite>, <cite path="01.01.2012.11">01.01.2012.11</cite>, and <cite path="01.01.2012.17">01.01.2012.17</cite>)</text>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Governor’s Office of Community Initiatives</text>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>The Governor’s Office of Community Initiatives (“GOCI”) shall include the following units, created by Executive Order: the Governor’s Commission on African Affairs, the Governor’s Commission on Asian and Pacific American Affairs, the Governor’s Commission on Caribbean Affairs, the Governor’s Commission on Hispanic and Latin American Community Affairs, the Governor’s Commission on Middle Eastern American Affairs, and the Governor’s Commission on South Asian American Affairs (together, the “Ethnic Commissions”), and any other commission designated by the Governor as a unit of GOCI.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>GOCI also houses the legislatively created Commission on Indian Affairs, Commission on LGBTQIA+ Affairs, and Governor’s Office of Immigrant Affairs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>Executive Director. GOCI shall be managed by an Executive Director, who serves at the pleasure of the Governor.  The Executive Director shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>Supervise, direct, manage, and coordinate the Ethnic Commissions designated in Section 1.A of this Order;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>Provide administrative supervision and support to the legislatively created units designated in Section 1.B of this Order;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>3.</num>
          <text>Direct community initiatives across State government and coordinate with federal and local governments, private sector entities, academia, and community organizations to strengthen community engagement; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>4.</num>
          <text>Represent the Governor on boards, forums, and councils as appropriate.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>D.</num>
        <text>Staffing.</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>GOCI shall be composed of staff appointed by the Executive Director, with the approval of the Governor.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>GOCI staff serve at the pleasure of the Executive Director, subject to the concurrence of the Governor.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>E.</num>
        <text>Duties. GOCI shall be responsible for the following activities:</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>Conducting a review of State programs in cooperation with appropriate State departments and agencies to identify legislative and regulatory barriers that impede the effectiveness of community organizations to deliver results-based social services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>Advising the Governor on policies and measures to enhance and improve the delivery of services to ethnic, immigrant, and faith-based communities;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>3.</num>
          <text>Conducting public outreach on behalf of the Governor to encourage greater involvement and participation by community organizations and constituent groups;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>4.</num>
          <text>Reviewing State and federal legislation to assist in the identification of funding opportunities for community organizations to implement initiatives that benefit the State of Maryland; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>5.</num>
          <text>Serving as principal liaison to the faith-based community and associated organizations.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>F.</num>
        <text>All State departments, agencies, commissions, and boards are directed to cooperate with GOCI in implementing the provisions of this Executive Order.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>G.</num>
        <text>Reports. By December 31 of each year, GOCI shall submit an annual report to the Governor on its activities.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>II.</num>
      <text>Ethnic Commissions</text>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>There are the following Ethnic Commissions within GOCI:</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>The Governor’s Commission on African Affairs;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>The Governor’s Commission on Asian and Pacific American Affairs;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>3.</num>
          <text>The Governor’s Commission on Caribbean Affairs;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>4.</num>
          <text>The Governor’s Commission on Hispanic and Latin American Community Affairs;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>5.</num>
          <text>The Governor’s Commission on Middle Eastern American Affairs; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>6.</num>
          <text>The Governor’s Commission on South Asian American Affairs.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Membership.</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>Each Ethnic Commission shall consist of fifteen (15) voting members appointed by the Governor.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>The Commission members shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>a)</num>
            <text>Reflect the diverse ancestry and national origins of the respective communities of Maryland; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>b)</num>
            <text>Provide representation from different geographic regions in the State.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>3.</num>
          <text>Members shall serve at the pleasure of the Governor consecutive four-year terms.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>4.</num>
          <text>If a member is appointed to a vacant seat with less than two years remaining in a term, such service does not count as a full term.  Such a member is eligible to serve two additional four-year terms.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>5.</num>
          <text>A Commission member holds a seat until a successor is appointed.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>6.</num>
          <text>The Governor shall designate a Chairperson and Vice Chairperson from among the members of the Commission. The Chairperson and Vice Chairperson shall serve at the pleasure of the Governor.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>7.</num>
          <text>In the event of a vacancy on a Commission, the Governor shall appoint a successor.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>8.</num>
          <text>Commission members are subject to the direction of the Executive Director and serve at the pleasure of the Governor.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>Eligibility and Appointment.</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>Members of the Ethnic Commissions shall demonstrate an affinity to the diasporic community that the commission represents. A Commission member may demonstrate affinity by being:</text>
          <para>
            <num>a)</num>
            <text>An immigrant of a diasporic community;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>b)</num>
            <text>A descendant of a diasporic community;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>c)</num>
            <text>A proven advocate for the interests of a diasporic community;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>d)</num>
            <text>A scholar or educator of the history of a diasporic community;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>e)</num>
            <text>An expert on issues important to a diaspora community; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>f)</num>
            <text>A former resident of a diasporic community.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>In making appointments to the Ethnic Commissions, the Governor shall consider the demographic and geographic diversity of the State.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>D.</num>
        <text>Procedures.  The following procedures govern the Ethnic Commissions:</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>The Commissions are public bodies subject to the Open Meetings Act.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>The Commissions shall meet at the call of the Chairperson, in coordination with GOCI, at least six times each year. Sufficient notice of meetings shall be published to encourage public attendance.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>3.</num>
          <text>The Commissions shall hold at least one administrative planning session each year for onboarding and scheduling purposes.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>4.</num>
          <text>A majority of the Commission members then serving shall constitute a quorum for the transaction of any business.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>5.</num>
          <text>The Commissions may adopt such other procedures and by-laws as may be necessary to ensure the orderly transaction of business.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>6.</num>
          <text>The Commissions may create committees or subcommittees subject to the approval of the Executive Director.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>7.</num>
          <text>By June 30th of each year, the Commissions shall submit an annual report to the Governor detailing the activities in the preceding calendar year, along with any appropriate recommendations.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>E.</num>
        <text>Expenses. Ethnic Commission members may not receive any compensation for their services, but may be reimbursed for reasonable expenses incurred in the performance of their duties, in accordance with the Standard State Travel Regulations, and as provided in the State budget.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>F.</num>
        <text>Operational Support. GOCI  shall provide publication, operational, and other support as needed to the Ethnic Commissions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>G.</num>
        <text>Duties. The Ethnic Commissions shall have the following duties and responsibilities:</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>Serve as an advisory body to the Governor and agencies within the Executive Department on matters relating to the Commission’s diasporic community within Maryland, including matters relating to economic, workforce, and business development domestically and abroad;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>Identify needs or problems affecting the Commission’s diasporic community, and make recommendations to the Governor on appropriate responses and programs;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>3.</num>
          <text>Conduct outreach to the Commission’s diasporic community groups within the State, and communicate information to them concerning public and private programs that are beneficial to their interests;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>4.</num>
          <text>Review and provide recommendations to the Governor on any proposed federal, State, or local legislation, regulations, policies, or programs that affect the Commission’s diasporic community of Maryland;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>5.</num>
          <text>Make recommendations to the Governor on matters affecting the health, safety, and welfare of the Commission’s diasporic community of Maryland; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>6.</num>
          <text>Perform any other duties that may be requested by the Governor or the Executive Director.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>H.</num>
        <text>The diasporic communities of the Ethnic Commissions are as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>Governor’s Commission on African Affairs: The diasporic countries of the Governor’s Commission on African Affairs include, but are not limited to: Algeria, Angola, Benin, Botswana, Burkina Faso, Burundi, Cameroon, Cabo Verde, Central African Republic, Chad, Comoros, Cote d’Ivoire, Democratic Republic of the Congo, Djibouti, Equatorial Guinea, Eritrea, Eswatini, Ethiopia, Gabon, Gambia, Ghana, Guinea, Guinea-Bissau, Kenya, Lesotho, Liberia, Libya, Madagascar, Malawi, Mali, Mauritania, Mauritius, Morocco, Mozambique, Namibia, Niger, Nigeria, Rwanda, Sao Tome and Principe, Senegal, Seychelles, Sierra Leone, Somalia, South Africa, South Sudan, Sudan, Tanzania, Togo, Tunisia, Uganda, Western Sahara, Zambia, Zimbabwe.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>Governor’s Commission on Asian and Pacific American Affairs: The diasporic countries, territories, and states of the Governor’s Commission on Asian and Pacific American Affairs include, but are not limited to: Brunei, Cambodia, China, Cook Islands, East Timor, Federated States of Micronesia, Fiji, Guam, Hawaii, Hong Kong, Indonesia, Japan, Kazakhstan, Kiribati, Kyrgyzstan, Laos, Lord Howe Island, Macau, Malaysia, Melanesia, Micronesia, Mongolia, Myanmar, Norfolk Island, North Korea, Oceanic islands of the Eastern Pacific, Palau, Papua New Guinea, Philippines, Polynesia, Republic of Marshall Islands, Samoa, Singapore, Solomon Islands, South Korea, Taiwan, Tajikistan, Thailand, the Revillagigedo Islands, Tonga, Turkmenistan, Tuvalu, Uzbekistan, Vanuatu, Vietnam.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>3.</num>
          <text>Governor’s Commission on Caribbean Affairs: The diasporic countries of the Governor’s Commission on Caribbean Affairs include, but are not limited to: Anguilla, Antigua and Barbuda, Aruba, the Bahamas, Barbados, Belize, Bermuda, the British Virgin Islands, Cayman Islands, Cuba, Dominica, Dominican Republic, Grenada, Guadeloupe, Haiti, Jamaica, Martinique, Montserrat, Netherlands Antilles, Puerto Rico, St. Barths, St. Kitts and Nevis, St. Lucia, St. Martin, St. Vincent, Trinidad and Tobago, Turks and Caicos.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>4.</num>
          <text>Governor’s Commission on Hispanic and Latin American Community Affairs: The diasporic countries of the Governor’s Commission on Hispanic and Latin American Affairs include, but are not limited to:  Argentina, Bolivia, Brazil, Argentina, Bolivia, Chile, Columbia, Costa Rica, Ecuador, El Salvador, Equatorial Guinea, French Guyana, Guatemala, Guyana, Honduras, Mexico, Nicaragua, Panama, Paraguay, Peru, Spain, Uruguay, Venezuela.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>5.</num>
          <text>Governor’s Commission on Middle Eastern American Affairs: The diasporic countries of the Governor’s Commission on Middle Eastern American Affairs include, but are not limited to: Bahrain, Cyprus, Egypt, Iran, Iraq, Israel, Jordan, Kuwait, Lebanon, Oman, Palestine, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, Syria, Turkey, United Arab Emirates, Yemen.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>6.</num>
          <text>Governor’s Commission on South Asian Affairs: The diasporic countries of the Governor’s Commission on South Asian Affairs include, but are not limited to: Afghanistan, Bangladesh, Bhutan, India, Maldives, Myanmar, Nepal, Pakistan, Sri Lanka.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2025-01-07">Effective Date: January 7, 2025.</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Statewide Digital Infrastructure Group</heading>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Establishment.</text>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>There is a Digital Infrastructure Group (“DIG”) in the Department of Information Technology (“DoIT” or the “Department”) whose purpose is to coordinate the efficient deployment of wired and wireless communications and digital information technology infrastructure among the various State, County and local partners.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>The Chair of the DIG shall be designated by the Secretary of DoIT (“Secretary”) and shall serve at the pleasure of the Secretary.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>II.</num>
      <text>Responsibilities.</text>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>The DIG shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>Develop, promote, and facilitate a Statewide vision for wired and wireless communications and digital information technology infrastructure;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>Promote collaboration among State, County and local agencies for the management and deployment of wired and wireless communications and digital information technology infrastructure;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>3.</num>
          <text>Communicate current and future wired and wireless communications and broadband infrastructure plans to relevant stakeholders;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>4.</num>
          <text>Develop recommendations for long-range plans for wired and wireless communications and broadband infrastructure consistent with State goals, objectives, and DoIT’s Statewide Information Technology Master Plan;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>5.</num>
          <text>Develop recommendations for policy, regulations, or legislation to facilitate strengthening Maryland’s wired and wireless communications, broadband, and information technology infrastructure;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>6.</num>
          <text>Advise on the planning, funding, and development of Statewide wired and wireless communications, broadband, and information technology infrastructure projects proposed by units of State government;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>7.</num>
          <text>Identify opportunities for productive partnerships and the use of new technologies, including public-private partnerships, that enable the sharing of resources and further the goal of expanding and strengthening Maryland’s wired and wireless communications, broadband, and information technology infrastructure; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>8.</num>
          <text>Ensure best management practices are employed for the use of State resources, assets, licenses, and funding and that these uses are consistent with State goals and objectives as well as DoIT’s Statewide Information Technology Master Plan.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>III.</num>
      <text>Composition.</text>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>The DIG shall be composed of senior State officials from DoIT, designated by the Secretary, and senior staff members from the following agencies or units of State Government, designated by the respective agency or unit head:</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>The Maryland State Police (MSP);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>The Maryland Department of Transportation and its Transportation Business Units (MDOT &amp; TBU’s);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>3.</num>
          <text>The Maryland Institute for Emergency Medical Services Systems (MIEMSS);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>4.</num>
          <text>The Department of Natural Resources (DNR);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>5.</num>
          <text>The Governor’s Office of Homeland Security;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>6.</num>
          <text>The Department of Housing and Community Development (DHCD);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>7.</num>
          <text>The Maryland Public Broadcasting Commission (MPT);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>8.</num>
          <text>The Department of General Services (DGS);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>9.</num>
          <text>The Maryland Department of Emergency Management (MDEM);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>10.</num>
          <text>The Department of Budget and Management (DBM);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>11.</num>
          <text>The Office of the Statewide Interoperability Coordinator (SWIC); and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>12.</num>
          <text>The Statewide Interoperability Executive Committee (SIEC).</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>The Secretary may appoint additional members from units of State and local governmental entities as necessary.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>The Secretary may establish one or more working groups and or subcommittees as necessary in support of the DIG.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>IV.</num>
      <text>Contributions, Goals, and Objectives.</text>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>In consultation with the DIG, DoIT shall create a “Single View” of State-owned wired and wireless communications, broadband, and information technology infrastructure inventory inclusive of all inground, aerial and vertical assets.  The “Single View” will include, at a minimum, each Executive Branch agency's qualifying assets and all approved Resource Sharing Agreement installations.  The “Single View” shall be used for long-range planning, joint build projects, promoting Resource Share Agreement (RSA) opportunities and in support of broadband and digital infrastructure expansion.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>DIG members shall share wired and wireless communications, broadband, and information technology infrastructure data with the Department to be included in the “Single View” that shall facilitate the consideration of how and where future wired and wireless infrastructure is deployed in the State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>In consultation with DIG, DoIT shall aggregate the various information technology policy-related advice generated by the various Executive Branch agencies, Statewide Interoperability Executive Committee, Statewide Interoperability Coordinator, and State Radio Control Board in order to provide recommendations and advice to the Secretary.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>D.</num>
        <text>DIG members shall seek opportunities to strategically plan and design a shared infrastructure model that effectively manages public real property information technology corridors and efficiently uses monetary resources to generate cost savings.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>E.</num>
        <text>Ensure DIG priorities are considered when evaluating RSA opportunities.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>F.</num>
        <text>Improve broadband access and digital equity across the State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>G.</num>
        <text>Address last-mile connectivity, particularly in rural areas.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>H.</num>
        <text>Provide strategies to achieve the availability of increased connectivity speeds to every Community Anchor Institution (CAI).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>I.</num>
        <text>Collaborate on how best to employ available funding, to include State and Federal Grants, to achieve the maximum coverage in the most effective manner.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>V.</num>
      <text>Frequency.</text>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>The Secretary shall determine how often DIG shall meet and may coordinate additional meetings dependent on workload.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>The Secretary shall determine how often each working group or subcommittee established under this Executive Order shall meet.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>VI.</num>
      <text>Each Executive Branch agency and unit of State government is hereby required, to the extent not inconsistent with law, to cooperate fully with DIG and to furnish such assistance, including data, reports, or other information as necessary to accomplish the purpose of this Executive Order.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>VII.</num>
      <text>Nothing contained in this Executive Order shall be construed to impair or otherwise affect the authority granted by law to an Executive Branch agency or unit of State government.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>VIII.</num>
      <text>This Executive Order shall be implemented in a manner that is consistent with all applicable statutes and regulations. Nothing in this Executive Order shall operate to contravene any State or federal law or to affect the State’s receipt of federal funding.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>IX.</num>
      <text>If any provision of this Executive Order or its application to any person, entity, or circumstance is held invalid by any court of competent jurisdiction, all other provisions or applications of the Executive Order shall remain in effect to the extent possible without the invalid provision or application. To achieve this purpose, the provisions of this Executive Order are severable.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2025-01-07">Effective: January 7, 2025</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section type="eo">
    <prefix>Executive Order</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Governor’s Office of Performance Improvement</heading>
    <text class="center">(Rescinds Executive Order <cite path="01.01.2015.26">01.01.2015.26</cite>)</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Governor’s Office of Performance Improvement. The Governor’s Office of Performance Improvement (“GOPI”) shall be responsible for improving the performance of Maryland State agencies through greater accountability, coordination, and capacity building.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>GOPI shall be managed by the Chief Performance Officer, who shall direct the operations of GOPI. The Chief Performance Officer shall be appointed by and serve at the pleasure of the Governor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>GOPI shall be comprised of staff appointed by the Governor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Duties. GOPI shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Develop the State Comprehensive Plan (“State Plan”), as defined in §3-1001 of the State Finance &amp; Procurement Article of the Annotated Code of Maryland, at the outset of a new gubernatorial administration, which shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a)</num>
          <text>Include a statement of goals which serve as broad directives for improving or making more cost-effective State resources and services; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b)</num>
          <text>Align State programs and services with the Governor’s priorities.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Direct State agencies to develop objectives, strategies, key milestones, and/or performance measures to track the State Plan implementation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Develop and implement common sense government modernization initiatives as well as improve State operations and service delivery in order to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a)</num>
          <text>Ensure strategic resource management.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b)</num>
          <text>Maintain fiscal sustainability.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c)</num>
          <text>Promote cost optimization strategies to ensure receipt of the highest value for state expenditures; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>d)</num>
          <text>Elimination duplication and fragmentation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Hold State agencies accountable for delivering results, and maintain a data-driven approach to performance improvement and decision-making by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a)</num>
          <text>Tracking progress on the State Plan and government-modernization initiatives;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b)</num>
          <text>Holding regular data-driven reviews with the Governor; Lieutenant Governor; and/or agency leaders;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c)</num>
          <text>Identifying areas for improvement and/or key actions;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>d)</num>
          <text>Building agency capacity to support a data-driven, action-oriented culture within State government; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>e)</num>
          <text>Leveraging social science and evidence of best practices to ensure results for Marylanders.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Establish a Performance Improvement Council (“PIC”) composed of State agency representatives to provide a forum for the exchange of ideas to enable continuous improvement in the delivery of government services, accountability, and cross-agency collaboration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Procedures</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each State agency and department of the Executive Branch shall appoint a performance lead to drive performance improvement at their agency, and who shall be primarily responsible for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a)</num>
          <text>Providing access to the data requested by GOPI to determine progress being made by the agency;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b)</num>
          <text>Collaborating with GOPI to analyze the collected data; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c)</num>
          <text>Following-up on areas of improvement identified by GOPI.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>On a regular basis, each Secretary or agency head, or their designee, shall meet with GOPI.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The State agencies and departments of the Executive Branch shall build a data-driven, action-oriented culture that is accountable for delivering results.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>All State agencies, departments, and boards and commissions within the Executive Branch are authorized and directed to cooperate with GOPI in implementing the provisions of this Executive Order.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>This Executive Order shall not be construed to alter existing authorities of any Executive agency or department, except that all Executive agencies and departments are directed to assist the GOPI in carrying out the purposes of this Executive Order.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation type="History" subtype="Administrative History" effective="2025-01-10">Effective: January 10, 2025</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</container>
