<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Summary Suspensions for Alcohol and Drug-Related Offenses</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter contains administrative procedures governing suspensions of driver's licenses for licensees who have refused a properly requested test or who have submitted to a test which showed a 0.08 or more alcohol concentration, under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-205">Transportation Article, §16-205</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This chapter includes procedures for administrative hearings in contested cases under the Maryland Vehicle Law, which are in accordance with the Maryland Administrative Procedure Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-201">State Government Article, §10-201 </cite>et seq., and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-201">Transportation Article, §12-201 </cite>et seq., Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>This chapter is meant to be read in conjunction with <cite path="|11.11.02">COMAR 11.11.02</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>To the extent this chapter conflicts with any other provisions of this title, the provisions of this chapter shall prevail.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Administration" means the Motor Vehicle Administration and includes the Office of Administrative Hearings.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Administrative law judge" means a person authorized to conduct hearings in contested cases under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 9, Subtitle 16, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Alcohol incident" includes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A conviction or probation before judgment for a violation of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|21-902">Transportation Article, §21-902(a), </cite>(b), (c), or (d), Annotated Code of Maryland;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An offense committed under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-205">Transportation Article, §16-205</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A conviction of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr">Criminal Law Article, Title 2, Subtitle 5, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A conviction or offense committed in another jurisdiction which is substantially similar to those offenses referred to in §B(3)(a), (b), or (c); or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>A violation of an alcohol restriction.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Director" means the Director of the Administrative Adjudication Division, Motor Vehicle Administration, or the Director's designee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"License" means a license to drive as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|11-128">Transportation Article, §11-128, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Licensee" is one whose legal rights, duties, statutory entitlements, or privileges may be affected by the outcome of a contested case.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"MVA branch office" means a facility of the Motor Vehicle Administration which provides licensing and titling services. It does not include limited service facilities known as MVA express offices.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Program" means the Ignition Interlock System Program established under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-404">Transportation Article, §16-404</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland, and approved by the Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Test" means either one or both of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A test of a person's breath or of one specimen of a person's blood to determine alcohol concentration;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A test or tests of one specimen of a person's blood to determine the drug or controlled dangerous substance content of the person's blood.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Request for Hearing.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>At the time of, or within 30 days from the date of, the issuance of an order of suspension served by a police officer pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-205">Transportation Article, §16-205</cite>.1(b)(3), Annotated Code of Maryland, the person may submit a written request for a hearing to be held before an administrative law judge.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Hearing requests shall be made in writing and include the person's:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Name;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Address;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Driver's license number; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Date of birth.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A hearing request shall be accompanied by the filing fee required by the Office of Administrative Hearings under <cite path="28.03.01.03">COMAR 28.03.01.03</cite>. The hearing request may be denied if not accompanied by the required filing fee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A written request for a hearing which is mailed shall be addressed to the Office of Administrative Hearings, 11101 Gilroy Road, Hunt Valley, Maryland 21031-1301, and shall be considered to have been made on the date of the U.S. Postal Service postmark.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A written hearing request may be personally delivered to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The police officer at the time of the issuance of the order of suspension;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Administrative Adjudication Division, Motor Vehicle Administration, 6601 Ritchie Highway, N.E., Glen Burnie, Maryland 21062, during regular office hours; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The chief clerk or deputy clerks of the Office of Administrative Hearings during regular business hours.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall deny a hearing if the person did not:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Surrender the driver's license to the police officer or the Administration and refused to sign a certification that the license was not in that person's possession to be surrendered to the police officer and that, upon possession, it will be forwarded to the Administration; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Submit a timely request for a hearing within 30 days of the issuance of the order of suspension.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>If the hearing request is not made within 30 days of the issuance of the order of suspension, the Administration may grant a hearing if the person was incapacitated to an extent rendering the person incapable of making a timely request.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The Administration may grant a hearing if the person who is the subject of the hearing requests a waiver of fees in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1604">State Government Article, §9-1604(b)(2), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and <cite path="28.03.01.06">COMAR 28.03.01.06</cite>, within 30 days of the issuance of the order of suspension and the request for waiver is granted.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Stay of Suspension.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A stay of an order of suspension issued under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-205">Transportation Article, §16-205</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland, shall be granted by the Administration in the following circumstances:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The person can show a compelling reason for being unable to appear at the scheduled hearing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Administration cannot provide a hearing within the time period required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-205">Transportation Article, §16-205</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The person and the Administration agree to a postponement; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The person is otherwise entitled to a stay of the suspension under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-205">Transportation Article, §16-205</cite>.1(f)(5)(iii) or §16-205.1(f)(6)(iii), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall be deemed to have agreed to a postponement of a hearing under the following circumstances:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The person can show a compelling reason for that person's inability to appear on the scheduled hearing date;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The person's attorney presents evidence of a conflict in the attorney's schedule and otherwise conforms with the requirements for postponement requests contained in Regulation .06; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The person can establish to the satisfaction of the Administration that the person did not receive actual notice of the hearing as a result of an error on the part of the Administration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The following circumstances constitute reasons deemed compelling for purposes of the Administration staying an order of suspension after a person fails to appear at a scheduled hearing or requests a postponement:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The person is in the military and is not stationed or on leave in Maryland on the date of the scheduled hearing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The person is incarcerated;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>There has been, within the past 5 days, a death or illness in the immediate family of the person or the person's attorney; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The person or the person's attorney can present satisfactory evidence that the person or the person's attorney was suffering from an incapacitating illness or was injured to the extent that it was impossible to appear for the scheduled hearing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in §A, if a hearing request is not made at the time of, or within 10 days from the date of, the issuance of the order of suspension, but within 30 days of the issuance of the order of suspension, the Administration may not stay the order of suspension.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Location of Hearings.</heading>
    <text>The Administration shall determine the location of the hearing. If a postponement or continuance is necessary for any reason, the Administration may change the location of the hearing.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Postponements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A postponement may not result in a stay of the suspension under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-205">Transportation Article, §16-205</cite>.1(f)(5)(iii)(1) and (f)(6)(iii)(1), unless the Administration has agreed to a postponement pursuant to Regulation .04B and C.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>For any satisfactory reason other than those designated in Regulation .04B and C, the Administration may grant a postponement if the licensee complies with <cite path="11.11.02.05">COMAR 11.11.02.05</cite>, but the postponement does not result in a stay of the suspension.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|11|03|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Request for Subpoenas.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A request for the issuance of a subpoena to require the attendance of witnesses or the production of documents shall be in writing and shall contain:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The name and complete mailing address of the licensee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The driver's license number of the licensee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The date of the scheduled hearing, if known;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The name, address, and telephone number of the attorney, if applicable;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A proffer of the expected testimony or evidence and its relevance to the proceeding; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The name and address of the requested witness.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The decision to issue a subpoena shall be in the discretion of the Administration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A request may be refused if the testimony or evidence to be offered:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is immaterial, irrelevant, or unduly repetitious; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Does not pertain to a genuine issue in the contested case.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If a subpoena request is made, the Administration may defer the decision on the request until the hearing is held. The administrative law judge may take testimony and receive evidence to determine if the request may be granted pursuant to <cite path="11|11|03|.07|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>. The administrative law judge may entertain a proffer from the licensee or the licensee's attorney as to the nature of the witness' testimony. If the administrative law judge decides to issue a subpoena for a witness, the administrative law judge shall continue the hearing and stay the suspension. The Administration may reschedule the hearing at a location most convenient for the witness.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A party, other than the Administration, requesting the issuance of a subpoena, shall pay the Administration a fee of $4 for each subpoena issued.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|11|03|.08">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Hearing.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Scheduling.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A hearing shall be provided by the Administration within the time periods required in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-205">Transportation Article, §16-205</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the Administration cannot provide a hearing within the time periods required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-205">Transportation Article, §16-205</cite>.1, and the suspension period has not begun by the time the hearing is provided, or the Administration stays the suspension under Regulation .04A(2), the Administration or administrative law judge may not dismiss the case.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the Administration cannot provide a hearing within the time periods required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-205">Transportation Article, §16-205</cite>.1, and the suspension period has begun as a result of the Administration's delay or oversight, the case shall be dismissed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Evidence.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each hearing shall be conducted in accordance with State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-201">10-201</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-214">10-214</cite>, and Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-201">12-201</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-208">12-208</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Certified copies of medical records of a medical laboratory containing results of a blood test for the alcohol concentration of the licensee shall be admitted at the hearing without the necessity of the personal appearance by the custodian of the records or any other employee of the facility which administered the test.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The administrative law judge, on the administrative law judge's own motion or upon request of a party, may allow the testimony of any nonparty witness to be taken by telephone with the consent of all parties. When testimony is taken by telephone, the administrative law judge shall employ appropriate techniques to ensure that the testimony is fully audible to all parties present at the hearing and the testimony is made a part of the hearing record. The parties shall be allowed to fully cross-examine any witness whose testimony is taken using this procedure.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the administrative law judge determines that the testimony of a witness adverse to the licensee may materially assist with making an informed decision on a genuine issue of fact in the case, the administrative law judge may either take the testimony of that adverse witness pursuant to §B(3) or may require the attendance at the hearing of that adverse witness.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>For the purpose of determining the accuracy of the test result indicating the alcohol concentration of the licensee, the breath testing instrument shall conform to the requirements set forth in <cite path="10.35.02.08">COMAR 10.35.02.08</cite>.B(2).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>There shall be a rebuttable presumption that the test result of a test of blood or breath indicating the alcohol concentration of the licensee is accurate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The reliability of breath testing instruments approved in <cite path="11|11|03|.08|B.|(5)">§B(5) of this regulation</cite> and the presumption established in <cite path="11|11|03|.08|B.|(6)">§B(6) of this regulation</cite> may not preclude a licensee from demonstrating that the specific breath testing instrument used to test the alcohol concentration of the licensee was malfunctioning at the time of testing, or that human error caused the test result to be inaccurate.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Record of Hearing. The administrative law judge shall maintain a record of the hearing which shall include all physical evidence submitted by the parties and the mechanical recording of the oral proceedings before the administrative law judge.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Hearing Dispositions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This regulation governs the dispositions of a hearing for licensees who refused a test or who submitted to a test that showed an alcohol concentration of 0.08 or more, under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-205">Transportation Article, §16-205</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In this regulation, "offense" means a violation of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-205">Transportation Article, §16-205</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The administrative law judge may modify a suspension or issue a restricted license under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-205">Transportation Article, §16-205</cite>.1(o), Annotated Code of Maryland, if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The licensee did not refuse to take a test or did not have a test result indicating an alcohol concentration of 0.15 or more and did not elect to participate in the Ignition Interlock System Program; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The licensee:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is required to drive a motor vehicle in the course of employment as evidenced by a letter from the employer on the employer's letterhead, or other reliable documentation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is required to drive a motor vehicle in order to attend an alcoholic prevention or treatment program as evidenced by satisfactory documentation from program officials;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Has no alternative means of transportation available to or from the licensee's place of employment and, without the license, the licensee's ability to earn a living would be severely impaired; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Has no alternative means of transportation available to the licensee or the licensee's immediate family members to obtain health care treatment, including a prescription that is necessary for the licensee or the licensee's immediate family.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The administrative law judge may modify a suspension or issue a restricted license under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-205">Transportation Article, §16-205</cite>.1(p), Annotated Code of Maryland, if the licensee refused to take a test or took a test that indicated an alcohol concentration of 0.15 or more only if the licensee agrees to participate in the Program for 1 year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>In determining whether a suspension should be modified, the administrative law judge shall consider the need to promote public safety and shall weigh the following factors:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The licensee's driving history, particularly any alcohol incidents; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The nature of the offense in question, including, but not limited to, the alcohol concentration level and whether personal injury or property damage occurred.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>In determining whether to issue a restrictive license, the licensee shall prove that there is a need for a restrictive license by submission of appropriate documentation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09-1</num>
    <heading>Hearing on Violation of the Ignition Interlock Program.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An individual who elects to participate or who is ordered to participate in the Program under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-205">Transportation Article, §16-205</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland, shall comply with all the requirements of the Program under <cite path="|11.11.13">COMAR 11.11.13</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the licensee becomes a participant, but is removed from the Program for one or more violations as set forth in <cite path="11.11.13.04">COMAR 11.11.13.04</cite> and .05, the Administration shall notify the licensee that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The licensee's driver's license is immediately suspended;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The licensee may request a hearing on the suspension; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The licensee’s driver’s license suspension will be held in abeyance pending the outcome of the hearing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Effective Date of Suspensions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If the hearing is not requested in writing within the 10 days, or if the person fails to appear at a requested hearing, the suspension will take effect on the 46th day after the issuance of the order of suspension.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If a hearing is conducted, and the administrative law judge decides a suspension is warranted, the suspension shall take effect immediately upon the administrative law judge's decision to suspend the license.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Term of Suspension.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Test Refusals.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In the case of a test refusal, the Administration shall suspend the license:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>270 days from a person's first offense; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>2 years for a person's second or subsequent offense.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Test refusal offenses occurring before and after January 1, 1990, shall be considered in determining the term of suspension to be imposed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Test Results.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In the case of a test result indicating an alcohol concentration of 0.08 or more, but less than 0.15 at the time of testing, the Administration shall suspend the license for 180 days for a person's first or subsequent offense.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For the purpose of this section, a prior offense is any test result on or after:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>January 1, 1990, indicating an alcohol concentration of 0.08 or more; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>January 1, 2007, indicating an alcohol concentration of 0.15 or more.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Test Results Indicating an Alcohol Concentration of 0.15 or More.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In the case of a test result indicating an alcohol concentration of 0.15 or more, the Administration shall suspend the license:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>180 days for a person's first offense; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>270 days for a person's second or subsequent offense.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For the purpose of this section, a prior offense is any test result on or after January 1, 2007, indicating an alcohol concentration of 0.15 or more.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|11|03|.12">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Stay of Enforcement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A licensee may request a stay of enforcement of the administrative law judge's decision pending judicial review under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-205">Transportation Article, §16-205</cite>.1(n), Annotated Code of Maryland. A request for a stay does not extend the time for filing an appeal.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A request for a stay shall be submitted to the Director in writing and shall include a:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Photocopy of the order for appeal filed with the circuit court; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Detailed statement of the reasons a stay is sought.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="11|11|03|.12|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>, a suspension imposed under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-205">Transportation Article, §16-205</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland, may not be stayed by the Administration pending an appeal.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If a person files an appeal and requests in writing a stay of suspension imposed under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-205">Transportation Article, §16-205</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland, the Director of the Division of Administrative Adjudication of the Administration may stay a suspension if the person:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Has appeared before an administrative law judge to contest the suspension of the person's license;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Has no other alcohol incidents within the past 5 years;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Can demonstrate irreparable injury without the issuance of a stay; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Can demonstrate that the issuance of a stay is not contrary to public safety.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>When Police Officers May Not Issue Temporary Licenses.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-205">Transportation Article, §16-205</cite>.1(b)(3), Annotated Code of Maryland, a police officer shall, among other duties, serve an order of suspension on the driver, confiscate the driver's license, and issue a temporary license permitting a person to drive if the person refuses to take a test or takes a test which results in an alcohol concentration of 0.08 or more at the time of testing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A police officer may not issue a temporary license to drive if the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Person's license to drive in Maryland is suspended, revoked, cancelled, refused, or disqualified at the time the order of suspension is served;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>License that was confiscated was invalid;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Person was not entitled to driving privileges for any other reason;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Person holds a license issued by another State; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Person is not in possession of the license and the person refuses to sign a certification stating that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The license is not in the person's possession, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Upon repossession the person will immediately surrender it to the Administration.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-1604">9-1604</cite>(b), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-201">10-201</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-222">10-222</cite>; Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-104">12-104</cite>(b), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-108">12-108</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-201">12-201</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-209">12-209</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-117">16-117</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-205">16-205</cite>.1; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-01-01">Regulations <cite path="|11|11|03|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|11|11|03|.13">.13</cite> adopted as a emergency provision effective January 1, 1990 (17:1 Md. R. 64) (Emergency provisions are temporary and not printed in COMAR)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-05-28">Regulations <cite path="|11|11|03|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|11|11|03|.13">.13</cite> adopted effective May 28, 1990 (17:10 Md. R. 1220)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-06-08"><cite path="|11|11|03|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective June 8, 1992 (19:11 Md. R. 1016)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-10-01"><cite path="|11|11|03|.01|A.">Regulation .01A</cite> amended effective October 1, 1990 (17:19 Md. R. 2321)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-04-09"><cite path="|11|11|03|.01|A.">Regulation .01A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective March 9, 2007 (34:7 Md. R. 694); amended permanently effective April 9, 2007 (34:7 Md. R. 699)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-10-01"><cite path="|11|11|03|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective October 1, 1990 (17:19 Md. R. 2321)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-04-09"><cite path="|11|11|03|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective March 9, 2007 (34:7 Md. R. 694); amended permanently effective April 9, 2007 (34:7 Md. R. 699)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-09-13"><cite path="|11|11|03|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective September 13, 1993 (20:18 Md. R. 1431)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-10-01"><cite path="|11|11|03|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite>, E, F amended effective October 1, 1990 (17:19 Md. R. 2321)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-10-01"><cite path="|11|11|03|.03|D.">Regulation .03D</cite>, E amended effective October 1, 2016 (43:19 Md. R. 1073)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-04-09"><cite path="|11|11|03|.03|E.">Regulation .03E</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective March 9, 2007 (34:7 Md. R. 694); amended permanently effective April 9, 2007 (34:7 Md. R. 699)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-10-01"><cite path="|11|11|03|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite> and C amended, and D adopted effective October 1, 1990 (17:19 Md. R. 2321)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-10-01"><cite path="|11|11|03|.06|A.">Regulation .06A</cite> amended effective October 1, 1990 (17:19 Md. R. 2321)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-10-01"><cite path="|11|11|03|.08">Regulation .08</cite> amended effective October 1, 1990 (17:19 Md. R. 2321)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-02-07"><cite path="|11|11|03|.08|B.">Regulation .08B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective October 18, 1999 (26:23 Md. R. 1775); amended permanently effective February 7, 2000 (27:2 Md. R. 145)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-03-28"><cite path="|11|11|03|.08|B.">Regulation .08B</cite> amended effective March 28, 2016 (43:6 Md. R. 409)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-04-09"><cite path="|11|11|03|.09">Regulation .09</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective March 9, 2007 (34:7 Md. R. 694); amended permanently effective April 9, 2007 (34:7 Md. R. 699)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-10-01"><cite path="|11|11|03|.09|C.">Regulation .09C</cite> amended effective October 1, 1990 (17:19 Md. R. 2321); April 22, 1996 (23:8 Md. R. 606); October 1, 2016 (43:19 Md. R. 1073)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-10-01"><cite path="|11|11|03|.09|D.">Regulation .09D</cite> amended effective October 1, 1990 (17:19 Md. R. 2321); October 1, 2016 (43:19 Md. R. 1073)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-04-09"><cite path="|11|11|03|.09-1">Regulation .09-1</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective March 9, 2007 (34:7 Md. R. 694); adopted permanently effective April 9, 2007 (34:7 Md. R. 699)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-11-03"><cite path="|11|11|03|.09-1">Regulation .09-1</cite> amended effective November 3, 2008 (35:22 Md. R. 1958)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-03-28"><cite path="|11|11|03|.09-1B">Regulation .09-1B</cite> amended effective March 28, 2016 (43:6 Md. R. 409)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-10-01"><cite path="|11|11|03|.11">Regulation .11</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective March 9, 2007 (34:7 Md. R. 694); amended permanently effective April 9, 2007 (34:7 Md. R. 699); October 1, 2016 (43:19 Md. R. 1073)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-10-01"><cite path="|11|11|03|.12|A.">Regulation .12A</cite> amended effective October 1, 1990 (17:19 Md. R. 2321); April 22, 1996 (23:8 Md. R. 606); October 1, 2016 (43:19 Md. R. 1073)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-10-01"><cite path="|11|11|03|.12|C.">Regulation .12C</cite> amended, and D adopted effective October 1, 1990 (17:19 Md. R. 2321)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-10-01"><cite path="|11|11|03|.13|A.">Regulation .13A</cite> amended effective October 1, 1990 (17:19 Md. R. 2321)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-04-09"><cite path="|11|11|03|.13|A.">Regulation .13A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective March 9, 2007 (34:7 Md. R. 694); amended permanently effective April 9, 2007 (34:7 Md. R. 699)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
