<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>08</num>
  <heading>Driver's License Suspension and Restrictions for Child Support Noncompliance</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter contains procedures governing driver's license and driving privilege suspensions and restrictions imposed for child support noncompliance, pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-203">Transportation Article, §16-203, </cite>and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|10-119">Family Law Article, §10-119, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Administration" means the Motor Vehicle Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"CSEA" means the Child Support Enforcement Administration of the Department of Human Services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Gainfully employed' means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>To have employment with private industry or a government agency, or to be self-employed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If not self-employed to have to complete an Employee Withholding Allowance Certificate (Form W-4, Internal Revenue Service); and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>To file State and federal income tax returns.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Work-restricted license" means a driver's license issued for the purpose of driving:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Directly to and from a scheduled work shift at the individual's place of employment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>During scheduled work shifts in the course of employment; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>When purchasing motor vehicle fuel or providing general maintenance for the individual's vehicle being driven for employment purposes.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Work-restricted privilege" means the privilege to operate a motor vehicle in the State for the purpose of driving:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Directly to and from a scheduled work shift at the individual's place of employment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>During scheduled work shifts in the course of employment; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>When purchasing motor vehicle fuel or providing general maintenance for the individual's vehicle being driven for employment purposes.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Notice of Suspension.</heading>
    <text>A notice of a proposed suspension by the Administration of an individual's driver's license or driving privilege for child support noncompliance shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Be in writing;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Be personally served on the individual or sent by U.S. mail to the individual at the address of the individual on record with the Administration;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>State the duration of the suspension; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Advise the individual:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Of the right, within 10 business days of the notice date, to file a written request for a hearing before the Administration, and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>That any hearing shall be limited to the issue of mistaken identity.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|11|08|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Work-Restricted License or Privilege.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A work-restricted driver's license may be issued or work-restricted privilege authorized by the Administration if the individual certifies that the individual understands the restriction conditions set forth in <cite path="11|11|08|.04|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Conditions of Work-Restricted License or Privilege.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Individuals shall be gainfully employed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Individuals shall operate a motor vehicle only for the purposes described in Regulation .02B(4) or (5) of this chapter, and may not operate a motor vehicle for any other purpose.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A work-restricted license or privilege shall be valid only when no other suspensions, cancellations, revocations, refusals, or disqualifications exist against the individual's driver's license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A work-restricted license issued under this chapter shall be cancelled by the Administration if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Administration receives notice from CSEA to remove the work restriction; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The driver's license of the individual is suspended, cancelled, revoked, or refused, or the individual is disqualified.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-104">12-104</cite>(b) and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-203">16-203</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1997-02-24">Effective date: February 24, 1997 (24:4 Md. R. 292)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
