<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>09</num>
  <heading>Access to Public Motor Vehicle Administration Records</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose and Scope.</heading>
    <text>The purpose of this chapter is to comply with the Maryland Public Information Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp">General Provisions Article, Title 4, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and with the federal Driver’s Privacy Protection Act of 1994 (18 U.S.C. §2721 et seq.) in order to:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Maintain the confidentiality of motor vehicle drivers' records including personal information; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Establish procedures for applicants to obtain records eligible to be disclosed.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Act” means the Maryland Public Information Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp">General Provisions Article, Title 4, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Administration” means the Motor Vehicle Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Applicant” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-101">General Provisions Article, §4-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Certified record” means a motor vehicle record certified by the Administration that is admissible in any judicial proceeding in the same manner as the original record, whose contents and time period covered may vary depending upon the eligibility of the requester under the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-320">General Provisions Article, §4-320, </cite>and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-111">Transportation Article, §12-111, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Custodian” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-101">General Provisions Article, §4-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Government agency” means an agency or unit of the federal, state, or local government, including a law enforcement agency.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Noncertified record” means a motor vehicle record provided by the Administration generally used for informational purposes that may or may not be used in judicial proceedings.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Person in interest” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-101">General Provisions Article, §4-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“Personal information” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-101">General Provisions Article, §4-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>“Public record” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-101">General Provisions Article, §4-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>“Records” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Accident reports;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Administrative hearing records and exhibits;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Alcohol education client records;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Applications and other related documents;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Certificates or other documents issued by the Administration;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Correspondence and reports related to the records listed in §B(11)(a)—(e) and (g)—(m) of this regulation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Driver improvement client records;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Driver record histories or other related documents;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Financial responsibility judgment case records;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Insurance certification documents and uninsured motorist complaint records;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Vehicle identification numbers;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>Vehicle registration records; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>Vehicle titles.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>“Specific identifier” means personal information that identifies an individual or person of interest including that individual's name, address, telephone number, driver's license number, email address, or any other identifying data or number.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02-1</num>
    <heading>Records.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-111">Transportation Article, §12-111, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the Administration shall keep a record of each application or other document with it and each certificate or other official document that it issues.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-117">Transportation Article, §16-117, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the Administration shall keep a drivers’ record file, which, except as otherwise provided, shall be open for public inspection.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Record Request.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant may request an individual's public record by completing a record request form furnished by the Administration which shall include the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Name of the applicant;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Signature of the applicant;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Business name of the applicant, if applicable;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Address of the applicant or business;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Name of the record requested;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Reason for the request; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Record identification number, such as:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Driver's license or Soundex, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Vehicle registration.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>To determine the applicant's eligibility for release of personal information when appearing in person, the applicant shall furnish a driver's license or State identification card and, if the application is for personal information for a different individual, upon request by the Administration, another form of personal identification such as a:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Federal tax identification or other business number;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Vendor contract number;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Law enforcement identification;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Government employment identification; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Professional license number with the name of the licensing agency.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Record Access.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In General. Pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-111">Transportation Article, §12-111, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, subject to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-320">General Provisions Article, §4-320, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and except as otherwise provided by law, all records of the Administration are public records and open to public inspection during office hours.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Records Not Open to Public Inspection. Pursuant to Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-111">12-111</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-117">16-117</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-118">16-118</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland, the following records are not open to public inspection:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A driving record entry that is over 3 years old;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A digital or photographic image or signature;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A record or notation of probation before judgment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A record of a first offense of driving with an alcohol concentration of 0.08 or more under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-205">Transportation Article, §16-205</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Records of the Medical Advisory Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Exceptions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Records of Any Age. Subject to the provisions of §§B, D and E of this regulation and pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-111">Transportation Article §12-111(b)(3), </cite>a driving record entry of any age shall be open to inspection by authorized representatives of any federal, State, or local government agency.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Photographic Images and Signatures. A digital photographic image or signature of an individual shall be open to inspection only as set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-111">Transportation Article §12-111, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Probation Before Judgment Records and Records of a First Offense of Driving With an Alcohol Concentration of 0.08 or More. A record or notation of probation before judgment and a record of a first offense of driving with an alcohol concentration of 0.08 or more shall be open to inspection only as set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-117">Transportation Article §16-117, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Medical Advisory Board Records. Records of the Medical Advisory Board shall be open to inspection only as set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-118">Transportation Article §16-118, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Public Records Containing Personal Information. Personal information referred to in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-320">General Provisions Article, §4-320(f)(2), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, shall generally be used in conformity with the purposes of State and federal law, as amended, and specifically in compliance with the following statutes:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Federal Automobile Information Disclosure Act (15 U.S.C. §1231 et seq.);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Motor Vehicle Information and Cost Saving Act (49 U.S.C. §32101 et seq.);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>National Traffic and Motor Vehicle Safety Act of 1996 (49.U.S.C. §30101 et seq.);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Anti-Car Theft Act of 1992 (49 U.S.C. §33101 et seq.);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Clean Air Act (42 U.S.C. §7401 et seq.);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Driver’s Privacy Protection Act of 1994 (18 U.S.C. §2721 et seq.); and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp">General Provisions Article, Title 4, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Waiver Procedures.</heading>
    <text>At the discretion of the custodian, a public record containing personal information may be released to an applicant not otherwise authorized to receive the information when the applicant:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Submits, from the person in interest, a notarized written consent;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Is the cosigner for driver licensing while the person in interest is younger than 18 years old; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Applying for a vehicle registration renewal:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Presents a registration renewal application signed by the person in interest; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If applying for renewal as co-owner of the vehicle, furnishes identification showing the same address as the other vehicle co-owner.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Disclosure Denial.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-320">General Provisions Article, §4-320, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the Administration shall deny disclosure of personal information and specific identifiers.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Disclosure of personal information may be denied if the custodian determines that the requested information is to be used for purposes other than those specified in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-320">General Provisions Article, §4-320(e) </cite>and (f), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-320">General Provisions Article, §4-320, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, if a record subject to disclosure contains personal information or specific identifiers, the personal information and specific identifiers shall be redacted prior to disclosing the record.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Disclosure Consent or Withdrawal of Consent.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A person in interest may consent, or subsequently withdraw consent, to disclose personal information.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The consent or withdrawal of consent shall be in writing and mailed or delivered to the Administration's Official Custodian. The request shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Soundex or driver's license number;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Full name;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Date of birth;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Signature; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A photocopy of the person in interest's last Maryland driver's license or identification card on record with the custodian.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The custodian shall maintain a record of a consent or withdrawal of consent of personal information.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Fees.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Fees for Driver and Vehicle Records. The fees for individual driver and vehicle records shall be as set forth in <cite path="11.11.05.06">COMAR 11.11.05.06</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Fees for Copies of Records Requested Under the Maryland Public Information Act.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The fee schedule for copying records is as follows.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Black and White Copies. The fee for each black and white copy of a noncertified record is 3.5 cents per page if reproduction is made by a photocopying machine within the Administration.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Color Copies. The fee for each color copy of a noncertified record is 15 cents per page if reproduction is made by a photocopying machine within the Administration.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Certified Copies. If an applicant requests a certified record, an additional fee of $3 per record shall be charged.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Other Reproductions. If records are not susceptible to photocopying (for example, punch cards, magnetic tapes, blueprints, and microfilm), the fee for copies shall be based on the actual cost of reproduction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Minimum Fee Charged. A charge may not be made if the total amount of the fee is less than $10.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Notwithstanding subsection(1) of this section, if the fees for copies, printouts, other reproductions, or certified copies of any record are specifically prescribed by a law or regulation other than the Act or this regulation, the prescribed fee shall be charged.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Before copying a record, the custodian shall estimate the cost of reproduction and obtain prepayment of any estimated fee before reproducing the record.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Fees for Search and Retrieval of Records Requested Under the Maryland Public Information Act.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in subsection (2) of this section, the official custodian may charge reasonable fees for officials’ or employees’ time expended searching for requested records or for any time expended preparing records for inspection and copying.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The official custodian may not charge any search or preparation fee for the first 2 hours of official or employee time needed to respond to a request for information.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The fee schedule for search and preparation is as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Computer Programming and Retrieval. The fee for computer programming and electronic retrieval of records is $250 per hour.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Clerical. The fee for clerical time expended for search and retrieval of documents is $30 per hour.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Waiver of Fees.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Upon request, the official custodian may waive or reduce any fee charged pursuant to the regulation if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>When requesting an individual’s own driving record, the individual displays identification acceptable to the Administration; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>When requesting all other records, the custodian determines that the waiver or reduction is in the public interest, considering, among other relevant factors, the ability of the applicant to pay the cost or fee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Records for Government Agencies.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>On request, the Administration may provide certified or noncertified records to government agencies without charge.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Administration may provide up to five records to government agency representatives who provide official identification at the time of making the request.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Multiple Requests. Requests from government agencies for more than five records without charge shall be made on the agency’s letterhead, and shall be addressed to the Motor Vehicle Administration, Custodian of Records, 6601 Ritchie Highway, Glen Burnie, Maryland 21062.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If the applicant requests that copies be mailed or delivered to the applicant, the custodian may charge the applicant for the cost of postage or delivery to the applicant.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">General Provisions Article, Title 4; Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-104">12-104</cite>(b), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-111">12-111</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-113">12-113</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-117">16-117</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-118">16-118</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-819">16-819</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-904">16-904</cite>; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-02-23">Effective date: February 23, 1998 (25:4 Md. R. 244)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-02-24"><cite path="|11|11|09|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective July 24, 2000 (27:14 Md. R. 1342); October 15, 2012 (39:20 Md. R. 1307); February 24, 2020 (47:4 Md. R. 261)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-10-15"><cite path="|11|11|09|.01-1">Regulation .01-1</cite> adopted effective October 15, 2012 (39:20 Md. R. 1307)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-02-24"><cite path="|11|11|09|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective December 20, 2004 (31:25 Md. R. 1791); October 15, 2012 (39:20 Md. R. 1307); February 24, 2020 (47:4 Md. R. 261)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-10-15"><cite path="|11|11|09|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite> amended effective July 24, 2000 (27:14 Md. R. 1342); October 15, 2012 (39:20 Md. R. 1307)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-10-15"><cite path="|11|11|09|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective October 15, 2012 (39:20 Md. R. 1307)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-02-24"><cite path="|11|11|09|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite>, D amended effective February 24, 2020 (47:4 Md. R. 261)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-10-15"><cite path="|11|11|09|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective October 15, 2012 (39:20 Md. R. 1307)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-10-24"><cite path="|11|11|09|.05|B.">Regulation .05B</cite>, C amended effective October 24, 2005 (32:21 Md. R. 1708)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-02-24"><cite path="|11|11|09|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective July 24, 2000 (27:14 Md. R. 1342); October 15, 2012 (39:20 Md. R. 1307); February 24, 2020 (47:4 Md. R. 261)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-07-24"><cite path="|11|11|09|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective July 24, 2000 (27:14 Md. R. 1342)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-10-15"><cite path="|11|11|09|.07|B.">Regulation .07B</cite> amended effective October 15, 2012 (39:20 Md. R. 1307)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-10-15"><cite path="|11|11|09|.08">Regulation .08</cite> adopted effective October 15, 2012 (39:20 Md. R. 1307)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
