<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>10</num>
  <heading>Vehicle Registration Refusal and Driver's License Suspension for Outstanding Warrants</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter contains procedures governing the refusal to register or transfer registration and for the suspension of the driver's license or privilege to drive of an individual who has an outstanding warrant, pursuant to Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-406">13-406</cite>.1 and 16-204, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Administration" means the Motor Vehicle Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Law enforcement agency" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-406">Transportation Article, §13-406</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"License" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|11-128">Transportation Article, §11-128, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Outstanding warrant" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-406">Transportation Article, §13-406</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Reporting Outstanding Warrant Information.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A participating law enforcement agency is responsible for transmitting outstanding warrant information to the Administration in a format specified by the Administration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A participating law enforcement agency may not report outstanding warrant information to the Administration until:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The outstanding warrant is 31 days old or older; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The law enforcement agency has made at least one attempt to serve the warrant, but failed to serve the individual named in the outstanding warrant due to the inability to locate the individual.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Registration Refusal and License Suspension.</heading>
    <text>Upon notification from a participating law enforcement agency that an individual has an outstanding warrant, the Administration shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Refuse to register or transfer the registration of any vehicle owned by the individual; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Suspend the driver's license or driving privilege of the individual.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Notice of Proposed Action.</heading>
    <text>Before refusing to register or transfer a vehicle registration and suspending the driver's license or privilege to drive of an individual with an outstanding warrant, the Administration shall send notice to the individual. The notice shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Be in writing;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Be personally served on the individual or sent by U.S. mail to the individual at the address on record with the Administration; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Advise the individual:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>That the registration or transfer of any vehicle owned by the individual has been refused and their driver's license or privilege to drive has been suspended;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Of the right to contest, within 15 days of the notice date, by making a written request for an administration hearing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>That the hearing request under this section shall be limited to the issue of mistaken identity; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>To contact the reporting law enforcement agency to resolve any questions regarding the outstanding warrant.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Reinstatement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall continue to refuse to register or transfer a vehicle registration and to suspend the driver's license or privilege to drive of an individual with an outstanding warrant until:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Administration is ordered by a court to register or transfer the vehicle registration and reinstate the driver's license or privilege to drive of the individual; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The participating law enforcement agency notifies the Administration that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The individual named in the outstanding warrant has been arrested; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The outstanding warrant has been satisfied.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The participating law enforcement agency shall notify the Administration within 24 hours of a warrant being satisfied.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-104">12-104</cite>(b), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-406">13-406</cite>.1, and 16-204, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-04-29">Effective date: April 29, 2002 (29:8 Md. R. 701)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
