<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>12</num>
  <heading>Commercial Driver's License Disqualification and Cancellation</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>The purpose of this chapter is to establish:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Procedures for the disqualification of commercial vehicle driving privileges for convictions of certain offenses determined by State and federal law as serious violations;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The period of disqualification for serious violations under this chapter;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Procedures for an emergency disqualification;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Conditions for reinstatement and denial of a lifetime disqualification; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Requirements to comply with federal regulations that were created to ensure uniformity among commercial driver license systems and to reduce or prevent commercial vehicle accidents, fatalities, and injuries.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Administration" means the Motor Vehicle Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Cancel” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|11-107">Transportation Article, §11-107, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Commercial driver's license" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|11-109">Transportation Article, §11-109, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Commercial motor vehicle" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-803">Transportation Article, §16-803, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Disqualification" has the meaning stated in 49 CFR §383.5.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Imminent hazard" has the meaning stated in 49 CFR §383.5.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Serious traffic violation" has the meaning stated in 49 CFR §383.5.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Disqualification for Serious Traffic Violations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A driver or holder of a commercial driver's license shall be disqualified from operating a commercial motor vehicle for a period of 60 days for a second conviction of any combination of serious traffic violations incurred in a separate incident within a 3-year period while operating a:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Commercial motor vehicle; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Noncommercial motor vehicle if the conviction results in the revocation, cancellation, refusal, or suspension of the individual's driver's license or privilege to drive.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A driver or holder of a commercial driver's license shall be disqualified from operating a commercial motor vehicle for a period of 120 days for a third conviction of any combination of serious traffic violations incurred in a separate incident within a 3-year period while operating a:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Commercial motor vehicle; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Noncommercial motor vehicle, if the conviction results in the revocation, cancellation, refusal, or suspension of the individual's driver's license or privilege to drive.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A disqualification imposed under this chapter shall be in addition to any other period of disqualification.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Disqualification for Major Traffic Violations.</heading>
    <text>A driver or holder of a commercial driver's license shall be disqualified from operating a commercial motor vehicle for a major traffic violation for 1 year, 3 years, or for life as specified in 49 CFR §383.51(b).</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Emergency Disqualification.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>On notification from the Federal Motor Carrier Safety Administration that a driver has been determined to constitute an imminent hazard and has been disqualified pursuant to 49 CFR §383.52, the Administration shall enter the disqualification on the driver's record.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A driver who is simultaneously disqualified under 49 CFR §383.52 and under the provisions of any other federal regulation or State law or regulation shall serve those disqualification periods concurrently.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Lifetime Disqualification Reinstatement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An individual with a lifetime disqualification may request reinstatement of the individual's commercial driving privilege if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A 10-year disqualification period has expired from the date of the lifetime disqualification;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The individual has voluntarily entered and successfully completed the approved rehabilitation program or programs required by the Administration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The individual had a valid driver's license during that 10-year period;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The individual has no record of any moving violations during the lifetime disqualification period; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The individual has met all the reinstatement requirements under 49 CFR §383.51.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration, after an investigation of the individual's habits, health, and driving ability and referral to the Medical Advisory Board established under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-118">Transportation Article, §16-118, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, may determine if it will be safe to reinstate the individual's commercial driving privilege.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The decision to grant the reinstatement shall be solely at the discretion of the Administrator or Administrator's designee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the reinstatement of the individual's commercial driving privilege is granted, the Administration shall require the applicant to submit to all testing requirements under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr">Transportation Article, Title 16, Subtitle 8, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and <cite path="|11.17.14">COMAR 11.17.14</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If an individual who has been reinstated with a commercial driving privilege under the provisions of this regulation is subsequently convicted of a disqualifying offense described in 49 CFR §383.51, the lifetime disqualification of the individual's commercial driving privilege shall be reinstated and any future request for reinstatement of the commercial driving privilege shall be denied.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Licensing Limitations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Administration may not issue any type of temporary, conditional, or work restricted license permitting an individual to drive a commercial motor vehicle during any period in which the individual's driving privilege is disqualified, refused, cancelled, suspended, or revoked in this or any other state in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-808">Transportation Article, §16-808, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and 49 CFR §384.210.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An applicant for a commercial driver's license with a restriction imposed under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-113">Transportation Article, §16-113(a)(1), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite> shall be issued a commercial driver's license with the restriction if it is determined by the Medical Advisory Board that the individual is physically qualified to operate a commercial motor vehicle.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Notification of Disqualification.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>After disqualifying a nonresident driver from operating a commercial motor vehicle, the Administration shall notify the licensing authority of the state that issued the commercial driver's license. The notice of disqualification shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be sent within 10 days of the disqualification; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Include the violation that resulted in the disqualification.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Upon notification from a licensing authority from another state that a Maryland resident driver has been disqualified from operating a commercial motor vehicle in that state, the Administration shall notify the resident driver of the disqualification from operating a commercial motor vehicle in Maryland. The notice of disqualification shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The violation that resulted in the disqualification; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The effective date of the disqualification.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Cancellation for Failure to Submit Current Medical Certification.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If a commercial driver’s license holder fails to submit their medical certification as required under 49 CFR §§391.43 and 391.45, the Administration shall cancel the commercial driver’s license privilege of the holder.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration may immediately reinstate the noncommercial Class C privilege of the driver in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-812">Transportation Article, §16-812(o), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-104">12-104</cite>(b), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-208">16-208</cite>.1, 16-808, 16-812, and 16-820,<br/>Annotated Code of Maryland; 49 CFR §§383.51, 383.52, 384.208, and 384.210</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-09-30">Effective date: September 30, 2005 (32:19 Md. R. 1588)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-10-10"><cite path="|11|11|12|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective October 10, 2016 (43:20 Md. R. 1110)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-04-09"><cite path="|11|11|12|.07">Regulation .07</cite> adopted effective April 9, 2007 (34:7 Md. R. 699)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-04-19"><cite path="|11|11|12|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective April 19, 2010 (37:8 Md. R. 617)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-11-03"><cite path="|11|11|12|.08">Regulation .08</cite> adopted effective November 3, 2008 (35:22 Md. R. 1958)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-10-10"><cite path="|11|11|12|.09">Regulation .09</cite> adopted effective October 10, 2016 (43:20 Md. R. 1110)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
