<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>13</num>
  <heading>Ignition Interlock Program</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>The Ignition Interlock System Program established by the Administration under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-404">Transportation Article, §16-404</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland, requires certain individuals who are convicted of a certain offense under certain circumstances to participate in the Program, requires certain individuals to participate in the Program as a condition of modification of a license suspension or revocation, and allows certain individuals with an alcohol-related driving offense or conviction to participate in the Program as a condition of continued licensure. The purpose of this chapter is to establish the eligibility requirements for participation in the Program, to monitor the participants, and to define the administrative action to be taken if a participant violates the conditions or requirements of the Program.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Administration" means the Maryland Motor Vehicle Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Approved service provider" or "service provider" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-404">Transportation Article, §16-404</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"BAC" means the breath alcohol concentration determined by a breath analyzer that measures the amount of alcohol in an individual's breath.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Ignition interlock device" or "interlock device" means an ignition interlock system as defined under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|21-902">Transportation Article, §21-902</cite>.2, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Interlock" means the mechanism by which a motor vehicle is prevented from starting when the test result of an individual's breath alcohol analysis exceeds a preset alcohol concentration level.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Participant" means an individual enrolled in the Ignition Interlock System Program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Program" means the Ignition Interlock System Program established by the Administration under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-404">Transportation Article, §16-404</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Reporting period" means the time period that begins at the time of installation of the ignition interlock device and reoccurs every 30 days thereafter until the successful completion of the Program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“Service Provider Certification” means an electronic verification that the data recorded by the device, and certified as accurate by the participant’s approved service provider, and transmitted to the Administration in the 3 consecutive months prior to the participant’s completion date did not contain any of the violations specified in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-404">Transportation Article, §16-404</cite>.1(n), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Successful completion" means satisfactorily fulfilling all the conditions for participation in the Program and the Administration is in receipt of the Service Provider Certification.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|11|13|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Requirements for Enrollment in the Program.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>To enroll as a participant in the Program, an individual shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Have a valid Maryland license that is not currently suspended, revoked, cancelled, or refused in this or any other state;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Notify the Administration, in writing, of the individual's choice to participate in the Program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Have an interlock device installed in the individual's vehicle by an approved service provider;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Surrender all Maryland driver's licenses, including a temporary license, or submit a signed statement certifying no driver's license is in the individual's possession;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Submit the service provider's completed sealed enrollment form to a full service Administration office;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Pay the required ignition interlock participation fee as set forth in <cite path="|11.11.05">COMAR 11.11.05</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Obtain a Maryland driver's license with an interlock restriction.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An individual will not receive credit for participation in the Program unless.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All the requirements set forth in <cite path="11|11|13|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> have been complied with; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The individual obtains a restricted driver’s license before the earlier of 30 days from installation of the ignition interlock or their first ignition interlock monthly calibration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An individual may only receive credit towards participation while they hold a valid driving privilege.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Except when the participant is a repeat offender subject to the provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-205">Transportation Article, §16-205(e), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, an employer waiver, allowing the participant to drive an employer vehicle in the course of the participant’s employment during normal working hours, may be granted by the courts, or by the Administration, with submission of documentation of current employment and the need for the participant to operate the motor vehicle in the course of employment, in a form that is acceptable to the Administration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An individual who requests an administrative hearing to show cause why the individual’s driver’s license should not be suspended or revoked is no longer eligible to participate in the Program unless:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The individual withdraws the request for an administrative hearing and completes all the requirements set forth in <cite path="11|11|13|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The individual’s license suspension or revocation is modified by a final decision of an administrative law judge of the Office of Administrative Hearings to allow participation in the Program.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If the device is installed in a vehicle not owned by the participant, the individual shall provide the Administration with a notarized signed statement from the owner of the vehicle authorizing the installation of the interlock device.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The participant shall abide by the terms and conditions of the service provider's agreement, including payment of all costs and fees associated with the Program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The Administration ignition interlock participation fee may be waived for participants experiencing financial hardship as set forth in <cite path="11.11.11.02">COMAR 11.11.11.02</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>As a condition of continued enrollment in the Program, a participant shall have the interlock device serviced and data downloaded by a service provider, at a frequency not to exceed 30 days.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|11|13|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Violations of the Program.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A participant is in violation of the Program requirements if the individual:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Receives a suspension, revocation, refusal, or cancellation of the individual's driving privilege;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Has the interlock device installed in a vehicle with an expired or invalid registration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Removes the interlock device without prior approval from the Administration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Operates a vehicle without an ignition interlock device installed in the vehicle;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Tampers with, bypasses, damages, or otherwise removes or renders the ignition interlock device inoperable, or allows another individual to tamper with, bypass, or render the device inoperable;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Attempts to start or operate a vehicle with a breath alcohol concentration greater than 0.025 percent, unless there is a subsequent test reading within 10 minutes that indicates a breath alcohol concentration below 0.026 percent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Fails to submit to a retest after starting the vehicle;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Fails to operate the interlock-equipped vehicle at least 50 times during a reporting period as recorded on the interlock device;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Fails to take the interlock-equipped vehicle to a scheduled monthly monitoring appointment with the service provider as set forth in <cite path="|11|11|13|.03|F.">Regulation .03F of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Fails to abide by the terms and conditions of the participant's agreement with the service provider;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Allows another individual to blow into the interlock device while the participant is operating the vehicle;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Participates in any other act or use of the interlock device that poses a threat to highway safety; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Receives an Order of Suspension under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-205">Transportation Article, §16-205</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall notify the participant when one or more violations are found during a reporting period.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>When a violation of the Program is found, there is a presumption that the violation has been committed by the participant when the person is not clearly visible and identifiable in the interlock device camera image.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If a participant alleged to have committed a violation of the requirements of <cite path="11|11|13|.04|A.|(7)">§A(7) of this regulation</cite> is deaf or hard of hearing, the Administration shall consider this circumstance when evaluating whether to assess a violation prior to removal from the Program.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Removal from the Program.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Administration may remove a participant from the Program and reinstate the original suspension or revocation if the Administration finds any violation of the Program requirements set forth in <cite path="|11|11|13|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration may extend the participant's required period of participation in the Program by 30 days instead of removal for a violation set forth in <cite path="|11|11|13|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall remove any participant who is in violation of Program requirements during more than three monthly monitoring cycles.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall notify the participant of the removal from the Program and reinstatement of a suspension or revocation, or of the Administration's decision to extend the participant's required period of participation in the Program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Credit for the time served in the Program is not given to a participant removed from the Program before successfully completing the individual's required period of participation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If a person is removed from the program before successfully completing the program, that person may request that the Administration allow re-enrollment and entry into the program no earlier than 30 days from the date of the participant’s removal.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A person who re-enters the program pursuant to this regulation shall be required to complete the full original period of assignment to the interlock program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>A person who fails to successfully complete the Program will not receive credit towards future participation in the program arising from the same incident.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Response to Notice of Violation.</heading>
    <text>The Administration may determine that a violation did not occur on receipt of verified documentation or other information satisfactory to the Administration from:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The participant, within 15 days of the notice of violation date, explaining why the participant contends the violation was not committed; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The participant's interlock service provider, indicating a reported violation resulted from a malfunction of the installed device for which the participant was not responsible.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Hearing Rights.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An individual participating in the program who is notified by the Administration that the individual will be removed for violations of the Program under this chapter, may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Request a hearing on the suspension or revocation resulting from the removal from the Program; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Have the suspension held in abeyance pending the outcome of the administrative hearing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The interlock unit shall remain installed in the vehicle until a final decision is rendered at the hearing regarding the individual’s participation in the interlock program.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Referral to Medical Advisory Board.</heading>
    <text>This chapter does not limit the Administration's authority to:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Refer a participant to the Medical Advisory Board; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Require that a participant in the Program be actively enrolled in or have completed a certified alcohol treatment or substance abuse program.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Successful Completion.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An individual has successfully completed the Program when:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The participant satisfactorily fulfilled all the conditions for participation in the Program; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Administration is in receipt of the Service Provider Certification as required in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-404">Transportation Article, §16-404</cite>.1(n), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A person who successfully completes the Program will receive credit towards future participation in the Program arising from the same incident.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-104">12-104</cite>(b), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-205">16-205</cite>.1, 16-404.1, and 21-902.2, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-11-03">Effective date: November 3, 2008 (35:22 Md. R. 1958)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-12-12"><cite path="|11|11|13|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective October 1, 2011 (38:21 Md. R. 1275); amended permanently effective December 12, 2011 (38:25 Md. R. 1582)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-10-01"><cite path="|11|11|13|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective October 1, 2016 (43:19 Md. R. 1073); October 1, 2019 (46:19 Md. R. 815)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-12-12"><cite path="|11|11|13|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective October 1, 2011 (38:21 Md. R. 1275); amended permanently effective December 12, 2011 (38:25 Md. R. 1582)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-12-12"><cite path="|11|11|13|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective March 28, 2016 (43:6 Md. R. 409); October 1, 2016 (43:19 Md. R. 1073); December 12, 2024 (51:24 Md. R. 1081)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-10-01"><cite path="|11|11|13|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite> amended effective July 26, 2010 (37:15 Md. R. 999); October 1, 2016 (43:19 Md. R. 1073)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-10-01"><cite path="|11|11|13|.04|C.">Regulation .04C</cite> adopted effective October 1, 2019 (46:19 Md. R. 815)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-04-15"><cite path="|11|11|13|.04|D.">Regulation .04D</cite> adopted effective April 15, 2024 (51:7 Md. Reg. 332)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-12-12"><cite path="|11|11|13|.05|F.">Regulation .05F</cite>, G adopted as an emergency provision effective October 1, 2011 (38:21 Md. R. 1275); amended permanently effective December 12, 2011 (38:25 Md. R. 1582)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-10-01"><cite path="|11|11|13|.05|H.">Regulation .05H</cite> adopted effective October 1, 2016 (43:19 Md. R. 1073)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-07-26"><cite path="|11|11|13|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective July 26, 2010 (37:15 Md. R. 999)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-12-12"><cite path="|11|11|13|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective October 1, 2011 (38:21 Md. R. 1275); amended permanently effective December 12, 2011 (38:25 Md. R. 1582)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-10-01"><cite path="|11|11|13|.09">Regulation .09</cite> adopted effective October 1, 2016 (43:19 Md. R. 1073)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
