<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>14</num>
  <heading>Service of Process for Nonresident Drivers</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose and Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcj|6-313">Courts and Judicial Proceedings, §6-313, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the Administration shall serve as the agent to receive a subpoena, summons, or other process for a nonresident driver named in an action brought in a court of this State related to an accident or collision involving a motor vehicle occurring within the State of Maryland on or after October 1, 2008. The purpose of this chapter is to establish regulations to implement the service of process for nonresident drivers.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>To the extent this chapter conflicts with any other provisions of this title, the provisions of this chapter shall prevail.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Administration" means the Motor Vehicle Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Certification of last known residence" means a form required by the Administration stating the last known address of the nonresident as certified by the party or party's attorney of record seeking to serve the Administration as statutory agent on behalf of the nonresident.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Motor vehicle" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|11-135">Transportation Article, §11-135, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Investigation Division" means the Investigation Division of the Motor Vehicle Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Nonresident" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|11-139">Transportation Article, §11-139, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Nonresident motor vehicle cases" means court cases involving motor vehicle accidents or collisions by nonresident drivers in which the Administration is authorized by law to accept service of process, as stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-104">Transportation Article, §12-104(f), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and this chapter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Service of process" means the service of a summons, subpoena, or other process issued under Court and Judicial Proceedings Article, §6-313, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Authorization of Employees.</heading>
    <text>Designated employees of the Investigation Division are authorized to receive the service of process on behalf of the Administration as statutory agent for out-of-State drivers in nonresident motor vehicle cases.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Request for Service of Process Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Service of process shall be made on the Administration as statutory agent for a nonresident driver under this chapter by personal delivery to the Investigation Division of the Motor Vehicle Administration at 6601 Ritchie Highway, N.E., Glen Burnie, Maryland 21062.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An individual seeking service of process shall submit a request on a form approved by the Administration and include with the request form:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A copy of the process;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Certification of last known address of the nonresident driver; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Payment of the fee for service of process established in <cite path="11.11.05.06">COMAR 11.11.05.06</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A separate request for service of process shall be made for each nonresident driver for which statutory service of process is sought.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Administration's Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall send a copy of the service of process to a nonresident driver upon the receipt of a completed application in which the applicant has met all the requirements set forth in <cite path="|11|11|14|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The copy of the service of process shall be sent to the nonresident driver by certified mail with return receipt requested to the last known address certified by the applicant.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>File an affidavit certifying service compliance with the clerk of the court where the case was filed; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide a copy of the affidavit to the applicant requesting the service of process.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Exceptions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Administration may not accept service of process as statutory agent under this chapter in any case that is not a nonresident motor vehicle case.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration may not accept a request for service of process as statutory agent under this chapter in any case where:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The requirements in <cite path="|11|11|14|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite> have not been met;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The person on whose behalf statutory service is sought is not a nonresident driver; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The cause of action was before October 1, 2008.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-104">Transportation Article, §12-104</cite>; <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcj|6-313">Courts and Judicial Proceedings, §6-313</cite>; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-04-06">Effective date: April 6, 2009 (36:7 Md. R. 525)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
