<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>15</num>
  <heading>Refusal to Renew or Transfer a Vehicle Registration and Refusal to Renew a Driver's License for Failure to Pay Undisputed Taxes and Unemployment Insurance Contributions</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter contains procedures governing the refusal to renew or transfer a vehicle registration and the refusal to renew a driver's license of an applicant as a result of unpaid tax liabilities or unpaid unemployment insurance contributions.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This chapter applies to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Individuals for whom or entities for which the Comptroller has notified the Administration of failure to pay all undisputed taxes or failure to provide for payment in a manner satisfactory to the Comptroller; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Individuals for whom or entities for which the Maryland Department of Labor has notified the Administration of failure to pay undisputed unemployment insurance contributions or failure to provide for payment in a manner satisfactory to the Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Administration" means the Motor Vehicle Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Comptroller" means the Comptroller of Maryland or the Comptroller’s designee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Driver’s license" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|11-116">Transportation Article, §11-116, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Maryland Department of Labor (MDL)” means the Secretary of Labor or the Secretary’s designee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Release” means evidence that an applicant either has paid all undisputed taxes and unemployment contributions payable to the Comptroller or the Maryland Department of Labor or has provided for payment in a manner satisfactory to the agency responsible for collection.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Undisputed tax liabilities” means an assessment of tax that has become final.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Reporting Undisputed Taxes and Unemployment Insurance Contributions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Comptroller or MDL shall transmit to the Administration, in a format and frequency agreed to by the Administration, Comptroller, and MDL:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Undisputed tax liabilities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Releases for tax liabilities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Undisputed unemployment insurance contribution liabilities; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Releases for unemployment insurance contribution liabilities.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In the event the Comptroller or MDL transmits to the Administration records which the Administration is unable to match to the Administration’s records, the Administration shall notify the Comptroller or MDL of all unmatched names and partially matched names.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In the event the Administration notifies the Comptroller or MDL of unmatched names and partially matched names, the Comptroller or MDL shall attempt to match all unmatched names and partially matched names and transmit back to the Administration.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Nonrenewal or transfer of Registration and Nonrenewal of Driver’s License.</heading>
    <text>Upon notification to the Administration from the Comptroller or MDL that an individual or entity has failed to pay undisputed taxes or unemployment insurance contributions, or has failed to arrange for a plan of payment in a manner satisfactory to the agency responsible for collection, and upon a positive match to that individual in Administration records, the Administration shall refuse:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>For any vehicle owned or co-owned by applicant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To renew the vehicle registration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>To transfer the vehicle registration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>To issue a replacement tag;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>To issue a substitute set of tags; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>To issue a substitute set of registration stickers; and</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>For the applicant’s driver’s license:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To renew the driver’s license; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>To renew the driver’s license with correction.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Notice of Proposed Action.</heading>
    <text>The Administration shall advise the applicant:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>That the registration renewal or transfer of any vehicle owned by the applicant and the renewal of the applicant’s driver's license will be refused; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>That the individual or entity must contact the Comptroller or MDL to resolve any questions regarding undisputed taxes and unemployment insurance contributions.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Reinstatement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall continue to refuse the transactions as set forth in <cite path="|11|11|15|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite> for an applicant who has failed to pay undisputed taxes and unemployment insurance contributions, until the Administration receives evidence from the Comptroller or MDL that all tax liabilities and unemployment insurance contribution liabilities have been released.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Comptroller or MDL shall notify the Administration on the next business day, excluding Maryland State holidays as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsp|9-201">State Personnel and Pensions Article, §9-201, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, when satisfactory arrangements have been made to pay undisputed taxes and unemployment insurance contributions.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-104">12-104</cite>(b), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-809">13-809</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-812">13-812</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-11-14">Regulations <cite path="|11|11|15|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|11|11|15|.06">.06</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective August 18, 2011 (38:19 Md. R. 1146); adopted permanently effective November 14, 2011 (38:23 Md. R. 1422)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
