<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>06</num>
  <heading>Armored Car Guard Supplemental Background Investigations</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Approved armored car company” is an armored car company that has applied for and been approved to complete supplemental background investigations</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Armored car company”, as defined in 15 U.S.C. §5904(2) (Title 15. Commerce and Trade; Chapter 85. Armored Car Industry Reciprocity), means a company subject to regulation under subchapter I of chapter 135 of title 49, United States Code (49 U.S.C. §§13501 et seq.) and that is registered under chapter 139 of such title (49 U.S.C. §§13901 et seq.), in order to engage in the business of transporting and protecting currency, bullion, securities, precious metals, supplemental nutrition assistance program benefits, and other articles of unusual value in interstate commerce.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Armored car guard” means an individual employed by an armored car company to provide armored car services and who carries a firearm or is authorized by the employer to access a firearm when providing armored car services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Armored car services” means services provided by an armored car company on a contractual basis for another person, firm, association, or corporation for a fee or other valuable consideration and performs the following primary function of providing secured transportation and protection from one place or point to another place or point of money, currency, coins, bullion, securities, checks, documents, stocks, bonds, jewelry, paintings, and other valuables for a fee or other valuable consideration</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Investigation supervisor” refers to the individual or individuals, assigned by the Secretary, to review and approve background investigations for wear and carry handgun permits issued by the Maryland State Police.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Secretary” means the Secretary of the Maryland State Police.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Supplemental background investigation”, as defined pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|5-305">Public Safety Article, §5-305, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, refers to a background investigation submitted to the Maryland State Police that is completed by a representative of an approved armored car company, to be considered with the additional required background investigation conducted by the Maryland Department of State Police, as described in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|5-306">Public Safety Article, §5-306, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Generally.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An armored car company shall complete an application, in a format determined by the Secretary, to be considered to conduct supplemental background investigations to be considered in the issuance of wear and carry handgun permits to armored car guards for their company.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Once approved by the Secretary to conduct and submit supplemental background investigations, an armored car company shall submit supplemental background investigations in a format determined by the Secretary.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A valid supplemental background investigation shall meet the same requirements as those required for all wear and carry handgun permit applicants, including any limitations or restrictions imposed by the Secretary.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Eligibility for Supplemental Background Investigations Conducted by an Armored Car Company.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Only armored car companies, as defined in <cite path="|29|04|06|.01">Regulation .01 of this chapter</cite>, shall be eligible to apply to conduct supplemental background investigations to be considered in the issuance of a wear and carry handgun permit by the Secretary.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A separate application and approval is required for each individual armored car company seeking to conduct wear and carry handgun permit supplemental background investigations, regardless of the ownership or relationship to any other approved armored car company.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An armored car company approved by the Secretary under this chapter may conduct and submit supplemental background investigations only for active employees of their company. Armored car companies are not required to conduct their own background investigations and may, at any time, submit applications for wear and carry handgun permits for investigation by the Maryland State Police.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Application Process to Become an Approved Armored Car Company.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Any application submitted by a company that does not meet the definition of an armored car company, as defined in <cite path="|29|04|06|.01">Regulation .01 of this chapter</cite> will not be considered for approval.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Any armored car company seeking to be approved to conduct supplemental background investigations shall be provided with an application packet in a format determined by the Secretary. This packet will include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A listing of guidelines for submission of supplemental investigations for wear and carry handgun permit applicants;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A detailed listing of mandatory requirements to be included in the wear and carry handgun permit supplemental background investigation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A copy of the relevant provisions listed in <cite path="29.03.01.03">COMAR 29.03.01.03</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps">Public Safety Article, Title 5, Subtitle 3, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and any other relevant sections of law which directly relate to the issuance of wear and carry handgun permits as prescribed by the Secretary.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An armored car company shall submit the completed application, in the format determined by the Secretary, to be considered for approval to conduct wear and carry handgun permit supplemental background investigations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>All completed applications submitted to the Secretary shall include the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Proof that the company meets the definition of an armored car company, as defined in <cite path="|29|04|06|.01|B.">Regulation .01B of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A sample supplemental background investigation which has been completed utilizing the format and requirements provided for and outlined in §B(1)—(3) of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Process for an Approved Armored Car Company to Conduct Supplemental Background Investigations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An armored car company seeking approval to complete supplemental background investigations shall submit an application in compliance with <cite path="|29|04|06|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>. All applications shall be reviewed for completeness and accuracy. Only completed applications shall be considered for approval. Completed applications shall be reviewed by the investigation supervisor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The armored car company’s application shall be approved or disapproved by the reviewing member of the Maryland State Police following the informal hearing. The applying company shall be notified of their approval or disapproval in writing. Any company that is disapproved will receive an explanation from the investigation supervisor for their disapproval.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>After approval of the application, a meeting will occur between the investigation supervisor and representatives of the armored car company that filed the application and will be completing the supplemental investigation to complete orientation and training. The armored car company may be questioned further regarding its policy and procedures used to complete the sample background investigation submitted with the application.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An approved armored car company shall receive an orientation packet from the investigation supervisor, with detailed instructions regarding the submission, correction, and approval of supplemental background investigations.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Process for Wear and Carry Handgun Permit — Employees of an Approved Armored Car Company.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>These procedures will apply to all submitted wear and carry handgun permit applications for armored car guards, with the exception of those submitted under <cite path="|29|04|06|.03|C.">Regulation .03C of this chapter</cite> to be investigated solely by the Maryland State Police.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Armored car companies shall submit completed supplemental background investigations together with the appropriately completed wear and carry handgun permit application. These will be submitted in the format established by the Secretary and in compliance with the procedures as outlined in <cite path="29.03.02.04">COMAR 29.03.02.04</cite> for the submission of wear and carry handgun permit applications.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Applications received without the supplemental background investigation shall be assigned to a member of Maryland State Police for investigation. Any supplemental background investigation completed by an approved armored car company submitted separately from the wear and carry handgun permit application will not be accepted.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Supplemental background investigations completed by armored car companies shall be used in determining the qualification of the applying armored car guard for a wear and carry handgun permit. The supplemental background investigation shall be used in conjunction with, not in lieu of, the required additional investigation by the Maryland State Police.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Compliance.</heading>
    <text>All supplemental background investigations completed by an approved armored car company shall be subject to review and audit by the Secretary or designee.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Revocation of Approval to Submit Supplemental Background Investigations for Handgun Permits.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An approved armored car company that submits supplemental background investigations for wear and carry handgun permits which do not meet the requirements as determined by the Secretary may have their approval to complete supplemental background investigations revoked.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An armored car company shall receive written notification of the revocation of their approval to complete supplemental background investigations. An armored car company that has its privilege revoked may be allowed to reapply for consideration to conduct supplemental background investigations for wear and carry handgun permits.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|5-305">Public Safety Article, §5-305, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-02-29">Effective date: February 29, 2016 (43:4 Md. R. 333)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
