<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Tenant Protection Assistance</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>General.</heading>
    <text>A tenant is entitled to tenant protection assistance, including relocation expenses and lease extensions, in accordance with §§7-212—7-219 of the Act.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Relocation Expenses.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>To receive the additional $475 for relocation expenses authorized in the Act, the tenant shall submit reasonable documentation of actual and reasonable relocation expenses to the owner within 60 days after the tenant vacates the unit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The owner shall pay the additional relocation expenses to the tenant within 15 days after the documented expenses are submitted to the owner.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Lease Extensions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The owner shall offer a lease extension for a period of at least 1 year from the date of the notice of intent to each assisted household that has not committed a material violation of the lease.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The owner shall include in each extended lease the criteria for early termination or cessation of the extended lease that are listed in §7-218 of the Act.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Designated Households.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Designated households that do not receive an extended tenancy under the Act may be eligible for rental equivalent payments and relocation expense payments under §7-219(e) of the Act.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>All designated households are eligible upon vacating their assisted unit for reimbursement by the project owner for ordinary relocation expenses payable to all assisted households in accordance with §7-212(b)(1) and (2) of the Act.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Designated Household Assistance — Records.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The owner shall create and maintain accurate records that set forth:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The relocation and reimbursement expenses paid to each assisted household;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The rates of rent charged for the assisted units; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any other information concerning tenant protection assistance provided by the owner.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The records shall be retained and available for inspection by the Department for five years after the date of the notice of intent delivered to the tenants.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Housing and Community Development Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ghs|7-101">7-101</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ghs|7-501">7-501</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-04-18">Effective date: April 18, 2011 (38:8 Md. R. 505)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
