<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>06</num>
  <heading>Enforcement and Waivers</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Due Diligence.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Settlement agents conducting real estate settlements involving the sale of residential rental projects, or the release of federally-assisted mortgages or related documents encumbering the projects, shall make inquiries of the owner as to the nature of the project, and the possible termination of federal assistance which may be governed by the Act and these regulations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If responses to the agent’s inquiries, the nature of the transaction and related documents, or any information otherwise known to the settlement agent raises a reasonable possibility that a sworn statement under §7-307 of the Act is required, the settlement agent shall use its best efforts to procure and file a sworn statement with the Department, and if unable to comply, shall notify the Department in writing before the settlement of the circumstances of the failure to deliver the sworn statement.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Settlement agents failing to comply with this regulation may be subject to civil liability and civil monetary penalties in accordance with the Act.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Waiver.</heading>
    <text>The Secretary may, by written determination, waive or vary particular provisions of these regulations, provided that:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The waiver is not inconsistent with the Act; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In the written determination of the Secretary, the application of the regulations in a specific case, or in an emergency situation, would be inequitable or contrary to the purposes of the Act, and would not substantially limit any significant protections to tenants required under the Act.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Housing and Community Development Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ghs|7-101">7-101</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ghs|7-501">7-501</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-04-18">Effective date: April 18, 2011 (38:8 Md. R. 505)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
