<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>07</num>
  <heading>Proxies, Consents, and Authorizations of Domestic Stock Insurers</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|04|07|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Applicability.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter does not apply to any insurer if 95 percent or more of its equity securities is owned or controlled by a parent or an affiliated insurer and the remaining securities are held of record by less than 500 persons. A domestic stock insurer which files with the Securities and Exchange Commission with respect to any class of securities forms of proxies, consents, and authorizations complying with the requirements of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934, as amended, and its applicable regulations, is exempt from the provisions of this chapter with respect to that class of securities.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A domestic stock insurer that has any class of equity securities held of record by 300 or more persons, or any director, officer, or employee of that insurer, or any other person, may not solicit, or permit the use of the person's name to solicit, by mail or otherwise, any proxy, consent, or authorization in respect to any class of equity securities in contravention of this regulation and Schedules A and B in Regulations .14 and .15 of this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Unless proxies, consents, or authorizations with respect to any class of equity securities of a domestic insurer subject to <cite path="31|04|07|.01|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> are solicited by or on behalf of the management of the insurer from the holders of record of the securities in accordance with this chapter and its schedules prior to any annual or other meeting of the security holders, the insurer shall file with the Commissioner and transmit to every security holder who is entitled to vote in regard to any matter to be acted upon at the meeting and from whom a proxy is not solicited a written information statement containing the information specified in Schedule C of <cite path="|31|04|07|.16">Regulation .16 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Affiliate" means a person that directly, or indirectly through one or more intermediaries, controls, or is controlled by, or is under common control with, the person specified.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Associate" means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A corporation or organization (other than the issuer or a majority owned subsidiary of the issuer) of which the person is an officer or partner or is, directly or indirectly, the beneficial owner of 10 percent or more of any class of equity securities;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A trust or other estate in which the person has a substantial beneficial interest or as to which the person serves as trustee or in a similar fiduciary capacity; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A relative or spouse of that person, or any relative of the spouse, who has the same home as the person or who is a director or officer of the issuer or any of its parents or subsidiaries.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Beneficial owner" means a person who, directly or indirectly, through a contract, arrangement, understanding, relationship, or otherwise, has or shares:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Voting power including the power to vote, or the power to direct voting of, a security; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Investment power which includes the power to dispose of, or to direct the disposition of, the security.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Control" (including the terms "controlling", "controlled by" and "under common control with") means the possession, direct or indirect, of the power to direct or cause the direction of the management and policies of a person, whether through the ownership of voting securities, by contract, or otherwise.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Issuer" means the issuer of the securities in respect of which a proxy is solicited.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Last fiscal year" means the last fiscal year of the issuer ending before the date of the meeting for which proxies are to be solicited.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Officer" means the president, secretary, treasurer, any vice president in charge of a principal business function (such as sales, administration, or finance), and any other individual who performs similar policy-making functions for the insurer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Parent" means an affiliate controlling the person directly or indirectly through one or more intermediaries.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Person" means an individual, a corporation, a partnership, an association, a joint stock company, a trust, an unincorporated organization, or a government or political subdivision of a government.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Proxy statement" means the statement required by <cite path="|31|04|07|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>, whether or not contained in a single document.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Solicitation.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Solicitation" means:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A request for a proxy, whether or not accompanied by or included in a form of proxy;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A request to execute or not to execute, or to revoke, a proxy; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The furnishing of a form of proxy or other communication to security holders under circumstances reasonably calculated to result in the procurement, withholding, or revocation of a proxy.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Solicitation" does not apply, however, to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The furnishing of a form of proxy to a security holder upon the unsolicited request of the security holder;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The performance by the issuer of acts required by <cite path="|31|04|07|.08">Regulation .08 of this chapter</cite>; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The performance by any person of ministerial acts on behalf of a person soliciting a proxy.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>"Trust" includes only a trust where the interest or interests of the beneficiary or beneficiaries are evidenced by a security.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Solicitations to Which Chapter Applies.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text><cite path="|31|04|07|.10">Regulation .10</cite> of this chapter applies to every solicitation that is subject to <cite path="|31|04|07|.01">Regulation .01 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Regulations <cite path="|31|04|07|.02">.02</cite>—<cite path="|31|04|07|.09">.09</cite> and <cite path="|31|04|07|.11">Regulation .11 of this chapter</cite> apply to every solicitation that is subject to Regulation .01 except the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A solicitation made otherwise than on behalf of the issuer where the total number of persons solicited is not more than ten;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A solicitation by a person with respect to securities carried in the person's name or in the name of the person's nominee (otherwise than as voting trustee), or held in the person's custody, if the person:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Receives no commission or remuneration for the solicitation, directly or indirectly, other than reimbursement of reasonable expenses;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Furnishes promptly to the solicited person a copy of all soliciting material with respect to the same subject matter or meeting received from all persons who shall furnish copies for that purpose and who shall, if requested, defray the reasonable expenses to be incurred in forwarding the material; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>In addition, does no more than impartially instruct the person solicited to forward a proxy to the person, if any, to whom the person solicited desires to give a proxy, or impartially request from the person solicited instructions as to the authority to be conferred by the proxy and state that a proxy will be given if no instructions are received by a certain date;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A solicitation by a person with respect to securities of which it is the beneficial owner;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A solicitation through the medium of a newspaper advertisement which informs security holders of a source from which they may obtain copies of a proxy statement, form of proxy, and any other soliciting material, and does no more than:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Name the issuer;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>State the reason for the advertisement; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Identify the proposal or proposals to be acted upon by security holders; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Any solicitation which the Commissioner finds for good cause should be exempted from this chapter or any part of this chapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|04|07|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Information to be Furnished Security Holders.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A solicitation subject to this chapter may not be made unless each person solicited is concurrently furnished or has previously been furnished with a written proxy statement containing the information specified in Schedule A.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Annual Report.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If the solicitation is made on behalf of the issuer and relates to an annual meeting of security holders at which directors are to be elected, each proxy statement furnished pursuant to <cite path="31|04|07|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall be accompanied or preceded by an annual report to security holders as decided in this section.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The report shall contain, in comparative columnar form, such financial statements for the last 2 fiscal years, prepared on a consistent basis, as will in the opinion of the management adequately reflect the financial position of the issuer at the end of each year, and the results of its operations for each year. Consolidated financial statements of the issuer and its subsidiaries shall be included in the report if they are necessary to reflect the financial position and results of operations of the issuer and its subsidiaries, but in that case the individual statements of the issuer may be omitted. The Commissioner may, upon the request of the issuer, permit the omission of financial statements for the earlier of the 2 fiscal years upon a showing of good cause.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The financial statements for the last 2 fiscal years required by <cite path="31|04|07|.04|B.|(2)">§B(2) of this regulation</cite> shall be prepared in a manner acceptable to the Commissioner.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The report shall include, in comparative columnar form, a summary of issuer's operations, or the operations of the issuer and its subsidiaries consolidated, or both as appropriate, for each of the last 5 fiscal years of the issuer (or the life of the issuer and its predecessors, if less).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The report shall contain a brief description of the business or businesses done by the issuer and its subsidiaries during the most recent fiscal year which will, in the opinion of management, indicate the general nature and scope of the business of the issuer and its subsidiaries.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The report shall identify each of the issuer's directors and officers and shall indicate the principal occupation or employment of each person and the name and principal business of any organization by which the person is so employed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The report shall identify the principal market in which securities of any class entitled to vote at the meeting are traded, stating the range of bid and asked quotations for each quarterly period during the issuer's 2 most recent fiscal years, and shall set forth each dividend paid during the 2-year period.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Subject to the foregoing requirements, the report may be in any form considered suitable by management, and the information required by §B(4)—(7) of this regulation may be presented in an appendix or other separate section of the report, if the attention of security holders is called to the presentation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>This section does not apply, however, to solicitations made on behalf of the management before the financial statements are available if solicitation is being made at the time in opposition to the management and if the management's proxy statement includes an undertaking in bold face type to furnish the annual report to all persons being solicited, at least 20 days before the date of the meeting.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Two copies of the report sent to security holders pursuant to this regulation shall be mailed to the Commissioner not later than the date on which the report was first sent or given to security holders, or the date on which preliminary copies of solicitation material are filed pursuant to <cite path="|31|04|07|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite>, whichever date is later.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the issuer knows that securities of any class entitled to vote at a meeting with respect to which the issuer intends to solicit proxies, consents, or authorizations are held of record by a broker, dealer, bank, or voting trustee, or their nominees, the issuer shall inquire of the record holder at least 10 days before the record date for the meeting of security holders whether other persons are the beneficial owners of the securities and, if so, the number of copies of the proxy and other soliciting material and, in the case of an annual meeting at which directors are to be elected, the number of copies of the annual report to security holders, necessary to supply these materials to beneficial owners. The issuer shall supply the record holder in a timely manner with additional copies assembled in a form and at a place the record holder may reasonably request, in order to address and send one copy to each beneficial owner of securities so held and shall, upon the request of the record holder, pay its reasonable expenses for mailing the materials to security holders to whom the material is sent.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|04|07|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Requirements as to Proxy.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Form of Proxy.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The form of proxy shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Indicate in bold face type whether or not the proxy is solicited on behalf of the insurer's board of directors, or, if not, by whom it is solicited;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Provide a specifically designated blank space for dating the proxy; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Identify clearly and impartially each matter or group of related matters intended to be acted upon, whether proposed by the issuer or by security holders.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Reference need not be made to proposals as to which discretionary authority is conferred pursuant to <cite path="31|04|07|.05|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Contents.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Means shall be provided in the form of proxy by which the person solicited is afforded an opportunity to specify by ballot a choice between approval or disapproval of, or abstention with respect to, each matter or group of related matters referred to as intended to be acted upon, other than elections to office. A proxy may confer discretionary authority with respect to matters as to which a choice is not specified, if the form of proxy states in bold face type how it is intended to vote the shares represented by the proxy in each case.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A form of proxy, which provides both for the election of directors and for action on other specified matters, shall be prepared clearly to provide, by a box or otherwise, a means by which the security holder may withhold authority to vote for any nominee for election as a director. The form of proxy, which is executed by the security holder in a manner as not to withhold authority to vote for the election of all nominees, shall be considered to grant authority for all nominees for which a vote is not withheld, if the form of proxy so states in bold face type.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A proxy may confer discretionary authority to vote with respect to any of the following matters:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Matters which the persons making the solicitation do not know, a reasonable time before the solicitation, are to be presented at the meeting, if a specific statement to that effect is made in the proxy statement or form of proxy;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Approval of the minutes of the prior meeting if the approval does not amount to ratification of the action taken at that meeting;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The election of any individual to any office for which a bona fide nominee is named in the proxy statement and the nominee is unable to serve or for good cause will not serve;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Any proposal omitted from the proxy statement and form of proxy pursuant to Regulation .09 or .10 of this chapter; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Matters incident to the conduct of the meeting.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A proxy may not confer authority to vote for the election of any individual to any office for which a bona fide nominee is not named in the proxy statement, or to vote at any annual meeting, other than the next annual meeting (or any adjournment of it), to be held after the date on which the proxy statement and form of proxy are first sent or given to security holders. A person is not considered to be a bona fide nominee and may not be named the bona fide nominee unless the individual has consented to being named in the proxy statement and to serve if elected.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The proxy statement or form of proxy shall provide, subject to reasonable specified conditions, that the securities represented by the proxy will be voted and that, if the person solicited specifies by means of a ballot provided pursuant to <cite path="31|04|07|.05|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> a choice with respect to any matter to be acted upon, the securities will be voted in accordance with specifications so made.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Presentation of Information in Proxy Statement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The information included in the proxy statement shall be clearly presented, the statements made shall be divided into groups according to subject matter, and the various groups of statements shall be preceded by appropriate headings.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>All proxy statements shall disclose, under an appropriate caption, the date by which proposals of security holders intended to be presented at the next annual meeting shall be received by the issuer for inclusion in the issuer's proxy statement and form of proxy relating to that meeting. This date shall be calculated in accordance with the provisions of <cite path="|31|04|07|.09|A.">Regulation .09A of this chapter</cite>. If the date of the next annual meeting is subsequently advanced by more than 30 calendar days or delayed by more than 90 calendar days from the date of the annual meeting to which the proxy statement relates, the issuer shall, in a timely manner, inform security holders of the change, and the date by which proposals of security holders must be received, by any means reasonably calculated to so inform them.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|04|07|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Material Required to be Filed.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Two preliminary copies of the proxy statement and form of proxy, and any other soliciting material to be furnished to security holders with the proxy (or the information statement pursuant to Schedule C), shall be filed with the Commissioner at least 10 days before the date final copies of the material are first sent or given to security holders, or a shorter period before that date as the Commissioner may authorize upon a showing of good cause.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Two preliminary copies of any additional soliciting material relating to the same meeting or subject matter to be furnished to security holders after the proxy statement shall be filed with the Commissioner at least 2 days (exclusive of Saturdays, Sundays, and holidays) before the date copies of the material are first sent or given to security holders, or a shorter period before the date as the Commissioner may authorize upon a showing of good cause.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Two definitive copies of the proxy statement, form of proxy, and all other soliciting material (or the information statement), in the form in which the material is furnished to security holders, shall be filed with, or mailed for filing to, the Commissioner not later than the date the material is first sent or given to any security holder.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Copies of replies to inquiries from security holders requesting further information, and copies of communications that do no more than request that forms of proxy previously solicited be signed and returned, do not need to be filed pursuant to this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Despite the provisions of §§A and B of this regulation and of <cite path="|31|04|07|.12|E.">Regulation .12E of this chapter</cite>, copies of soliciting material in the form of speeches, press releases, and radio or television scripts may, but need not, be filed with the Commissioner before use or publication. Definitive copies, however, shall be filed with or mailed for filing to the Commissioner as required by <cite path="31|04|07|.07|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> not later than the date the material is used or published. The provisions of §§A and B of this regulation and of <cite path="|31|04|07|.12|E.">Regulation .12E of this chapter</cite> apply, however, to any reprints or reproductions of all or any part of this material.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If any proxy statement, form of proxy, or other material filed pursuant to this regulation is amended or revised, one of the copies of the amended or revised material filed pursuant to this regulation shall be marked to indicate clearly and precisely the changes.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|04|07|.08">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Mailing Communications for Security Holders.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If the management of the issuer has made or intends to make any solicitation subject to this chapter, the issuer shall perform the acts in §§B—D of this regulation requested in writing with respect to the same subject matter or meeting by any security holder who is, or security holders who are, entitled to vote at least 1 percent of the votes entitled to be voted on the matter and who shall defray the reasonable expenses to be incurred by the issuer in the performance of the act or acts requested.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The issuer shall mail or otherwise furnish to a security holder, as promptly as practicable after the receipt of the request:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A statement of the approximate number of record owners and, to the extent known to the issuer, the approximate number of beneficial owners of any class of securities, any of whom have been or are to be solicited on behalf of the management, or any group of whom the security holder shall designate; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An estimate of the cost of mailing a specified proxy statement, form of proxy, or other communication to the owners.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Issuer Responsibilities.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Copies of any proxy statement, form of proxy, or other communication furnished by the security holder shall be mailed by the issuer to any of the security owners specified in <cite path="31|04|07|.08|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite> as the security holder designates.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The material furnished by the security holder shall be mailed with reasonable promptness after receipt of the material to be mailed, envelopes or other containers, and postage or payment for postage. The issuer need not, however, mail any material before the first day that solicitation is made on behalf of the issuer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The issuer is not responsible for the proxy statement, form of proxy, or other communication.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Instead of performing the acts specified in §§B—C of this regulation, the issuer may, at its option, furnish promptly to a security holder:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A reasonably current list of the names and addresses of the record owners and, to the extent known to the issuer, the beneficial owners the security holder designates; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A schedule of the handling and mailing costs if the schedule has been supplied to the issuer.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Proposals of Security Holders.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If any holder or holders of an issuer's securities (hereafter referred to as the "proponent") notifies the issuer in writing not less than 90 days before the issuer's annual meeting of holder's intention to present a lawful proposal for action at an upcoming meeting of the issuer's security holders, and at the time of the notice the proponent is entitled to vote at least 1 percent of the votes entitled to be voted on the proposal, the issuer shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Set forth the proposal in its proxy statement with the name and address of the proponent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Identify it in its form of proxy; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Provide for the specification of approval or disapproval of the proposal.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the issuer opposes any proposal received from a proponent, it shall also, at the request of the proponent, include in its proxy statement a statement by the proponent of not more than 200 words in support of the proposal.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The issuer may omit a proposal and any statement in support from its proxy statement and form of proxy under any of the following circumstances:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The proponent has submitted more than one proposal in connection with a particular meeting;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The proposal is more than 300 words in length;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The proposal or the supporting statement is contrary to any provision of this chapter or the schedules attached, including <cite path="|31|04|07|.10">Regulation .10 of this chapter</cite> which prohibits false or misleading statements in proxy soliciting materials;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The proposal relates to the enforcement of a personal claim or the redress of a personal grievance against the issuer, its management, or any other person;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The proposal deals with a matter not significantly related to the issuer's business, a matter beyond the issuer's power to effectuate, a matter relating to the conduct of the ordinary business operations of the issuer, or an election to office;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The proposal is counter to a proposal to be submitted by the issuer at the meeting, the proposal has been rendered moot, or the proposal relates to specific amounts of cash or stock dividends;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The proposal is substantially duplicative of a proposal previously submitted to the issuer by another proponent, which proposal will be included in the management's proxy material for the meeting; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Substantially the same proposal has previously been submitted to security holders in the issuer's proxy statement and form of proxy relating to any annual or special meeting of security holders held within the preceding 5 calendar years, and received less than 5 percent of the total number of votes cast at the time of its most recent submission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the issuer intends to omit any proposal from its proxy statement or forms of proxy, or both, it shall notify the proponent in writing of its intention at least 10 days before the issuer's preliminary proxy material is filed pursuant to <cite path="|31|04|07|.07|A.">Regulation .07A of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>False or Misleading Statements.</heading>
    <text>A proxy statement, form of proxy, notice of meeting, information statement, or other communication, written or oral, subject to this regulation may not contain any statement which, at the time and in the light of the circumstances under which it is made:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Is false or misleading with respect to any material fact; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Omits to state any material fact necessary:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In order to make the statements not false or misleading; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>To correct any statement in any earlier communication with respect to the same meeting or subject matter which has become false or misleading.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Prohibition of Certain Solicitations.</heading>
    <text>A person making a solicitation that is subject to this chapter may not solicit any undated or postdated proxy, or any proxy that provides that it shall be considered to be dated as of any date after the date on which it is signed by the security holder subject to this chapter.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|04|07|.12">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Special Provisions Applicable to Election Contests.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Solicitations to Which this Regulation Applies. This regulation applies to any solicitation by any person or group for the purpose of opposing a solicitation subject to this chapter by any other person or group with respect to the election or removal of directors at any annual or special meeting of security holders.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Participant or Participant in a Solicitation.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In this regulation, "participant" and "participant in a solicitation" include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The issuer;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Any director of the issuer, and any nominee for whose election as a director proxies are solicited; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Any other person, acting alone or with one or more other persons, committees, or groups, in organizing, directing, or financing the solicitation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In this regulation, "participant" and "participant in a solicitation" do not include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A bank, broker, or dealer who, in the ordinary course of business, lends money or executes orders for the purchase or sale of securities, and who is not otherwise a participant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Any person or organization retained or employed by a participant to solicit security holders, or any person who merely transmits proxy soliciting material or performs ministerial or clerical duties;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Any person employed in the capacity of attorney, accountant, advertising, public relations, or financial adviser, whose activities are limited to the performance of duties in the course of that employment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Any person regularly employed as an officer or employee of the issuer or any of its subsidiaries or affiliates who is not otherwise a participant; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Any officer or director of, or any person regularly employed by, any other participant, if the officer, director, or employee is not otherwise a participant.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Filing of Information Required by Schedule B.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A solicitation subject to this section may not be made by any person other than the issuer unless at least 5 business days prior, or a shorter period as the Commissioner may authorize upon a showing of good cause, there has been filed with the Commissioner, by or on behalf of each participant in the solicitation, a statement in duplicate containing the information specified by Schedule B and a copy of any material proposed to be distributed to security holders in furtherance of the solicitation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Within 5 business days after a solicitation subject to this regulation is made by the issuer, or a longer period the Commissioner may authorize upon showing of good cause, there shall be filed with the Commissioner, by or on behalf of each participant in the solicitation other than the issuer, a statement in duplicate containing the information specified by Schedule B.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If any solicitation on behalf of the issuer or any other person has been made, or if proxy material is ready for distribution, before a solicitation subject to this regulation in opposition, a statement in duplicate containing the information specified in Schedule B shall be filed with the Commissioner, by or on behalf of each participant in the prior solicitation, other than the issuer, as soon as reasonably practicable after the commencement of the solicitation in opposition.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If, after the filing of the statements required by §§A, B, and C of this regulation, additional persons become participants in a solicitation subject to this regulation, there shall be filed with the Commissioner, by or on behalf of these persons, a statement in duplicate containing the information specified by Schedule B, within 3 business days after the person becomes a participant, or a longer period the Commissioner may authorize upon a showing of good cause.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If any material change occurs in the facts reported in any statement filed by or on behalf of any participant, an appropriate amendment to the statement shall be filed promptly with the Commissioner.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Each statement and amendment filed pursuant to this section shall be part of the public files of the Commissioner.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Solicitations Before Furnishing Required Written Proxy Statement. Notwithstanding the provisions of <cite path="|31|04|07|.04|A.">Regulation .04A of this chapter</cite>, a solicitation subject to this regulation may be made before furnishing security holders a written proxy statement containing the information specified in Schedule A with respect to the solicitation, if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The statements required by <cite path="31|04|07|.12|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> are filed by or on behalf of each participant in the solicitation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>No form of proxy is furnished to security holders before the time the written proxy statement required by <cite path="|31|04|07|.04|A.">Regulation .04A of this chapter</cite> is furnished to these persons; however, <cite path="31|04|07|.12|D.|(2)">§D(2) of this regulation</cite> does not apply if a proxy statement meeting the requirements of Schedule A has been furnished to security holders;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>At least the information specified in §C(2) and (3) of this regulation of the statements required by <cite path="31|04|07|.12|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> to be filed by each participant, or an appropriate summary, are included in each communication sent or given to security holders in connection with the solicitation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A written proxy statement containing the information specified in Schedule A with respect to a solicitation is sent or given to security holders at the earliest practicable date.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Solicitations Before Furnishing Required Written Proxy Statement-Filing Requirements. Two copies of any soliciting materials proposed to be sent or given to security holders before the furnishing of the written proxy statement required by <cite path="|31|04|07|.04|A.">Regulation .04A of this chapter</cite> shall be filed with the Commissioner in preliminary form at least 5 business days before the date definitive copies of the material are first sent or given to the persons, or a shorter period the Commissioner may authorize upon a showing of good cause.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Notwithstanding the provisions of <cite path="|31|04|07|.04|B.">Regulation .04B of this chapter</cite>, two copies of any portion of the annual report referred to in <cite path="|31|04|07|.04|B.">Regulation .04B of this chapter</cite> which comments upon or refers to any solicitation subject to this regulation, or to any participant in any solicitation, other than the solicitation by the management, shall be filed with the Commissioner as proxy material subject to this chapter. This portion of the report shall be filed with the Commissioner, in preliminary form, at least 5 business days before the date copies of the report are first sent or given to security holders.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Solicitations and Materials Complying With NAIC Model Regulation and Schedules.</heading>
    <text>Notwithstanding the foregoing regulations, the Commissioner may permit the solicitation of proxies, consents, or authorizations, if the manner of solicitation and the form of proxy, proxy statement, and other documents used in the solicitation comply with Regulations <cite path="|31|04|07|.14">.14</cite>—<cite path="|31|04|07|.16">.16</cite> of this chapter.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Schedule A.</heading>
    <text>Item 1. Revocability of Proxy.</text>
    <text>State whether or not the person giving the proxy has the power to revoke it. If the right of revocation before the proxy is exercised is limited, or is subject to compliance with any formal procedure, briefly describe the limitation or procedure.</text>
    <text>Item 2. Dissenters' Rights of Appraisal.</text>
    <text>Outline briefly any rights of appraisal or similar rights of dissenters with respect to any matter to be acted upon, and indicate any statutory procedure required to be followed by dissenting security holders in order to perfect their rights. When these rights may be exercised only within a limited time after the proposal's date of adoption, the filing of a charter amendment, or other similar act, indicate whether the person solicited will be notified of the date.</text>
    <text>Item 3. Persons Making the Solicitation.</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Solicitations not Subject to <cite path="|31|04|07|.12">Regulation .12 of this Chapter</cite>.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>State if the solicitation is made by the issuer. Give the name of any director of the issuer who has informed the issuer in writing that the director intends to oppose an action intended to be taken by the issuer, and indicate the action which the director intends to oppose.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the solicitation is made by someone other than by the issuer, state the names of the persons by whom and on whose behalf it is made.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the solicitation is to be made by other than the use of the mails, describe the methods to be employed. If the solicitation is to be made by specially engaged employees or paid solicitors, state:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The material features of any contract or agreement for the solicitation and identify the parties; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The cost or anticipated cost.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>State the names of the persons who will bear the cost of solicitation, directly or indirectly.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Solicitations Subject to <cite path="|31|04|07|.12">Regulation .12 of this Chapter</cite>.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>State who will make the solicitation and describe the methods employed to solicit security holders.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If regular employees of the issuer or any other participant in a solicitation have been or are to be employed to solicit security holders, describe the class or classes of employees to be so employed, and the manner and nature of their employment for this purpose.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If specially engaged employees, representatives, or other persons have been or are to be employed to solicit security holders, state:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The material features of any contract or arrangement for the solicitation, and identify the parties;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The cost or anticipated cost; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The approximate number of employees or employees of another person (naming the other person) who will solicit security holders.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>State the total amount estimated to be spent and the total expenditures to date for, or in connection with, the solicitation of security holders.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>State who will bear the cost of the solicitation. If reimbursement will be sought from the issuer, state whether the question of reimbursement will be submitted to a vote of security holders.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>If a solicitation is terminated pursuant to a settlement between the issuer and another participant in the solicitation, describe the terms of the settlement, including the cost or anticipated cost to the issuer.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <aftertext>Item 4. Interest of Certain Persons in Matters to be Acted Upon.</aftertext>
    <para>
      <num proof="done">A.</num>
      <text>Solicitations Not Subject to <cite path="|31|04|07|.12">Regulation .12 of this Chapter</cite>. Describe briefly any substantial interest, direct or indirect, of each of the following persons in a matter to be acted upon, other than elections to office:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If the solicitation is made on behalf of the issuer, each current director or officer of the issuer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the solicitation is made for other than on the issuer's behalf, any person who would be a participant in a solicitation (except the issuer or an officer, director, or nominee of the issuer);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Each nominee for election as a director of the issuer; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Each associate of the foregoing persons.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Solicitations Subject to <cite path="|31|04|07|.12">Regulation .12 of this Chapter</cite>. Describe briefly any substantial interest, direct or indirect, of each participant (except the issuer) in any matter to be acted upon at the meeting. Include, with respect to each participant, the information required by Items 2A, 2D, 3, 4B, and 4C of Schedule B.</text>
    </para>
    <aftertext>Item 5. Voting Securities and Principal Holders of Voting Securities.</aftertext>
    <para>
      <num proof="done">A.</num>
      <text>State, for each class of voting securities of the issuer entitled to be voted at the meeting, the number of shares outstanding and the number of votes to which each class is entitled.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Give the date that the record of security holders entitled to vote at the meeting will be determined. If the right to vote is not limited to security holders of record on that date, indicate the conditions under which other security holders may be entitled to vote.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If action is to be taken with respect to the election of directors and if the persons solicited have cumulative voting rights:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Make a statement that they have these rights;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Describe the rights;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>State the conditions precedent to the exercise of these rights; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Indicate if discretionary authority to cumulate votes is solicited.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Furnish the following information as of the most practicable date, in substantially the tabular form indicated, with respect to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person or group of persons who is known to be the beneficial owner of more than 5 percent of any class of securities; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All directors and nominees, naming them, and directors and officers of the issuer as a group, without naming them.</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th>(1)</th>
                <th>(2)</th>
                <th>(3)</th>
                <th>(4)</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Name of Beneficial Owner</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Amount and Nature of Beneficial Ownership</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Percent of Class</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Change in Control.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If, to the knowledge of the person on whose behalf the solicitation is made, a change in control of the issuer has occurred since the beginning of its last fiscal year, state:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The name of the person or persons who acquired control;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The amount and the source of the consideration used by the person or persons;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The basis of the control;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The date and a description of the transactions that resulted in the change of control;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The percentage of voting securities of the issuer now beneficially owned directly or indirectly by the person or persons who acquired control; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The identity of the person or persons from whom control was assumed.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Describe any arrangements which may at a later date result in a change of control of the issuer.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <aftertext>Item 6. Directors and Executive Officers.</aftertext>
    <aftertext>If action is to be taken with respect to the election of directors, furnish the following information, in tabular form to the extent practicable, about each person nominated for election as a director and each person whose term of office will continue after the meeting. However, if the solicitation is made on behalf of persons other than the issuer, the information required should only be furnished as to nominees of the persons making the solicitation.</aftertext>
    <para>
      <num proof="done">A.</num>
      <text>Identification of Directors and Officers. List the names and ages of all directors and officers of the issuer and all persons nominated or chosen to become directors or officers. Indicate all positions and offices with the issuer held by each person; state the term of office as director or officer, or both, and any period during which the person served. Briefly describe any arrangement or understanding between the person and any other person or persons (naming the persons) pursuant to which the person was or is to be selected as a director, officer, or nominee. The information regarding officers does not need to be furnished in proxy or information statements if the information is furnished in a separate item in the issuer's annual report to stockholders.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Family Relationships. State the nature of a family relationship not more remote than first cousin between a director, officer, or person nominated or chosen by the issuer to become a director or officer. State the nature of any family relationship between any such person and an officer or director of any of the issuer's parent companies, subsidiaries, or other affiliates.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Business Experience. State the principal occupations and employment during the past 5 years of each director and each person nominated or chosen to become a director or officer, and the name and principal business of any corporation or other organization in which the occupations and employment were carried on.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Directorships. Indicate other directorships held by each director or person nominated or chosen to become a director.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Involvement in Certain Legal Proceedings. Describe any legal proceedings that have occurred during the past 5 years or which are pending that are material to an evaluation of the ability or integrity of any director or nominee for director or officer of the issuer.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Describe any of the following relationships that exist:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If the nominee or director is, or has within the last 2 full fiscal years been, an officer, director, or employee of, or owns, or has within the last 2 fiscal years owned, directly or indirectly, an equity interest in, any firm, corporation, or other business in excess of a 1 percent:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>That has made payments to the issuer or its subsidiaries during the issuer's last full fiscal year, or that proposes to make payments to the issuer or its subsidiaries during the current fiscal year, in excess of 1 percent of the issuer's consolidated gross revenues for its last full fiscal year;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>To which the issuer or its subsidiaries were indebted at any time during the issuer's last fiscal year in an aggregate amount in excess of 1 percent of the issuer's total consolidated assets at the end of the fiscal year;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>To which the issuer or its subsidiaries have made payments during the entity's last fiscal year, or to which the issuer or its subsidiaries propose to make payments during the entity's current fiscal year, in excess of 1 percent of the entity's consolidated gross revenues for its last full fiscal year;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>In order to determine whether payments made or proposed to be made exceed 1 percent of the consolidated gross revenues of any entity other than the issuer for the entity's last full fiscal year, it is appropriate to rely on information provided by the nominee or director;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>In calculating payments for property and services, the following may be excluded:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Payments where the rates or charges involved in the transaction are determined by competitive bids, or the transaction involves the rendering of services as a public utility at rates or charges fixed in conformity with law or governmental authority;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Payments that arise solely from the ownership of securities of the issuer, and no extra or special benefit not shared on a pro rata basis by all holders of the class of securities is received;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>In calculating indebtedness for purposes of §F(1)(b) above, debt securities that have been publicly offered, admitted to trading on a national securities exchange, or quoted on the automated quotation system of a registered securities association may be excluded;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The nominee or director is a member or employee of, or is associated with, a law firm which the issuer has retained in the last 2 full fiscal years or proposes to retain in the current fiscal year where fees paid or anticipated to be paid by the issuer are material to either the law firm, the issuer, or both;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The nominee or director is a director, partner, officer, or employee of any investment banking firm that has performed services for the issuer, other than as a participating underwriter in a syndicate in the last 2 full fiscal years or which the issuer proposes to have perform services in the current year; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The nominee or director is a control person of the issuer (other than solely as a director of the issuer).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Committees.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>State whether or not the issuer has standing audit, nominating, and compensation committees of the board of directors, or committees performing similar functions. If the issuer has these committees, however designated, identify each committee member, state the number of committee meetings held by each committee during the last fiscal year, and describe briefly the functions performed by the committees.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the issuer has a nominating or similar committee, state whether the committee will consider nominees recommended by shareholders. If so, describe the procedures to be followed by shareholders in submitting the recommendations.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>State the total number of meetings of the board of directors (including regularly scheduled and special meetings) that were held during the last full fiscal year. Name each incumbent director who, during the last full fiscal year, attended fewer than 75 percent of the aggregate of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The total number of meetings of the board of directors (held during the period for which he has been a director); and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The total number of meetings held by all committees of the board on which he served (during the periods that he served).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>If a director has resigned or declined to stand for reelection to the board of directors since the date of the last annual meeting of shareholders because of a disagreement with the issuer on any matter relating to the issuer's operations, policies, or practices, and if the director has furnished the issuer with a letter describing that disagreement and requesting that the matter be disclosed, the issuer shall state the date of resignation or declination to stand for reelection and summarize the director's description of the disagreement. If the issuer believes that the description provided by the director is incorrect or incomplete, it may include a brief statement presenting its views of the disagreement.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Classes of Voting Stock.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>With respect to those classes of voting stock that participated in the election of directors at the most recent meeting where directors were elected:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>State the percentage of shares present at the meeting and voting or withholding authority to vote in the election of directors; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Disclose, in tabular format, the percentage of total shares cast for and withheld from the vote for or, if applicable, cast against, each nominee, which, respectively, were voted for and withheld from the vote for, or voted against, the nominee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When groups of classes or series of classes vote together in the election of a director or directors, they shall be treated as a single class for the purpose of §J(1)(b).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Instructions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Calculate the percentage of shares present at the meeting and voting or withholding authority to vote in the election of directors, referred to in §J(1)(a), by dividing the total shares cast for and withheld from the vote for or, if applicable, voted against, the director for whom the highest aggregate number of shares was cast by the total number of shares outstanding that were eligible to vote as of the record date for the meeting.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>No information need be given in response to Item 6J unless, with respect to any class of voting stock (or group of classes which voted together), 5 percent or more of the total shares cast for and withheld from the votes for or, if applicable, cast against any nominee were withheld from the vote for or cast against the nominee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If an issuer elects less than the entire board of directors annually, disclosure is required for all directors if 5 percent or more of the total shares cast for and withheld from, the vote for or, if applicable, cast against an incumbent director were withheld from, or cast against, the vote for the director at the meeting where the person was most recently elected.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>No information shall be given in response to Item 6J if the issuer has previously furnished to its security holders a report of the results of the most recent meeting of security holders where directors were elected which includes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A description of each matter voted upon at the meeting and a statement of the percentage of the shares voting that were voted for and against each matter; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The information that would be called for by this Item 6J.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If an issuer has previously furnished the results to its security holders, this fact should be stated in a letter accompanying the filing of preliminary proxy materials with the Commissioner.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <aftertext>Item 7. Remuneration of Directors and Officers.</aftertext>
    <aftertext>Furnish the following information if action is to be taken concerning:(i) the election of directors; (ii) any bonus, profit sharing or other remuneration plan, contract, or arrangement that a director, nominee for election as a director, or officer of the issuer will participate; (iii) a pension or retirement plan where a person will participate; or (iv) the granting or extension to a person of any options, warrants, or rights to purchase securities, other than warrants or rights issued to security holders on a pro rata basis. If the solicitation is made on behalf of persons other than the issuer, the information required need be furnished only as to nominees of the person making the solicitation and associates of the nominees.</aftertext>
    <para>
      <num proof="done">A.</num>
      <text>Current Remuneration. Furnish the information required in the table below, in substantially the tabular form specified, concerning all remuneration of the following persons and groups for services in all capacities to the issuer and its subsidiaries during the issuer's last fiscal year or, in specified instances, certain prior fiscal years:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Five Officers or Directors. Name each of the five most highly compensated officers or directors of the issuer who have a total remuneration required to be disclosed in Columns C-1 and C-2 below that would exceed $50,000.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All Officers or Directors. All officers and directors of the issuer as a group, stating the number of persons in the group without naming them.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Specified Tabular Format.</text>
        <text>
          <table class="layout-table">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th>(A)</th>
                <th>(B)</th>
                <th colspan="2">(C)</th>
                <th>(D)</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Name of individual or number of persons in groups</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Capacities in which served</td>
                <td colspan="2" data-vertical-align="middle">Cash and cash equivalent forms of remuneration</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Aggregate of contingent forms of remuneration</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <td/>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(C-1) Salaries, fees, directors' fees, commissions, and bonuses</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(C-2) Securities of property, insurance benefits or reimbursements, personal benefits</td>
                <td/>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Information to be Included. Columns C-1, C-2, and D of the table should contain with respect to each person or group of persons specified in §A(1) and A(2) of this Item 7 a dollar amount that reflects the total of all items of remuneration described in the heading to that column including, but not necessarily limited to, those items set forth in the subparagraphs of that column.</text>
        <text>
          <table class="layout-table" high-density="true">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th colspan="2">COLUMN C Include all cash and cash equivalent forms of remuneration received during the fiscal year and all amounts accrued during the fiscal year which, with reasonable certainty, will be distributed or vested in the future.</th>
                <th>COLUMN D Include all contingent forms of remuneration, vesting and measurement of which is subject to future events. Report only amounts relating to the latest fiscal year, not amounts accrued in previous periods.</th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <th>COLUMN C-1 Salaries, Bonuses, Fees, and Commissions</th>
                <th>COLUMN C-2 Securities, Property, Insurance Benefits or Reimbursements, Personal Benefits</th>
                <th/>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">1. All cash remuneration distributed or accrued in the form of salaries, commissions, bonuses and fees for services rendered. 2. Compensation earned for services performed in the latest fiscal year even if it is deferred for future payment. 3. Payments received in the latest fiscal year but earned in prior years that were deferred until the latest year, if the amounts were not shown in an earlier proxy statement or annual report to stockholders.</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">1. Spread between the acquisition price, if any, and fair market price of securities or property acquired under any contract, plan, or arrangement. 2. Cost of any life insurance premiums, health insurance premiums, and medical reimbursement plans. Premiums for nondiscriminatory plans generally available to all salaried employees are excluded. 3. Personal benefits (perquisites) not directly related to job performance, excluding benefits provided on a nondiscriminatory basis, valued on the basis of cost to the issuer of providing the benefits. a. If unreasonable effort or expense is required to determine the amounts of personal benefits, they may be omitted if their aggregate value does not exceed $10,000 for each officer. b. If the amount of personal benefits exceed 10 percent of the total remuneration or $25,000, which- ever is less, the amount and a brief description of the benefits shall be disclosed in a footnote. 4. Vested company contributions to thrift, profit sharing, pension stock purchase, and similar plans.</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">1. Amount expensed for financial reporting purposes representing non-vested contributions, payments, or accruals under any pension or retirement plans, annuities, or employment contracts deferred compensation plans including IRS qualified plans, unless the amount for the individual cannot be separated, in which case a footnote is required indicating the percentage that contributions to the plan bear to participants' total remuneration. 2. The amount expensed for financial reporting purposes under any incentive plans (long-term income plans), such as stock appreciation rights, stock options, or performance share plans, when payout is based on objective standards or stock values. In subsequent years, if the corporation credits compensation expense for financial reporting purposes as a result of a decline in the value of contingent compensation, Column D may be reduced by a corresponding amount. A footnote explaining the action should be included. 3. The amount expensed for financial reporting purposes for any nonvested contribution payment or accrual to stock purchase plans, profit sharing, and thrift plans whether or not they are qualified under the Internal Revenue Code.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Transactions with Third Parties. Item 7A, among other things, includes transactions between the issuer and a third party when the primary purpose of the transaction is to furnish remuneration to the persons specified in Item 7A. Other transactions between the issuer and third parties in which persons specified in Item 7A have an interest, or may realize a benefit, generally are addressed by other disclosure requirements concerning the interest of management and others in certain transactions. Item 7A does not require disclosure of remuneration paid to a partnership in which any officer or director was a partner; these transactions should be disclosed pursuant to these other disclosure requirements, and not as a note to the remuneration table presented pursuant to Item 7A.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Other Permitted Disclosure. The issuer may provide additional disclosure through a footnote to the table, through additional columns or otherwise, describing the components of aggregate remuneration in greater detail as is appropriate.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Proposed Remuneration.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Briefly describe all remuneration payments proposed to be made in the future, pursuant to any existing plan or arrangement to the persons and groups specified in Item 7A. As to defined benefit or actuarial plans with respect to amounts not included in the table, include a separate table showing the estimated annual benefits payable upon retirement to persons in specified remuneration and years-of-service classifications.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Information does not need to be furnished with respect to any group life, health, hospitalization, or medical reimbursement plans that do not discriminate in favor of officers or directors of the issuer and that are available generally to all salaried employees.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Remuneration of Directors. Describe any standard or special arrangements, stating amounts, by which directors of the issuer are compensated for services as a director.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Options, Warrants, or Rights.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Furnish the information required by the following table for all options to purchase securities from the issuer or its subsidiaries that were granted to or exercised by the persons and groups specified in Item 7A since the beginning of the issuer's last fiscal year, and as to all options held by these persons as of the latest practicable date.</text>
        <text>The following tabulation shows as to certain directors and officers, and as to all directors and officers as a group:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The amount of options granted since the beginning of the issuer's last full fiscal year;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The amount of shares acquired since that date through the exercise of options;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The amount of shares of the same class sold during the period; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The amount of shares subject to all unexercised options held as of the most recent practicable date.</text>
          <text>
            <table>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th>Title of Securities</th>
                  <th>Name</th>
                  <th>Name</th>
                  <th>Name</th>
                  <th>All directors and officers as a group</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">Granted-20[ ] to date:</td>
                  <td/>
                  <td/>
                  <td/>
                  <td/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">Number of shares</td>
                  <td/>
                  <td/>
                  <td/>
                  <td/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">Average per share option price</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">$</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">$</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">$</td>
                  <td/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">Exercised-20[ ] to date:</td>
                  <td/>
                  <td/>
                  <td/>
                  <td/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">Number of shares</td>
                  <td/>
                  <td/>
                  <td/>
                  <td/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">Aggregate option price of options exercised</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">$</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">$</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">$</td>
                  <td/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">Aggregate market value of shares on date options exercised</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">$</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">$</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">$</td>
                  <td/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">Sales-20[ ] to date:</td>
                  <td/>
                  <td/>
                  <td/>
                  <td/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">Number of shares</td>
                  <td/>
                  <td/>
                  <td/>
                  <td/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">Unexercised at 20[ ]:</td>
                  <td/>
                  <td/>
                  <td/>
                  <td/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">Number of shares</td>
                  <td/>
                  <td/>
                  <td/>
                  <td/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">Average per share option price</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">$</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">$</td>
                  <td data-vertical-align="middle">$</td>
                  <td/>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <aftertext>In addition, during the period employees were granted options for  shares at an average price per share of $  .</aftertext>
      <aftertext>1 Sales by directors and officers who exercised options during the period 20[ ] to date.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>Instructions:</aftertext>
      <para>
        <num proof="done">(1)</num>
        <text>All figures should be adjusted, if applicable, in accordance with the terms of the options to reflect stock splits and to give effect to share dividends.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Other tabular presentations are acceptable if they include the necessary data. Tabular presentation may not be needed if only a very few options have been granted.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Total Market Value.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If the total market value on the granting dates of the securities called for by all options granted during the period specified does not exceed $10,000 for any officer or director named in answer to Item 7A, or $40,000 for all officers and directors as a group, this item need not be answered with respect to options granted to a person or group.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the total market value on the dates of purchase of all securities purchased through the exercise of options during the period specified does not exceed $10,000 for a person or $40,000 for a group, this item does not need to be answered with respect to options exercised by a person or group.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If the total market value as of the latest practicable date of the securities called for by all options held at the time does not exceed $10,000 for a person or $40,000 for a group, this item does not need to be answered with respect to options held as of the specified date by a person or group.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The term "options", as used in §D includes all options, warrants, or rights, other than those issued to security holders as such on a pro rata basis. If the average option price per share is called for, the weighted average price per share shall be given.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The extension, regranting, or material amendment of options shall be considered the granting of options within the meaning of this subsection.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>If the options relate to more than one class of securities, the information shall be given separately for each class.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Indebtedness of Management.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>State for each director or officer of the issuer, each nominee for election as a director, and each associate of a director, officer, or nominee who was indebted to the issuer or its subsidiaries at any time since the beginning of the last fiscal year of the registrant:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The largest aggregate amount of indebtedness outstanding at any time during the period;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The nature of the indebtedness outstanding and the transaction in which it was incurred;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The amount outstanding as of the latest practicable date; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The rate of interest paid or charged.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Section E does not apply to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Any person whose aggregate indebtedness did not exceed $10,000 or 1 percent of the issuer's total assets, whichever is less, at any time during the period specified; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Indebtedness under an insurance policy.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Transactions with Management.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Describe briefly any transaction since the beginning of the issuer's last fiscal year, or any presently proposed transactions, to which the issuer or any of its subsidiaries was or is to be a party, in which any of the following persons had or is to have a direct or indirect material interest, naming the person and stating the relationship to the issuer, the nature of the interest in the transaction, and, if practicable, the amount of the interest:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A director of officer of the issuer;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A nominee for election as a director;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A security holder who is known to the issuer to own of record or beneficially more than 10 percent of any class of the issuer's voting securities; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A relative or spouse of any of the foregoing persons, or any relative of the spouse, who has the same home as the person or who is a director or officer of a parent or subsidiary of the issuer.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Also, describe briefly any material legal proceedings in which a person is an adverse party to the issuer or any of its subsidiaries, or has an adverse material interest to the issuer or any of its subsidiaries.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Information does not need to be given in response to this Item 7F as to any remuneration or other transaction reported in response to Item 7A, B, C, D, or E, or as to any transaction with respect to which information may be omitted pursuant to these items.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Information does not need to be given in answer to this Item 7F for any transaction where:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The rates or charges involved in the transaction are determined by competitive bids, or at rates or charges fixed in conformity with law or governmental authority;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The transaction involves services as a bank depository of funds, transfer agent, registrar, trustee under a trust indenture, or similar services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The amount involved in the transaction or series of similar transactions, including all periodic installments in the case of any lease or other agreement providing for periodic payments or installments, does not exceed $40,000; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The interest of the specified person arises solely from the ownership of securities of the issuer, and the specified person receives no extra or special benefit not shared on a pro rata basis by all holders of securities of the class.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>It should be noted that this item calls for disclosure of indirect, as well as direct, material interests in transactions. A person who has a position or relationship with a firm, corporation, or other entity, that engages in a transaction with the issuer or its subsidiaries, may have an indirect interest in the transaction by reason of the position or relationship. However, a person shall be considered not to have a material indirect interest in a transaction within the meaning of this Item 7F if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The interest arises only from:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The person's position as a director of another corporation or organization (other than a partnership) which is a party to the transaction;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The direct or indirect ownership by the person and all other persons specified in Item 7F of less than a 10 percent equity interest in another person (other than a partnership) which is a party to the transaction; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Both the position and ownership;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The interest arises only from the person's position as a limited partner in a partnership in which the person and all other persons specified in Item 7F had an interest of less than 10 percent; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The interest of the person arises solely from the holding of an equity interest (including a limited partnership interest but excluding a general partnership interest) or a creditor interest in another person which is a party to the transaction with the issuer or any of its subsidiaries and the transaction is not material to the other person.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <aftertext>Instructions:</aftertext>
      <para>
        <num proof="done">(1)</num>
        <text>In describing any transaction involving the purchase or sale of assets by or to the issuer or any of its subsidiaries, other than in the ordinary course of business, state the cost of the assets to the purchaser and, if acquired by the seller within 2 years before the transaction, the cost to the seller. Indicate the principle followed in determining the issuer's purchase or sale price, and the name of the person making the determination.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Information shall be furnished in answer to this Item with respect to transactions not excluded above which involve remuneration from the issuer or its subsidiaries, directly or indirectly, to any of the specified persons for services in any capacity unless the interest of these persons arises solely from the ownership individually and in the aggregate of less than 10 percent of any class of equity securities of another corporation furnishing the services to the issuer or its subsidiaries.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Transactions with Pension or Similar Plans.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Describe briefly any transactions since the beginning of the issuer's last fiscal year, or any presently proposed transactions, to which any pension, retirement, savings, or similar plan provided by the issuer, or any of its parents or subsidiaries, was or is to be a part, in which any of the persons specified in Item 7F or the issuer or any of its subsidiaries had or is to have a direct or indirect material interest naming the person and stating the person's relationship to the issuer, the nature of the person's interest in the transaction and, if practicable, the amount of the interest.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Information does not need to be given in answer to §G(1) with respect to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Payments to the plan, or payments to beneficiaries, pursuant to the terms of the plan;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Payment of remuneration for services not in excess of 5 percent of the aggregate remuneration received by the specified person during the issuer's last fiscal year from the issuer and its subsidiaries; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Any interest of the issuer or any of its subsidiaries that arises solely from its general interest in the success of the plan.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <aftertext>Instructions:</aftertext>
      <para>
        <num proof="done">(1)</num>
        <text>Item 7F(3) applies to this Item 7G.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Without limiting the general meaning of the term "transaction", there shall be included in the answer to this item any remuneration received or any loans received or outstanding during the period, or proposed to be received.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <aftertext>Item 8. Matters Related to Accounting.</aftertext>
    <aftertext>If the solicitation is made on behalf of the issuer and relates to an annual meeting of security holders at which directors are to be elected, or financial statements are included, furnish the following information:</aftertext>
    <para>
      <num proof="done">A.</num>
      <text>State if the issuer's financial statements are not certified by independent public or certified accountants.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>State if the board of directors has no audit or similar committee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the issuer's financial statements are certified by independent public or certified accountants, state that fact and provide the following information:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The name of the principal accountant selected or being recommended to shareholders for election, approval, or ratification for the current year. If no accountant has been elected or recommended, so state and briefly describe the reasons.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The name of the principal accountant for the fiscal year most recently completed if different from the accountant selected or recommended for the current year, or if no accountant has been elected or recommended for the current year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>State if a change or changes in accountants have taken place since the date of the proxy statement for the most recent annual meeting of shareholders. If, in connection with the change, a material disagreement in connection with financial disclosure between the accountant and issuer has occurred, the disagreement shall be described. Before filing the preliminary proxy materials with the Commissioner that contain or amend the description, the issuer shall furnish the description of the disagreement to an accountant with whom the disagreement has occurred. If that accountant believes that the description of the disagreement is incorrect or incomplete, the accountant may include a brief statement, not to exceed 200 words, in the proxy statement presenting the accountant's view of the disagreement. This statement shall be submitted to the issuer within 10 business days of the date the accountant receives the issuer's descriptions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The proxy statement shall indicate whether or not representatives of the principal accountants for the current year and for the most recently completed fiscal year are expected to be present at the stockholders' meeting with the opportunity to make a statement if they desire to do so and whether or not the representatives are expected to be available to respond to appropriate questions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If a change in accountants has taken place since the date of the proxy statement for the most recent annual meeting of shareholders, state whether the change was recommended or approved by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An audit or similar committee of the board of directors, if the issuer has this committee; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The board of directors, if the issuer has no committee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>For the fiscal year most recently completed, describe each professional service provided by the principal accountant, state the percentage relationship that the aggregate of the fees for all nonaudit services bear to the audit fees, and, except as provided below, state the percentage relationship that the fee for each nonaudit service bears to the audit fees. Indicate whether, before each professional service provided by the principal accountant was rendered, it was approved by, and the possible effect on the independence of the accountant was considered by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An audit or similar committee of the board of directors; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The board of directors for a service not approved by an audit or similar committee.</text>
      </para>
      <aftertext>Instructions:</aftertext>
      <para>
        <num proof="done">(1)</num>
        <text>For purposes of this section, all fees for services provided in connection with the audit function (for example, reviews of quarterly reports) may be computed as part of the audit fees. Indicate which services are reflected in the audit fees computation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the fee for any non-audit service is less than 3 percent of the audit fees, the percentage relationship does not need to be disclosed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Each service should be specifically described. Broad general categories such as "tax matters" or "management advisory services" are not sufficiently specific.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Describe the circumstances and give details of any services provided by the issuer's independent accountant during the latest fiscal year that were furnished at rates or terms that were not customary.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Describe any existing direct or indirect understanding or agreement that places a limit on current or future years' audit fees, including fee arrangements that provide fixed limits on fees that are not subject to reconsideration if unexpected issues involving accounting or auditing are encountered. Disclosure of fee estimates is not required.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <aftertext>Item 9. Bonus, Profit Sharing, and Other Remuneration Plans: Pension and Retirement Plans.</aftertext>
    <aftertext>If action is to be taken with respect to any bonus, profit sharing, or other remuneration plan, or any pension or retirement plan, furnish the following information:</aftertext>
    <para>
      <num proof="done">A.</num>
      <text>Describe briefly the material features of the plan, identify each class of persons who will participate, indicate the approximate number of persons in each class, and state the basis of the participation;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Furnish the information, in addition to that required by this item and Item 7, as may be necessary to describe adequately the provisions already made pursuant to all bonus, profit sharing, pension, retirement, stock option, stock purchase, deferred compensation, or other remuneration or incentive plans, now in effect or in effect within the past 5 years, for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each director or officer named in answer to Item 7A who may participate in the plan to be acted upon;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All present directors and officers of the issuer as a group, if any director or officer may participate in the plan; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All employees, if employees may participate in the plan;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the plan to be acted upon can be amended otherwise than by a vote of stockholders, to increase the cost to the issuer or to alter the allocation of the benefits as between the directors and officers on the one hand and employees on the other, state the nature of the amendments which can be made;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>With regard to any bonus, profit sharing, or other remuneration plan, on which action is to be taken, furnish the following information:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>State separately the amounts which would have been distributable under the plan during the last fiscal year of the issuer:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>To directors and officers; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>To employees if the plan had been in effect;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>State the name and position with the issuer of each person specified in Item 7A who will participate in the plan and the amount each person would have received under the plan for the last fiscal year of the issuer if the plan had been in effect;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>With regard to any pension or retirement plan on which action is to be taken, furnish the following information:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>State:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The approximate total amount necessary to fund the plan with respect to past services, the period over which the amount is to be paid, and the estimated annual payments necessary to pay the total amount over the period;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The estimated annual payment to be made with respect to current services; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The amount of the annual payments to be made for the benefit of</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Directors and officers, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Employees;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>State:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The name and position with the issuer of each person specified in Item 7A who will be entitled to participate in the plan;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The amount which would have been paid or set aside by the issuer and its subsidiaries for the benefit of the person for the last fiscal year of the issuer if the plan had been in effect; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The amount of the annual benefits estimated to be payable to the person in the event of retirement at normal retirement date.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <aftertext>Instructions:</aftertext>
      <para>
        <num proof="done">(1)</num>
        <text>If action is to be taken with respect to the amendment or modification of an existing plan, the item shall be answered with respect to the plan as proposed to be amended or modified and shall indicate any material differences from the existing plan.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The following instruction applies to §B:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Information need only be given with respect to benefits received or set aside within the past 5 years.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Information does not need to be included as to payments made for, or benefits to be received from, group life or accident insurance, group hospitalization, or similar group payments or benefits.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If action is to be taken with respect to any plan in which directors or officers may participate, the information called for by Item 7D shall be furnished for the last 5 fiscal years of the issuer and any period after the end of the latest fiscal year, in aggregate amounts for the entire period for each person and group. If any named person, or any other director or officer, purchased securities through the exercise of options during the period, state the aggregate amount of securities of that class sold during the period by the named person, and by the named person and other directors and officers as a group. The information called for by this instruction is in lieu of the information since the beginning of the issuer's last fiscal year called for by Item 7D. If employees may participate in the plan to be acted upon, state the aggregate amount of securities called for by all options granted to employees during the 5-year period and, if the options were other than "restricted" or "qualified" stock options or options granted pursuant to an "employee stock purchase plan," as the quoted terms are defined in Sections 422 through 424 of the Internal Revenue Code, state that fact and the weighted average option price per share. The information called for by this instruction may be furnished in the form of the table set forth in Item 7D.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the plan to be acted upon is set forth in a written document, three copies shall be filed with the Commissioner at the time preliminary copies of the proxy statement and form of proxy are filed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The information called for by §E(1)(c) or (2)(b) of Item 9 does not need to be given as to payments made on an actuarial basis pursuant to any group pension plan that provides for fixed benefits in the event of retirement at a specified age or after a specified number of years of service.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <aftertext>Item 10. Options, Warrants, or Rights.</aftertext>
    <aftertext>If action is to be taken with respect to the granting or extension of any options to purchase securities of the issuer or any subsidiary, furnish the following information:</aftertext>
    <para>
      <num proof="done">A.</num>
      <text>State:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The title and amount of securities called for or to be called for by the options;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The prices, expiration dates, and other material conditions upon which the options may be exercised;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The consideration received or to be received by the issuer or subsidiary for the granting or extension of the options;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The market value of the securities called for or to be called for by the options as of the latest practicable date; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>In the case of options, the federal income tax consequences of the issuance and exercise of the option to the recipient and to the issuer;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>State:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Separately the amount of options received or to be received by the following persons, naming each person:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Each director or officer named in answer to Item 7A;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Each nominee for election as a director of the issuer;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Each associate of the directors, officers, or nominees; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Each other person who received or is to receive 10 percent or more of the options;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The total amount of the options received or to be received by all directors and officers of the issuer as a group, without naming them;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Furnish the information, in addition to that required by this item and Item 7, necessary to describe adequately the provisions already made pursuant to all bonus, profit sharing, pension, retirement, stock option, stock purchase, deferred compensation, or other remuneration or incentive plans, now in effect or in effect within the past 5 years, for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each director or officer named in answer to Item 7A who may participate in the plan to be acted upon;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All present directors and officers of the issuer as a group, if any director or officer may participate in the plan; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All employees, if employees may participate in the plan.</text>
      </para>
      <aftertext>Instructions:</aftertext>
      <para>
        <num proof="done">(1)</num>
        <text>For the purpose of this Item 10, the term option includes any option, warrant, or right.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Sections B and C do not apply to warrants or rights to be issued to security holders on a pro rata basis.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Instruction 2 to Item 9 also applies to §C of this item.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the options described in answer to this item are issued pursuant to a plan which is set forth in a written document, three copies shall be filed with the Commissioner at the time preliminary copies of the proxy statement and form of proxy are filed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <aftertext>Item 11. Authorization or Issuance of Securities Otherwise than for Exchange.</aftertext>
    <aftertext>If action is to be taken with respect to the authorization or issuance of any securities otherwise than for exchange for outstanding securities of the issuer, furnish the following information:</aftertext>
    <para>
      <num proof="done">A.</num>
      <text>State the title and amount of securities to be authorized or issued;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the securities are other than additional shares of common stock of a class outstanding, furnish a brief summary of the following, if applicable: dividend, voting, liquidation, preemptive and conversion rights, redemption and sinking fund provisions, interest rate, and date of maturity;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Describe briefly the transaction in which the securities are to be issued, including a statement as to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The nature and approximate amount of consideration received or to be received by the issuer; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The approximate amount devoted to each purpose, as far as is determinable, for which the net proceeds have been or are to be used;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If it is impracticable to describe the transaction in which the securities are to be issued, state the reason, indicate the purpose of the authorization of the securities, and state whether further authorization for the issuance of the securities by a vote of security holders will be solicited before issuance;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If the securities are to be issued otherwise than in a general public offering for cash, state the reasons for the proposed authorization or issuance and the general effect upon the rights of existing security holders.</text>
    </para>
    <aftertext>Item 12. Modification or Exchange of Securities.</aftertext>
    <aftertext>If action is to be taken with respect to the modification of any class of securities of the issuer, or the issuance or authorization for issuance of securities of the issuer in exchange for outstanding securities of the issuer, furnish the following information:</aftertext>
    <para>
      <num proof="done">A.</num>
      <text>If outstanding securities are to be modified, state the title and amount. If securities are to be issued in exchange for outstanding securities, state the title and amount of securities to be so issued, the title and amount of outstanding securities to be exchanged, and the basis of the exchange.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Describe any material differences between the outstanding securities and the modified or new securities.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>State the reasons for the proposed modification or exchange and the general effect upon the rights of existing security holders.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Furnish a brief statement as to arrears in dividends or as to defaults in principal or interest with respect to the outstanding securities which are to be modified or exchanged and furnish other information appropriate in the particular case to disclose adequately the nature and effect of the proposed action.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Outline briefly any other material features of the proposed modification or exchange. If the plan of proposed action is set forth in a written document, file copies it with the Commissioner at the time the preliminary proxy material is filed.</text>
    </para>
    <aftertext>Item 13. Mergers, Consolidations, Acquisitions, and Similar Matters.</aftertext>
    <aftertext>Furnish the following information if action is to be taken with respect to any plan for:(i) the merger or consolidation of the issuer into or with another person or of another person into or with the issuer; (ii) the acquisition by the issuer or any of its security holders of securities of another issuer; (iii) the acquisition by the issuer of another going business or of its assets; (iv) the sale or other transfer of all or any substantial part of the assets of the issuer; or (v) the liquidation or dissolution of the issuer:</aftertext>
    <para>
      <num proof="done">A.</num>
      <text>Outline briefly the material features of the plan. State the reasons for the plan and the general effect of the plan upon the rights of existing security holders. If the plan is set forth in a written document, file three copies with the Commissioner at the time preliminary copies of the proxy statement and form of proxy are filed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Furnish the following information as to the issuer and each person which is to be merged into the issuer, or into or with which the issuer is to be merged or consolidated, or the business or assets that are to be acquired, or which is the issuer of securities to be acquired by the issuer in exchange for all or a substantial part of its assets or to be acquired by security holders of the issuer. What is required is information essential to an investor's appraisal of the action proposed to be taken.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Describe briefly the business of the person.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>State the location and describe the general character of the plants and other important physical properties of the person. The description is to be given from an economic and business standpoint, as distinguished from a legal standpoint. Portfolio or investment assets of an insurer do not need to be disclosed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Furnish a brief statement as to dividends in arrears or defaults in principal or interest in respect of any securities of the issuer or of the person, and as to the effect of the plan on the issuer and the person and other information as may be appropriate in the particular case to disclose adequately the nature and effect of the proposed action.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Furnish a tabulation in columnar form showing the existing and the pro forma capitalization.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Furnish in columnar form for each of the last 5 fiscal years a historical summary of earnings, and show per share amounts of net earnings, dividends declared for each year, and book value per share at the end of the latest period.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Furnish in columnar form for each of the last 5 fiscal years a combined pro forma summary of earnings, as appropriate in the circumstances, indicating the aggregate and pre-share earnings for each year and the pro forma book value per share at the end of the latest period. If the transaction establishes a new basis of accounting for assets of any of the persons included, the pro forma summary of earnings shall be furnished only for the most recent fiscal year and interim period, and shall reflect appropriate pro forma adjustments resulting from the new basis of accounting.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>To the extent material for the exercise of prudent judgment in regard to the matter to be acted upon, furnish the historical and pro forma earnings data specified in §B(5) and (6) above for interim periods of the current and prior fiscal years, if available. Instructions: §B of this Item 13 does not apply if the plan described in answer to §A involves only the issuer and one or more of its totally held subsidiaries.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>As to each class of securities of the issuer, or of any person specified in §B, which is admitted to dealing on a national securities exchange or with respect to which a market otherwise exists, and that will be materially affected by the plan, state the high and low sale prices (or, in the absence of trading in a particular period, the range of the bid and asked prices) for each quarterly period within 2 years. This information may be omitted if the plan involves merely the liquidation or dissolution of the issuer.</text>
    </para>
    <aftertext>Item 14. Financial Statements.</aftertext>
    <para>
      <num proof="done">A.</num>
      <text>If action is to be taken with respect to any matter specified in Items 11, 12, or 13, furnish financial statements of the issuer and its subsidiaries complying with the requirements of Regulation .04B(1), (2) and (3) of the chapter, including schedules of supplementary profit and loss information. The statements may be omitted with respect to a plan described in answer to Item 13 if the plan involves only the issuer and one or more of its totally held subsidiaries.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If action is to be taken with respect to any matter specified in Item 13B, furnish for each person specified, other than the issuer, financial statements complying with the requirements of Regulation .04B(1), (2), and (3) of the chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner may, upon the request of the issuer, permit the omission of any of the statements required where the statements are not necessary for the exercise of prudent judgment in regard to any matter to be acted upon, or may permit the filing in substitution of appropriate statements of comparable character. The Commissioner may also require the filing of other statements in addition to, or in substitution for, the statements required in any case where the statements are necessary or appropriate for an adequate presentation of the financial condition of any person whose financial statements are required, or whose statements are otherwise material for the exercise of prudent judgment in regard to any matter to be acted upon. In the usual case, financial statements are considered material to the exercise of prudent judgment where the matter to be acted upon is authorization or issuance of a material amount of senior securities, but are not considered material where the matter to be acted upon is the authorization or issuance of common stock, otherwise than in an exchange, merger or consolidation, acquisition, or similar transaction.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The proxy statement may incorporate by reference any financial statements contained in an annual report sent to security holders with respect to the same meeting as that to which the proxy statement relates, if the financial statements substantially meet the requirements of this item.</text>
    </para>
    <aftertext>Item 15. Acquisition or Disposition of Property.</aftertext>
    <aftertext>If action is to be taken with respect to the acquisition or disposition of any property, furnish the following information:</aftertext>
    <para>
      <num proof="done">A.</num>
      <text>Describe briefly the general character and location of the property.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>State the nature and amount of consideration to be paid or received by the issuer or any subsidiary. To the extent practicable, outline briefly the facts bearing upon the question of the fairness of the consideration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>State the name and address of the transferor or transferee, as the case may be, and the nature of any material relationship of the person to the issuer or an affiliate of the issuer.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Outline briefly any other material features of the contract or transaction.</text>
    </para>
    <aftertext>Item 16. Restatement of Accounts.</aftertext>
    <aftertext>If action is to be taken with respect to the restatement of any asset, capital, or surplus account of the issuer, furnish the following information:</aftertext>
    <para>
      <num proof="done">A.</num>
      <text>State the nature of the restatement and the date as of which it is to be effective.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Outline briefly the reasons for the restatement and for the selection of the particular effective date.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>State the name and amount of each account (including any reserve accounts) affected by the restatement and the effect of the restatement on the account. Tabular presentation of the amounts shall be made when appropriate, particularly in the case of recapitalizations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>To the extent practicable, state whether and the extent, if any, to which the restatement will, as of the date of the restatement, alter the amount available for distribution to the holders of equity securities.</text>
    </para>
    <aftertext>Item 17. Action with Respect to Reports.</aftertext>
    <aftertext>If action is to be taken with respect to any report of the issuer, or of its directors, officers, or committees, or any minutes of meetings of its stockholders, furnish the following information:</aftertext>
    <para>
      <num proof="done">A.</num>
      <text>State whether or not the action is to constitute approval or disapproval of any of the matters referred to in the reports or minutes;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Identify each of the matters which it is intended will be approved or disapproved, and furnish the information required by the appropriate item or items of this schedule with respect to each matter.</text>
      <text>Item 18. Matters Not Required to be Submitted.</text>
      <text>If action is to be taken with respect to any matter which is not required to be submitted to a vote of security holders, state the nature of the matter, the reasons for submitting it to a vote of security holders, and what action is intended to be taken by the management in the event of a negative vote on the matter by the security holders.</text>
      <text>Item 19. Amendment of Charter, Bylaws, or Other Documents.</text>
      <text>If action is to be taken with respect to any amendment of the issuer's charter, bylaws, or other documents as to which information is not required above, state briefly the reasons for, and general effect of, the amendment. If the matter to be acted upon is the classification of directors, state whether vacancies which occur during the year may be filled by the board of directors to serve only until the next annual meeting or may be so filled for the remainder of the full term.</text>
      <text>Item 20. Other Proposed Action.</text>
      <text>If action is to be taken with respect to any matter not specifically referred to above describe briefly the substance of each matter in substantially the same degree of detail as is required by Items 5—19.</text>
      <text>Item 21. Vote Required for Approval.</text>
      <text>As to each matter that is to be submitted to a vote of security holders, other than elections to office or the selection or approval of auditors, state the vote required for its approval.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Schedule B.</heading>
    <text>INFORMATION TO BE INCLUDED IN STATEMENTS FILED BY OR ON BEHALF OF A PARTICIPANT (OTHER THAN THE ISSUER) IN A PROXY SOLICITATION IN AN ELECTION CONTEST</text>
    <text>Item 1. Issuer.</text>
    <text>State the name and address of the Issuer.</text>
    <text>Item 2. Identity and Background.</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>State the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Your name and business address;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Your present principal occupation or employment and the name, principal business, and address of any corporation or other organization in which the employment is carried on.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>State the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Your residence address;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Information as to all material occupations, positions, offices, or employments during the last 10 years, giving starting and ending dates of each and the name, principal business and address of any business corporation, or other business organization in which each occupation, position, office, or employment was carried on.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>State whether or not you are or have been a participant in any other proxy contest involving this company or other companies within the past 10 years. If so, identify the principals, the subject matter, and your relationship to the parties, and the outcome.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>State whether or not, during the past 10 years, you have been convicted in a criminal proceeding (excluding traffic violations or similar misdemeanors) and, if so, give dates, nature of conviction, name and location of court, and penalty imposed or other disposition of the case. A negative answer to this subitem does not need to be included in the proxy statement or other proxy soliciting material.</text>
    </para>
    <aftertext>Item 3. Interest in Securities of the Issuer.</aftertext>
    <para>
      <num proof="done">A.</num>
      <text>State the amount of each class of securities of the issuer that you own beneficially, directly or indirectly.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>State the amount of each class of securities of the issuer that you own of record but not beneficially.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>State, with respect to all securities of the issuer purchased or sold within the past 2 years, the dates when they were purchased or sold, and the amount purchased or sold on each date.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>State if any part of the purchase price or market value of any of the securities specified in §C is represented by funds borrowed or otherwise obtained for the purpose of acquiring or holding securities. Indicate the amount of the indebtedness as of the latest practicable date. If funds were borrowed or obtained otherwise than pursuant to a margin account or bank loan in the regular course of business of a bank, broker, or dealer, briefly describe the transaction and state the names of the parties.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>State whether or not you are a party to any contracts, arrangements, or understandings with any person with respect to any securities of the issuer including but not limited to joint ventures, loan or option arrangements, puts or calls guarantees against losses or guarantees of profits, division of losses or profits, or the giving or withholding of proxies. If so, name the persons with whom some contracts, arrangements, or understandings exist, and give the details of it.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>State the amount of securities of the issuer owned beneficially, directly or indirectly, by each of your associates, and the name and address of each associate.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>State the amount of each class of securities of any parent, subsidiary, or affiliate of the issuer that you own beneficially, directly or indirectly.</text>
    </para>
    <aftertext>Item 4. Further Matters.</aftertext>
    <para>
      <num proof="done">A.</num>
      <text>Describe the time and circumstances under which you became a participant in the solicitation, and state the nature and extent of your activities or proposed activities as a participant.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Describe briefly, and if practicable state the approximate amount of any material interest, direct or indirect, of yourself and of each of your associates in any material transactions since the beginning of the company's last fiscal year, or in any material proposed transactions, to which the company or any of its subsidiaries or affiliates was or is to be a party.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Arrangement or Understanding.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>State whether or not you or any of your associates have any arrangement or understanding with any person:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>With respect to any future employment by the issuer or its subsidiaries or affiliates; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>With respect to any future transactions to which the issuer or any of its subsidiaries or affiliates will or may be a party.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If so, describe the arrangement or understanding, and state the names of the parties.</text>
      </para>
      <aftertext>Item 5. Signature.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>The statement shall be dated and signed in the following manner:</aftertext>
      <aftertext>I certify that the statements made in this statement are true, complete, and correct to the best of my knowledge and belief.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>_________________________________________</aftertext>
      <aftertext>(Date)</aftertext>
      <aftertext>__________________________________________</aftertext>
      <aftertext>(Signature of participant or authorized representative)</aftertext>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Schedule C.</heading>
    <text>INFORMATION REQUIRED IN INFORMATION STATEMENT</text>
    <text>Note: Where any item, other than Item 5, calls for information with respect to any matter to be acted upon at the meeting, the item need be answered only with respect to proposals to be made by the issuer.</text>
    <text>Item 1. Information Required by Items of Schedule 14A.</text>
    <text>Furnish the information called for by all of the items of Schedule A (other than Items 1, 3, and 4) that would be applicable to any matter to be acted upon at the meeting if proxies were to be solicited in connection with the meeting.</text>
    <text>Item 2. Statement That Proxies Are Not Solicited.</text>
    <text>The following statement shall be set forth on the first page of the information statement in bold face type:</text>
    <text>WE ARE NOT ASKING YOU FOR A PROXY AND YOU ARE REQUESTED NOT TO SEND US A PROXY.</text>
    <text>Item 3. Date, Time, and Place of Meeting.</text>
    <text>State the date, time, and place of the meeting of security holders, unless the information is otherwise disclosed in material furnished to security holders with the information statement.</text>
    <text>Item 4. Interest of Certain Persons in or Opposition to Matters to Be Acted Upon.</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Describe briefly any substantial interest, direct or indirect, by security holdings or otherwise, of each of the following persons in any matter to be acted upon, other than elections to office:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each person who has been a director or officer of the issuer at any time since the beginning of the last fiscal year;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Each nominee for election as a director of the issuer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Each associate of the foregoing persons.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Give the name of any director of the issuer who has informed the management in writing that he intends to oppose any action to be taken by the management at the meeting, and indicate the action that he intends to oppose.</text>
    </para>
    <aftertext>Item 5. Proposals by Security Holders.</aftertext>
    <aftertext>If any security holder entitled to vote at the meeting has, not less than 90 days before the issuer's annual meeting, submitted to the issuer a proposal that is accompanied by notice of the issuer's intention to present the proposal, and indicate the disposition proposed to be made of the proposal by the management at the meeting.</aftertext>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Insurance Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|2-109">2-109</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|4-113">4-113</cite>(a)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|7">7</cite>)—(9), and 4-115, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1968-05-01">Effective date: May 1, 1968</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1970-04-30">Amended effective April 30, 1970</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-09-07" discontinuity="true">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|09.30.02">COMAR 09.30.02</cite> to <cite path="|31.04.07">COMAR 31.04.07</cite> effective September 7, 1998 (25:18 Md. R. 1439)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-02-12" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|31|04|07|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|31|04|07|.13">.13</cite> repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|31|04|07|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|31|04|07|.16">.16</cite> adopted effective February 12, 2007 (34:3 Md. R. 303)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
