<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Continuing Education</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>General.</heading>
    <text>In order to renew a license, a licensed marine contractor shall submit to the Board satisfactory proof of the completion of at least 12 credit hours of approved continuing education.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Approval of Continuing Education.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Approved continuing education shall be designed to improve, advance, or extend the licensee’s professional skill and knowledge relating to the provision of marine contractor services.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board shall approve courses for purposes of satisfying the continuing education requirements in <cite path="|26|30|03|.01">Regulation .01 of this chapter</cite>, based on the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Course objectives;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Course outline;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Training material;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Instructor credentials;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Student evaluation methods and criteria; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Relevance to the applicable license category.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Approved continuing education may consist of participation in any of the following, provided there is satisfactory proof of completion acceptable to the Board:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>College-level or postgraduate course work given by an accredited college or university;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Courses, seminars, workshops, or lectures;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Extension studies and correspondence courses;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Papers published in professional journals and requiring peer review;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Instruction of approved continuing education courses; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Other continuing education acceptable to the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Board shall maintain a current list of all continuing education that has been approved by the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Board shall determine the credit hours of approved continuing education as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Credits shall be approved in not less than ½ hour increments;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Credits shall be approved on an hour-for-hour basis for attendance at an approved continuing education program; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Credits are approved on a two-for-one hour basis for the instructor of an approved continuing education program.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The sponsor of a continuing education course or a licensed marine contractor may request that the Board approve a course by submitting a request for approval on a form provided by the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Proof of Continuing Education.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Approved continuing education obtained within the appropriate license renewal period shall be credited as provided under <cite path="|26|30|03|.02|E.">Regulation .02E of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Each licensed marine contractor is responsible for the submission of proof of all approved continuing education to the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Proof of continuing education consists of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Official transcripts from the educational institution;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A certificate or other documentation signed by the instructor or sponsor of the continuing education, attesting to the satisfactory completion of the continuing education; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Other documentation determined by the Board to be adequate, in light of the nature of the continuing education, to establish that the continuing education was actually received by the licensed marine contractor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Environment Article, Title 17, Subtitles 1—5, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-03-18">Effective date: March 18, 2024 (51:5 Md. R. 233)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
