<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>Movement of Vegetable Plants into Maryland</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope of Regulations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Regulated Area. All states, territories, and districts outside of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Regulated Articles. Vegetable plants intended for transplanting, including broccoli, brussel sprout, cabbage, cauliflower, collard, eggplant, kale, lettuce, onion, pepper, asparagus, sweet potato, and tomato.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Conditions of Movement into Maryland.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Any of the regulated articles, free from soil or in soil freed from plant pests by methods acceptable to the certifying agency, may be moved into Maryland when accompanied by an official inspection certificate of the state of origin. The certificate shall establish that the plants were grown under, and meet the requirements of, an official plant certification program of the state of origin and that the plants were certified to be free of plant pests based on an inspection made not more than 3 days before shipment or removal from the soil.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The official inspection certificate shall be attached to each crate, basket, or other container.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Each crate, basket, or other container of plants shall be labeled individually as to variety and number of transplants.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Transplant Standards.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Imported transplant standards include the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All plants shall be of good quality in color, freshness, firmness, strength, straightness, undamaged condition, uniformity of size, and physical condition;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Plants shall be apparently free from injurious pests, fruit, excessive bloom, and weeds;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Plant count shall equal or exceed the number listed on the container.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Inspection at Maryland Destination.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Any of the regulated articles entering the State are subject to inspection by the Department, and, if any are found to be infested with plant pests, or do not meet transplant standards, or are not accompanied by a valid certificate, they may be destroyed immediately or ordered removed from the State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Each container shall be conspicuously labeled with the name and address of the grower and shipper, the varietal name or names, and the plant count of each variety.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Agriculture Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|5-301">5-301</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|5-313">5-313</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1977-04-13">Effective date: April 13, 1977 (4:8 Md. R. 644)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
