<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Plant Pest Control Regulations</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Broker" means a person, except a nurseryman or dealer, who solicits, takes orders, sells, or distributes nursery stock.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Dealer.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Dealer" means a person, except a nurseryman or broker, who:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Advertises nursery stock for sale or installation; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Buys, collects, or otherwise acquires wild plants or nursery stock for the purpose of selling, planting, or distributing them.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Dealer" does not include a person who acquires plants for personal use.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Department" means Maryland Department of Agriculture.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Inspection" means the physical or visual examination of nursery stock or other plant materials and its environs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Inspector" means an employee of the Department designated to enforce these regulations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Location" means each place from which nursery stock is sold, offered for sale, or distributed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Nursery" means a place where nursery stock is produced for sale or distribution.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Nursery Inspection Certificate (NIC)" means a certificate issued by the Department to a designated nursery.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Nurseryman" means a person engaged in the production of nursery stock for sale or distribution.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Nursery stock" means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Any hardy plant or plant that survives Maryland winters, including a deciduous or evergreen tree, shrub or woody vine whether cultivated, native, or wild, and all viable parts of the plant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Any nonhardy plant or plant part to be distributed in another state that requires plant inspection and certification before entering that state; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Any other plant included by the Secretary, if regulating its movement is necessary to control any dangerously injurious plant pest.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Person" means an individual, partnership, corporation, association, organized group of persons, or any other legal entity.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>"Plant Broker License (PBL)" means a license issued by the Department to any persons designated as a broker.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>"Plant Dealer License (PDL)" means a license issued by the Department to any persons designated as a dealer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>"Plant pest" means any insect, snail, nematode, fungus, virus, bacteria, weed, or any other form of terrestrial or aquatic plant or microorganism which is normally considered to be a plant pest or which the Secretary declares to be a plant pest.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>"Secretary" means Secretary of Agriculture or the Secretary’s designee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>"State of origin" means the state where nursery stock was produced or maintained during the previous growing season.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Categories of Operation.</heading>
    <text>The following categories of operations are established and, upon meeting the requirements of these regulations, a person in these categories will be issued the type of certificate or license indicated:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Nursery Inspection Certificate.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Christmas tree production—the production of Christmas trees.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Greenhouse plant production—the growing of nursery stock under glass, fiberglass, plastic or other similar material.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Landscape nursery operation—the production of nursery stock to be used for landscape purposes by the producing nursery.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Nursery stock production—the growing of nursery stock for sale or distribution.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Public agency nursery—a federal, State, or local government agency engaged in the production of nursery stock for research or educational purposes, for reforestation projects, or for use on public lands.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Plant Broker License. Broker—a person acting as an agent or middleman between a grower and a wholesale or a retail customer.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Plant Dealer License.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Chain store—one of two or more retail outlets owned by a person selling nursery stock.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Collector—a person engaged in the collection and the sale or distribution of wild or native nursery stock.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Garden center—an operation engaged in the sale or distribution of nursery stock.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Landscape contractor—a person who installs nursery stock on the property of another.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Mail order--the shipping or drop-shipping (at retail) of nursery stock from orders solicited or received through the mail.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Certification of Nurseries.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A nursery producing nursery stock for distribution, exchange, or sale shall hold a valid Nursery Inspection Certificate for each sales location.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Requirements for Certification. An applicant must fulfill the following requirements for certification:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Make application to the Department on forms provided by the Department;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Furnish an affidavit attesting to the number of acres, or part of an acre, devoted to the production or maintenance of nursery stock;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Pay annual fees as specified in Regulation .06A at the time of application for, or renewal of, a certificate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Provide access for the inspection of all nursery stock;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Follow appropriate cultural practices such that an adequate inspection of the nursery stock can be made;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Provide a suitable means of identifying similar blocks of nursery stock, as required by the Department;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Keep nursery stock free of plant pests;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Furnish a list of his suppliers of nursery stock.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A nursery will be assigned a permanent certification number at the time all requirements for certification have been met and the original Nursery Inspection Certificate is issued. Unless sooner revoked, a certificate is valid for a year beginning January 1, or date of issuance, and ending December 31.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A certificate is not transferable.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Nursery inspection certificates will be renewed annually upon meeting all requirements as outlined in this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Plant Dealer License.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A plant dealer engaged in the sale or distribution of nursery stock shall hold a valid Plant Dealer License for each sales location.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Requirements for Licensure. An applicant must fulfill the following requirements for licensure:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Make application to the Department on forms provided by the Department;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Furnish a list of his suppliers of nursery stock;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Maintain records for 1 year of plant acquisitions, including certificate of inspection or another document indicating consignor and state of origin;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Furnish an affidavit attesting to the number of acres, or part of an acre, used as a holding or sales yard for nursery stock;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Pay annual fees as specified in Regulation .06A at the time of application for, or renewal of, a license;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Provide access for the inspection of all nursery stock;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Follow appropriate cultural practices such that an adequate inspection of the nursery stock can be made;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Provide a suitable means of identifying similar blocks of nursery stock as required by the Department; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Keep nursery stock free of plant pests.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A plant dealer will be assigned a permanent license number at the time all requirements for licensure have been met and the original license is issued. Unless sooner revoked, a license is valid for a year beginning January 1, or date of issuance, and ending December 31.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A license is not transferable.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Plant dealer licenses will be renewed annually upon meeting all requirements as outlined in this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Plant Broker License.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A plant broker engaged in the business of soliciting, taking orders, selling, or distributing nursery stock in the State shall hold a valid Plant Broker License.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Requirements for Licensure. An applicant must fulfill the following requirements for licensure:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Make application to the Department on forms provided by the Department;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Pay the annual license fee as specified in Regulation .06B at the time of application for, or renewal of, a license;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Furnish a list of nurseries for which he acts as a broker.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A plant broker will be assigned a permanent license number at the time all requirements have been met and the original license is issued. Unless sooner revoked, the license is valid for a year beginning January 1, or date of issuance, and ending December 31.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A license is not transferable.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Plant broker licenses will be renewed annually upon meeting all requirements as outlined in this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Fee Schedule.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Fees shall be assessed according to the requirements in §§B—I of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Persons Issued a Nursery Inspection Certificate or a Plant Dealer License.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For field inspections of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>1 acre or less— $20;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>More than 1 acre to 5 acres—$30;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>More than 5 acres to 10 acres—$40;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>More than 10 acres—$5 for each acre or part of any acre, up to a maximum of $1,500.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Nursery Inspection Certificate—$150 a year for each sales location.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Plant Dealer License—$150 a year for each sales location.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Persons issued a Plant Broker License. Plant Broker License—$100 a year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Certified Seed Potatoes.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Production.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Field Inspection—$4 an acre or part thereof a year.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Bin Inspection—2 cents for each 100 pounds.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Imported Seed for Planting. Boxcar or Warehouse Inspection—8 cents for each 100 pounds.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Fees are due upon receipt of an invoice from the Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Trueness to Name Plant Certification.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Fees—$50 per acre or part of an acre in plant production.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Fees are due upon receipt of an invoice from the Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Virus-Free Plant Certification.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Certification Fee. Each plant producer shall pay the Secretary the following certification fee for each acre, or part of an acre, in plant production:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Strawberry plants—$50;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Grapevines, fruit trees, and bramble plants—$70.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Fees are due upon receipt of an invoice from the Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Miscellaneous Service Fees.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Soil sample analysis:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>pH—$10;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Fertility—$10;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Pathogen—$25;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Nematode—$25.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Pest identification:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Routine—$5;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Nonroutine—$15;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Urgent—$25.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Equipment fumigation:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Equipment pick up—$25;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Equipment return—$25;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Hive body/deep super—$4;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Shallow super—$3.50;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Miscellaneous equipment—$1.50.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Phytosanitary certificates:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Including travel—$25;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Excluding travel—$5.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Other Miscellaneous Fees—up to $25 for each:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Publication;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Inspection;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Analysis; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Sample.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>A federal, State, or local public agency is exempt from the license and inspection fees required by this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation app="2025-10-27" doc="Maryland Register, Volume 52, Issue 21" eff="2025-10-27" path="regulations|final|25-135-F" type="History" display="false"/>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="15|06|02|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Plant Standards.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Identification of Nursery Stock Produced in Maryland.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each piece of nursery stock offered for retail sale shall be accompanied by a label containing the following information, except as provided in §A(2), below:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Plant Name. This name may be the scientific name or an approved common name, or both. The variety name may also be on the label, but may not be used in lieu of the scientific or approved common name.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Height or caliper or grade or diameter if sold by this measure.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Price of each plant.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Nursery stock offered for retail sale shall be exempt from individualized labeling, provided it meets one of the following requirements:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Nursery stock that is balled and burlapped, packaged, or in a container shall be grouped by identical size, variety, and cost into a bed or lot separated from similar beds or lots. Each bed or lot shall be marked with a permanent legible sign containing the information required by <cite path="15|06|02|.07|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Each block, bed, or row of nursery stock growing in the field shall be marked with a permanent legible sign containing the plant name.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Each piece of nursery stock, or lot of identical pieces, sold or transported for wholesale, shall be accompanied by a bill of lading, delivery ticket, invoice, or label containing the information, except price, required by §A(1), above.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Identification of Nursery Stock Grown Outside the State.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All nursery stock grown outside the State and shipped into the State shall meet the minimum standards for nursery stock grown in the State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If this nursery stock is to be sold at retail, it shall comply with §A(1), above, at time of retail sale.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If this nursery stock is sold at wholesale, it shall comply with §A(3), above.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If nursery stock is to be shipped from the State to any other state, it shall remain labeled conspicuously as to the name of the plant and the state of origin while maintained in the State. This nursery stock shipped from Maryland shall comply with §A(3), above.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Labeling and Advertising.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Nursery stock may not be labeled or advertised with false or misleading information.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A label shall be legible at the time of sale.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person may not offer for sale, sell, or distribute, any nursery stock represented to be "virus-free", "essentially virus-free", or any other similar notation, unless that stock is produced under a program accepted by the Department. All plants offered for sale as "virus-free," "essentially virus-free", or any other similar notation shall have state of origin and name of producer on the label.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Maintenance of Nursery Stock.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Nursery stock offered for sale shall be kept in a healthy condition.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Nursery stock which is dead or dying may not be sold or offered for sale.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Infested Plants or Plant Parts.</heading>
    <text>Any plant or plant part, whether or not included under the definition of nursery stock, found in the State infested with injurious plant pests, is subject to stop sale or condemnation seizure procedures outlined in Regulations . 09 and .10, respectively. Infested plants may be returned to the shipper, treated, destroyed, or otherwise disposed of by the inspector without compensation to the consignor.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Stop Sale.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Nursery stock infested or infected with a dangerously injurious plant pest (See Regulation .12A) may be marked with a stop- sale tag indicating that it may not be sold or distributed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The owner, tenant, or person in charge of the property where nursery stock covered by a stop-sale notice is located shall be given written notice of the stop-sale action.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A person may not sell, offer for sale, use, dispose of, or in any way destroy nursery stock covered by a stop-sale notice, or detach, alter, or destroy any attached tag without the Department's written authorization.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Nursery stock covered by a stop-sale notice shall be treated or destroyed as specified by the Department.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Condemnation Seizure.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A condemnation seizure notice may be issued for nursery stock originating in, or shipped into, the State, infested or infected with plant pests.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Nursery stock infested or infected with any pest listed in Regulation .12A shall be destroyed unless the shipper or consignor agrees to have the plants returned to him at his expense.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Nursery stock infested or infected with any pest listed in Regulation .12B shall be destroyed unless the shipper or consignor agrees to have the plants returned or treated at his expense.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Nursery stock ordered treated may not be sold or offered for sale until it has been released for sale by the inspector. The cost of any required treatment shall be paid by the shipper or consignor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The shipper or consignor shall forfeit any nursery stock condemned, seized, or destroyed, and may not collect its value from a purchaser or consignee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A condemnation seizure notice may be issued for nursery stock that is not properly certified by the state of origin. The nursery stock shall be destroyed unless the shipper or consignor agrees to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Have the nursery stock returned at his expense;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide proper certification;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Authorize an inspector to examine and certify the nursery stock at the expense of the shipper or consignor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Treatment or Destruction Orders.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Nursery stock infested or infected with a plant pest (See Regulation .12A--B) shall be ordered treated or destroyed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The owner, tenant, or person in charge of nursery stock covered by a treatment order shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Learn from the inspector of suitable techniques for control of the pests;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Have the nursery stock treated; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Inform the inspector in writing when pests have been controlled.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If a suitable control technique is not available, or if control is not obtained, or if the owner, tenant, or person in charge of the nursery stock fails to comply with a treatment order, nursery stock shall be destroyed by the owner in a manner approved and supervised by the Department.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the owner, tenant, or person in charge refuses or fails to comply with the destruction order, the</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Department shall seize, destroy, or treat the infested or infected nursery stock and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Owner shall pay costs.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Classification of Plant Pests.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Dangerously Injurious Plant Pests.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A stop sale notice may be issued when any plant pest of quarantine significance is detected or is a plant pest that is not known to occur in the State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Insects. A stop-sale notice may be issued when the following insects are detected:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Stem and trunk borers such as Dogwood, Ash, Lilac, Iris, Rhododendron, Lesser peach tree, Bronze birch, and peach tree;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Scale insects, such as Euonymus, Elongate hemlock, Hemlock, Pit, Obscure, Japanese maple, Latania, Camellia, Oystershell, San Jose, Tea, White peach, Yangicola;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Beetles, such as Whitefringed, Black vine weevil, Fullers rose beetle, White pine weevil;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Caterpillars such as Gypsy moth;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Gall adelgids such as Eastern spruce;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Leafminers, such as Boxwood;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Plant Diseases. A stop-sale notice may be issued when the following plant diseases are detected:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Vascular wilt diseases, such as Dutch elm disease, Oak wilt, Verticillium wilt, Mimosa wilt, Phytophthora wilt, Elm phloem necrosis;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Canker diseases, such as Chestnut blight, Nectria cankers, Botryosphaeria cankers, Cytospora cankers, White pine blister rust, Phytophthora cankers, Fusarium cankers, Strumella cankers, Volutella cankers, Phomopsis cankers, Discula anthracnose of dogwood;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Bacterial diseases, such as Crown gall, Fire blight, Wetwood (Slime-flux);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Galls, such as Rust galls on Pinus spp., Black knot on Prunus spp., Cedar-apple rust galls on Juniperus spp., Crown gall, Root-knot nematode;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Plants infected with viruses or phytoplasms, such as Holly ringspot, Rose mosaic, Rose ring pattern, Stem pitting of Prunus, Fasciation, Witches'-broom Tospoviruses;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Root diseases, such as Armillaria root rot (Shoestring root rot); Phytophthora, Pythium, Rhizoctonia, and Fusarium root rots; Damping-off; Wilts; Root-knot, cyst, and other plant parasitic nematodes;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Needle blight, needle cast, and needle rust diseases of evergreens, such as Diplodia tip blight, Phomopsis blight, Brown spot needle blight, Lophodermium needle cast, Rhabdocline needle cast, Coleosporium needle rust;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Gymnosporangium rusts, such as Hawthorn, and Cedar-apple;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Any other disease or abnormal condition of growth determined by the Department to be dangerously injurious to plants.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Weeds. A stop-sale notice may be issued when the following weeds are detected infesting the soil known as the root ball: Mugwort, Bermudagrass, Dodder, Johnsongrass, Poison ivy, Thistles, Witchweed, Mile-a-Minute, or any other weed determined by the Department to be dangerously injurious.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Harmful Plant Pests.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Insects. A treatment order may be issued when the following insects constitute a serious threat or are causing economic damage to nursery stock:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Scale insects, such as Gloomy, Putnam, Scurfey, Wax, Magnolia, Tulip trees, Peony;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Caterpillars, such as Bagworm, European pine shoot moth, Nantucket pine tip moth;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Lace bugs, such as Azalea, Andromeda, Hawthorn;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Adelgids, such as pine bark;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Leafminers, such as Holly;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Mites, such as Twospotted spider, Spruce spider, Southern red;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Beetles, such as Japanese, Japanese Weevil, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Aphids.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Diseases. A treatment order may be issued when the following diseases or disorders constitute a serious threat or are causing economic damage to nursery stock: Foliar and flower diseases, such as Anthracnose, Powdery mildew, Leaf spots, Botrytis blight, Scab, Sooty mold, Leaf blister, Petal and flower blights, nutritional problems.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Weeds. A treatment order may be issued when the following weeds are detected in a nursery or sales yard: Mugwort, Dodder, Johnsongrass, Yellow Nutsedge, Thistle, or any other weed determined by the Department to be harmful.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Reciprocal Agreements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Nursery stock from other states shall be received in the State on the same basis as nursery stock from the State is received in other states.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An official directory of certified nurseries and licensed plant dealers will be accepted from other states in lieu of an individually filed certificate or license.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>All fees for inspection, certification, registration, or licensure, or all of these, will be waived by the Department for out- of-state nurseries, plant dealers, and brokers selling or distributing nursery stock in the State, providing similar fees are waived for State nurseries, plant dealers, and brokers by the reciprocating state.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Importation of Living Insects, Plant Disease Agents and Other Pests.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A person may not import into the State any live insect, plant disease agent, or other pest for research, educational, or other purposes unless that importation is authorized by a permit issued by the Department.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Applications for permits are furnished by the Department upon request.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Permit holders shall comply with the conditions specified on the permit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Any shipment or lot which is not authorized by a valid permit shall be destroyed immediately unless the Secretary determines that the contents of a shipment or lot do not pose any danger to agriculture. If the Secretary issues this determination, a shipment or lot will be held for proper certification or will be returned to its point of origin.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Plant Certification Programs.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A person producing plants for special certification under a program supervised by the Department shall meet the standards for certification required by the Department.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A person producing certified plants will be assessed a fee as indicated in Regulation .06.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Phytosanitary Certificates.</heading>
    <text>Plants shipped interstate or internationally may be required by another jurisdiction to have a Department-issued phytosanitary certificate before shipment. The Department will issue a certificate only when required by the destination state or country. If a person requests the Department to issue this certificate, that person shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Notify the Department at least 2 weeks before the scheduled shipping date;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Provide information as required by the Department; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Provide access for the inspection of plants to be certified.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.17</num>
    <heading>Revocation, Suspension or Denial of License, Certificate, or Permit.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Department, after notice and an opportunity for a hearing, may revoke, suspend, or deny a license, certificate, or permit or impose a civil penalty for a failure to comply with the Plant Pest Control Law or regulations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A person may appeal the denial, revocation, or suspension of a license, certificate, permit, or civil penalty according to Departmental regulations and the Administrative Procedure Act.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.18</num>
    <heading>Criminal Penalty.</heading>
    <text>A person who violates any provision of these regulations is subject to the following penalties or fines:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>First offense: Upon conviction, a fine not exceeding $500, or imprisonment not exceeding 3 months, or both.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Second or subsequent offense: Upon conviction, a fine not exceeding $1,000, or imprisonment not exceeding 1 year, or both.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="15|06|02|.19">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.19</num>
    <heading>Civil Penalty.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If the Department determines that a violation of this subtitle has occurred, it may impose a civil penalty of not more than $500 for each violation:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Instead of, or in addition to, suspension of the license, permit, or certificate; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In addition to revocation of the license, permit, or certificate.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In assessing a civil penalty imposed under <cite path="15|06|02|.19|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite>, the Department shall give consideration to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The willfulness of the violation, the extent to which the existence of the violation was known to the violator, but uncorrected by the violator, and the extent to which the violator exercised reasonable care;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Any actual harm to the agriculture, environment, and natural resources of this State; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The extent to which the current violation is part of a recurrent pattern of the same or similar type of violation committed by the violator.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Unless a stay has been granted, a person against whom a civil penalty has been imposed under this regulation shall pay the amount of the penalty to the Department.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Agriculture Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|5-301">5-301</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|5-314">5-314</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|9-302">9-302</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1978-01-13">Effective date: January 13, 1978 (5:1 Md. R. 19)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Regulations .01B, J; .06; .07A, C; .12A; and .16 amended effective February</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">10, 1986 (13:3 Md. R. 273)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-08-03"><cite path="|15|06|02|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective August 3, 1992 (19:15 Md. R. 1393)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-10-02" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective October 2, 2000 (27:19 Md. R. 1728)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-10-27"><cite path="|15|06|02|.06|B.">Regulation .06B</cite> amended effective October 27, 2025 (52:21 Md. R. 1025)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-08-09"><cite path="|15|06|02|.06|B.">Regulation .06B</cite>, C amended effective August 9, 2010 (37:16 Md. R. 1060)</annotation>
    <annotation app="2025-10-27" doc="Maryland Register, Volume 52, Issue 21" eff="2025-10-27" path="regulations|final|25-135-F" type="History" display="false"/>
  </annotations>
</container>
