<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Utility Code of Conduct</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Prohibited Utility Conduct with Affiliate.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This regulation does not apply to the practice of a utility holding company advertising companies within the utility holding company corporate family.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Services Generally. A utility may not:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Represent to a customer or potential customer that any advantage or superior service will accrue because of the relationship between the utility and a core service affiliate or non-core service affiliate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Give any preference to a core service affiliate, or non-core service affiliate, or a customer of either in providing regulated utility service;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Condition or tie the provision of regulated utility service to any other product or service;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="|20|40|02|.02">Regulation .02 of this chapter</cite>, engage in promotions, marketing, or advertising with a core or non-core service affiliate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Except with the informed consent of the customer and in compliance with the Commission's consumer protection regulations, disclose any customer-specific information obtained in connection with the provision of regulated utility service;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Offer discounts, rebates, fee waivers, penalty waivers, or other special provisions for a tariff service to an affiliate or a customer of an affiliate, unless it makes the offer available to all similarly situated persons, and makes the offer in a manner designed to allow all an equal ability to utilize the offering;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="|20|40|02|.02">Regulation .02 of this chapter</cite>, market or promote its standard offer service;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Provide sales leads to its core or non-core service affiliate; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Circumvent the provisions of this subtitle through the use of an affiliate as a conduit between the utility and its core service affiliate.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Core Service. A utility may not:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Initiate a joint sales call with its core service affiliate, except when requested by a customer or when the customer has a contractual relationship with the utility and its core service affiliate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Operate from the same physical location used by a core service affiliate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Share core service information with a core service affiliate that could provide a competitive advantage in a discriminatory manner;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Unless a utility has sufficient safeguards in place to prevent a core service employee from gaining access to utility information that it is prohibited from sharing under this subtitle, share electronic databases or electronic files with its core service affiliate; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Speak or appear to speak on behalf of its core service affiliate.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|40|02|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Authorized Utility — Affiliate Activity.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Use of Corporate Name, Trade Names, Trademarks, and Logos.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A utility may authorize its affiliate to use advertising, which uses the utility's corporate name, trade names, trademarks, and logos.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Disclaimer.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Except as provided in <cite path="20|40|02|.02|A.|(3)">§A(3) of this regulation</cite>, when a utility authorizes an affiliate to use its corporate name, trade name, trademark, or logo in an advertisement for a core or non-core service, the utility shall require the affiliate to include a disclaimer in the advertisement.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The disclaimer required under <cite path="20|40|02|.02|A.|(2)|(a)">§A(2)(a) of this regulation</cite> is: "(affiliate name) is not the same company as (utility name), a regulated utility".</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>When a utility authorizes an affiliate to use its corporate name, trade name, trademark, or logo in an image advertisement, regulatory filing, or materials intended to provide information about corporate securities, the utility is not required to mandate that its affiliate include the disclaimer prescribed in <cite path="20|40|02|.02|A.|(2)">§A(2) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A utility may engage in a joint promotion with a core service affiliate if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>It affords all similarly situated non-affiliated licensed electricity or gas suppliers the opportunity to participate in the promotion; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The offer to participate is made in a manner designed to allow an equal opportunity to utilize the promotion.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A utility may provide unbiased information about the availability and terms of standard offer service.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|40|02|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Required Utility Conduct.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Information.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a customer requests information about a competitive core service and the utility responds by identifying licensed electricity or gas suppliers, the utility shall provide the names of all licensed electricity or gas suppliers of core services operating within its Maryland service territory in a nonpreferential manner.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A utility may not promote its core service affiliate when responding to a customer request for information.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Service Requests. A utility shall process all requests for service by a licensed electricity or gas supplier in the same nonpreferential manner and within the same period of time as it processes similar requests for service from its core service affiliate.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Electricity and Gas Suppliers. When providing utility service, a utility shall treat a licensed electricity or gas supplier and their customers in the same manner as the utility treats its core service affiliate or its core service affiliate's customers.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Public Disclosure.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="20|40|02|.03|D.|(3)">§D(3) of this regulation</cite>, a utility shall contemporaneously disclose to all licensed retail electricity or gas suppliers on its system all information it provides to a retail electricity or gas supplier about:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Its system;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The marketing or sale of energy to a customer or potential customer; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The delivery of energy to or on its system.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A utility shall comply with the requirements of <cite path="20|40|02|.03|D.|(1)">§D(1) of this regulation</cite> by posting information:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>On its electronic bulletin board;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>On its web site; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>In any commercially reasonable and nonpreferential manner.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A utility may share the following information without making the disclosure required in <cite path="20|40|02|.03|D.|(1)">§D(1) of this regulation</cite>:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Information relating to the administration of a contract to supply standard offer service, or default energy service, or to carry out an interconnection agreement;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Information to a supplier as necessary for the supplier to bill or provide services to its customers; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Information with its associated holding company to the extent necessary to comply with federal and State laws and regulations.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|40|02|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Utility and Utility-Affiliate Shared Personnel.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Exceptions. This regulation does not apply to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Employee-sharing between a utility and another utility, or any operating division of the same utility, regulated by the Commission or another state's utility regulatory body; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Personnel sharing permitted by the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Permitted Personnel Sharing. Except as provided in <cite path="20|40|02|.04|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, a utility may share personnel with its affiliate.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Restrictions on Personnel Sharing. A utility may not share with its core service affiliate:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Operational, advertising, marketing, or market research personnel; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Any other individual, if that individual:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Possesses information that is competitively sensitive to the electric or gas supply markets; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Will use this information in the course of performing the shared job function.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|40|02|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Asset Transactions Involving an Affiliate.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This regulation does not apply to transactions between a utility and another utility, or any operating division of the same utility, which is regulated by the Commission or another state's utility regulatory body.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Subject to <cite path="20|40|02|.05|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, a utility may enter into an asset transfer or receipt transaction with its affiliate.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If a utility enters into a transaction with an affiliate involving the transfer or receipt of an asset that has a book value of more than $75,000 per item, or a total book value of $1,000,000, other than a transaction resulting from an open bidding process, including an auction or a request for proposal with an independent evaluator, the utility shall record the transaction in its financial records based on asymmetric pricing to the extent permitted by federal law or regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|40|02|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Utility Loans or Debt Guarantees to an Affiliate.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This regulation does not apply to a utility's participation in a cash management or money pool subject to federal regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Except as provided under <cite path="20|40|02|.06|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, a utility may make a loan or provide a debt guarantee to its affiliate.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Restrictions on Loans or Debt Guarantees.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a loan or guarantee by a utility to its affiliate creates a reasonable likelihood that the utility's cost of capital, creditworthiness, or ability to provide regulated service will be adversely affected in a material manner, a utility may not:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Lend money to its affiliate; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Guarantee the debt of its affiliate.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>New Loan or Debt Guarantee.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If a new loan or debt guarantee by a utility to its affiliate is in excess of $25,000,000 or 2 percent of the equity capital of the utility, whichever is greater, or the loan causes the utility's proprietary capital ratio to fall below 30 percent, the utility shall inform the Commission that it is making the loan or guarantee at least 90 days before the transaction is closed.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If, within 90 days of receiving the notice under <cite path="20|40|02|.06|C.|(2)|(a)">§C(2)(a) of this regulation</cite>, the Commission finds that the loan or guarantee creates a reasonable likelihood that the utility's cost of capital, creditworthiness, or ability to provide regulated service will be adversely affected, it may disapprove the loan or guarantee.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If the Commission does not act within 90 days of receiving notice of the loan or guarantee, the utility may undertake the loan or guarantee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A utility loan under this regulation shall include an interest rate equal to the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Fair market interest rate at the time of execution of the loan; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Rate directed or approved by a federal agency having jurisdiction over the loan.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|40|02|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Cost Allocation Manual (CAM).</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This regulation does not apply to a utility that does not have a core or non-core service affiliate.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Any time a utility files a general rate case, a utility shall file its CAM with the Commission.</text>
      <para>
        <num proof="done">(2)</num>
        <text>A utility shall file with the Commission any change to a CAM policy that allocates or assigns cost, within 30 days of the effective date of the change.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A utility filing required under <cite path="20|40|02|.07|B.|(2)">§B(2) of this regulation</cite> shall include a detailed narrative that describes and justifies each change including a showing of the estimated impact of the change.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A CAM shall contain the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Corporate organization chart;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Officers of the parent or holding company, the utility, and the service company, as applicable;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Complete description of the types of all costs shared with an affiliate; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Methodology and procedure used to allocate costs.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Record and Reporting Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each Cost Allocation Manual filed as directed in <cite path="|20|40|02|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite> shall contain the following items:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The amount the utility allocated or assigned the previous calendar year for each type of cost identified in its CAM;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An affidavit stating that its cost allocation and the transfer pricing of an asset complies with this subtitle; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A certification that a training program is in place to train personnel as necessary to comply with this subtitle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>On or before May 15 of each calendar year a utility shall file with the Commission a report for the previous calendar year ending December 31 titled "Ring Fencing Report" containing the following items:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A summary of all measures intended to protect the utility's financial strength and credit ratings from the activities of core service and non-core service affiliates;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A corporate organization chart identifying the utility and its core service and non-core service affiliates;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A description of each core service and non-core service affiliate's business;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If available, a copy of each core service and non-core service affiliate's most recently published credit rating report made by a nationally recognized credit rating agency;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If a utility shares personnel with a core service or non-core service affiliate, a personnel-sharing report listing the shared personnel's position title and function;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A list of asset transactions between a utility and its core service and non-core service affiliate consistent with the following guidelines:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>For an asset transferred to or from a utility where the book value is above $75,000, the report shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Describe the transferred asset;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Indicate the affiliate providing or receiving the asset;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Provide the value received or given for the transferred asset; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Provide an external appraisal or the market value of the transferred asset; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For an individual asset transferred to or from a utility where the book value is below $75,000, the report shall identify the type of asset transferred and the affiliate providing or receiving the asset;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>A list of all assets, if individually accounted for, or asset categories owned by the utility which were loaned or shared with a core service or non-core service affiliate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>A list of all assets jointly owned with a core service or non-core service affiliate; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>A list of all core service or non-core service affiliate debt guaranteed by the utility or secured by any utility asset.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A utility shall maintain a detailed monthly record of any cost allocation and assignment and make this record available for Commission review and audit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A utility shall permit the Commission to have access to any report and associated work papers prepared for a utility by an independent auditor hired to perform an audit under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|4-208">Public Utilities Article, §4-208, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A utility shall notify the Commission within 7 days after the utility or its affiliate:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Files for bankruptcy; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is in material breach of any debt obligation which is guaranteed by the utility or secured by its assets.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Public Utilities Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-113">2-113</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-121">2-121</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-505">7-505</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-604">7-604</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-606">7-606</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-03-13">Effective date: March 13, 2006 (33:5 Md. R. 522)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-07-08"><cite path="|20|40|02|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective July 8, 2024 (51:13 Md. R. 648)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-03-18"><cite path="|20|40|02|.07|B.">Regulation .07B</cite> amended effective March 18, 2013 (40:5 Md. R. 412)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-03-18"><cite path="|20|40|02|.08|A.">Regulation .08A</cite> amended effective March 18, 2013 (40:5 Md. R. 412)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
