<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>Advance Directive Registry</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter defines key terms and sets out requirements and procedures for an Advance Directive Registry.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Advance Directive.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Advance directive" has the meaning stated in Health-General Article, §5-601, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Advance directive" includes an Instructions on Current Life-Sustaining Treatment Options form developed under Health-General Article, §5-608.1, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Authorized person" means an individual:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Designated in writing by a registrant; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Under the conditions specified in federal or State law, authorized to obtain access to the medical records of the registrant.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Department" means the Maryland Department of Health.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Filing" means the presentation of an advance directive for registration to the Secretary.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Health care facility" has the meaning stated in Health-General Article, §19-114, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Health care provider" has the meaning stated in Health-General Article, §5-601, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Instructions on a Current Life-Sustaining Treatment Options form" means the form developed under Health-General Article, §5-608.1, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Registrant" means an individual who registers the individual's advance directive with the Department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Registry" means the depository for advance directives in the Department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Secretary" means the Secretary of Health or a designee of the Secretary.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|23|01|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Filing and Registration.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An individual may submit an advance directive to the Department for registration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In order for the Department to register an advance directive, a registrant shall provide to the Department:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A completed application on the form provided by the Department;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The required fee, as set forth in <cite path="|10|23|01|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An advance directive that contains:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The registrant's signature;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The date on which the advance directive was signed by the registrant; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The signatures of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Two witnesses as provided in Health-General Article, §5-602, Annotated Code of Maryland; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>If an Instructions on a Current Life-Sustaining Treatment Options form is submitted and the registrant is incapable of making an informed decision, the registrant's health care agent or surrogate and the registrant's attending physician.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>On receipt of the items set forth in <cite path="10|23|01|.03|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, the Department shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Create a digital reproduction of the form and advance directive;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Enter the reproduced form and advance directive into the advance directive database; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Assign each advance directive a file number and password.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>After processing the advance directive presented for registration, the Department shall provide to each registrant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A copy of the registrant's documents on file in the Registry;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Instructions for accessing a copy of the registrant's advance directive;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Instructions for amending or revoking an advance directive;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A wallet card indicating registration of an advance directive; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A sticker to affix to a driver's license or identification card that shows that an advance directive has been filed with the Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Nonregistration of Advance Directive.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An individual is not required to register an advance directive with the Department.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An advance directive that is not submitted to the Registry is valid in accordance with applicable law.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Amendment or Revocation of a Registered Advance Directive.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The registrant shall notify the Registry if a registered advance directive has been:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Amended; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Revoked.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Department shall amend the file of a registrant on receipt of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An application for amendment on a form provided by the Department;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A copy of the amended advance directive that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is complete; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Contains all information set forth in <cite path="|10|23|01|.03|B.">Regulation .03B of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A health care provider that becomes aware that a registrant has amended or revoked a registered advance directive shall, at the request of the registrant, provide the registrant with information on how to notify the Registry of the amendment or revocation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Department shall delete the file of a registrant on receipt of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An application for revocation on a form provided by the Department; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Written documentation of revocation as provided in Health-General Article, §5-604, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Fees — Repealed.</heading>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Disclosure of Information.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Department shall provide access to a registered advance directive to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The registrant; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An authorized person.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>To access an advance directive:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A registrant or a registrant's designee shall supply the registrant's file number and password; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A representative of a health care facility shall supply the facility's username and password.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Storage of Data.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Department shall establish a Registry that is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Secure, in accordance with data security standards customarily applied to the protection of electronic medical records; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Available 24 hours a day, 7 days a week.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Department may provide for services related to the establishment and operation of the Registry through contract with a person or agency.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Department or its contractor may store in the Registry only documents that are:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Identical to those submitted by the registrant; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In a digital, read-only format preventing modification.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Department shall destroy the paper copy of an advance directive submitted by a registrant when the paper copy has been fully and accurately converted to digital copy.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Public Outreach.</heading>
    <text>The Department shall carry out educational and outreach efforts to increase public awareness of the Registry.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Liability of Health Care Providers.</heading>
    <text>A health care provider is not subject to criminal prosecution or civil liability and may not be determined to have engaged in unprofessional conduct by the appropriate licensing authority for:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Failure to access the Registry; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Relying on information provided by the Registry.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Registry Funding.</heading>
    <text>Implementation of this chapter is contingent on the availability of funds, in accordance with State Finance and Procurement Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|7-234">7-234</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|7-235">7-235</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health-General Article, §§5-620 — 5-626, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-12-06">Effective date: December 6, 2007 (34:24 Md. R. 2158)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-08-29"><cite path="|10|23|01|.05|B.">Regulation .05B</cite> amended effective August 29, 2016 (43:17 Md. R. 953)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-08-29"><cite path="|10|23|01|.06">Regulation .06</cite> repealed effective August 29, 2016 (43:17 Md. R. 953)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
