<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Requirements for Designated Trauma or Specialty Referral Centers</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Requirements for Trauma or Specialty Referral Centers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A hospital designated as a trauma or specialty referral center shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Comply with the applicable standards for trauma or specialty care as developed by MIEMSS and set forth in <cite path="|30.08.05">COMAR 30.08.05</cite>—30.08.12;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Receive all trauma or specialty patients, regardless of race, color, religion, age, sex, marital status, national origin, ancestry, physical or mental disability, or ability to pay;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Upon MIEMSS' request, provide data to MIEMSS related to trauma or specialty care programs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Allow MIEMSS to monitor compliance with applicable regulations and standards as set forth by MIEMSS, including providing MIEMSS with access to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Patient discharge summaries,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Patient care logs,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Patient care records,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Hospital trauma or specialty care quality management program records, including minutes, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Other documents that MIEMSS determines to be relevant; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Require confidentiality of information relating to an individual patient, provider, and hospital care outcomes in accordance with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 1, Subtitle 4, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp">General Provisions Article, Title 4, Subtitle 3, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Emergency Standards.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>MIEMSS may impose additional requirements on a trauma or specialty referral center if it determines that the requirements are necessary for the immediate protection of trauma or specialty patients.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>MIEMSS shall provide the designated trauma or specialty referral center with advance written notice of an additional emergency standard.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The designated trauma or specialty referral center shall have reasonable time to comply with the emergency standard.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Prehospital Triage and Transport.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>MIEMSS shall develop and distribute to health care providers prehospital triage and transport protocols for patients needing trauma or specialty referral services to ensure that patients who meet the triage criteria established by the protocols are transported directly to an appropriate facility.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In the absence of extenuating circumstances, a health care provider shall transport a patient to the closest appropriate trauma or specialty referral center, consistent with the triage protocols.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Prohibited Acts.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A hospital may not represent itself to be a trauma or specialty referral center unless it is so designated by MIEMSS and approved by the EMS Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A designated trauma or specialty referral center may not advertise services or capabilities for the treatment of patients above the trauma care level or specialty for which it has been designated.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|13-509">Education Article, §13-509, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1997-03-24">Effective date: March 24, 1997 (24:6 Md. R. 488)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-07-01">Regulations <cite path="|30|08|03|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|30|08|03|.03">.03</cite> amended effective July 1, 2002 (29:12 Md. R. 932)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-10-23"><cite path="|30|08|03|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective June 1, 2006 (33:15 Md. R. 1276); amended permanently effective October 23, 2006 (33:21 Md. R. 1678)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-10-12"><cite path="|30|08|03|.01|A.">Regulation .01A</cite> amended effective December 19, 2005 (32:25 Md. R. 1947); October 12, 2015 (42:20 Md. R. 1265)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
