<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>16</num>
  <heading>Cardiac Interventional Center Standards</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Cardiac Interventional Center" means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An in-State hospital that meets the requirements in <cite path="|30|08|16|.02">Regulation .02 of this chapter</cite> and is designated by MIEMSS and approved by the EMS Board to receive patients transported by ambulance with acute ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction (STEMI) who need Primary Percutaneous Coronary Intervention; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An out-of-State hospital that has entered into an agreement with MIEMSS and has been approved by the EMS Board to receive patients with acute ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction who need Primary Percutaneous Coronary Intervention.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Jurisdiction" means a state, commonwealth, or the District of Columbia.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI)" means a variety of catheter-based techniques, including balloon angioplasty, capable of relieving coronary vessel narrowing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Primary PCI" means PCI capable of relieving coronary vessel narrowing associated with acute ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction (STEMI).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"STEMI" means coronary vessel narrowing associated with ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Cardiac Interventional Center.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A Cardiac Interventional Center shall be licensed as an acute care hospital by the hospital licensing authority in the jurisdiction in which it is located.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If located in Maryland, a Cardiac Interventional Center shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Have one of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A Certificate of Need (CON) issued by the Maryland Health Care Commission for a cardiac surgery and percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI) program; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A current waiver issued by the Maryland Health Care Commission to provide primary percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI) services to STEMI patients meeting certain criteria without on-site cardiac surgery; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Be a base station approved under <cite path="|30.03.06">COMAR 30.03.06</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If not located in Maryland, a Cardiac Interventional Center shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Possess all government approvals required to provide Primary PCI under the laws of the jurisdiction in which it is located including, if required, a CON; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Satisfy one of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be a base station approved under <cite path="|30.03.06">COMAR 30.03.06</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Have the equipment necessary to conduct a dual consult between EMS and a Maryland base station for each Maryland patient transported to the Cardiac Interventional Center.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A Cardiac Interventional Center shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provide primary PCI as soon as possible and not to exceed 90 minutes from patient arrival, that is, door to balloon time of less than 90 minutes, for 75% of appropriate STEMI patients;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide primary PCI for appropriate STEMI patients 24 hours per day, 7 day per week;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Have adequate physician, nursing, and technical staff to provide cardiac catheterization and coronary care unit services 24 hours per day, 7 days per week;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Have a single call access system for receiving patients with STEMI;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Participate in the County Hospital Alert Tracking System (CHATS) program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Abide by the Maryland Emergency Medical Services Inter-Hospital Transfer Guidelines published by MIEMSS in addition to any applicable transfer requirements in <cite path="|10.24.17">COMAR 10.24.17</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Communicate as soon as possible with the STEMI patient's primary physician and cardiologist regarding patient outcome;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Establish a Cardiac Interventional Center medical review committee which shall be a medical review committee under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|1-401">Health Occupations Article, §1-401, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, as a committee established in the Maryland Institute for Emergency Medical Services Systems which:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Meets at least three times a year;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Reviews practice patterns; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Modifies practice patterns as appropriate; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Comply with the requirements of <cite path="|30.08.04">COMAR 30.08.04</cite>, including participating in:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A Cardiovascular Data registry jointly approved by MHCC and MIEMSS, including any registry data reporting requirements established by either MIEMSS or MHCC; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>State specialty care quality management activities of MIEMSS or of MHCC that are approved by MIEMSS.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Catheterization Lab.</heading>
    <text>A Cardiac Interventional Center may receive STEMI patients transported by ambulance directly to the catheterization lab when approved by the base station physician if the catheterization lab has a physician, appropriately credentialed to evaluate and stabilize an acute cardiac patient, a registered nurse, and a technician, capable of activating the catheterization lab, immediately available in house when:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The 12 lead EKG in the field is interpreted by an advanced life support EMS provider as a high probability of a STEMI; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The 12 lead EKG in the field has been reviewed by an ED physician, a cardiologist, or both, and determined to be a STEMI.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="30|08|16|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Site Reviews.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Notwithstanding <cite path="30.08.02.06">COMAR 30.08.02.06</cite>, MIEMSS may designate any Cardiac Interventional Center without a site review.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Notwithstanding <cite path="30|08|16|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, MIEMSS staff may conduct an onsite review to verify compliance with this chapter, including:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Inspecting the hospital's physical plant;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Interviewing team members and management personnel;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Examining the hospital's Cardiac Interventional Center related documents, including patient care records; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Reviewing other materials considered appropriate by MIEMSS.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Maryland Health Care Commission staff may participate in any review conducted by MIEMSS to verify compliance with <cite path="|30.08.15">COMAR 30.08.15</cite>, including reviewing application materials, and participating in any on-site review.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>MIEMSS staff may participate in any review conducted by the Maryland Health Care Commission to verify compliance with <cite path="|10.24.17">COMAR 10.24.17</cite>, including reviewing application materials, and participating in any on-site visits.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|13-509">Education Article, §13-509, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-05-03">Effective date: May 3, 2010 (37:9 Md. R. 674)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
