<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>08</num>
  <heading>Access to Unemployment Insurance Records</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>This chapter sets out the procedures for access to and inspection of unemployment insurance records related to the determination of a claim. The procedures described in this chapter are in addition to the procedures for obtaining access to and inspection of records under the Maryland Public Information Act pursuant to <cite path="|09.01.04">COMAR 09.01.04</cite>. A claimant or employer, as defined in this chapter, may choose to proceed under either <cite path="|09.01.04">COMAR 09.01.04</cite> or this chapter in order to obtain access to and inspection of unemployment insurance records.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Claimant" means an individual who submits a claim for unemployment insurance benefits.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Department" means the Maryland Department of Labor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Employer" means a person or governmental entity who employs at least one individual within the State and who is an interested party in the determination of the claimant's claim.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Unemployment insurance office" means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Any local office that processes claims for unemployment insurance benefits; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The central office of the Office of Unemployment Insurance of the Maryland Department of Labor.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Applicability.</heading>
    <text>This chapter applies only to requests made to an unemployment insurance office by a claimant or employer for the inspection or copying of unemployment insurance records related to the determination of a claim for unemployment insurance benefits.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Procedures.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A claimant or employer, or an authorized representative of a claimant or employer, may request to inspect or copy the unemployment insurance records related to the determination of the claimant's claim for benefits. The request may be directed to either the manager of the unemployment insurance office where the claim was filed or the custodian of records of the Office of Unemployment Insurance.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Upon the request of a claimant or employer, or an authorized representative, and upon the reasonable verification of the claimant's or employer's or representative's identify, the unemployment insurance office to whom the request was made shall, with reasonable promptness, make available to the requestor for inspection and copying unemployment insurance records related to the determination of the claimant's claim.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A claimant or employer who requests access to and inspection of unemployment insurance records may inspect the records during the normal working hours of the unemployment insurance office to which the request was made.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If a determination of a claim for unemployment insurance benefits is appealed, the unemployment insurance office where the claim was filed shall maintain a copy of all records upon which the determination is based and make them available to a claimant or employer, or the authorized representative of the claimant or employer, upon request.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gle|8-305">Labor and Employment Article, §8-305, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-05-04">Effective date: May 4, 1998 (25:9 Md. R. 679)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
