<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>08</num>
  <heading>Mandatory Written Solicitation Requirements</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Public Information Act Notice.</heading>
    <text>A public information act notice is a mandatory provision for all requests for proposals. The following notice is preferred:</text>
    <text>"Offerors should give specific attention to the identification of those portions of their proposals that they deem to be confidential, proprietary information or trade secrets and provide any justification why such materials, upon request, should not be disclosed by the State under the Access to Public Records Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 10, Subtitle 6, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>."</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Bid Bond Notice.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Solicitations for construction contracts reasonably expected by the procurement officer to exceed $100,000 shall contain notice of bid security requirements (See <cite path="|21.06.07">COMAR 21.06.07</cite>).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Solicitations for all other contracts reasonably expected by the procurement officer to exceed $50,000 and for which the procurement officer wishes to require bid security shall contain notice of the bid security requirements.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Notwithstanding §§A and B of this regulation, notice of bid security is required if a federal law or a condition of federal assistance for the contract requires it.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Minority Business Enterprise Notice.</heading>
    <text>A minority business enterprise notification is a mandatory provision for all solicitations as follows:</text>
    <text>"Minority business enterprises are encouraged to respond to this solicitation".</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Minority Business Enterprise Subcontract Participation Goal.</heading>
    <text>Any solicitation containing an MBE subcontract participation goal, except small procurements made under <cite path="|21.05.07">COMAR 21.05.07</cite>, shall include a clause the same as or similar to the following:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>"An overall MBE subcontract participation goal of _____ percent of the total contract dollar amount, including all renewal option terms, if any, has been established for this procurement. By submitting a response to this solicitation, the bidder or offeror acknowledges the overall MBE subcontractor participation goal, and commits to achieving the goal by utilizing certified minority business enterprises or requests a full or partial waiver of the goal.”; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>"An overall MBE subcontract participation goal of _____ percent of the total contract dollar amount, including all renewal option terms, if any, has been established for this procurement. The overall MBE subcontract participation goal includes the following subgoals, which have been established for this procurement:</text>
      <text>_____% for African-American MBEs;</text>
      <text>_____% for Asian-American MBEs;</text>
      <text>_____% for Hispanic-American MBEs; and</text>
      <text>_____% for Woman-Owned MBEs.</text>
      <text>By submitting a response to this solicitation, the bidder or offeror acknowledges the overall MBE subcontractor participation goal and subgoals, and commits to achieving the overall goal and subgoals by utilizing certified minority business enterprises, or requests a full or partial waiver of the overall goal and subgoals.”</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="21|05|08|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Nonvisual Access Clause.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="21|05|08|.05|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, the following clause is a mandatory provision for each invitation for bid under <cite path="|21.05.02">COMAR 21.05.02</cite> or request for proposals under <cite path="|21.05.03">COMAR 21.05.03</cite> for the purchase of new or upgraded information and communication technology:</text>
      <text>“The bidder or offeror warrants that the information and communication technology offered under this bid or proposal (1) provides equivalent access for effective use by both visual and nonvisual means consistent with the standards of § 508 of the federal Rehabilitation Act of 1973 and Code of Maryland Regulations <cite path="|14.33.02">14.33.02</cite>; (2) provides an individual with disabilities with nonvisual access in a way that is fully and equally accessible to and independently usable by the individual with disabilities so that the individual is able to acquire the same information, engage in the same interactions, and enjoy the same services as users without disabilities, with substantially equivalent ease of use; (3) will present information, including prompts used for interactive communications, in formats intended for both visual and nonvisual use; (4) if intended for use in a network, can be integrated into networks for obtaining, retrieving, and disseminating information used by individuals who are not blind or visually impaired; and (5) is available, whenever possible, without modification for compatibility with software and hardware for nonvisual access. The bidder or offeror further warrants that the cost, if any, of modifying the information and communication technology for compatibility with software and hardware used for nonvisual access will not increase the cost of the information and communication technology by more than 15 percent.</text>
      <text>“Within 18 months after the award of any contract the Secretary of the Department of Information Technology, or the Secretary’s designee, will determine whether the information and communication technology procured under this bid or proposal meets the nonvisual access standards set forth in the Code of Maryland Regulations <cite path="|14.33.02">14.33.02</cite>. If the information and communication technology procured under this solicitation does not meet the nonvisual access standards set forth in the Code of Maryland Regulations <cite path="|14.33.02">14.33.02</cite>, the State will notify the bidder or offeror in writing that the bidder or offeror, at its own expense, has 12 months after the date of the notification to modify the information and communication technology in order to meet the nonvisual access standards. If the bidder or offeror fails to modify the information and communication technology to meet the nonvisual access standards within 12 months after the date of the notification, the bidder or offeror may be subject to a civil penalty of a fine not exceeding $5,000 for a first offense, and a fine not exceeding $10,000 for a subsequent offense.</text>
      <text>“The bidder or offeror shall defend, indemnify, and hold the State harmless from any claims, costs, losses, damages, liability, judgments, and expenses resulting from or arising out of the use of information and communication technology that does not meet the applicable nonvisual access standards.</text>
      <text>“For purposes of this regulation, the phrase ‘equivalent access’ means the ability to receive, use, and manipulate information and operate controls necessary to access and use information and communication technology by nonvisual means. Examples of equivalent access include keyboard controls used for input and synthesized speech, Braille, or other audible or tactile means used for output.”</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The nonvisual access clause is not required if the procurement officer makes a determination that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The information and communication technology is not available with nonvisual access because the essential elements of the information and communication technology are visual and nonvisual equivalence cannot be developed; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The cost of modifying the information and communication technology for compatibility with software and hardware used for nonvisual access would increase the cost of the procurement by more than 15 percent.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The procurement officer may request such documentation as is reasonably necessary to implement this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Arrearages.</heading>
    <text>An arrearages clause is a mandatory provision for all solicitations. The language may be varied but shall contain the following information:</text>
    <text>"By submitting a response to this solicitation, a vendor shall be deemed to represent that it is not in arrears in the payment of any obligation due and owing the State of Maryland, including the payment of taxes and employee benefits, and that it shall not become so in arrears during the term of the contract if selected for contract award."</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="21|05|08|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Bid/Proposal Affidavit.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each solicitation shall provide notice that the affidavit in <cite path="21|05|08|.07|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> shall be completed and submitted to the procurement agency with the vendor's bid or offer.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Mandatory Solicitation Addendum. The solicitation addendum shall be in substantially the same form as follows<em> and include all certification language required by the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf">State Finance and Procurement Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite></em>:</text>
      <include>
        <text>BID/PROPOSAL AFFIDAVIT</text>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>Authority</text>
          <text>I HEREBY AFFIRM THAT:</text>
          <text>I (print name)_____________________ possess the legal authority to make this Affidavit.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>CERTIFICATION REGARDING COMMERCIAL NONDISCRIMINATION</text>
          <text>The undersigned bidder hereby certifies and agrees that the following information is correct: In preparing its bid on this project, the bidder has considered all proposals submitted from qualified, potential subcontractors and suppliers, and has not engaged in “discrimination” as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|19">§19–103 of the State Finance and Procurement Article of the Annotated Code of Maryland; to wit: discrimination in the solicitation, selection, or commercial treatment of any subcontractor, vendor, supplier, or commercial customer on the basis of race, color, religion, ancestry or national origin, sex, age, marital status, sexual orientation, gender identity, or on the basis of disability or other unlawful forms of discrimination. Without limiting the foregoing, “discrimination” also includes retaliating against any person or other entity for reporting any incident of “discrimination”. Without limiting any other provision of the solicitation for bids on this project, it is understood and agreed that, if this certification is false, such false certification will constitute grounds for the State to reject the bid submitted by the bidder on this project, and terminate any contract awarded based on the bid. As part of its bid or proposal, the bidder shall provide to the State a list of all instances within the immediate past 4 years where there has been a final adjudicated determination in a legal or administrative proceeding in the State of Maryland that the bidder discriminated against its subcontractors, vendors, suppliers, or commercial customers, and a description of the status or resolution of that complaint, including any remedial action taken. As a condition of submitting a bid or proposal to the State, the bidder agrees to comply with the State’s Commercial Nondiscrimination Policy as described under Title 19 of the State Finance and Procurement Article of the Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.”</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B-1.</num>
          <text>Certification Regarding Minority Business Enterprises.</text>
          <text>The undersigned bidder hereby certifies and agrees that it has fully complied with the State Minority Business Enterprise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|14-308">State Finance and Procurement Article, §14-308(a)(2), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, which provides that, except as otherwise provided by law, a contractor may not identify a certified minority business enterprise in a bid or proposal and:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Fail to request, receive, or otherwise obtain authorization from the certified minority business enterprise to identify the certified minority proposal;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Fail to notify the certified minority business enterprise before execution of the contract of its inclusion in the bid or proposal;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Fail to use the certified minority business enterprise in the performance of the contract; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Pay the certified minority business enterprise solely for the use of its name in the bid or proposal.</text>
          </para>
          <aftertext>Without limiting any other provision of the solicitation on this project, it is understood that if the certification is false, such false certification constitutes grounds for the State to reject the bid submitted by the bidder on this project, and terminate any contract awarded based on the bid.</aftertext>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B-2.</num>
          <text>Certification Regarding Veteran-Owned Small Business Enterprises. The undersigned bidder hereby certifies and agrees that it has fully complied with the State veteran-owned small business enterprise law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|14-605">State Finance and Procurement Article, §14-605, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, which provides that a person may not:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Knowingly and with intent to defraud, fraudulently obtain, attempt to obtain, or aid another person in fraudulently obtaining or attempting to obtain public money, procurement contracts, or funds expended under a procurement contract to which the person is not entitled under this title;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Knowingly and with intent to defraud, fraudulently represent participation of a veteran-owned small business enterprise in order to obtain or retain a bid preference or a procurement contract;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Willfully and knowingly make or subscribe to any statement, declaration, or other document that is fraudulent or false as to any material matter, whether or not that falsity or fraud is committed with the knowledge or consent of the person authorized or required to present the declaration, statement, or document;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Willfully and knowingly aid, assist in, procure, counsel, or advise the preparation or presentation of a declaration, statement, or other document that is fraudulent or false as to any material matter, regardless of whether that falsity or fraud is committed with the knowledge or consent of the person authorized or required to present the declaration, statement, or document;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Willfully and knowingly fail to file any declaration or notice with the unit that is required by <cite path="|21.11.12">COMAR 21.11.12</cite>; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>Establish, knowingly aid in the establishment of, or exercise control over a business found to have violated a provision of §B-2(1)—(5) of this regulation.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>AFFIRMATION REGARDING BRIBERY CONVICTIONS</text>
          <text>I FURTHER AFFIRM THAT:</text>
          <text>Neither I, nor to the best of my knowledge, information, and belief, the above business (as is defined in Section 16-101(b) of the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf">State Finance and Procurement Article of the Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>), or any of its officers, directors, partners, controlling stockholders, or any of its employees directly involved in the business's contracting activities including obtaining or performing contracts with public bodies has been convicted of, or has had probation before judgment imposed pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcp|6-220">Criminal Procedure Article, §6-220, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or has pleaded nolo contendere to a charge of, bribery, attempted bribery, or conspiracy to bribe in violation of Maryland law, or of the law of any other state or federal law, except as follows (indicate the reasons why the affirmation cannot be given and list any conviction, plea, or imposition of probation before judgment with the date, court, official or administrative body, the sentence or disposition, the name(s) of person(s) involved, and their current positions and responsibilities with the business):</text>
          <text>____________________________________________________________</text>
          <text>____________________________________________________________</text>
          <text>___________________________________________________________.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>D.</num>
          <text>AFFIRMATION REGARDING OTHER CONVICTIONS</text>
          <text>I FURTHER AFFIRM THAT:</text>
          <text>Neither I, nor to the best of my knowledge, information, and belief, the above business, or any of its officers, directors, partners, controlling stockholders, or any of its employees directly involved in the business's contracting activities including obtaining or performing contracts with public bodies, has:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Been convicted under state or federal statute of:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>A criminal offense incident to obtaining, attempting to obtain, or performing a public or private contract; or</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>Fraud, embezzlement, theft, forgery, falsification or destruction of records or receiving stolen property;</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Been convicted of any criminal violation of a state or federal antitrust statute;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Been convicted under the provisions of Title 18 of the United States Code for violation of the Racketeer Influenced and Corrupt Organization Act, 18 U.S.C. §1961 et seq., or the Mail Fraud Act, 18 U.S.C. §1341 et seq., for acts in connection with the submission of bids or proposals for a public or private contract;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Been convicted of a violation of the State Minority Business Enterprise Law, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|14-308">§14-308 of the State Finance and Procurement Article of the Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Been convicted of a violation of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|11-205">§11-205.1 of the State Finance and Procurement Article of the Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>Been convicted of conspiracy to commit any act or omission that would constitute grounds for conviction or liability under any law or statute described in subsections (1)—(5) above;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text>Been found civilly liable under a state or federal antitrust statute for acts or omissions in connection with the submission of bids or proposals for a public or private contract;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(8)</num>
            <text>Been found in a final adjudicated decision to have violated the Commercial Nondiscrimination Policy under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf">Title 19 of the State Finance and Procurement Article of the Annotated Code of Maryland</cite> with regard to a public or private contract;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(9)</num>
            <text>Been convicted of a violation of one or more of the following provisions of the Internal Revenue Code:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>§7201, Attempt to Evade or Defeat Tax;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>§7203, Willful Failure to File Return, Supply Information, or Pay Tax,</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(c)</num>
              <text>§7205, Fraudulent Withholding Exemption Certificate or Failure to Supply Information,</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(d)</num>
              <text>§7206, Fraud and False Statements, or</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(e)</num>
              <text>§7207 Fraudulent Returns, Statements, or Other Documents;</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(10)</num>
            <text>Been convicted of a violation of 18 U.S.C. §286 Conspiracy to Defraud the Government with Respect to Claims, 18 U.S.C. §287, False, Fictitious, or Fraudulent Claims, or 18 U.S.C. §371, Conspiracy to Defraud the United States;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(11)</num>
            <text>Been convicted of a violation of the Tax-General Article, Title 13, Subtitle 7 or Subtitle 10, Annotated Code of Maryland;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(12)</num>
            <text>Been found to have willfully or knowingly violated State Prevailing Wage Laws as provided in the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf">State Finance and Procurement Article, Title 17, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, if:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>A court:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(i)</num>
                <text>Made the finding; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <text>Decision became final; or</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>The finding was:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(i)</num>
                <text>Made in a contested case under the Maryland Administrative Procedure Act; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <text>Not overturned on judicial review;</text>
              </para>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(13)</num>
            <text>Been found to have willfully or knowingly violated State Living Wage Laws as provided in the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf">State Finance and Procurement Article, Title 18, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, if:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>A court:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(i)</num>
                <text>Made the finding; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <text>Decision became final; or</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>The finding was:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(i)</num>
                <text>Made in a contested case under the Maryland Administrative Procedure Act; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <text>Not overturned on judicial review;</text>
              </para>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(14)</num>
            <text>Been found to have willfully or knowingly violated the Labor and Employment Article, Title 3, Subtitles 3, 4, or 5, or Title 5, Annotated Code of Maryland, if:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>A court:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(i)</num>
                <text>Made the finding; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <text>Decision became final; or</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>The finding was:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(i)</num>
                <text>Made in a contested case under the Maryland Administrative Procedure Act; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <text>Not overturned on judicial review; or</text>
              </para>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(15)</num>
            <text>Admitted in writing or under oath, during the course of an official investigation or other proceedings, acts or omissions that would constitute grounds for conviction or liability under any law or statute described in §§B and C and subsections D(1)—(14) of this regulation, except as follows (indicate reasons why the affirmations cannot be given, and list any conviction, plea, or imposition of probation before judgment with the date, court, official or administrative body, the sentence or disposition, the name(s) of the person(s) involved and their current positions and responsibilities with the business, and the status of any debarment):</text>
          </para>
          <aftertext>____________________________________________________________</aftertext>
          <aftertext>____________________________________________________________</aftertext>
          <aftertext>___________________________________________________________.</aftertext>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>E.</num>
          <text>AFFIRMATION REGARDING DEBARMENT</text>
          <text>I FURTHER AFFIRM THAT:</text>
          <text>Neither I, nor to the best of my knowledge, information, and belief, the above business, or any of its officers, directors, partners, controlling stockholders, or any of its employees directly involved in the business's contracting activities, including obtaining or performing contracts with public bodies, has ever been suspended or debarred (including being issued a limited denial of participation) by any public entity, except as follows (list each debarment or suspension providing the dates of the suspension or debarment, the name of the public entity and the status of the proceedings, the name(s) of the person(s) involved and their current positions and responsibilities with the business, the grounds of the debarment or suspension, and the details of each person's involvement in any activity that formed the grounds of the debarment or suspension).</text>
          <text>____________________________________________________________</text>
          <text>____________________________________________________________</text>
          <text>___________________________________________________________.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>F.</num>
          <text>AFFIRMATION REGARDING DEBARMENT OF RELATED ENTITIES</text>
          <text>I FURTHER AFFIRM THAT:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The business was not established and it does not operate in a manner designed to evade the application of or defeat the purpose of debarment pursuant to Sections 16-101, et seq., of the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf">State Finance and Procurement Article of the Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The business is not a successor, assignee, subsidiary, or affiliate of a suspended or debarred business, except as follows (you must indicate the reasons why the affirmations cannot be given without qualification):</text>
          </para>
          <aftertext>____________________________________________________________</aftertext>
          <aftertext>____________________________________________________________</aftertext>
          <aftertext>___________________________________________________________.</aftertext>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>G.</num>
          <text>SUB-CONTRACT AFFIRMATION</text>
          <text>I FURTHER AFFIRM THAT:</text>
          <text>Neither I, nor to the best of my knowledge, information, and belief, the above business, has knowingly entered into a contract with a public body under which a person debarred or suspended under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf">Title 16 of the State Finance and Procurement Article of the Annotated Code of Maryland</cite> will provide, directly or indirectly, supplies, services, architectural services, construction related services, leases of real property, or construction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>H.</num>
          <text>AFFIRMATION REGARDING COLLUSION</text>
          <text>I FURTHER AFFIRM THAT:</text>
          <text>Neither I, nor to the best of my knowledge, information, and belief, the above business has:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Agreed, conspired, connived, or colluded to produce a deceptive show of competition in the compilation of the accompanying bid or offer that is being submitted;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>In any manner, directly or indirectly, entered into any agreement of any kind to fix the bid price or price proposal of the bidder or offeror or of any competitor, or otherwise taken any action in restraint of free competitive bidding in connection with the contract for which the accompanying bid or offer is submitted.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>I.</num>
          <text>CERTIFICATION OF TAX PAYMENT</text>
          <text>I FURTHER AFFIRM THAT: Except as validly contested, the business has paid, or has arranged for payment of, all taxes due the State of Maryland and has filed all required returns and reports with the Comptroller of the Treasury, the State Department of Assessments and Taxation, and the Maryland Department of Labor, as applicable, and will have paid all withholding taxes due the State of Maryland prior to final settlement.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>J.</num>
          <text>CONTINGENT FEES</text>
          <text>I FURTHER AFFIRM THAT:</text>
          <text>The business has not employed or retained any person, partnership, corporation, or other entity, other than a bona fide employee, bona fide agent, bona fide salesperson, or commercial selling agency working for the business, to solicit or secure the Contract, and that the business has not paid or agreed to pay any person, partnership, corporation, or other entity, other than a bona fide employee, bona fide agent, bona fide salesperson, or commercial selling agency, any fee or any other consideration contingent on the making of the Contract.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>K.</num>
          <text>CERTIFICATION REGARDING INVESTMENTS IN IRAN</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The undersigned certifies that, in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|17-705">State Finance and Procurement Article, §17-705, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>It is not identified on the list created by the Board of Public Works as a person engaging in investment activities in Iran as described in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|17-702">State Finance and Procurement Article, §17-702, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>It is not engaging in investment activities in Iran as described in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|17-702">State Finance and Procurement Article, §17-702, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num proof="done">2.</num>
            <text>The undersigned is unable to make the above certification regarding its investment activities in Iran due to the following activities: ________________________________________________________</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>L.</num>
          <text>CONFLICT MINERALS ORIGINATED IN THE DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC OF CONGO (FOR SUPPLIES AND SERVICES CONTRACTS)</text>
          <text>I FURTHER AFFIRM THAT:</text>
          <text>The business has complied with the provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|14-413">State Finance and Procurement Article, §14-413, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite> governing proper disclosure of certain information regarding conflict minerals originating in the Democratic Republic of Congo or its neighboring countries as required by federal law.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>M.</num>
          <text>I FURTHER AFFIRM THAT:</text>
          <text>Any claims of environmental attributes made relating to a product or service included in the bid or proposal are consistent with the Federal Trade Commission’s Guides for the Use of Environmental Marketing Claims as provided in 16 CFR §260, that apply to claims about the environmental attributes of a product, package, or service in connection with the marketing, offering for sale, or sale of such item or service.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>N.</num>
          <text>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</text>
          <text>I ACKNOWLEDGE THAT this Affidavit is to be furnished to the Procurement Officer and may be distributed to units of: (1) the State of Maryland; (2) counties or other subdivisions of the State of Maryland; (3) other states; and (4) the federal government. I further acknowledge that this Affidavit is subject to applicable laws of the United States and the State of Maryland, both criminal and civil, and that nothing in this Affidavit or any contract resulting from the submission of this bid or proposal shall be construed to supersede, amend, modify or waive, on behalf of the State of Maryland, or any unit of the State of Maryland having jurisdiction, the exercise of any statutory right or remedy conferred by the Constitution and the laws of Maryland with respect to any misrepresentation made or any violation of the obligations, terms and covenants undertaken by the above business with respect to (1) this Affidavit, (2) the contract, and (3) other Affidavits comprising part of the contract.</text>
          <text>I DO SOLEMNLY DECLARE AND AFFIRM UNDER THE PENALTIES OF PERJURY THAT THE CONTENTS OF THIS AFFIDAVIT ARE TRUE AND CORRECT TO THE BEST OF MY KNOWLEDGE, INFORMATION, AND BELIEF.</text>
          <text>Date: ______________</text>
          <text>By: ________________________________ (print name of Authorized Representative and Affiant)</text>
          <text>_________________________________ (signature of Authorized Representative and Affiant)</text>
        </para>
      </include>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="21|05|08|.08">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Conflict of Interest.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definitions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In this regulation, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Terms Defined.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Conflict of interest" means that, because of other activities or relationships with other persons:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A person is unable or potentially unable to render impartial assistance or advice to the State;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The person's objectivity in performing the contract work is or might be otherwise impaired; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A person has an unfair competitive advantage.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Person.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>"Person" has the meaning stated in <cite path="21.01.02.01|B.|(64)">COMAR 21.01.02.01B(64)</cite>.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>"Person" includes a bidder, offeror, contractor, consultant, or subcontractor or subconsultant at any tier, and also includes an employee or agent or any of them if the employee or agent has or will have the authority to control or supervise all or a portion of the work for which a bid or offer is made.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A solicitation that will result in the selection of a contractor who will assist a unit in the formation, evaluation, selection, award, or execution of a State contract shall provide notice of the requirements of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|13-212">State Finance and Procurement Article, §13-212</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland, and this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the procurement officer makes a determination before award that facts or circumstances exist giving rise or which could in the future give rise to a conflict of interest, the procurement officer may reject a bid or offer under <cite path="21.06.02.03|B.">COMAR 21.06.02.03B</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Termination.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>After award, the State may terminate the contract, in whole or in part, if it considers termination necessary to avoid an actual or potential conflict of interest.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the contractor knew or reasonably could have been expected to know of an actual or potential conflict of interest before or after award and did not disclose it or misrepresented relevant information to the procurement officer, the State may terminate the contract for default, institute proceedings to debar the contractor from further State contracts, or pursue other remedies as may be permitted by law or the contract.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A conflict of interest may be waived if the procurement officer, with approval of the agency head, determines that waiver is in the best interest of the State. The determination shall state the reasons for the waiver and any controls that avoid, mitigate, or neutralize the conflict of interest.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A bidder or offeror responding to a solicitation that will result in the selection of a contractor who will assist a unit in the formation, evaluation, selection, award, or execution of another State contract shall provide the affidavit and disclosures set forth in <cite path="21|05|08|.08|G.">§G of this regulation</cite> to the procurement officer with the bid or offer and at other times as may be required by the procurement officer.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The affidavits and disclosures required by <cite path="21|05|08|.08|F.">§F of this regulation</cite> shall be in substantially the same form as follows:</text>
      <include>
        <text>CONFLICT OF INTEREST AFFIDAVIT AND DISCLOSURE</text>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>"Conflict of interest" means that because of other activities or relationships with other persons, a person is unable or potentially unable to render impartial assistance or advice to the State, or the person's objectivity in performing the contract work is or might be otherwise impaired, or a person has an unfair competitive advantage.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>"Person" has the meaning stated in <cite path="21.01.02.01|B.|(64)">COMAR 21.01.02.01B(64)</cite> and includes a bidder, offeror, contractor, consultant, or subcontractor or subconsultant at any tier, and also includes an employee or agent of any of them if the employee or agent has or will have the authority to control or supervise all or a portion of the work for which a bid or offer is made.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>The bidder or offeror warrants that, except as disclosed in §D, below, there are no relevant facts or circumstances now giving rise or which could, in the future, give rise to a conflict of interest.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>D.</num>
          <text>The following facts or circumstances give rise or could in the future give rise to a conflict of interest (explain detail—attach additional sheets if necessary):</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>E.</num>
          <text>The bidder or offeror agrees that if an actual or potential conflict of interest arises after the date of this affidavit, the bidder or offeror shall immediately make a full disclosure in writing to the procurement officer of all relevant facts and circumstances. This disclosure shall include a description of actions which the bidder or offeror has taken and proposes to take to avoid, mitigate, or neutralize the actual or potential conflict of interest. If the contract has been awarded and performance of the contract has begun, the contractor shall continue performance until notified by the procurement officer of any contrary action to be taken.</text>
          <text>I DO SOLEMNLY DECLARE AND AFFIRM UNDER THE PENALTIES OF PERJURY THAT THE CONTENTS OF THIS AFFIDAVIT ARE TRUE AND CORRECT TO THE BEST OF MY KNOWLEDGE, INFORMATION, AND BELIEF.</text>
          <text>Date:____________________By:______________________________________</text>
          <text>(Authorized Representative and Affiant)</text>
        </para>
      </include>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Mercury Content.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Mercury Content. If required under <cite path="|21.11.07">COMAR 21.11.07</cite>, a price preference not exceeding 5 percent shall be applied in the evaluation of bids or proposals in favor of products that are mercury free or if stated elsewhere in the solicitation, to products containing the least amount of mercury. The following mercury affidavit shall be completed and returned with the bid or proposal.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Mercury Affidavit.</text>
      <include>
        <text>MERCURY AFFIDAVIT</text>
        <text>AUTHORIZED REPRESENTATIVE</text>
        <text>THEREBY AFFIRM THAT:</text>
        <text>I am the  _________________ (Title) and the duly authorized representative of _______________________ (Business). I possess the legal authority to make this affidavit on behalf of myself and the business for which I am acting.</text>
        <text>MERCURY CONTENT INFORMATION:</text>
        <text>[ ]  The product(s) offered do not contain mercury.</text>
        <text>OR</text>
        <text>[ ]  The product(s) offered do contain mercury.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Describe the product or product component that contains mercury.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Provide the amount of mercury that is contained in the product or product component. Indicate the unit of measure being used.</text>
        </para>
        <aftertext>I ACKNOWLEDGE THAT this affidavit is to be furnished to the procurement officer and may be distributed to units of(1) the State of Maryland; (2) counties or other subdivisions of the State of Maryland; (3) other states; and (4) the federal government. I further acknowledge that this Affidavit is subject to applicable laws of the United States and the State of Maryland, both criminal and civil, and that nothing in this affidavit or any contract resulting from the submission of this bid or proposal shall be construed to supersede, amend, modify, or waive, on behalf of the State of Maryland, or any unit of the State of Maryland having jurisdiction, the exercise of any statutory right or remedy conferred by the Constitution and the laws of Maryland with respect to any misrepresentation made or any violation of the obligations, terms and covenants undertaken by the above business with respect to(1) this affidavit, (2) the contract, and (3) other affidavits comprising part of the contract.</aftertext>
        <aftertext>I DO SOLEMNLY DECLARE AND AFFIRM UNDER THE PENALTIES OF PERJURY THAT THE CONTENTS OF THIS AFFIDAVIT ARE TRUE AND CORRECT TO THE BEST OF MY KNOWLEDGE, INFORMATION, AND BELIEF.</aftertext>
        <aftertext>________________     By ___________________________</aftertext>
        <aftertext>Date				Signature</aftertext>
        <aftertext>Print Name: ____________________________________</aftertext>
        <aftertext>Authorized Representative and Affiant</aftertext>
      </include>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Janitorial Services.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A bid or proposal submitted in response to a solicitation for janitorial services shall include at a minimum:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Labor costs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Cost of cleaning supplies; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Projected labor hours to satisfactorily complete the work.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This regulation does not apply to procurements governed by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf">State Finance and Procurement Article, Title 14, Subtitle 1, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">: Election Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|14-101">14-101</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|14-108">14-108</cite>; State Finance and Procurement Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|3-412">3-412</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|3">3</cite>.5-311, 11-206, 12-101, 13-207, 13-218, 13-221, 14-303, 14-308, 14-406, 16-102, 16-202, 16-203, 17-401—17-402, and Title 19; Annotated Code of Maryland; Ch. 293, Acts of 2009</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1981-07-01">Effective date: July 1, 1981 (8:13 Md. R. II-5)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1982-07-05"><cite path="|21|05|08|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective March 17, 1982 (9:6 Md. R. 612); emergency status expired June 30, 1982; adopted permanently effective July 5, 1982 (9:13 Md. R. 1354)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-05-06">Regulations .05A and B amended effective May 6, 1985 (12:9 Md. R. 816)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1984-06-04">Regulations .06 and .07 adopted effective June 4, 1984 (11:11 Md. R. 963)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-01-09" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|21|05|08|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|21|05|08|.07">.07</cite> repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|21|05|08|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|21|05|08|.07">.07</cite> adopted effective January 9, 1989 (15:27 Md. R. 3138)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1996-05-20"><cite path="|21|05|08|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended and C adopted effective May 20, 1996 (23:10 Md. R. 733)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-01-02"><cite path="|21|05|08|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective March 18, 2002 (29:5 Md. R. 505); January 2, 2017 (43:26 Md. R. 1449)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-08-02"><cite path="|21|05|08|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective August 2, 1993 (20:15 Md. R. 1221)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-11-20"><cite path="|21|05|08|.05">Regulation .05</cite> repealed effective November 20, 1994 (21:23 Md. R. 1936)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-03-08"><cite path="|21|05|08|.05">Regulation .05</cite> adopted effective March 8, 1999 (26:5 Md. R. 393)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-04-29"><cite path="|21|05|08|.05|A.">Regulation .05A</cite>, B amended September 18, 2023 (50:18 Md. R. 800); April 29, 2024 (51:8 Md. R. 369)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-03-16"><cite path="|21|05|08|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective March 16, 2015 (42:5 Md. R. 488)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-03-03"><cite path="|21|05|08|.07|B.">Regulation .07B</cite> amended effective October 1, 1990 (17:19 Md. R. 2322); August 2, 1993 (20:15 Md. R. 1221); November 20, 1994 (21:23 Md. R. 1936); January 26, 1998 (25:2 Md. R. 79); November 7, 2005 (32:22 Md. R. 1759); March 12, 2007 (34:5 Md. R. 562); April 7, 2008 (35:7 Md. R. 751); May 31, 2010 (37:11 Md. R. 766); August 8, 2011 (38:16 Md. R. 946); July 23, 2012 (39:14 Md. R. 839); May 13, 2013 (40:9 Md. R. 789); January 2, 2017 (43:26 Md. R. 1449); March 3, 2025 (52:4 Md. R. 221)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1997-10-16"><cite path="|21|05|08|.08">Regulation .08</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective August 8, 1997 (24:18 Md. R. 1294); emergency status rescinded effective October 16, 1997 (24:23 Md. R. 1608)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-07-09"><cite path="|21|05|08|.08">Regulation .08</cite> adopted effective July 9, 2001 (28:13 Md. R. 1216)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-01-02"><cite path="|21|05|08|.08|B.">Regulation .08B</cite> amended effective January 2, 2017 (43:26 Md. R. 1449)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-04-07"><cite path="|21|05|08|.08|B.">Regulation .08B</cite>, E amended effective April 7, 2008 (35:7 Md. R. 751)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-05-26"><cite path="|21|05|08|.09">Regulation .09</cite> adopted effective May 26, 2003 (30:10 Md. R. 668)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-03-05"><cite path="|21|05|08|.10">Regulation .10</cite> adopted effective March 5, 2012 (39:4 Md. R. 338)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
