<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>11</num>
  <heading>Design-Build</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Design build" means a project delivery method in which a single entity is contractually responsible for both design and construction of a project.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Design professional" means an architect or professional engineer who is licensed to conduct business in the State of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Determination on Use of the Design-Build Method.</heading>
    <text>Before the solicitation is issued, the procurement officer shall prepare a written determination justifying the use of the design-build method which addresses some or all of the following criteria:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The extent to which the unit can adequately define the project requirements;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Time constraints for delivery of the project;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Capability and experience of prospective contractors with the design-build method or similar experience;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Suitability of the project for use of the design-build method of project delivery with respect to time, schedule, costs, and quality factors; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Capability of the agency to manage the project.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Licensing Requirements.</heading>
    <text>Each design-builder shall employ or have as a partner, member, officer, joint venture partner, or subcontractor at least one design professional duly licensed and registered to do business in the State.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Selection of the Design-Builder.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Selection of a design-builder shall be conducted using the multi-step sealed bid procurement method as provided in <cite path="21.05.02.17">COMAR 21.05.02.17</cite> or the competitive sealed proposals procurement method as provided in <cite path="|21.05.03">COMAR 21.05.03</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The invitation for bids or request for proposals shall contain at a minimum:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The minimum qualifications of the design-builder;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Requirements for construction and design experience and experience in other design-build projects provided the requirements do not unduly restrict competition;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The scope of work; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Responsibilities of the State and design-builder particularly in the areas of design defects and warranties.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">State Finance and Procurement Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|12-101">12-101</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|13-103">13-103</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|13-104">13-104</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-08-23">Effective date: August 23, 2010 (37:17 Md. R. 1186)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
