<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>Definitions; General Provisions</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this subtitle, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Act” means the Maryland Public Information Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp">General Provisions Article, Title 4, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Applicant” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-101">General Provisions Article, §4-101(b), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Board” means the State Public Information Act Compliance Board, as described in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-1">General Provisions Article, §4-1</cite>A-02, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Custodian” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-101">General Provisions Article, §4-101(d), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Designated representative” means an attorney, an employee organization representative, or any other individual authorized in writing by a party to represent the party.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Dispute” has the meaning stated in <cite path="14.37.01.01|B.">COMAR 14.37.01.01B</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Exemption” has the meaning stated in <cite path="14.37.01.01|B.">COMAR 14.37.01.01B</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Final Determination” means the written document issued by the Public Access Ombudsman pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-1">General Provisions Article, §4-1</cite>B-04(b), Annotated Code of Maryland, stating that a specific dispute has been resolved or partially resolved or not been resolved.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“Inmate” means an individual who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is confined in a correctional or other detention facility pursuant to a court order in a criminal or juvenile delinquency case; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has no direct access to the U.S. Postal Service or the ability to submit a complaint or other information electronically.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>“Official custodian” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-101">General Provisions Article, §4-101(f), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>“Ombudsman” means the Public Access Ombudsman, as described in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-1">General Provisions, §4-1</cite>B-03, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>“Public record” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-101">General Provisions Article, §4-101(k), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>“Sociological information” means any of the following information concerning a person that may be contained in a record of the Board:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Social security number;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Personal address;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Personal phone number;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Personal email address; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Date of birth.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>“Unreasonable fee” means a fee that does not bear a reasonable relationship to the recovery of actual costs incurred by a governmental unit responding to a request for a public record.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Jurisdiction.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Subject to the procedure outlined in <cite path="|14.02.02">COMAR 14.02.02</cite>, the Board shall review and resolve complaints from an applicant or the applicant’s designated representative alleging that a custodian:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Denied inspection of a public record in violation of the Act;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Charged an unreasonable fee or charged an unreasonable estimated fee of more than $350 under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-206">General Provisions Article, §4-206, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Failed to respond to a request for a public record within the time limits established under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-203">General Provisions Article, §4-203(a) </cite>or (d), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Subject to the procedure outlined in <cite path="|14.02.03">COMAR 14.02.03</cite>, the Board shall review and resolve complaints from a custodian alleging that an applicant’s request or pattern of requests is frivolous, vexatious, or in bad faith.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Recusal of Board Members.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Standard for Recusal.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A Board member shall recuse himself or herself from Board proceedings that involve circumstances in which the Board member:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Has a conflict of interest; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Cannot participate fairly and impartially.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Personal familiarity with an applicant or custodian does not, of itself, require recusal of a Board member.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board member who is recused from a matter before the Board may not:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Participate in the Board’s discussion or decision on the matter; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Discuss the matter or the Board’s review of the matter with members of the Board, the parties, or staff or counsel to the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Board shall document the recusal of the Board member from a matter in its written decision on the matter.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Consolidation of Complaints.</heading>
    <text>In its discretion, the Board may consolidate complaints filed under <cite path="|14.02.02">COMAR 14.02.02</cite> and <cite path="|14.02.03">COMAR 14.02.03</cite> if both complaints involve the same applicant and same custodian, and if consolidation will promote efficient and fair resolution of the complaints.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Computation of Time.</heading>
    <text>Computation of a period of time shall be governed by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|1-302">General Provisions Article, §1-302, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="14|02|01|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Date of Receipt.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A complaint, response, or reply to a response is deemed received on the date that it is postmarked or sent by email to the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Inmate Applicants.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A complaint, response, or reply to a response is deemed received on the date that the complaint, response, or reply to a response, in mailable form and with proper postage affixed is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Deposited by the inmate applicant into a receptacle designated by the facility for outgoing mail; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Personally delivered to an employee of the facility authorized by the facility to collect such mail.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A date stamp affixed pursuant to <cite path="12.02.20.04|A.">COMAR 12.02.20.04A</cite> or <cite path="12.12.20.04|A.">COMAR 12.12.20.04A</cite>, or a similar date stamp affixed by a county detention center or other detention facility not within the control of the Division of Correction, is evidence of the date on which an inmate applicant sent a complaint, response, or reply to a response under <cite path="14|02|01|.06|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="14|02|01|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Record.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board shall maintain a record of each matter, including an index.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board’s internal record of a matter shall consist of the following, if filed in a matter:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The complaint;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The response to a complaint;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The reply to the response;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Written notices;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Written requests for information;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Records or additional information received by the Board pursuant to <cite path="14.02.05.03">COMAR 14.02.05.03</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The recording of an informal conference; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The Board’s written decision.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The public record of a matter shall consist of the records listed in <cite path="14|02|01|.07|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, if filed, except that records or additional information received by the Board pursuant to <cite path="14.02.05.03">COMAR 14.02.05.03</cite> may not be included.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-1">General Provisions Article, §4-1</cite>A-04, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-06-13">Effective date: June 13, 2022 (49:12 Md. R. 641)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
