<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Complaint Process — Applicants</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Filing a Complaint.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant or the applicant’s designated representative may file a complaint with the Board within 30 days after receiving a Final Determination from the Ombudsman that a specific dispute has not been resolved.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The complaint shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Pertain only to the dispute described in the Final Determination;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Be submitted in writing; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Be signed by the applicant.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The substance of the complaint shall, at minimum:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Identify the custodian that is the subject of the complaint; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Describe the action of the custodian, the date of the action, and the circumstances of the action.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A complaint may be filed by email or regular mail.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Documents Attached to Complaint.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If available, an applicant shall attach to the complaint:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A copy of the original request for a public record;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A copy of the custodian’s response; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Ombudsman’s Final Determination.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An applicant may attach to the complaint additional documents relevant to the dispute, including correspondence between the applicant and the custodian.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="14|02|02|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Response to Complaint.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Upon receipt of a complaint, the Board shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Promptly send the complaint to the custodian identified in the complaint; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Request that the custodian send a response to the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A custodian shall file a written response to a complaint within 30 days after receiving the complaint and request for a response from the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Complaints Alleging that a Custodian Denied Inspection of a Public Record in Violation of the Act.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a complaint alleges that a custodian denied inspection of a public record in violation of the Act, the custodian’s response shall, to the extent relevant to the dispute:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Explain why denial was necessary;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Explain why redacting information would not address the reasons for denial;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Provide the legal authority for the denial; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Without disclosing protected information or creating a descriptive index, provide a brief description of the undisclosed records that allows the Board to assess the applicability of the legal authority for the denial.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the custodian’s response to the applicant’s request for public records contains all of the information required by <cite path="14|02|02|.03|C.|(1)">§C(1) of this regulation</cite>, then it is sufficient for the custodian to attach the response.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If a complaint alleges that a custodian charged an unreasonable fee or charged an unreasonable estimated fee of more than $350 under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-206">General Provisions Article, §4-206, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the response shall, to the extent relevant to the dispute, include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The hourly salary rates for the staff who responded or who are likely to respond to the applicant’s request for a public record;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The number of hours expended by each staff, or the number of hours the custodian anticipates will be expended by each staff, to respond to the applicant’s request for a public record;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A description of the tasks each staff performed or is likely to perform to respond to the applicant’s request for public records; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>An explanation of how fees for reproduction of the records are calculated.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If a complaint alleges that a custodian failed to respond to a request for a public record within the time limits established by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-203">General Provisions Article, §4-203(a) </cite>or (d), Annotated Code of Maryland, the response shall, to the extent relevant to the dispute:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provide the date and nature of correspondence with the applicant, if any;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Describe the circumstances that prevented the custodian from responding in a timely manner; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Explain how the custodian intends to respond to the applicant’s request for public records.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A custodian may not attach to its response records that it claims are confidential, privileged, or otherwise exempt from disclosure.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A custodian shall send a copy of the response to the applicant.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Reply to Response.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board may, in its discretion, permit the applicant to file a reply to the custodian’s response.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If permitted to file a reply, the applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>File the reply within 15 days after receiving the custodian’s response; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Send a copy of the reply to the custodian.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Effect of Failure to Respond.</heading>
    <text>If a written response from a custodian is not received within 30 days after the Board notifies the custodian of the complaint and requests a response and the Board has not requested any additional information, the Board shall decide the case on the facts before it.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="14|02|02|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Transfer of Information from Ombudsman.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Ombudsman may transfer basic information about a dispute to the Board, including:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The identity of the applicant and custodian;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A brief summary of the nature of the dispute; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A copy of the Final Determination relevant to the complaint.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Confidential Communications or Information.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Ombudsman may not disclose to the Board any confidential mediation communications or mediation information, defined in <cite path="14.37.01.01|B.|(8)">COMAR 14.37.01.01B(8)</cite> and (10), that are made or received in the course of attempting to resolve a dispute.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Ombudsman may disclose confidential communications or information referenced in <cite path="14|02|02|.06|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite> if all parties have consented to the disclosure in writing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Withdrawal of Complaint.</heading>
    <text>An applicant may withdraw a complaint at any time until the Board’s decision is issued.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Dismissal of Complaint.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board shall dismiss a complaint if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board lacks jurisdiction to review the complaint;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The complaint is filed more than 30 days after the applicant received the Ombudsman’s Final Determination; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The complaint is not signed by the applicant.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the Board dismisses a complaint because it is not signed by the applicant, the applicant may refile a signed complaint within the same 30 days of receiving the Final Determination from the Ombudsman.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Effect of Filing.</heading>
    <text>A complaint, the custodian’s response to a complaint, and a reply to the custodian’s response are public records of the Board subject to inspection under the Act.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">General Provisions Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-1">4-1</cite>A-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|04">04</cite>(a) and (c), 4-1A-05, and 4-1A-06, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-06-13">Effective date: June 13, 2022 (49:12 Md. R. 641)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
