<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Complaint Process — Custodians</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Filing a Complaint.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A custodian may file a complaint with the Board within 30 days after receiving a Final Determination from the Ombudsman that a dispute has not been resolved.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The complaint shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Pertain only to the dispute described in the Final Determination;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Be submitted in writing; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Be signed by the custodian.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The substance of the complaint shall, at minimum:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Identify the applicant that is the subject of the complaint;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Describe the action of the applicant, the date of the action, and the circumstance of the action, including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The number and scope of the applicant’s past requests, if any;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The custodian’s responses to past requests, if any; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Efforts to cooperate with the applicant; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Explain why, in the custodian’s opinion, the applicant’s request or pattern of requests is frivolous, vexatious, or in bad faith.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A complaint may be filed by email or regular mail.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Documents Attached to Complaint.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If available, a custodian shall attach to the complaint:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A copy of the original request for a public record;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A copy of the custodian’s response; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Ombudsman’s Final Determination.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A custodian may attach to the complaint additional documents relevant to the dispute, including correspondence between the applicant and the custodian.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Response to Complaint.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Upon receipt of a complaint, the Board shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Promptly send the complaint to the applicant identified in the complaint; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Request that the applicant send a response to the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An applicant shall file a written response to a complaint within 30 days after receiving the complaint and request for a response from the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An applicant shall send a copy of the response to the custodian.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Reply to Response.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board may, in its discretion, permit the custodian to file a reply to the applicant’s response.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If permitted to file a reply, the custodian shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>File the reply within 15 days after receiving the applicant’s response; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Send a copy of the reply to the applicant.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Effect of Failure to Respond.</heading>
    <text>If a written response from an applicant is not received within 30 days after the Board notifies the applicant of the complaint and requests a response and the Board has not requested any additional information, the Board shall decide the case on the facts before it.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="14|02|03|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Transfer of Information from Ombudsman.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Ombudsman may transfer basic information about a dispute to the Board, including:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The identity of the applicant and custodian;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A brief summary of the nature of the dispute; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A copy of the Final Determination relevant to the complaint.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Confidential Communications or Information.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Ombudsman may not disclose to the Board any confidential communications or information, defined in <cite path="14.37.01.01|B.|(8)">COMAR 14.37.01.01B(8)</cite> and (10), that are made or received in the course of attempting to resolve a dispute.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Ombudsman may disclose confidential communications or information referenced in <cite path="14|02|03|.06|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite> if all parties have consented to the disclosure in writing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Withdrawal of Complaint.</heading>
    <text>A custodian may withdraw a complaint at any time until the Board’s decision is issued.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Dismissal of Complaint.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board shall dismiss a complaint if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board lacks jurisdiction to review the complaint;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The complaint is filed more than 30 days after the custodian received the Ombudsman’s Final Determination; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The complaint is not signed by the custodian.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the Board dismisses a complaint because it is not signed by the custodian, the custodian may refile a signed complaint within the same 30 days of receiving the Final Determination from the Ombudsman.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Effect of Filing.</heading>
    <text>A complaint, the applicant’s response to a complaint, and a reply to the applicant’s response are public records of the Board subject to inspection under the Act.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">General Provisions Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-1">4-1</cite>A-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|04">04</cite>(b) and (c), 4-1A-05, and 4-1A-06, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-06-13">Effective date: June 13, 2022 (49:12 Md. R. 641)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
