<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Request for Records or Additional Information</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Form of Request.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board may send a request for additional information by email or regular mail.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board shall send a copy of a request for additional information to all parties.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Board may direct the party providing the additional information to send a copy of the additional information provided in response to the Board’s request to the other party.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Request for Custodian’s Response to Request for Public Record.</heading>
    <text>If a complaint alleges that a custodian failed to respond to a request for a public record within the time limits established under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-203">General Provisions Article, §4-203(a) </cite>or (d), Annotated Code of Maryland, the Board may request the response to the request for a public record.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="14|02|05|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Requests Related to Public Records.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If a complaint alleges that a custodian denied inspection of a public record in violation of the Act, the Board may request that the custodian provide, as appropriate in the Board’s discretion:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A copy of the public record for in camera inspection, unless the custodian’s response to the request for a public record indicated that inspection was denied under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-301">General Provisions Article, §4-301(a)(2)(ii), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A descriptive index of the public record; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A written reason why the record cannot be disclosed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board shall maintain the confidentiality of records or information provided under <cite path="14|02|05|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Request for Basis for Fee Charged.</heading>
    <text>If a complaint alleges that a custodian charged an unreasonable fee or estimated fee under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-206">General Provisions Article, §4-206, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the Board may request that the custodian provide more information about the basis for the fee or estimated fee charged.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Frivolous, Vexatious, or Bad Faith Requests.</heading>
    <text>If necessary to resolve the complaint, the Board may request more information related to an alleged frivolous, vexatious, or bad faith request, including information about the applicant’s pattern or history of requests.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Request for Affidavit or Statement.</heading>
    <text>The Board may request that a custodian or applicant provide an affidavit, in the form provided by Maryland Rule 1-304, or a statement containing the facts that are at issue in the complaint.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Timing.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board shall request additional records or information, if needed, as soon as practicably possible.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A custodian or applicant shall send to the Board the additional records or information requested as soon as practicably possible after receipt of the Board’s request, but no later than 30 days after receipt of the request.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">General Provisions Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-1">4-1</cite>A-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|04">04</cite>(c) and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-1">4-1</cite>A-06(b), Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-06-13">Effective date: June 13, 2022 (49:12 Md. R. 641)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
