<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>18</num>
  <heading>Comprehensive Rehabilitation Facilities</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following words have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Commission on Accreditation of Rehabilitation Facilities" means the private, nonprofit organization formed in 1966 which has established standards of quality for rehabilitation services, and which accredits those who provide the services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Comprehensive physical rehabilitation services" has the meaning stated in Health-General Article, §19-1201(b), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Comprehensive rehabilitation facility" means any person who provides or holds itself out as providing comprehensive physical rehabilitation services on an out-patient basis.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Specialized rehabilitation program" has the meaning stated in Health-General Article, §19-1201(e), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter does not apply to a home health agency or special rehabilitation hospital.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Compliance Required.</heading>
    <text>A comprehensive rehabilitation facility shall comply with the requirements of this chapter before the facility may provide:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Comprehensive rehabilitation services; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A specialized rehabilitation program.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>License Provisions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A comprehensive rehabilitation facility license is required before a person may provide or hold itself out as providing comprehensive physical rehabilitation services in the State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>To obtain a comprehensive rehabilitation facility license, a person shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Submit an application on the written or electronic form provided by the Secretary;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Pay to the Secretary an application fee of $10; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Meet any requirement imposed under Health-General Article, Title 19, Subtitle 1, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Applications on behalf of a corporation, association, or governmental unit or agency shall be made by two officers of the corporation, or governmental unit or agency, and names of their Board members shall be submitted. Ownership of property, real estate, and equipment shall be disclosed if it is other than the licensee's. The names of persons holding 2 percent or more of the stock or assets shall be disclosed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A comprehensive rehabilitation license expires on the first anniversary of its effective date, unless it is renewed for a 1-year term.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An application for the renewal of the license shall be made on the written or electronic form provided by the Secretary at least 60 days before expiration of the issued license.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Separate licenses are required for institutions maintained on separate premises, even though both institutions are operated under the same management.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Standards of Operation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A comprehensive rehabilitation facility:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall be accredited by the Commission on Accreditation of Rehabilitation Facilities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>May provide only those specialized rehabilitation programs that the facility has been accredited to provide by the Commission on Accreditation of Rehabilitation Facilities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Shall meet the standards provided by the Commission on Accreditation of Rehabilitation Facilities as set forth in the 2002 Medical Rehabilitation Standards Manual (Commission on Accreditation of Rehabilitation Facilities, 4891 East Grant Road, Tucson, AZ 85712) which is incorporated by reference;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Shall meet any other requirements that may be imposed by law.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Waiver of Accreditation.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To allow a comprehensive rehabilitation facility to achieve accreditation by the Commission on Accreditation of Rehabilitation Facilities as required under this regulation, the accreditation requirement shall be waived for any comprehensive rehabilitation facility that has submitted an appropriate application for accreditation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The waiver under this section shall be effective for not more than 2 years from the later of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>July 1, 1986; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The date on which the facility begins operations.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Secretary may inspect a comprehensive rehabilitation facility to assure that the facility meets the requirements of this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Records and Reports — Inspection.</heading>
    <text>Licensees shall keep such records and make reports in the manner and form as the Secretary shall prescribe, and all these records shall be open to inspection by the Secretary.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Enforcement.</heading>
    <text>The Secretary may enforce the provisions of this chapter by any method available at law, including any civil action or criminal prosecution. Civil actions include, but are not limited to, license revocations.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health-General Article, §19-1201 et seq., Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-12-01">Regulations <cite path="|10|07|18|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|07|18|.07">.07</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective July 1, 1986 (13:15 Md. R. 1727); adopted permanently December 1, 1986 (13:24 Md. R. 2558)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-03-13"><cite path="|10|07|18|.04|B.">Regulation .04B</cite>, E amended effective March 13, 2017 (44:5 Md. R. 292)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-09-16"><cite path="|10|07|18|.05|A.">Regulation .05A</cite> amended effective June 24, 1991 (18:12 Md. R. 1339); September 16, 2002 (29:18 Md. R. 1443)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
