<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>04</num>
  <heading>Proficiency Testing</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Proficiency Testing — General.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Proficiency Testing. Each year a licensee shall participate in an external proficiency testing program for each forensic science discipline in which the laboratory performs forensic tests and examinations, including but not limited to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Firearms and toolmarks;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Questioned documents;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Latent prints;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Trace evidence;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Biology;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Controlled dangerous substances; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Toxicology.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Proficiency Testing Performance and Participation Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Annually, a forensic analyst shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Participate in a proficiency test for each discipline for which the forensic analyst is qualified to perform tests or examinations for casework; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Perform the proficiency testing analysis using the same methods and procedures routinely used for performing the forensic analysis of casework.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For each subdiscipline for which a forensic analyst performs casework, the forensic analyst shall perform proficiency testing at least once in the 3-year license period or if applicable within the required time period outlined by the accreditation organization.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Proficiency Testing Performance, Participation Schedule, and Documentation. The quality assurance manager or technical leader, as designated by the director, shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Establish a formal, written proficiency testing protocol covering both external and internal proficiency tests for each forensic science discipline and subdiscipline in which the laboratory performs tests and examinations; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Document and maintain all records of proficiency testing and results for each individual forensic analyst required to participate in proficiency testing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Proficiency Testing — Forensic DNA Analysis.</heading>
    <text>Regardless of whether the individual provides results or conclusions, an individual who provides technical support for DNA analysis, performs DNA analysis, or is designated by the technical leader as a participant in DNA casework, shall meet the proficiency testing requirements set forth in 42 U.S.C. §14131, which is incorporated by reference.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Proficiency Testing Provider Approval.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Approval Required. A private, nonprofit, or commercial organization or government agency may not provide a proficiency test in this State for use by a forensic laboratory without first obtaining proficiency testing approval from the Department.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Approval Granted by the Secretary. The Department may approve a proficiency testing provider for a forensic science discipline or subdiscipline, if the proficiency testing provider:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provides reliable, documented evidence to the Department that the proficiency test is technically and administratively able to meet the applicable requirements of this chapter; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Submits directly to the Department evaluations of all proficiency test results from each laboratory that holds a Maryland forensic laboratory permit.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health-General Article, Title 17, Subtitle 2A, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-05-28">Effective date: May 28, 2012 (39:10 Md. R. 660)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
