<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>06</num>
  <heading>Safety Equipment</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Protective Eye Devices.</heading>
    <text>Regulations governing the use and care of protective eye devices in the public schools of Maryland shall include the following:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Career and Technology Education or Technology Education Laboratories, or Visual Arts Classrooms and Studios.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Protective Eye Devices for General Use. All students, teachers, and visitors upon entering and participating in career and technology education or technology education laboratories, or visual arts classrooms and studios in the public schools, where the activities enumerated in the law are in progress, shall be required to wear, for general use, protective eye devices meeting the specifications of the American National Standard: Practice for Occupational and Educational Eye and Face Protection, Z87.1-1979 and OSHA Safety and Health Standard 29 CFR §1910.133, both of which are incorporated by reference.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Protective Eye Devices for Special Areas Within a Laboratory or Visual Arts Classroom or Studio.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>These devices shall meet the standards and specifications of the American National Standard: Practice for Occupational and Educational Eye and Face Protection, Z87.1-1979.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Face Shields. A face shield shall be worn by an individual when participating in, or exposed to the immediate vicinity, where:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Hot molten metal or solder is being prepared, poured, or used in any form;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Heat treatment, tempering, kiln firing of any metal or other materials takes place.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Cup Goggles, Helmets, and Hand Shields.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Gas Welding Area. An individual participating in or observing gas welding operations shall wear cup goggles with appropriate filter lenses and clear cover glass for eye protection in this activity area.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Electric Arc Welding. An individual participating in or observing electric arc welding operations shall wear a welding helmet or hand shield equipped with the appropriate filter lenses and clear cover glass for this activity.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Welding Flash Protection. Gas and electric arc welding working stations shall be screened off adequately so as to protect nonwelding students, teachers, and visitors from welding flash.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Splash-Proof Vented Goggles or Face Shields. An individual using, exposed to, or observing the use of any caustic or explosive materials shall wear a splash-proof vented goggle or a face shield protective device.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Chemical or Combined Chemical-Physical Laboratories and Visual Arts Classrooms and Studios.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Protective eye devices shall be available in all courses in chemistry and biology, in all laboratory-centered general science courses, in physics and other physical science courses, and in ceramics, photography, and printmaking courses.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Protective Eye Devices for General Use.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A general purpose goggle of clear plastic frame and lens, sufficient to protect against splashing and spattering, as provided in the American National Standard: Practice for Occupational and Educational Eye and Face Protection, Z87.1-1979, shall be considered adequate for basic protection purposes.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A spectacle-type protective device or a general purpose goggle cited by the American Standards Association shall be available to protect visitors to the public schools' science and art department facilities.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Use of Protective Eye Devices.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Common Classroom, Studio, or Laboratory Activity. All students, teachers, and visitors shall wear protective eye devices when caustic or explosive chemicals or hot liquids or solids are:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Being used and manipulated by individuals within the classroom; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Being used by groups of individuals during a laboratory or studio activity.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Individual Project Activity. When less than the total class is engaged in activities involving caustic or explosive chemicals or hot liquids or solids, appropriate protective eye devices shall be worn by individuals:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Directly involved and all individuals adjacent to the immediate vicinity of the activity; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Working in preparation areas of the science laboratory.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Teacher or Student Demonstrations. Every effort should be made to afford adequate protection during demonstrations. All demonstrators shall be adequately protected with eye protective devices during these periods.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Protective Eye Devices for Visitors. Protective eye devices shall be made available to all visitors entering science laboratories or visual arts classrooms and studios identified above. Visitors shall be required to wear the protective devices when caustic or explosive chemicals or hot liquids or solids are actually in use.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Provision and Maintenance of Eye Protective Devices. The local board of education shall adopt such regulations as may be necessary for the provision and maintenance of eye protective devices as required to meet the provisions of the law.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|7-407">Education Article, §7-407, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1964-07-01">Effective date: July 1, 1964</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1980-02-22"><cite path="|13A|06|06|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective February 22, 1980 (7:4 Md. R. 351);</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-09-12">July 1, 1988 (15:7 Md. R. 851); September 12, 1994 (21:18 Md. R. 1511)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
