<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>09</num>
  <heading>Maryland Early Literacy Initiative</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>The Maryland Early Literacy Initiative is a grant program that will assist up to 50 qualifying schools in at least three school systems to implement an evidence-based literacy program in the school to work with participating students to meet literacy proficiency targets by the end of eighth grade.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Evidence-based early literacy program” means a program that satisfies §8101(21)(A)(i)(I) or §8101(21)(A)(i)(II) under Title 8, General Provisions of the Every Student Succeeds Act, and includes systematic, direct instruction in phonemic awareness, phonics, vocabulary development, fluency, and comprehension.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Initiative” means the Maryland Early Literacy Initiative.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Interventionist” means a trained professional whose primary responsibility is to deliver evidence-based early literacy intervention.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Nonprofit organization” means a nonprofit organization that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is based in the State;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is incorporated or registered under the laws of the State;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Is exempt from federal income tax under §501(c)(3), (4), or (6) of the Internal Revenue Code;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Is current in the payment of all tax obligations to the State or any unit or subdivision of the State; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Has been in active business for 3 years or more at the time the application is submitted or has a fiscal sponsor who can meet the requirements of this section.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Participating student” means a student:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In prekindergarten through eighth grade; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A student who performs below a certain score, as determined by the Department, on the assessment the Department uses to assess reading level.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Qualifying school” means a public school categorized by the local school system as a Title I school.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Program Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>For the 2018—19 school year through the 2021—22 school year, a qualifying school may apply to the Department to receive a grant to develop an evidence-based early literacy program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A qualifying school may apply for a grant only if the local superintendent endorses the school’s grant application.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A qualifying school may coordinate and partner with other qualifying schools in the county to apply jointly for a grant to develop a literacy program among the partnering qualifying schools.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A qualifying school may apply for and accept donations, grants, or other financial assistance from a governmental entity, a nonprofit organization, or any other private organization to benefit the literacy program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A local school board may apply on behalf of one or more qualifying schools in the local school system.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Grant Application.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An application shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Identify whether the qualifying school will work in collaboration with a nonprofit organization or the local board of education to implement the literacy program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide the name and qualifications of the nonprofit organization, if the qualifying school will work in collaboration with a nonprofit organization; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Include a description of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The literacy program to be implemented at the qualifying school;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The training that will be provided to the interventionist to provide the services in this section;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>How the literacy program will meet the grant requirements in this section; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Any other information required by the Department.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A literacy program developed under the Initiative shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provide early literacy intervention services for participating students;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Require participating students to receive direct services at least twice a week;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Have clear literacy targets at each grade level for participating students;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Have benchmark assessments multiple times a year to identify students who need one-on-one interventions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Collect data on student progress at least monthly;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Be implemented by staff hired and supervised by the collaborating nonprofit organization or the local board of education; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Use literacy programs that utilize various evidence-based approaches and methodologies for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Comparison purposes; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The collection of multiple data points for long-term review.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Grant Award.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>To the extent that funds are available, the Department shall distribute up to 50 grants in at least three school systems for a 2-year period.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In awarding grants under the Initiative, the Department will fund only those qualifying schools that use literacy programs that utilize various evidence-based approaches and methodologies for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Comparison purposes; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The collection of multiple data points for long-term review.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the number of applications exceeds the number of available grants, the Department shall give priority to a qualifying school serving a high concentration of students in prekindergarten through third grade who are living in poverty.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A grant made to each qualifying school may not exceed $75,000 each year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A grant made under this section shall be renewed by the Department after a 2-year period if the qualifying school presents evidence that the qualifying school is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In compliance with all grant requirements; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Meeting identified targets and benchmarks.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|2-205">2-205</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|5-216">5-216</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland;<br/>Ch. 361, Acts of 2018</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-12-31">Effective date: December 31, 2018 (45:26 Md. R. 1249)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
