<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>10</num>
  <heading>Purple Star Schools Program</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>The purpose of this action is to implement <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|7-129">Education Article, §7-129, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, which establishes a Purple Star Schools Program to recognize public schools that provide strong services and support for military-connected students and their families when, as a result of military service, a military-connected student transfers schools.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|06|10|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Department” means the Maryland State Department of Education.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Military-connected student” means a student who is a dependent of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A current member of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The United States military serving in the Army, Navy, Air Force, Space Force, Marine Corps, or Coast Guard on active duty;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration Commissioned Officer Corps;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The Public Health Service Commissioned Corps;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>The Maryland National Guard;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>The National Guard of any other State; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>A reserve force of the United States military; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A member of a military or reserve force described in <cite path="13A|06|10|.02|B.|(2)|(a)">§B(2)(a) of this regulation</cite> who was killed in the line of duty.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|06|10|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Criteria.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>To be eligible for designation as a Purple Star School, a public school shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Designate a staff member as a military liaison, whose duties include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Identifying military-connected students who are newly enrolled or soon to be enrolled at the school;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Serving as the point of contact between the school and the newly enrolled or soon to be enrolled military-connected students and their families;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Determining appropriate school services available to newly enrolled or soon to be enrolled military-connected students;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Assisting in coordinating school programs for newly enrolled or soon to be enrolled military-connected students;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Providing information, resources, and professional development to school staff on the needs of military-connected students and their families; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Generally aiding with a military-connected student’s transition to a new school;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Establish on the school’s website an easily accessible webpage that includes resources for military-connected students and their families, including information regarding:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Relocation to, enrollment at, registration at, and transferring records to the school;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Preparation for a move from a student’s current school to the school at which the student is newly enrolled or is soon to be enrolled;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Academic planning, course sequences, advanced classes, and graduation requirements;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Special education and related services; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Counseling and other support services available for military-connected students transitioning into the school;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Maintain a transition program led by students at the school, whenever appropriate, and overseen by the designated military liaison that assists military-connected students enrolled at the school by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Facilitating guided tours of the campus;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Organizing an orientation to familiarize the new student with school information; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If requested, accompanying the student throughout the campus during the first week of school during school hours; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Offer professional development to school staff on issues related to military-connected students transferring to new schools.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A public school may partner with a county board to fulfill the criteria described in <cite path="13A|06|10|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> to qualify as a Purple Star School.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Application and Renewal.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>To be considered for designation as a Purple Star School, a public school’s military liaison shall complete an application available on the Department’s website.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Department will release the Purple Star School application on December 1 of each year, beginning with the 2023—2024 school year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A public school that receives the Purple Star School designation shall hold the designation for a period of 2 school years and be eligible to reapply for the designation in the final year of the 2-year period.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A public school that fails to receive the Purple Star School designation is eligible to reapply for the designation the following year.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Selection Process.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Department shall identify a panel of stakeholders to review Purple Star School applications based on the criteria described in <cite path="|13A|06|10|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Department shall issue its decision on a Purple Star School application no later than the end of the school year in the local school system where the applicant school is located.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|2-205">2-205</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|7-129">7-129</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland, Ch. 361, Acts of 2018</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-03-20">Effective date: March 20, 2023 (50:5 Md. R. 182)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-03-03"><cite path="|13A|06|10|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective March 3, 2025 (52:4 Md. R. 219)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
