<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Freedom to Read Act</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>The purpose of this chapter is to establish as a matter of policy and priority that:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Library materials, services, and resources exist and should be provided for the interest, information, and enlightenment of all persons the library serves;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A library should not exclude material from its catalog because of the origin, background, or views of a person who created the material; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A library should not prohibit or remove material from its catalog because of partisan, ideological, or religious disapproval.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“County” means any county of the State and Baltimore City.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Library.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Library” includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The State Library Resource Center;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A Regional Resource Center;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A correctional facility library;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>A county library system and the Enoch Pratt Free Library in Baltimore;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>The Maryland State Library for the Blind and Print Disabled;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>The Maryland Deaf Culture Digital Library; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>A metropolitan cooperative service program.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Library” does not include a school library media program established by a local school system.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Objection” means a formal challenge submitted to a library for the purpose of removing, reconsidering, or restricting the presence of materials in a library collection.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“School library media program” means a library in a school in the public elementary and secondary education system of this State.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="14|38|02|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Library Policies and Procedures.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each library shall adopt and follow a written policy for operation of the library that is consistent with the State standards for libraries set forth in <cite path="|14|38|02|.01">Regulation .01 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Each policy adopted pursuant to <cite path="14|38|02|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An acknowledgement that all Marylanders have the freedom to read;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An affirmation that it is the responsibility of the library to provide adequate library services to satisfy the diverse needs of their users;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A policy and procedures for librarians and library staff to identify materials that meet users’ needs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A requirement that librarians and library staff curate and develop collections that provide access to the widest possible array of books and other materials that support learning; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A materials reconsideration policy and procedures.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A materials reconsideration policy and procedures shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Establish a uniform process to submit an objection to materials in the library;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Require material under review due to an objection to remain available for use by the public and library staff until the review process has concluded; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Establish a reasonable timeline to conduct and conclude the review process in a timely manner.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A library board of trustees or other governing body of a library may not dismiss, suspend, discipline, demote, reassign, transfer, or otherwise retaliate against an employee for performing their job duties consistent with the library’s written policy adopted under <cite path="14|38|02|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>State Funding.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The State Library Board shall ensure that each library that receives State funding is operated in a manner consistent with the State standards for libraries set forth in <cite path="|14|38|02|.01">Regulation .01 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Receipt of State funding by a public library is contingent upon the library board of trustees or other governing body for the library adopting a written policy that is consistent with the State standards for libraries and conducting the operation of the library in a manner consistent with the written policy.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the State Library Board certifies that a library has failed to meet the State standards for libraries, the State Library Board shall notify the Comptroller to withhold all State funds from that library.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Comptroller shall continue to withhold funds until the State Library Board certifies that the library has adopted a written policy consistent with the State standards for libraries.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|4-142">4-142</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|23-101">23-101</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|23-102">23-102</cite>.1, 23-105-106, 23-202-202.1, 23-205, 23-406, 23-503 and 23-506-507, <br/>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-03-03">Effective date: March 3, 2025</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
