<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Grant Programs for the Law Enforcement Cadet Apprenticeship Program and the Apprenticeship Career Training Pilot Program for Formerly Incarcerated Individuals</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>These regulations prescribe the policies, procedures, and authorizations for administering the Law Enforcement Cadet Apprenticeship Program and the Apprenticeship Career Training Pilot Program for Formerly Incarcerated Individuals.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Act” means Labor and Employment Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gle|11-603">11-603</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gle|11-604">11-604</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland, as amended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Council” means the Maryland Apprenticeship and Training Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Department” means the Department of Labor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Division” means the Division of Workforce Development and Adult Learning.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Grantee” means an employer to whom an award is made under the terms of this chapter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Law enforcement agency” has the meaning set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gle|11-603">Labor and Employment Article, §11-603(a)(3), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Program” means the grant programs for the Law Enforcement Cadet Apprenticeship Program and the Apprenticeship Career Training Pilot Program for Formerly Incarcerated Individuals.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Secretary” means the Secretary of Labor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Application and Review Procedures.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Grant Application.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An applicant may apply for a grant under the Act as set forth in this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An applicant shall apply to the Department on an application prescribed by the Department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An applicant shall submit documentation that the Department requires to establish the eligibility of the applicant and apprentice.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Review Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Upon receipt of the grant application and any required documentation, the Department shall review each application to determine whether an applicant will be awarded a grant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Secretary may delegate to the Assistant Secretary of the Division or an employee of the Department the authority to review grant applications and supporting documentation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If a grant application is rejected, the Department shall notify the applicant in writing within 60 days of receipt of the grant application.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The notice of grant rejection shall state the reason the grant was rejected.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>An applicant may request reconsideration within 15 days of the date of the notice of grant rejection by filing a request in writing with the Assistant Secretary of the Division.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Grant Monitoring.</heading>
    <text>The Department may monitor grants and disbursement of grant funds to ensure that grant funds are properly disbursed.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Retention of Grant Records.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Grantees shall retain and maintain all records regarding the application for at least 3 years after the final disbursement of grant funds.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The records shall be open to the inspections of representatives of the Department during reasonable working hours.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Application Records.</heading>
    <text>The Department shall ensure that Program guidelines, information and application forms are publicly available on the Department’s website and at its offices.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Waiver.</heading>
    <text>The Secretary may waive or modify a particular provision of this chapter to the extent that the waiver is not inconsistent with the Act if, in the determination of the Secretary, the application of a regulation in a specific case is inequitable or contrary to the purposes of the Act.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Amount of Law Enforcement Cadet Apprenticeship Program Grant.</heading>
    <text>The maximum amount that a Law Enforcement Agency may be awarded during a fiscal year may not exceed $400,000.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Amount of Apprenticeship Career Training Pilot Program Grant for Formerly Incarcerated Individuals.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The maximum amount that a grantee may be awarded during a fiscal year may not exceed $25,000.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Grants may not exceed $1,000 per apprentice employed by a grantee.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Labor and Employment Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gle|11-603">11-603</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gle|11-604">11-604</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-04-19">Effective date: April 19, 2021 (48:8 Md. R. 309)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
