<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Maryland New Start Grant Program</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>These regulations prescribe the policies, procedures, and authorizations for administering the Maryland New Start Grant Program.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Act" means <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gle|11-606">Labor and Employment Article, §11-606, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Department" means the Department of Labor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Division” means the Division of Workforce Development and Adult Learning.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Grant” means an award under the terms of this chapter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Grantee” means an organization to whom an award is made under the terms of this chapter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Program” means the Maryland New Start Grant Program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Secretary” means the Secretary of Labor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Eligible Grantees.</heading>
    <text>Eligible grantees shall meet the following requirements to qualify for a grant:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Have all requisite legal capacity and due authority to enter into the grant;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Satisfy all legal requirements to operate in the State; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Meet the performance standards of the Department, as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Not have defaulted on a prior grant or loan from the Department; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Not be currently barred or suspended from any of the Department's programs.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Proposal and Review Procedures.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Department shall ensure that the Program guidelines, information and application forms are publicly available on the Department’s website and at its physical locations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Grant Proposal. The Department shall provide guidelines and detailed instructions for submitting a proposal for the Department’s consideration. Each proposal shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The information required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gle|11-606">Labor and Employment Article, §11-606(d)(2)(iii), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A description of the entrepreneurship development program as described in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gle|11-606">Labor and Employment Article, §11-606(d)(3), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An explanation of how the requirement of matching funds required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gle|11-606">Labor and Employment Article, §11-606(e), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, will be satisfied; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Any other information the Secretary requires related to the Program.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Review Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Upon receipt of the grant proposal and any required documentation, the Department shall review each application to determine whether an applicant will be awarded a grant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Secretary may delegate to the Assistant Secretary of the Division or an employee of the Department the authority to review grant proposals and supporting documentation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Grant Agreement.</heading>
    <text>Upon approval of a grant proposal by the Department, the applicant, on a Departmental form, shall execute a grant agreement. The grant agreement shall at least require an applicant to meet the following obligations:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Establish and operate the project according to the project description;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Maintain and provide records and reports as required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gle|11-606">Labor and Employment Article, §11-606(g), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, to the Department; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Use grant funds for only those activities provided in the approved project proposal.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Grant Monitoring.</heading>
    <text>The Department may monitor grants and disbursement of grant funds to ensure that grant funds are properly disbursed by a grantee.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Retention of Grant Records.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Grantees shall retain and maintain all records regarding the application for at least 3 years after the final disbursement of grant funds.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The records shall be open to the inspections of representatives of the Department during reasonable working hours.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Expiration of the Program.</heading>
    <text>This chapter remains in effect until the earlier of:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The date that funding for the Program ceases to be available; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>June 30, 2029.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gle|11-606">Labor and Employment Article, §11-606, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-05-15">Effective date: May 15, 2023 (50:9 Md. R. 378)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
