<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Certification — Residential Child Care Program Administrators</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|57|02|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Application Procedures.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In order to obtain a certificate as a residential child care program administrator, the applicant shall submit to the Board:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An application on the form provided by the Board;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The application fee set forth in <cite path="|10.57.07">COMAR 10.57.07</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Independent written verification from the applicant’s employer or employers describing the nature and duration of the applicant’s experience in the human service field;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A certified copy of a transcript with a school seal from an accredited college or university to document the receipt of a baccalaureate or master's degree; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Evidence that the applicant:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is of good moral character;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has completed a State and national criminal history records check;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Unless waived in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|20">Health Occupations Article, §20</cite>–303(d), Annotated Code of Maryland, has submitted to a child protective services background clearance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Meets the requirements of Regulations .02 and .03 of this chapter;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Is 21 years old or older; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Is responsible for the day-to-day management and operation of a residential child care program.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Experience Required in <cite path="10|57|02|.01|A.|(3)">§A(3) of this Regulation</cite>.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At least one employment verification under <cite path="10|57|02|.01|A.|(3)">§A(3) of this regulation</cite> shall be provided by a present or former supervisor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For individuals who are in a leadership role of a residential child care program and do not have a supervisor, an employment verification from the program's Chief Administrator or other appropriate program authority is sufficient to meet this requirement.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Employment verification shall be submitted to the Board:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>On the form provided by the Board; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>In a sealed envelope that is signed by the writer on the back of the envelope over the seal.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Day-to-day management and operation of a residential child care program required in <cite path="10|57|02|.01|A.|(5)|(f)">§A(5)(f) of this regulation</cite> includes, but is not limited to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Administering, directing, or managing the residential child care program to ensure that the basic needs of the child are met;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Recruiting, hiring, training, and supervising staff;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Developing and implementing an appropriate staffing plan based upon the needs of the children in the residential child care program and in accordance with applicable laws and regulations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Coordinating, supervising, and implementing the services provided to ensure the child has access to appropriate medical, psychosocial and educational services as established in the child's service plan;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Maintaining records in a manner that conforms to the requirements of this chapter and other applicable laws and regulations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Monitoring the quality of services provided by the residential child care program; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Ensuring that all requirements of this chapter and other applicable laws and regulations are met.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Board may not consider an application completed until it has received all required materials.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An applicant shall be responsible for the payment of any costs required to obtain supporting documentation for an application.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Incomplete Applications.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If an incomplete application is submitted to the Board, the Board shall notify the applicant within 30 days after the receipt of an incomplete application of the materials that are required.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the applicant fails to provide the required documentation within 120 days, the Board may:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Administratively close the application; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Deny the application, pursuant to <cite path="|10|57|02|.04|E.">Regulation .04E of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An applicant whose application is administratively closed or denied may reapply and submit with the new application proof of compliance with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>This subtitle; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 20, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>An applicant whose application has been denied shall disclose on future applications that the applicant had been denied certification.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|57|02|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Academic and Experience Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Degrees and Experience. For certification as a certified program administrator, an applicant shall submit proof of one of the following to the Board:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Receipt of a baccalaureate degree from an accredited college or university and 4 years experience in the human service field with at least 3 years in a supervisory or administrative capacity; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Receipt of a master's degree from an accredited college or university and 2 years experience in the human service field with at least 1 year in a supervisory or administrative capacity.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Supervisory or Administrative Capacity Required in <cite path="10|57|02|.02|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Supervisory or administrative capacity required under <cite path="10|57|02|.02|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> includes the responsibility for hiring, assigning duties, disciplining and rewarding, approving leave requests, and formally evaluating.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Experience within the following settings may not be considered supervisory or administrative capacity experience:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Child placing agency;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Child placing institutional experience;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Foster parenting; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Serving as a caregiver in a foster home.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Experience shall be obtained within 10 years before the application date.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Review of Foreign Credentials. An applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provide proof of equivalency of the applicant's educational credentials to a baccalaureate degree or master's degree awarded from an accredited college or university in the United States; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Submit their educational credentials at the applicant's expense to an educational evaluation agency approved by the Board with the request that the evaluation report be sent directly to the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|57|02|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Examination Procedures.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Unless waived by the Board as provided in <cite path="10|57|02|.03|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>, an applicant shall pass a Board-approved written examination before certification.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A minimum passing score of 75 percent is required on the examination.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In order to qualify for certification, an applicant shall pass the examination within 3 years of the first time the applicant takes the examination.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Waiver of Examination. The Board may waive the examination requirement for an applicant who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Pays the application fee as provided in <cite path="|10.57.07">COMAR 10.57.07</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is certified as a program administrator in any other state that the Board determines has a comparable certification process; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Provides adequate evidence that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>At the time the applicant was certified in the other state, the applicant was qualified to take the examination that then was required by the laws of this State;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The applicant qualified for a certificate in the other state by passing an examination given in that or any other state;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The applicant has completed a State and national criminal history records check; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Unless waived by the Board in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|20">Health Occupations Article, §20</cite>–303(d), Annotated Code of Maryland, the applicant has submitted to a child protective services background clearance.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Reexamination.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An applicant who fails the examination:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>May retake the examination three times within the 12-month period after a failed examination; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>May not retake the examination within 6-months of failing the examination for the third time.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Before or on the day of the repeat examination, the applicant shall pay to the Board the examination fee as established in <cite path="|10.57.07">COMAR 10.57.07</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An applicant may request a waiver of the 6-month waiting period after failure of the third examination upon proof of exceptional circumstances.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Applicants Requiring Special Accommodation.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An applicant with a disability may request modifications in examination materials or procedures.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The applicant shall make the request for modification in writing and include in the request the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The applicant's name;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The date of the examination to be modified; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A letter from the appropriate licensed professional which:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Confirms the disability; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Provides information describing the accommodations required.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Requests for modification and supporting documentation shall be received by the application deadline.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Action on Application.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Criminal History Record Information.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Upon receipt of an applicant’s criminal history records information in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|20-303">Health Occupations Article, §20-303, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the Board shall consider the following factors in determining whether to grant a certificate:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The age at which the crime was committed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The circumstances surrounding the crime;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The length of time that has passed since the crime;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Subsequent work history;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Employment and character references; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Other evidence that demonstrates whether the applicant poses a threat to the public health or safety.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Board may not issue a certificate if the criminal history record information required under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|20-303">Health Occupations Article, §20-303, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, has not been received.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Upon review of a completed application, the Board shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notify the applicant that the applicant is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Approved for certification; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Qualified to take the examination; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Deny certification.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Denial of Applications.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board may deny certification if the applicant has:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Not completed the academic and experience requirements in <cite path="|10|57|02|.02">Regulation .02 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Failed the examination requirements in <cite path="|10|57|02|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Failed to remit a fee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Failed to properly complete the application form;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Violated <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 20, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or any provision of this subtitle; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Been shown to have a lack of good moral character.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the Board denies certification under §E(1)(e) or (f) of this regulation, the Board or the Board's designee shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Provide the applicant written notification of the Board's intent to deny and the basis for that denial; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Notify the applicant of the applicant's right to request a formal hearing to appeal the denial.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An applicant whose certification has been denied may reapply and shall submit with the new application proof of compliance with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>This subtitle; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 20, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Issuance of Certificate.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If the Board approves an applicant for certification and the applicant passes the State Standards Examination, the Board shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Send the applicant a notice specifying that the applicant has qualified for a certificate; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Issue a certificate, available online, to the applicant.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Board shall include on each certificate the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Full name of the certificate holder; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Serial number assigned by the Board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation app="2025-10-13" doc="Maryland Register, Volume 52, Issue 20" eff="2025-10-13" path="regulations|final|25-125-F" type="History" display="false"/>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Expiration and Renewal.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Unless the Board suspends or revokes the certificate, the certification is effective for up to 2 years from the date issued and authorizes the individual to administer a residential child care program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>At least 1 month before the certificate expires, the Board shall send to the certified program administrator, by electronic means or first-class mail to the last known electronic or physical address, a renewal notice that states:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The date on which the current certificate expires;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The date by which the renewal application shall be received by the Board for the renewal to be issued; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The amount of the renewal fee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Board shall renew the certificate of a certified program administrator who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Otherwise is entitled to obtain a certificate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Pays to the Board a renewal fee set by the Board; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Submits to the Board:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A renewal application on a form that the Board requires;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Satisfactory evidence of compliance with any continuing education and other qualifications and requirements set by the Board.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Unless waived by the Board in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|20-310">Health Occupations Article, §20-310(f), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, evidence of application for a child protective services background clearance; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Evidence of having submitted to a State and national criminal history records check conducted by the Central Repository.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Criminal History Record Information.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Upon receipt of an applicant’s criminal history records information in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|20-303">Health Occupations Article, §20-303, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the Board shall consider the following factors in determining whether to grant a certificate:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The age at which the crime was committed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The circumstances surrounding the crime;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The length of time that has passed since the crime;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Subsequent work history;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Employment and character references; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Other evidence that demonstrates whether the applicant poses a threat to the public health or safety.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Board may not issue a certificate if the criminal history record information required under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|20-303">Health Occupations Article, §20-303, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, has not been received.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation app="2025-10-13" doc="Maryland Register, Volume 52, Issue 20" eff="2025-10-13" path="regulations|final|25-125-F" type="History" display="false"/>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Reinstatement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board shall reinstate the certificate of a program administrator who has failed to renew the certificate for any reason, if the individual:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Has not had the certificate suspended or revoked;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Meets the renewal requirements in <cite path="|10|57|02|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Pays to the Board the reinstatement fee set by the Board;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Submits to the Board:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>40 continuing education units taken within the last 2 years;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Evidence of having submitted to a State and national criminal history records check conducted by the Central Repository; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Unless waived by the Board in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|20-311">Health Occupations Article, §20-311(c), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, evidence of application for a child protective services background clearance; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Applies to the Board for reinstatement of the certificate within 5 years after the certificate expires.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board may not reinstate the certificate of a program administrator who fails to apply for reinstatement of the certificate within 5 years after the certificate expires. However, the program administrator may be certified by meeting the current requirements for obtaining a new certificate under this subtitle.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Duplicate or Corrected Certificate.</heading>
    <text>The Board shall issue a duplicate certificate, electronically, to the certificate holder if:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The certificate holder has a change of name and does the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Makes the request to the Board in writing on the form provided by the Board; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provides appropriate legal documentation of the change; or</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board, as a result of its error, issues an incorrect certificate and the certificate holder:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notifies the Board in writing within 6 weeks of discovery of the incorrect certificate; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Does not receive electronic verification of the certificate within 6 weeks of issuance and provides a statement to the Board attesting to the unavailability of the certificate online within 4 months of the date the certificate was issued by the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation app="2025-10-13" doc="Maryland Register, Volume 52, Issue 20" eff="2025-10-13" path="regulations|final|25-125-F" type="History" display="false"/>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Resignation, Removal, or Death of a Program Administrator.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If a program administrator resigns or is removed from a position as a program administrator by death or for any other unexpected cause, the residential child care program's Chief Administrator or other appropriate program authority shall immediately designate a certified program administrator to serve in that capacity.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In the event a certified program administrator is not available, the residential child care program's Chief Administrator or other appropriate program authority may appoint a noncertified individual to serve in the capacity of acting program administrator for a period not exceeding 90 days if the individual:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is approved by the Board; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Meets the minimum qualifications for a program administrator as set forth in <cite path="|10.57.02">COMAR 10.57.02</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Approval of Noncertified Individual to Serve as Acting Program Administrator.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In order to obtain approval from the Board for the approval of a noncertified individual to serve as the acting program administrator, the residential child care program's Chief Administrator or other appropriate program authority shall immediately submit to the Board:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An application on the form provided by the Board;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The application fee set forth in <cite path="|10.57.07">COMAR 10.57.07</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Written justification clarifying the reason why acting capacity is necessary, that includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The name and title of the individual requesting approval of a non-certified individual, including mailing address, phone, and email address;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The qualifications and credentials of the individual selected for acting capacity; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A summary of the efforts made by the residential child care program to recruit a certified program administrator;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A copy of the individual's resume or curriculum vitae; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The State and national criminal history records check.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Board shall review all of the documentation provided to verify that individual appointed meets the minimum qualifications of a program administrator as set forth in <cite path="|10.57.02">COMAR 10.57.02</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Upon review of the request, the Board may:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Approve the request for acting capacity;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Approve the request for acting capacity with conditions; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Deny request for acting capacity.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The 90 day period begins on the date that the program administrator leaves or is removed from the position as a program administrator.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Board may extend the 90 day period for a further period of not more than 30 days.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Display of Certificate and Renewal Certificates.</heading>
    <text>An individual certified as a residential child care program administrator shall display an original certificate and certificate card, or certificate renewal card in a conspicuous place in the office or place of business or employment of the program administrator.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|20-205">20-205</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|20-301">20-301</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|20-302">20-302</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|20-303">20-303</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|20-305">20-305</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|20-307">20-307</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|20-310">20-310</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|20-311">20-311</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|20-404">20-404</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-04-07">Regulations <cite path="|10|57|02|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|57|02|.06">.06</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective January 7, 2008 (35:9 Md. R. 894); adopted permanently effective April 7, 2008 (35:7 Md. R. 749)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-04-19" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective April 19, 2010 (37:8 Md. R. 617)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-11-07" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective November 7, 2016 (43:22 Md. R. 1223)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-12-27"><cite path="|10|57|02|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective December 27, 2021 (48:26 Md. R. 1112)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-12-31"><cite path="|10|57|02|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective December 31, 2018 (45:26 Md. R. 1246)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-10-13"><cite path="|10|57|02|.04|B.">Regulation .04B</cite>, D amended effective October 13, 2025 (52:20 Md. R. 1002)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-10-13"><cite path="|10|57|02|.05|A.">Regulation .05A</cite>, B amended effective October 13, 2025 (52:20 Md. R. 1002)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-12-31"><cite path="|10|57|02|.05|D.">Regulation .05D</cite> adopted effective December 31, 2018 (45:26 Md. R. 1246)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-10-13"><cite path="|10|57|02|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective October 13, 2025 (52:20 Md. R. 1002)</annotation>
    <annotation app="2025-10-13" doc="Maryland Register, Volume 52, Issue 20" eff="2025-10-13" path="regulations|final|25-125-F" type="History" display="false"/>
  </annotations>
</container>
