<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Letter of Authorization</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="26|23|03|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Activities Requiring a Letter of Authorization.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except for regulated activities proposed within the Critical Area, an activity that qualifies for a letter of authorization is exempt from the permit and mitigation requirements of this subtitle. Activities proposed in the Critical Area are not exempt from the mitigation requirements of <cite path="26.23.04.02">COMAR 26.23.04.02</cite>—.07.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Upon application, the activities listed below may qualify for a letter of authorization provided that the conditions in <cite path="|26|23|03|.02|B.">Regulation .02B of this chapter</cite> are satisfied and best management practices, which may be required by the Department, are all met:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Activities in isolated nontidal wetlands of less than 1 acre and having no significant plant or wildlife value. An applicant's determination of whether an area is an isolated nontidal wetland shall be based on published hydrologic and hydraulic data or data obtained in the field which shows whether the nontidal wetland is hydrologically connected.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Activities whose cumulative loss of nontidal wetlands and buffer, which contains no significant plant or wildlife value, is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Less than 5,000 square feet; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Greater than 5,000 square feet, provided that:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The actual loss of nontidal wetlands is less than 5,000 square feet, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Activities in the buffer result in minimal additional adverse impacts to nontidal wetlands, as determined by the Department.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Installation of Utility Lines.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The installation of utility lines includes the following activities:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Trenching, jetting, jackhammering, or plowing of nontidal wetlands;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Laying of pipe, cable, or wire;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Backfilling of the excavated trench containing the pipe, cable, or wire;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Placement of riprap; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Rectification of nontidal wetland areas which have been disturbed.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Utility lines do not include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Intake and outfall structures;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Pipe or pipeline used to transport any liquid or slurry substance except as associated with water and sewage lines;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Natural gas lines greater than 12 inches in diameter; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Storm water conveyance systems.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Construction of overhead power transmission lines.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Mitigation projects not required under this subtitle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Regulated activities which impact the buffer, and less than 2 acres of farmed nontidal wetlands with 15 or more consecutive days of inundation during the growing season, except in nontidal wetlands of special State concern or their expanded buffer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The repair of the following serviceable structures or fills:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Aboveground and underground utilities;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Structures in rights-of-way;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Railroad beds;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Road beds, roadside ditches, culverts, and outlet ditches;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Bridges;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Dams;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Dikes;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Levees;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Water and wastewater control structures; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Facilities designed for storm water management.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Activities which will result in the loss of nontidal wetlands that have been temporarily created by a permitted or authorized construction activity or as a result of a permitted mining activity, including wetlands created:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Incidental to mining activities that were conducted under an approved mining plan or permit, or wetlands that have been created incidental to a mining activity, and that will be impacted during implementation of an approved reclamation plan;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>As a result of the construction of an approved sediment control structure; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>For a specific purpose that will remain for a specified period of time, including wash ponds and grassed waterways.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The following conditions apply to the activities listed in <cite path="26|23|03|.01|B.|(7)">§B(7) of this regulation</cite>:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If the structure or fill has been put to uses other than the use originally intended or authorized for the original construction, and the repair activity will alter or impair any additional nontidal wetland area, the repair of the structure may not be exempted.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Repair to be made more than 3 years after damage occurs or is first identified does not qualify for an exemption.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An applicant seeking a letter of authorization under <cite path="26|23|03|.01|B.|(8)">§B(8) of this regulation</cite> shall submit the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Information regarding the creation of the wetlands;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The purpose of the wetland creation, if applicable;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The length of time the wetland will exist;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A copy of the approved site plan, erosion and sediment control plan, mining plan, or reclamation plan;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A description of the function the created wetland will serve;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A request for the length of time the letter of authorization is to be valid; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Justification for conducting the regulated activity in the nontidal wetland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Structures that have been placed in nontidal wetlands (for example, sediment traps), or that have impacted nontidal wetlands through their construction or operation do not qualify for a letter of authorization under <cite path="26|23|03|.01|B.|(8)">§B(8) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A letter of authorization issued under <cite path="26|23|03|.01|B.|(8)">§B(8) of this regulation</cite> is in effect for a period of up to 5 years and may be extended for one additional 5-year period. A letter of authorization granted under §B(8) may not be extended for more than one 5-year period, for a total of 10 years, unless the regulated activity is part of a permitted mining activity or involves implementation of a mining reclamation plan.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="26|23|03|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Best Management Practices for Letters of Authorization.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If a letter of authorization is granted, the Department may require an applicant to comply with best management practices, including one or more of the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Conduct the regulated activity so as not to harm a threatened or endangered species, or species in need of conservation, or alter or impair the critical habitat of these species;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Properly maintain the structure or fill;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Design the project to first avoid and then minimize any adverse impacts to the nontidal wetlands' existing topography, vegetation, fish and wildlife resources, and hydrologic conditions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Conduct the regulated activity so as not to restrict or impede the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Movement of wildlife indigenous to the nontidal wetlands or adjacent water, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Passage of normal or expected high water flows;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Adhere to time-of-year restrictions as required by the Department under <cite path="|26.08.02">COMAR 26.08.02</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Avoid any disturbances in breeding areas for migratory waterfowl;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Maintain the hydrologic regime of the nontidal wetlands upstream, downstream, or adjacent to the exempted activity;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Remove excess fill or construction material or debris to an upland disposal area;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Place materials in a location and manner which does not adversely impact surface or subsurface water flow into or out of the nontidal wetland;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>If backfill is obtained from sources other than the originally excavated material, use clean material free of waste metal products, unsightly debris, toxic material, or any other deleterious substance;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Place heavy equipment on mats or suitably design the equipment to prevent damage to the nontidal wetlands;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Repair and maintain any serviceable structures or fills so as not to result in a substantial deviation from the plans or specifications or the original structure or fill, although minor deviations due to changes in materials or construction techniques, and which are necessary for repair and maintenance, are permitted;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Rectify any nontidal wetlands temporarily impacted by any proposed repair and maintenance activity;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>Repair and maintain any serviceable structure or fill so there is no permanent loss of nontidal wetlands in excess of nontidal wetlands lost under the original construction or fill;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>Conduct the activity so as not to cause or contribute to a degradation of water quality as determined by the Department;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>For installation of utility lines, make postconstruction grades and elevations of nontidal wetlands the same as the original grades and elevations.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A proposed activity does not qualify for a letter of authorization if the Department determines that the activity:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Does not qualify under <cite path="|26|23|03|.01">Regulation .01 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>May result in significant individual or cumulative impacts to nontidal wetlands, attributable to an entire and complete project; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Does not comply with the best management practices in this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Activities of a Similar Nature.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Applicants proposing to conduct repeated regional or Statewide activities of a similar nature that may qualify for a letter of authorization may submit a single application to the Department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Department may issue a single letter of authorization for these activities in <cite path="26|23|03|.02|C.|(1)">§C(1) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Activities may include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Structural repair and maintenance; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Work within rights-of-way.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Environment Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|5-901">5-901</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|5-911">5-911</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-03-15">Effective date: March 15, 1990 (17:5 Md. R. 637)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1991-01-01">Chapter revised as an emergency provision effective January 1, 1991 (18:2 Md. R. 128)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1991-05-13">Chapter revised effective May 13, 1991 (18:9 Md. R. 1007)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-10-01">Regulations <cite path="|26|23|03|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|26|23|03|.04">.04</cite>, .08, .09, .14, .15, and .22 amended and Regulation .27 adopted as an emergency provision effective October 1, 1993 (20:21 Md. R. 1649); emergency status expired April 1, 1994</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-10-24">Regulations <cite path="|26|23|03|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|26|23|03|.04">.04</cite>, .08, .09, .14, .15, and .22 amended and Regulation .27 adopted as an emergency provision effective June 1, 1994 (21:13 Md. R. 1151); Regulations <cite path="|26|23|03|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|26|23|03|.04">.04</cite>, .08, .09, .14, and .22 amended and .27 adopted permanently effective October 24, 1994, (21:21 Md. R. 1813)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-11-07">Regulations .01 and .15—.18 amended and Regulation .17-1 adopted effective November 7, 1994 (21:22 Md. R. 1874)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" discontinuity="true">Regulations .01 and .02 were recodified from Regulations .09 and .10, respectively, under <cite path="|08.05.04">COMAR 08.05.04</cite> Nontidal Wetlands, June 1996</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-06-18"><cite path="|26|23|03|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective June 18, 2018 (45:12 Md. R. 620)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-06-18"><cite path="|26|23|03|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective June 18, 2018 (45:12 Md. R. 620)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1996-10-22"><cite path="|26|23|03|.02|C.">Regulation .02C</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective October 22, 1996 (23:23 Md. R. 1552); emergency status expired April 22, 1997</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
