<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Licensure and Continuing Education</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>These regulations govern an individual practicing as a speech-language pathologist or audiologist, or both, in Maryland.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Accredited educational institution” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A college or university located in the U.S. whose program has been accredited by a national accrediting association recognized by the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Council for Higher Education Accreditation; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>United States Department of Education; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A college or university located outside the U.S. whose program has met the standards for certification of the governing educational body that is regulated by the government of the country where the college or university is located.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Board” means the Board of Examiners for Audiologists, Hearing Aid Dispensers, Speech-Language Pathologists, and Music Therapists.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Credit” means 1 semester hour except when specified in these regulations. “Credit” is used only with reference to fulfilling academic requirements for original licensure application.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Continuing education unit (CEU)” means a period of 60 minutes for a licensee's direct participation in an approved continuing education experience. “Continuing education unit (CEU)” is used only with reference to fulfilling requirements for renewal of full licensure.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Examination” means the National Examination in Speech-Language Pathology or the National Examination in Audiology.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Oral competency” means the demonstration of general English-speaking proficiency by receiving a passing score on a standardized test that the Board has approved.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Pro bono work” means work provided within the State within the scope of practice of the licensee that is performed without financial reimbursement or direct financial gain.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|41|03|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Licensure Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Limited Licensure.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person who has met all requirements for licensure except supervised post-graduate professional experience or examination, or both, may apply for limited licensure.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An individual seeking limited licensure shall fulfill the following requirements:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Hold a master's degree in speech-language pathology or a doctoral degree in audiology, or both, from an accredited educational institution having a graduate or doctoral program in either field;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Have met the academic and practicum requirements for a Certificate of Clinical Competence of the American Speech-Language-Hearing Association or Board Certification in Audiology from the American Board of Audiology that were in effect at the time a master's degree in speech pathology or doctoral degree in either field was obtained; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Demonstrate oral English competency as follows:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Completion of at least 60 credits from an undergraduate college or university where English was the language of instruction throughout the applicant's inclusive dates of attendance; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Achievement of a minimum score of 105, with at least a 26 on Speaking and Listening, on the Test of English as a Foreign Language (TOEFL) within the 2 years preceding license application.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Application.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An individual applying for limited licensure shall submit a complete application.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Board shall determine whether an application is complete.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A complete application shall include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The application fee;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>All required documentation regarding supervision of the limited licensee; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>An official transcript from the accredited educational institution attended by the applicant.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Upon approval of an application, the Board shall issue a document authorizing the applicant to practice in this State in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|2-306">Health Occupations Article, §2-306, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and the regulations in this chapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Supervision of Professional Experience for Audiologists.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Supervisory Plan for Audiologists.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Each applicant shall submit to the Board for approval a description of the supervisory plan to be followed during the period of limited licensure.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The plan shall show adequate supervision, in accordance with this chapter.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Board may accept completion of the clinical fellowship required for the American Speech-Language-Hearing Association Certificate of Clinical Competence or completion of the mentored practice required for American Board of Audiology Certification as meeting the requirements for supervised practice in this chapter.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Unless an exception is approved by the Board for extenuating circumstances, an applicant shall begin the clinical training within 2 years after completion of the academic course work and academic clinical practicum requirements and shall complete the clinical training within 24 months.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>To complete a clinical training, the applicant shall be employed as a professional in the field of audiology under appropriate on-site direct supervision for not less than 9 months with a minimum of 36 hours of work per week. This requirement may also be met with part-time employment as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>14—16 hours a week for a period of 24 months;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>17—20 hours a week for a period of 18 months;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>21—24 hours a week for a period of 15 months;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>25—35 hours a week for a period of 12 months.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>At least 80 percent of the applicant's employment during the clinical training shall be in direct client contact which includes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Assessment/diagnosis/evaluation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Screening, response to intervention (RTI), or observations of clients;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Treatment, such as:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Hearing device fitting;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Diagnostic assessment; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Rehabilitation; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Activities related to client management including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Writing reports and notes;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Billing;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Making rounds; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Attendance at an individualized education program (IEP), individualized family service plan (IFSP) meeting, or other meetings related to the management of a client’s diagnosis and treatment plan.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>An individual serving as a supervisor:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Shall hold a valid license issued by the Board in audiology, or if the supervisor is employed by a facility whose employees qualify for an exemption from licensure the Certificate of Clinical Competence of the American Speech-Language-Hearing Association in audiology or Board Certification in Audiology from the American Board of Audiology;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Shall have been in practice for a minimum of 3 years after completion of the clinical training;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Shall supervise not more than three limited licensees at one time; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>May not have been formally disciplined by the Board within the previous 5 years.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>An individual serving as a supervisor of a limited licensee is legally and ethically responsible for services provided or omitted by the limited licensee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Change in Supervisor or Place of Professional Employment.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>During the period of limited licensure, if an individual changes supervisor, or place of professional employment, or both, the individual shall submit a revised supervisory plan to the Board for Board approval.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Board shall approve the new supervisor or the new setting before the individual may begin to practice under the new supervisor or in the new setting.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>A supervisor shall notify the Board within 5 days if the supervisor withdraws from supervising a limited licensee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Supervision of Clinical Fellowship for Speech Pathologists.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Supervisory Plan for Speech Pathologists.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An applicant shall submit to the Board for approval a description of the supervisory plan to be followed during the period of limited licensure.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The plan shall show adequate supervision, in accordance with this chapter.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Board may accept completion of the clinical fellowship required for the American Speech-Language-Hearing Association Certificate of Clinical Competence as meeting the requirements for supervised practice in this chapter.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Unless an exception is approved by the Board for extenuating circumstances, an applicant shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Begin the clinical fellowship within 2 years after completion of the academic course work and clinical practicum requirements; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Complete the clinical fellowship within 24 months.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>To complete a clinical fellowship, the applicant shall be employed as a professional in the field of speech-language pathology under appropriate supervision for not less than 9 months with a minimum of 30 hours of work per week. This requirement may also be met with part-time employment as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>15—19 hours a week for a period of 18 months;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>20—24 hours a week for a period of 15 months; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>25—29 hours a week for a period of 12 months.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>At least 80 percent of the applicant's employment during the clinical fellowship shall be in direct client contact, which includes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Assessment/diagnosis/evaluation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Screening, response to intervention (RTI), or observations of clients;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Treatment, such as:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Diagnostic assessment; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Rehabilitation; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Activities related to client management, including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Writing reports and notes;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Billing;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Making rounds; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Attendance at an individualized education program (IEP), individualized family service plan (IFSP) meeting, or other meetings related to the management of a client’s diagnosis and treatment plan.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>An individual serving as a supervisor:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Shall hold a valid license issued by the Board in speech pathology, or if the supervisor is employed by a facility whose employees qualify for an exemption from licensure the Certificate of Clinical Competence of the American Speech-Language-Hearing Association in speech pathology;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Shall have been in practice for a minimum of 2 years after completion of the clinical fellowship;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>May not supervise more than three limited licensees at one time;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>May not have been formally disciplined by the Board within the previous 5 years; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Shall provide a minimum of 4 hours per month for at least 9 months of supervisory activities during the clinical fellowship to include a minimum of 2 hours of other monitoring activities each month.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>An individual serving as a supervisor of a limited licensee is legally and ethically responsible for services provided or omitted by the limited licensee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Change in Supervisor or Place of Professional Employment.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>During the period of limited licensure, if an individual changes supervisor, or place of professional employment, or both, the individual shall submit a revised supervisory plan to the Board for Board approval.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Board shall approve the new supervisor or the new setting before the individual may begin to practice under the new supervisor or in the new setting.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>A supervisor shall notify the Board within 5 days if the supervisor withdraws from supervising a limited licensee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Full Licensure.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Licensure Requirements for Audiologists.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An individual may apply for full licensure if the individual fulfills all of the following requirements:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The individual holds a current unsuspended and unrevoked certificate of licensure to practice audiology from another state or jurisdiction which was obtained by meeting requirements that are at least equivalent to the requirements of <cite path="10|41|03|.03|D.|(2)">§D(2) of this regulation</cite>;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The individual has completed the academic requirements, the supervised on-site direct clinical experience, the examination requirements as set forth in <cite path="10|41|03|.03|D.|(2)">§D(2) of this regulation</cite>, and submits evidence of the successful completion of the clinical training.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The supervised post-graduate professional practice shall have been supervised by an individual who, at the time of supervision, held a valid audiology license issued by the Board, or if the supervisor is employed by a facility whose employees qualify for an exemption from licensure the Certificate of Clinical Competence of the American Speech-Language-Hearing Association or Board Certification in Audiology from the American Board of Audiology.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The supervisor's license or certificate shall be in audiology.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The applicant shall demonstrate oral English competency as follows:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Completion of at least 60 credits from an undergraduate college or university where English was the language of instruction throughout the applicant's inclusive dates of attendance; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Achievement of a minimum score of 105, with at least a 26 on Speaking and Listening, on the Test of English as a Foreign Language (TOEFL) within the 2 years preceding license application.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Examination Requirements for Audiologists.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An applicant shall have obtained a passing score on the National Examination in Audiology.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If a passing score on the National Examination in Audiology was not obtained within the 5 years before applying for licensure, the applicant shall fulfill one or more of the following requirements as approved by the Board:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Provide evidence that the applicant has practiced in audiology for 3 of the 5 years before applying for licensure;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Complete a period of supervised practice equivalent to that required of a limited licensee; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Hold a current license in another state and submit proof of continuing education as stated in <cite path="|10|41|03|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite> for the time period not practicing.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A first time licensee, who has not held a full license in this State or another state for 1 full year, shall submit verification from the academic institution conferring the individual's degree attesting to the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The academic course work completed by the individual applying for a license is consistent with the standards established by the Accreditation Commission for Audiology Education (ACAE) or the Council for Academic Accreditation (CAA); and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The individual applying for licensure has completed 1,000 actual patient contact hours while working under direct on-site supervision.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Licensure Requirements for Speech-Language Pathologists.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An individual may apply for full licensure if the individual fulfills any of the following requirements:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The individual holds a valid Certificate of Clinical Competence in speech-language pathology from the American Speech-Language-Hearing Association and meets the academic, practicum, examination, and supervised professional practice requirements of this chapter and the requirements of <cite path="10|41|03|.03|D.|(5)">§D(5) of this regulation</cite>;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The individual holds a current unsuspended and unrevoked certificate of licensure to practice speech-language pathology from another state or jurisdiction which was obtained by meeting requirements that are at least equivalent to the requirements of this State and that meet the requirements of <cite path="10|41|03|.03|D.|(5)">§D(5) of this regulation</cite>; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The individual has completed the academic requirements, the supervised direct clinical experience, the examination requirements as set forth in <cite path="10|41|03|.03|D.|(5)">§D(5) of this regulation</cite>, and submits evidence of the successful completion of the clinical fellowship.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The supervised post-graduate professional practice shall have been supervised by an individual who, at the time of supervision, held a valid speech-language pathology license issued by the Board, or if the supervisor is employed by a facility whose employees qualify for an exemption from licensure, the Certificate of Clinical Competence of the American Speech-Language-Hearing Association.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The supervisor's license or certificate shall be in the area of speech pathology.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The applicant shall demonstrate oral English competency as follows:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Completion of at least 60 credits from an undergraduate college or university where English was the language of instruction throughout the applicant's inclusive dates of attendance; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Achievement of a minimum score of 105, with at least a 26 on Speaking and Listening, the Test of English as a Foreign Language (TOEFL) within the 2 years preceding license application.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Examination Requirements for Speech-Language Pathologists.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An applicant shall have obtained a passing score on the National Examination in Speech-Language Pathology.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If a passing score on the National Examination in Speech-Language Pathology was not obtained within the 5 years before applying for licensure, the applicant shall fulfill one or more of the following requirements as approved by the Board:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Provide evidence that the applicant has practiced in speech-language pathology for 3 of the 5 years before applying for licensure;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Complete a period of supervised practice equivalent to that required of a limited license; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Hold a current speech-language pathologist license in another state and submit proof of continuing education as stated in <cite path="|10|41|03|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite> for the time period not practicing.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Fees for Licensure.</heading>
    <text>The fees for licensure shall be nonrefundable and may not be prorated. A license shall become effective on the date of issue.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Renewal of Licensure.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Limited Licensure. A limited license shall be effective for 1 year from the date of issue and may be renewed once for one additional year on Board approval. The Board will renew a limited license if the limited licensee:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Has not yet passed the national examination;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Has a part-time supervised post-graduate position requiring additional weeks of employment; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Has a reason for renewal of the limited license that is acceptable to the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Full Licensure.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A license shall be renewed on or before May 31 of the year in which it expires.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The applicant for license renewal is required to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Maintain evidence of satisfactory completion of continuing education requirements; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For an audiologist or hearing aid dispenser, submit proof of calibration for each audiometer in use within the previous 12-month period.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A licensee who fails to complete the continuing education requirements within the time frame specified under <cite path="|10|41|03|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite> may be subject to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Informal or formal discipline for failure to meet the requirements; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A monetary fine not to exceed $250.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A licensee shall undergo a new criminal records history check as set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|2-303">Health Occupations Article, §2-303</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland, every three renewal cycles or every 6 years.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Failure to Renew a License. A licensee who has failed to renew a license to practice in this State by June 30 of the year in which the license is due to be renewed is prohibited from practicing in this State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the Board determines that a licensee has practiced in this State after the license has expired, the Board may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Order the licensee to immediately cease and desist practice in this State until the license has been reinstated by the Board; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Take action as follows against a licensee for unprofessional conduct if it determines that the licensee practiced in this State after the license has expired:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Provide the licensee with a settlement conference; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Charge the licensee with unprofessional conduct as provided in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|2314">Health Occupations Article, §2314(10), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, for practicing without a license.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Continuing Education.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Required Continuing Education Units.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within the 2-year renewal period immediately preceding the licensee's application for renewal, the licensee shall earn 30 continuing education units (CEUs) as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A minimum of 20 CEUs in the area of licensure that includes a minimum of 1 CEU in each of the following areas:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Cultural competency; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Ethics;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>No more than 10 CEUs in areas related to speech-language pathology or audiology or both, including practice management, that includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Supervision;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Billing; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Interdisciplinary collaboration; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Related training that does not include annual training requirements for:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Job orientation;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Job maintenance; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Other general training or information related to human health.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>It is recommended that a licensee applying for the renewal of a license successfully complete, within the 2-year licensing period as a part of the required 30 hours of Board-approved continuing education programs, a minimum of 2 CEUs in the area of supervision.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Within the 2-year renewal period immediately preceding the licensee's application for renewal, an individual licensed as both an audiologist and a speech-language pathologist shall earn 40 CEUs as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A minimum of 15 CEUs in each area of licensure that includes a minimum of 1 CEU in each of the following areas:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Cultural competency; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Ethics;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>No more than 10 CEUs in areas related to speech-language pathology and audiology, including practice management, that includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Supervision;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Billing; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Interdisciplinary collaboration; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Related training that does not include annual training requirements for:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Job orientation;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Job maintenance; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Other general training or information related to human health.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>It is recommended that a licensee applying for the renewal of a license successfully complete, within the 2-year licensing period as a part of the required 30 hours of Board-approved continuing education programs, a minimum of 2 CEUs in the area of supervision.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Board shall notify the licensee 60 days before the date the license expires.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Time Period for CEUs.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An audiologist licensee shall complete the required CEUs within the 2-year renewal period.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A speech-language pathologist licensee shall complete the required CEUs within the 2-year period immediately preceding the license expiration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An individual licensed as both an audiologist and a speech-language pathologist shall complete the required CEUs within the 2-year period immediately preceding the license expiration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Continuing education units may not be carried over from one renewal period to the next.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If the licensee presents evidence that failure to obtain the required CEUs was due to circumstances beyond the licensee's control, the Board may grant an extension of time to obtain the required CEUs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>If the Board grants an extension of time to obtain the required CEUs, the Board may require the licensee to obtain, as additional CEUs, not more than twice the number of missing credits in order to renew the license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The Board may reduce or waive the continuing education requirements for an individual under extenuating circumstances.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The Board shall waive all continuing education requirements for a speech-language pathologist or audiologist obtaining full licensure within 6 months of the renewal cycle. This includes newly licensed individuals, reinstatements, and transfers from other states.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Continuing education units shall be prorated for licensees holding a full license for at least 6 months but less than 2 years during the renewal cycle. This includes newly licensed individuals, reinstatements, and transfers from other states.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Approval of Continuing Education Programs.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board shall establish a committee to evaluate and approve continuing education programs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Providers of continuing education shall give a participant a certificate of completion which includes the following information:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Date of completion;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Course title;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Name of participant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Name of provider; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Number of hours.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Not later than 30 days before a program, a provider of continuing education shall submit to the Board a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Request for approval of the program, using the form available on the Board’s website; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Biography for each course presenter.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Individual Approval of Program.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If a provider has not requested prior approval of a program, a licensee may apply to the Board for approval of continuing education units for the program, using the approved form available on the Board’s website.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Not later than 30 days after a program, the licensee shall submit to the Board a request for approval of continuing education units for individual participation, using the approved form available on the Board’s website.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If the activity directly concerns the practice of speech-language pathology or audiology, the licensee is not required to submit a request for approval of the program to the Board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The following are examples of areas in which CEUs may be earned in activities concerning speech-language pathology and audiology:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Academic course work in areas of speech-language pathology or audiology, or both, or related disciplines, taken at accredited colleges or universities where, along with the submission of an unofficial transcript and course description<em>:</em></text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>15 CEU credit hours will be awarded for each 3 credit course earned;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>10 CEU credit hours will be awarded for each 2 credit course earned; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>5 CEU credit hours will be awarded for each 1 credit course earned;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Lectures and scheduled courses or workshops at local, regional, national, or international conferences concerning speech-language pathology or audiology, or both;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Attendance at lectures, workshops, or in-service programs;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Other professional activities such as presentations, books, papers, or publications, where:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>1 hour of CEU credit may be earned by the presenter for each hour of presentation of a program, with a maximum of 3 CEUs;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>10 hours of CEU credit may be earned for a professional or scientific paper prepared by the licensee or certificate holder, with a maximum per paper of 10 CEUs for the first author, 8 CEUs for the second author, 6 CEUs for the third author, and 4 CEUs for all other authors;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Authoring of a book chapter may earn a maximum of 10 CEUs, only in the year of publication; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Editing or reviewing of a scientific or professional journal recognized by the Board, with a maximum of 8 CEUs for each year of service; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Attendance at regularly scheduled Board meetings where:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>1 hour of an open session of a Board meeting equals 1 hour of continuing education credit; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Not more than 5 hours of continuing education credit may be earned in a single continuing education cycle.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Independent Study Activities.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>CEUs may be earned through independent study activities including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Professional journals which include post-tests to document completion;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Audio or video tapes of programs approved by the Board for continuing education credit with a post-test;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Internet programs approved by the Board for continuing education credit with a post-test; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Other independent study activities approved by the Board.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The licensee shall complete the post-test successfully for CEUs to be granted.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If proof of passing the post-test is obtained, there is no limit on the number of credit hours that may be earned through independent study activities.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Pro Bono Work.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>CEUs may be earned for pro bono work performed outside of a place of employment at the rate of 1 Maryland CEU  per hour of Board-approved CEU activity, up to a maximum of 10 CEU credits in any single 2-year period.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The licensee shall obtain approval from the Board for all pro bono work.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The licensee shall provide the Board a written description of the proposed work not later than 60 days before beginning pro bono work. The description shall include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The place where the pro bono work will take place;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The type of work to be performed;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The number of hours of actual work to be performed for which the licensee desires CEU credit;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>A description of how the work will enhance the licensee's ongoing education; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>A statement guaranteeing that the licensee will not receive any financial gain from the work provided.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The licensee shall submit a written statement to the Board from the facility verifying the number of pro bono work hours completed.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>CEU credit may not be granted for work that did not receive prior approval from the Board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Documentation of CEUs.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A licensee shall submit a signed form to the Board via mail or by electronic means attesting to the licensee’s completion of the required CEUs at the time of license renewal.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A licensee shall retain supporting documents for inspection by the Board for 4 years after the date of renewal.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If a licensee submits the renewal form after the expiration date, the Board shall assess a late fee and may audit the licensee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Failure to meet continuing education requirements or failure to substantiate CEUs submitted upon request of the Board may result in suspension, revocation, or denial of licensure or other disciplinary action by the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Continuing Education Audit Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At each renewal period, the Board shall audit 10 percent of the renewal applications.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Board members shall be audited for the required CEUs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Board shall send notification of audit to licensees to be audited.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The licensee being audited shall submit to the Board official certificates or transcripts via mail or by electronic means showing evidence of the continuing education hours required for renewal by the date indicated on the audit notification.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Board may take formal disciplinary action against the licensee, if the licensee:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Submits a false statement of continuing education; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Fails to submit the required documents by the date indicated on an audit notification.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Reactivation.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a license has been in an inactive status for no more than three 2-year renewal cycles of inactivity, the licensee may apply for reactivation of the inactive license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Board shall reactivate the license if the speech-pathologist or audiologist:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Submits to the Board satisfactory proof of completion of at least 30 hours of CEU activity for every 2-year cycle of inactivity; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Pays to the Board the renewal fee and the reactivation fee set by the Board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Reinstatement Requirement.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a license has been expired for 5 years or less, a speech-language pathologist or audiologist may apply for reinstatement of the expired license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Board shall reinstate the license if the speech-language pathologist or audiologist:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Submits to the Board satisfactory proof of completion of at least 30 hours of CEU activity for every 2-year cycle of inactivity; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Pays to the Board the renewal fee and the reinstatement fee set by the Board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Reapplication Requirement.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board may not reinstate the license of a speech-language pathologist or audiologist who fails to apply for reinstatement of the license within 5 years after the license expires.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The speech-language pathologist or audiologist whose license has been expired for more than 5 years may become licensed if the speech-language pathologist or audiologist:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Meets the current requirements for obtaining a license;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Submits to the Board satisfactory proof of completion of  at least 30 hours of CEU activity for every 2-year cycle of inactivity, not to exceed 100 hours; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Pays to the Board the application fee set by the Board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Licensee Responsibilities.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A licensee shall notify the Board in writing of a change of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Mailing address within 30 days after the change;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Name within 30 days after the change; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Email address within 30 days after the change if the licensee has previously submitted an email address to the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A licensee who fails to comply with the requirements of this regulation may be subject to disciplinary action.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Incomplete Applications.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If an incomplete application is submitted to the Board, the Board shall notify the applicant within 30 days after receipt of an incomplete application of the materials that are required.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An application is not complete until all required material, including the application fee and supporting documentation, is received by the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the applicant fails to provide the required documentation within 1 year of receipt of the initial receipt, the Board may administratively close the application.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An applicant whose application is administratively closed may reapply and submit with the new application proof of compliance with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>This subtitle; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|2-205">2-205</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|2-302">2-302</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|2-302">2-302</cite>.2, 2-304, 2-305, 2-308, 2-310, 2-310.2, 2-311(c), 2-312 (b), 2-314(11), and 2-314.9, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1980-03-21">Effective date: March 21, 1980 (7:6 Md. R. 609)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-12-19"><cite path="|10|41|03|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective December 19, 1994 (21:25 Md. R. 2106)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-12-19"><cite path="|10|41|03|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective December 19, 1994 (21:25 Md. R. 2106)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-08-05"><cite path="|10|41|03|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective October 20, 2008 (35:20 Md. R. 1824); March 23, 2009 (36:6 Md. R. 492); April 18, 2011 (38:8 Md. R. 506); August 5, 2024 (51:15 Md. R. 708)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-08-05"><cite path="|10|41|03|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective December 19, 1994 (21:25 Md. R. 2106); August 5, 2024 (51:15 Md. R. 708)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-05-19"><cite path="|10|41|03|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective January 11, 2008 (35:3 Md. R. 286); amended permanently effective May 19, 2008 (35:10 Md. R. 972)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-06-20"><cite path="|10|41|03|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite> amended effective November 7, 1983 (10:22 Md. R. 1966); June 20, 2016 (43:12 Md. R. 667)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-12-11"><cite path="|10|41|03|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite>, B amended effective December 11, 2003 (30:24 Md. R. 1742)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-10-20"><cite path="|10|41|03|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite>, D amended effective October 20, 2008 (35:21 Md. R. 1824)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-03-17"><cite path="|10|41|03|.03|D.">Regulation .03D</cite> amended effective September 17, 2012 (39:18 Md. R. 1197); March 17, 2014 (41:5 Md. R. 347)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-12-19"><cite path="|10|41|03|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective November 7, 1983 (10:22 Md. R. 1966); December 19, 1994 (21:25 Md. R. 2106)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-12-11"><cite path="|10|41|03|.05|A.">Regulation .05A</cite>, amended effective December 11, 2003 (30:24 Md. R. 1742)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-06-08"><cite path="|10|41|03|.05|B.">Regulation .05B</cite> amended effective October 28, 2013 (40:21 Md. R. 1775); June 8, 2015 (42:11 Md. R. 725)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-08-05"><cite path="|10|41|03|.05|B.">Regulation .05B</cite>, D amended effective August 5, 2024 (51:15 Md. R. 708)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-06-08"><cite path="|10|41|03|.05|C.">Regulation .05C</cite>, D adopted effective June 8, 2015 (42:11 Md. R. 725)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1983-11-07"><cite path="|10|41|03|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective November 7, 1983 (10:22 Md. R. 1966);</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-12-19"><cite path="|10|41|03|.06">Regulation .06</cite> repealed and new Regulation .06 adopted effective December 19, 1994 (21:25 Md. R. 2106)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-08-05"><cite path="|10|41|03|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective December 11, 2003 (30:24 Md. R. 1742); August 5, 2024 (51:15 Md. R. 708)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-04-02"><cite path="|10|41|03|.06|A.">Regulation .06A</cite> amended effective May 30, 2011 (38:11 Md. R. 672); April 2, 2012 (39:6 Md. R. 409)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-04-02"><cite path="|10|41|03|.06|B.">Regulation .06B</cite> amended effective January 28, 2008 (35:2 Md. R. 127); March 23, 2009 (36:6 Md. R. 492); September 19, 2011 (38:19 Md. R. 1147); April 2, 2012 (39:6 Md. R. 409)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-01-07"><cite path="|10|41|03|.06|C.">Regulation .06C</cite> amended effective March 23, 2009 (36:6 Md. R. 492); January 7, 2013 (39:26 Md. R. 1665)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-06-20"><cite path="|10|41|03|.07">Regulation .07</cite> adopted effective June 20, 2016 (43:12 Md. R. 667)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-02-27"><cite path="|10|41|03|.08">Regulation .08</cite> adopted effective February 27, 2017 (44:4 Md. R. 255)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
