<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Music Therapy</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter governs all persons licensed as music therapists in the State.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Board” means the State Board of Examiners for Audiologists, Hearing Aid Dispensers, Speech-Language Pathologists, and Music Therapists.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“CBMT-certified” means a music therapist who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is currently certified by the Certification Board for Music Therapists; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has completed the educational and clinical training requirements established by the American Music Therapy Association.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Individualized music therapy treatment plan” means a music therapy treatment plan for a client that identifies the goals, objectives, and potential strategies for the music therapy services appropriate for the client using music therapy interventions, including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Music improvisation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Receptive music listening;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Songwriting;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Lyric discussion;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Music and imagery;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Music performance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Learning through music; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Movement to music.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Licensed professional music therapist” means an individual who is licensed by the Board to engage in the practice of music therapy.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Practice of music therapy” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|2-4">Health Occupations Article, §2-4</cite>A-01, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|41|05|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Licensure Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>To qualify for a license, an applicant shall be an individual who meets the requirements of this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be of good moral character;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Be at least 18 years old;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Be a CBMT-certified music therapist;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Provide proof of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Passing the examination for certification offered by the Certification Board for Music Therapists (CBMT) or any successor organization approved by the Board; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Being transitioned into Board licensure and that the applicant is currently a CBMT-certified music therapist;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Hold a bachelor’s degree or higher in music therapy, or its equivalent, including clinical training, from an educational program that is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Approved by the American Music Therapy Association or any successor organization; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Within an accredited college or university;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Be in good standing based on a review of the applicant’s music therapy licensure, certification, or registration history in other jurisdictions, including a review of any disciplinary actions in the practice of music therapy; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Meet any other requirements established by the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>To apply for a license, an applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Submit an application to the Board on the form that the Board requires;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Pay to the Board the application fee set by the Board; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Submit to a criminal history records check in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|2">Health Occupations Article, §2</cite>–303.1, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Board shall issue a license to any applicant who meets the requirements of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 2, Subtitle 4A, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text><cite path="10|41|05|.03|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> and provides evidence satisfactory to the Board that the applicant is licensed and in good standing as a music therapist in another jurisdiction where the qualifications required are equal to or greater than those required in this subtitle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Board shall include on each license that the Board issues:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The full name of the licensed music therapist;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The dates of issuance and expiration; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A license number.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A music therapist license authorizes the licensee to engage in the practice of music therapy while the license is effective.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|41|05|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Renewal of Licensure.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A license expires on a date set by the Board unless the license is renewed for an additional term as set forth under <cite path="10|41|05|.04|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A license may not be renewed for a term longer than 2 years.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>At least 1 month before a license expires, the Board shall send to the licensee, by first-class mail or email to the last known address of the licensee, a renewal notice that states the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Expiration date;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Due date by which the renewal application shall be received by the Board for the renewal to be issued and mailed before the license expires; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Amount of the renewal fee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Before a license expires, the licensee periodically may renew the license for an additional term if the licensee:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Otherwise is entitled to be licensed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Pays to the Board a renewal fee set by the Board; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Submits to the Board:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A renewal application on the form that the Board requires; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Satisfactory evidence of compliance with any continuing education requirements established by the Board under <cite path="|10|41|05|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A licensee shall undergo a new criminal records history check as set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|2-303">Health Occupations Article, §2-303</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland, every three renewal cycles or every 6 years.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Continuing Education Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The continuing education requirements shall include proof of completion of at least 40 hours of continuing education in a program approved by CBMT or any successor organization approved by the Board that includes:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A minimum of 1 CEU in the area of cultural competency;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A minimum of 1 CEU in the area of ethics;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Supervision;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Billing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Interdisciplinary collaboration; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Related training that does not include annual training requirements for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Job orientation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Job maintenance; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Other general training or information related to human health.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>It is recommended that a licensee applying for the renewal of a license successfully complete, within the 2-year licensing period as a part of the required 40 hours of Board-approved continuing education programs, a minimum of 2 CEUs in the area of supervision.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Board shall renew the license of each licensee who meets the requirements of Regulations .04 and .05 of this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|41|05|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Inactive Status, Reactivation, Reinstatement, and Reapplication.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Inactive Status.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board shall place a licensee on inactive status if the licensee submits to the Board:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An application for inactive status on the form that the Board requires; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The inactive status fee set by the Board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Board shall license an individual on inactive status who applies for a license if the individual meets:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The renewal requirements of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|2">Health Occupations Article, §2</cite>–4A–10, Annotated Code of Maryland; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Any continuing education requirements established by the Board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Board may not require payment of a late fee by an individual as a condition to licensing set forth under <cite path="10|41|05|.06|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Reactivation.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a license has been in an inactive status for no more than two 2-year renewal cycles of inactivity, the licensee may apply for reactivation of the inactive license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Board shall reactivate the license if the music therapist:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Submits to the Board satisfactory proof of completion of at least 40 hours of CEU activity, in a program approved by CBMT or any successor organization, for every 2-year cycle of inactivity; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Pays to the Board the renewal fee and the reactivation fee set by the Board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Reinstatement.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a license has been expired for 5 years or less, a music therapist may apply for reinstatement of the expired license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Board shall reinstate the license if the music therapist:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Submits to the Board satisfactory proof of completion of continuing education hours required of a music therapist on active status during the period of inactivity; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Pays to the Board the renewal fee and the reinstatement fee set by the Board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Reapplication.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board may not reinstate the license of a music therapist who fails to apply for reinstatement of the license within 5 years after the license expires.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The music therapist whose license has been expired for more than 5 years may become licensed if the music therapist:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Meets the current requirements for obtaining a license;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Submits to the Board satisfactory proof of completion of continuing education hours required of a music therapist on active status during the period of inactivity; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Pays to the Board the application fee set by the Board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Licensee Responsibilities.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A licensee shall notify the Board in writing of a change of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Mailing address within 30 days after the change;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Name within 30 days after the change; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Email address within 30 days after the change if the licensee has previously submitted an email address to the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A licensee who fails to comply with the requirements of this regulation may be subject to disciplinary action.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|2-101">2-101</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|2-201">2-201</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|2-202">2-202</cite>(a), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|2-206">2-206</cite>(a) and (d)(2), 2-501, and 2-4A-01—2-4A-25, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1997-03-24">Effective date: March 24, 1997 (24:6 Md. R. 485)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-11-10"><cite path="|10|41|05|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective November 10, 2003 (30:22 Md. R. 1582)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-11-10"><cite path="|10|41|05|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite>, B amended effective November 10, 2003 (30:22 Md. R. 1582)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-11-10"><cite path="|10|41|05|.04">Regulation .04</cite> adopted effective November 10, 2003 (30:22 Md. R. 1582)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-03-23" discontinuity="true">Chapter repealed effective March 23, 2009 (36:6 Md. R. 492)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-08-05" discontinuity="true">New Regulations <cite path="|10|41|05|.01">.01</cite>-<cite path="|10|41|05|.07">.07</cite> adopted under new chapter Music Therapy effective  August 5, 2024 (51:15 Md. R. 708)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
