<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>16</num>
  <heading>Carrier Provider Panels — Application Process</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Applicability.</heading>
    <text>This chapter applies to all insurers, nonprofit health service plans, health maintenance organizations, dental plans, and to any other person or organization which utilizes a provider panel and which provides health benefit plans subject to regulation in this State.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Carrier.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Carrier" means:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>An insurer;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A nonprofit health service plan;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A health maintenance organization;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>A dental plan organization; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Any other person or organization that provides health benefit plans subject to State regulation.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Carrier" includes an entity that arranges a provider panel for a carrier.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Provider" means a health care practitioner or a group of health care practitioners licensed or otherwise authorized by law to provide health care services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Provider Panel.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Provider panel" means those providers with which a carrier contracts to provide health care services to the carrier's enrollees under the carrier's health benefit plan.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Provider panel" does not include an arrangement between a carrier and providers in which a provider may participate solely on the basis of the provider's contracting with the carrier to provide services at a discounted fee-for-service rate.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|10|16|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Requirements for Application Process.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A carrier that utilizes a provider panel shall establish written procedures for reviewing applications for participation in the provider panel.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A carrier that utilizes a provider panel shall, upon request, make its applications publicly available.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The form of application:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall include instructions for completion of the application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shall provide a specifically designated space for dating the receipt of the application by the carrier; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Shall comply with federal and State laws concerning the Americans with Disability Act.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A carrier shall maintain an application log which, at a minimum, provides the following information:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Name of the provider requesting or submitting the application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Date the provider requested an application, if applicable;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Date the application is sent or delivered to the provider, if applicable;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Date the application is received from the provider;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Date the application is returned to the provider with a request for additional information to complete the application, if applicable;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Date of receipt by the carrier of an application previously returned for additional information, if applicable;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Date that the provider is notified of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Rejection, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Carrier's intent to continue the credentialing process; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Date after completion of credentialing that the provider is notified of acceptance or rejection in the provider panel.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The log shall be available for inspection by the Commissioner.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Notice.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A carrier shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If the carrier maintains a web site:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Post on the web site a notice of how to apply to the carrier's provider panel; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Provide, on request, a paper copy of the notice of how to apply to the carrier's provider panel; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the carrier does not maintain a web site, provide on request a paper copy of the notice of how to apply to the carrier's provider panel.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The notice required pursuant to <cite path="31|10|16|.03|F.|(1)">§F(1) of this regulation</cite> shall include relevant addresses and telephone numbers for contact purposes.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Application Fees.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A carrier may charge a reasonable fee for any application that a provider submits to the carrier.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The fee shall be nonrefundable and uniform for all applicants within a practice specialty.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The fee may not exceed $75 for each provider application.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A carrier may not charge additional fees for processing an application which was returned because of insufficient information.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Document Retention.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A carrier shall maintain its provider application log for a minimum of 3 years or until its next market conduct examination, whichever occurs last.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A carrier shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Date stamp each application received from a provider upon initial receipt; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Maintain a legible copy of each application, and any correspondence regarding that application, for a minimum of 3 years or until its next market conduct examination, whichever occurs last.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Insurance Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|2-109">2-109</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-112">15-112</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1996-06-17">Effective date: June 17, 1996 (23:12 Md. R. 870)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-09-07" discontinuity="true">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|09.31.13">COMAR 09.31.13</cite> to <cite path="|31.10.16">COMAR 31.10.16</cite> effective September 7, 1998 (25:18 Md. R. 1439)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-04-21"><cite path="|31|10|16|.03|C.">Regulation .03C</cite> amended effective April 21, 2008 (35:8 Md. R. 812)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-05-09"><cite path="|31|10|16|.03|D.">Regulation .03D</cite> amended effective May 9, 2016 (43:9 Md. R. 532)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-12-23"><cite path="|31|10|16|.03|F.">Regulation .03F</cite> amended effective December 23, 2002 (29:25 Md. R. 1984)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-12-06"><cite path="|31|10|16|.05|B.">Regulation .05B</cite> amended effective December 6, 2018 (45:24 Md. R. 1164)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
