<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>35</num>
  <heading>Domestic Partner Coverage</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>The purpose of this chapter is to establish:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The use of the term domestic partner in a contract; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The proof that a carrier may use to determine if an individual is a domestic partner of another individual.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Carrier" means an insurer, a nonprofit health service plan, or a health maintenance organization.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Commissioner" means the Maryland Insurance Commissioner.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Contract" means either of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A health insurance contract that is issued or delivered in Maryland by an insurer or a nonprofit health service plan that provides inpatient hospital, medical, or surgical benefits to individuals or groups on an expense-incurred basis; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A contract issued or delivered in Maryland by a health maintenance organization to individuals or groups.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Health maintenance organization" has the meaning stated in Health-General Article, §19-701, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Insurer" has the meaning defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|1-101">Insurance Article, §1-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Nonprofit health service plan" means a person who has received a certificate of authority from the Commissioner to act as a nonprofit health service plan in the State.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|10|35|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Domestic Partner Coverage.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The term "domestic partner" in a contract or rider to a contract shall include individuals of the same and the opposite sex.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If an individual makes an application to include a domestic partner or a child dependent of a domestic partner as a dependent under a contract, the carrier may require the individual to submit not more than the following as proof of the domestic partner relationship:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The affidavit described in <cite path="31|10|35|.03|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Proof that the individual meets one criteria from <cite path="31|10|35|.03|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Proof that the individual meets one criteria from <cite path="31|10|35|.03|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Affidavit Attesting to Domestic Partnership.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An affidavit signed by both the insured and the domestic partner shall include only the following attestations:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Both individuals are 18 years old or older;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Neither individual is related to the other by blood or marriage within four degrees of consanguinity under civil law rule;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Neither individual is married or in a civil union or domestic partnership with another individual;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Both individuals have been financially interdependent for at least 6 consecutive months prior to application in which each individual contributes to some extent to the other individual's maintenance and support with the intention of remaining in the relationship indefinitely; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Both individuals share a common primary residence.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Carriers may develop their own affidavits or may use the affidavit set forth in <cite path="31|10|35|.03|C.|(3)">§C(3) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The following is a sample affidavit that complies with the requirements of <cite path="31|10|35|.03|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite>:<strong>AFFIDAVIT OF DOMESTIC PARTNERSHIP</strong></text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <aftertext>
      <strong>Instructions:</strong>
    </aftertext>
    <aftertext>In order to enroll your Domestic Partner for medical benefits, you and your Domestic Partner must sign this Affidavit of Domestic Partnership. Please carefully read this Affidavit and the information below.</aftertext>
    <aftertext>Both you and your Domestic Partner must certify that you are Domestic Partners by completing and signing below.</aftertext>
    <aftertext>I, {Name of Subscriber} and {Name of Partner} certify that we are Domestic Partners and that we:</aftertext>
    <para>
      <num>1.</num>
      <text>Are at least 18 years old;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>2.</num>
      <text>Are not related to the other by blood or marriage within four degrees of consanguinity under civil law rule;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>3.</num>
      <text>Are not married or in a civil union or domestic partnership with another individual;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>4.</num>
      <text>Have been financially interdependent for at least 6 consecutive months prior to application in which each individual contributes to some extent to the other individual's maintenance and support with the intention of remaining in the relationship indefinitely; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>5.</num>
      <text>Share a common primary residence.</text>
    </para>
    <aftertext>We understand that a civil action may be brought against us for losses, including reasonable attorney fees and court costs, because of willful falsification of information in this Affidavit of Domestic Partnership.</aftertext>
    <aftertext>We understand that willful falsification of information contained in this Affidavit may result in our termination of enrollment.</aftertext>
    <aftertext>We certify under penalty of perjury under applicable state laws, that the foregoing is true and accurate to the best of our knowledge.</aftertext>
    <aftertext>_________________________________________________________________________</aftertext>
    <aftertext>Signature of Subscriber	Date</aftertext>
    <aftertext>_________________________________________________________________________</aftertext>
    <aftertext>Signature of Domestic Partner	Date</aftertext>
    <para>
      <num proof="done">D.</num>
      <text>The carrier shall accept any one of the following documents as proof of a common primary residence between domestic partners:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Common ownership of the primary residence via joint deed or mortgage agreement;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Common leasehold interest in the primary residence;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Driver's license or State-issued identification listing a common address; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Utility or other household bill with both the name of the insured and the name of the domestic partner appearing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The carrier shall accept any one of the following documents as proof of financial interdependence between domestic partners:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Joint bank account or credit account;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Designation as the primary beneficiary for life insurance or retirement benefits of the domestic partner;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Designation as primary beneficiary under the domestic partner's will;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Mutual assignments of valid durable powers of attorney under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="get|13-601">Estates and Trusts Article, §13-601, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Mutual valid written advanced directives under Health-General Article, §5-601 et seq., Annotated Code of Maryland, approving the other domestic partner as health care agent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Joint ownership or holding of investments; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Joint ownership or lease of a motor vehicle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A carrier may require a group policyholder to obtain the documents specified under this chapter prior to enrolling a domestic partner or a child dependent of a domestic partner.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Insurance Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|2-109">2-109</cite>(a)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|1">1</cite>) and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-403">15-403</cite>.2, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-01-10">Regulations <cite path="|31|10|35|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|31|10|35|.04">.04</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective January 10, 2008 (35:3 Md. R. 287); emergency status expired July 8, 2008</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-07-08">Regulations <cite path="|31|10|35|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|31|10|35|.03">.03</cite> adopted effective July 8, 2008 (35:12 Md. R. 1122)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
