<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>42</num>
  <heading>Continuity of Health Care Notice</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter applies to each:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Receiving carrier that issues or delivers individual or group health benefit plans in Maryland; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Receiving managed care organization that enrolls Program recipients in Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Carrier” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An insurer authorized to sell health insurance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A nonprofit health service plan;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A health maintenance organization;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A dental plan organization; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Any other entity providing a plan of health insurance, health benefits, or health services authorized under the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin">Insurance Article of the Annotated Code of Maryland</cite> or the Affordable Care Act.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Enrollee” means a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Person entitled to health care benefits from a carrier; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Program recipient who is enrolled in a managed care organization.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Health benefit plan” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-140">Insurance Article, §15-140, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Managed care organization” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A certified health maintenance organization that is authorized to receive medical assistance prepaid capitation payments;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A corporation that:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Is a managed care system that is authorized to receive medical assistance prepaid capitation payments;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Enrolls only Program recipients or individuals or families served under the Maryland Children’s Health Program; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Is subject to the requirements of Health-General Article, §15-102.4, Annotated Code of Maryland.; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A prepaid dental plan that receives fees to manage dental services.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Program recipient” means an individual who receives benefits under the Maryland Medical Assistance Program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Receiving carrier” means the carrier that issues the new health benefit plan when an enrollee transitions from another carrier or a managed care organization.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Receiving managed care organization” means the managed care organization that accepts the enrollee when the enrollee transitions from another managed care organization or a carrier.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Relinquishing carrier” means a carrier that issued the prior health benefit plan when an enrollee transitions to a new carrier or a managed care organization.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“Relinquishing managed care organization” means a managed care organization in which an enrollee had been enrolled prior to the enrollee’s transition to a new managed care organization or a carrier.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>“Transitioning enrollee” means an enrollee:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Who has an effective date of coverage with a receiving carrier or a receiving managed care organization on or after January 1, 2015, under a contract that is issued or renewed on or after January 1, 2015; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Whose coverage under the receiving carrier or receiving managed care organization began within 1 month of the date coverage terminated under the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Health benefit plan with a relinquishing carrier; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Relinquishing managed care organization.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|10|42|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Requirement to Provide Continuity of Health Care Notice.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A receiving carrier shall send a transitioning enrollee the Continuity of Health Care Notice set forth in <cite path="|31|10|42|.04|A.">Regulation .04A of this chapter</cite>:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="31|10|42|.03|A.|(2)">§A(2) of this regulation</cite>, within 30 days of the enrollee’s effective date of coverage; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the enrollee’s coverage is made effective retroactively, within 30 days of the date the receiving carrier is notified of the enrollment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A receiving managed care organization shall send a transitioning enrollee the Continuity of Health Care Notice set forth in <cite path="|31|10|42|.04|B.">Regulation .04B of this chapter</cite>:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="31|10|42|.03|B.|(2)">§B(2) of this regulation</cite>, within 30 days of the enrollee’s effective date of coverage; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the enrollee’s coverage is made effective retroactively, within 30 days of the date the receiving managed care organization is notified of the enrollment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Continuity of Health Care Notices shall be in the language and format described in <cite path="|31|10|42|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite> in not less than 12-point type.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Continuity of Health Care Notice.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The following form is to be used by receiving carriers as the Continuity of Health Care Notice required by <cite path="|31|10|42|.03|A.">Regulation .03A of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The following form is to be used by receiving managed care organizations as the Continuity of Health Care Notice required by <cite path="|31|10|42|.03|B.">Regulation .03B of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      <text>
        <cite path="31|10|42|attachments|31.10.42.04-forms">FORMS AT END OF CHAPTER</cite>
      </text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Insurance Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|2-109">2-109</cite>(a)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|1">1</cite>), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-140">15-140</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-10">15-10</cite>D-01, Annotated Code of Maryland and Ch. 159, §3, Acts of 2013</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-04-27">Regulations <cite path="|31|10|42|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|31|10|42|.04">.04</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective January 1, 2015 (42:1 Md. R. 16); adopted permanently effective April 27, 2015 (42:8 Md. R. 608)</annotation>
  </annotations>
  <attachments>
    <attachment name="31.10.42.04-forms" url="/us/md/exec/comar/initial-attachments/31.10.42.04-forms.pdf"/>
  </attachments>
</container>
