<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Martin State Airport</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Words not specifically defined in this regulation which relate to aeronautical practices, processes, and equipment, will be construed according to their general usage in the aviation industry.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Abandon" means forsake, desert, give up and surrender one's claim or right.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Administration" means the Maryland Aviation Administration of the Department of Transportation, established pursuant to the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|5-201">Transportation Article, §5-201, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Aircraft" means any contrivance now known or hereafter designed, invented, or used for navigation or flight in the air or space, except a parachute or other contrivance used primarily as safety equipment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Air operations area" means any area of the Airport used or intended to be used for landing, taking off, or surface maneuvering of aircraft.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Airport" means Martin State Airport, owned by the State and operated by the Maryland Aviation Administration, as now existing or as the same may hereafter be developed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Airport Director" means the Airport Director, Maryland Aviation Administration, Martin State Airport, or the Airport Director's designated representative.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Authorized" means acting under or pursuant to a written contract, permit, or other evidence of right issued by the Maryland Aviation Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Bus" means a motor vehicle operated by an appropriately authorized agency on a fixed route and predetermined schedule to and from the Airport.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Combustible liquid" means any liquid that has a closed cup flash point at or above 100°F.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Commercial activity" means the sale, exchange, trading, buying, merchandising, hiring, marketing, promotion, or selling of commodities, goods, services, or property of any kind, or any revenue-producing activity, on the Airport.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Control tower" means an air traffic control tower located at the Airport.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>"Courtesy car" means a car operated to and from the Airport by hotel, motel, public parking firms, car rental companies, or other business specifically for the transportation or convenience of their patrons or for the execution of any part of a private business transaction.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>"Curbside" means the curb of the roadway adjacent to the Terminal Building.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>"Department" means the Department of Transportation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>"Domestic animal" means any animal of a species usually domesticated in the United States and customarily found in the home.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>"Executive Director" means the Executive Director of the Maryland Aviation Administration, whose office is established pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|5-202">Transportation Article, §5-202</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland, or the Executive Director's duly authorized representative.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>Fire Marshal.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Fire marshal" means an individual from the Airport Fire Marshal's Office or a fire prevention inspector who is employed by the BWI Airport Fire and Rescue Department.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Fire marshal" includes any designated representative of the State Fire Marshal's Office.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>"Fire Prevention Code" means the State Fire Prevention Code as defined in <cite path="|29.06.01">COMAR 29.06.01</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>"Flammable liquids" means any liquid  that has a closed cup flash point below 100°F.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>"Garbage" means any refuse, food, trash, or rubbish.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>"Grounding or bonding" means providing a conductive path to equalize the potential static electricity between fueling equipment and aircraft by use of a cable.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>"IBC" has the meaning stated in <cite path="05.02.07.03|B.|(7)">COMAR 05.02.07.03B(7)</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>"Industrial waste" means any waste product, liquid, gaseous, or solid, derived from industrial activity.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(24)</num>
        <text>"Labeled" means equipment or materials to which has been attached a label, symbol, or other identifying mark of an organization:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>That is acceptable to the authority having jurisdiction and is concerned with product evaluation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>That maintains periodic inspection of production of labeled equipment or materials; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>By whose labeling the manufacturer indicates compliance with appropriate standards or performance in a specified manner.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(25)</num>
        <text>"Law enforcement officer" means any person vested with a police power of arrest under federal, State, county, or city authority, and identifiable by uniform, badge, or other indicia of authority.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(26)</num>
        <text>"Limousine" means any motor vehicle having a rated seating capacity of six or more persons, not including the driver, operating to and from the Airport according to a valid certificate issued by the appropriate governmental agency.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(27)</num>
        <text>"Listed" means equipment, materials, or services included in a list published by an organization:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>That is acceptable to the authority having jurisdiction and concerned with evaluation of products or services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>That maintains periodic inspection of production of listed equipment or materials; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Whose listing states that either the equipment, material, or service meets identified standards or has been tested and found suitable for a specified purpose.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(28)</num>
        <text>"Motor vehicle" means a device in, upon, or by which a person or property may be propelled, moved, or drawn upon land, except a device moved by human or animal power, and except aircraft and devices moved exclusively upon stationary rails or tracks.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(29)</num>
        <text>"Movement area" means the runways, taxiways, and other areas of the Airport that are used for the taxiing, takeoff, and landing of aircraft, except loading ramps and parking areas.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(30)</num>
        <text>"NFPA" has the meaning stated in <cite path="29.06.01.05|B.|(5)">COMAR 29.06.01.05B(5)</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(31)</num>
        <text>"Officer" means a law enforcement officer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(32)</num>
        <text>"Oil" means any substance of vegetable, animal, or mineral origin with an oily consistency, easily liquefiable on warming and soluble in ether but not in water.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(33)</num>
        <text>"Operator" means a person who is in actual physical control of an aircraft or a motor vehicle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(34)</num>
        <text>"Owner" means a person who holds the legal title to an aircraft or motor vehicle; or, if the aircraft or motor vehicle is the subject of a conditional sale or lease with the right of purchase upon performance of the conditions stated in the agreement, and with the immediate right of possession of an aircraft or motor vehicle on the Airport, or, if a mortgagor of an aircraft or motor vehicle is entitled to the possession, then the conditional vendee, lessee, or mortgagor shall be considered the owner for the purpose of these regulations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(35)</num>
        <text>"Parking lot" means any designated parking area such as employee and public areas, including parking structures.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(36)</num>
        <text>"Person" means any individual, firm, partnership, corporation, company, association, or joint stock association, and includes any trustee, receiver, committee, assignee, or other representative or employee thereof.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(37)</num>
        <text>"Regulations" means these regulations as they may be amended and supplemented from time to time.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(38)</num>
        <text>"Restricted area" means Airport areas with access limited to authorized persons only.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(39)</num>
        <text>"Solid waste" means any garbage, refuse, sludge, solid, liquid, semisolid, or contained gaseous materials which are by-products of commercial activity, as defined by <cite path="|26.03.03">COMAR 26.03.03</cite> and <cite path="|26.13.02">26.13.02</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(40)</num>
        <text>"State" means the State of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(41)</num>
        <text>"Sunset" or "sunrise" means the time of sunset or sunrise at the Airport as published by the United States National Weather Service.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(42)</num>
        <text>"Taxicab" means any motor vehicle that carries persons for a fare, usually determined by a meter, and that is appropriately licensed as a taxicab by a proper governmental authority.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(43)</num>
        <text>"Terminal" or "terminal building" means any passenger terminal facility at the Airport, including all roadways and parking facilities associated with the facility.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(44)</num>
        <text>"Toxic material" means any material, liquid, gaseous, or solid substance, containing a poisonous agent.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(45)</num>
        <text>"Traffic" means pedestrians and vehicles, either singly or together, using any Airport area, while they are using it.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(46)</num>
        <text>"Weapon" means a gun, knife (other than a pocketknife, maximum 4-inch blade), blackjack, slingshot, metal knuckles, aerosol irritant projector, or any explosive device except when properly packaged for shipment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(47)</num>
        <text>"Wild animal" means any animal of a species not usually domesticated in the United States or customarily found in the home.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Aircraft Regulations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Negligent Operations Prohibited. Aircraft may not be operated:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At the Airport in a careless or negligent manner;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In disregard of the rights and safety of others;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Without due caution and circumspection; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>At a speed or in a manner which endangers or is likely to endanger persons or property.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Compliance with Orders.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Aeronautical activities shall conform to the current applicable provisions of the Federal Aviation Administration regulations and orders, applicable State law, these regulations, and orders issued by the Administration, the Airport Director, or an air traffic controller on duty in the control tower.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All aircraft operated from the Airport, except aircraft specifically exempt from these requirements by law, shall be registered with the Federal Aviation Administration and shall have a Federal Aviation Administration certificate of airworthiness.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The owner of an aircraft based or hangared at the Airport may not operate or allow the operation of that aircraft without a liability insurance policy in force which covers the owner and the pilot for claims by passengers or other persons for injuries to them and their property which might arise out of the operation of the aircraft.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The liability insurance policy shall provide coverage for at least $50,000 bodily injury per individual, $100,000 bodily injury per accident, and $50,000 property damage protection.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Denial of Use of Airport. The Executive Director may deny the use of the Airport to any pilot in violation of these regulations and shall have the authority to close the Airport or any portion of it to air operations or to any specific aircraft or class of aircraft if, in the Executive Director's opinion, the use of the Airport by the aircraft might endanger persons or property or jeopardize the operational efficiency of the Airport.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Aircraft Accidents.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person operating an aircraft who is involved in an accident on the Airport, resulting in injury to any person or damage to any property, shall, if physically able:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Stop the aircraft at the scene of the accident or as close as possible to it without obstructing other aircraft operations or motor vehicle traffic more than necessary;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Notify the Airport Director and the Federal Aviation Administration;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Then return to and remain at the scene of the accident until he has given a full report of it to the investigating official;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Upon request, exhibit to the investigating officer any permit, license, registration, or other document relevant to the accident or the persons or property involved.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person operating an aircraft who is involved in an accident on the Airport, and the owner of the aircraft, if other than the operator, shall, if physically able, make a full written report of the accident to the Airport Director within 24 hours after the accident, or as soon as possible thereafter, including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The names and addresses of the persons involved;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The registration and license number of the aircraft involved;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The name of the insurance company shown on the liability insurance policy, and the policy or binder number; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Any other information relevant to the accident.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person may not remove from the scene of the accident an aircraft involved in an accident on the Airport until permitted to do so by the Federal Aviation Administration, the National Transportation Safety Board, and the Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A person damaging any airfield lighting equipment or fixtures by means of contact with aircraft shall report the damage to the Airport Director immediately, and shall be fully responsible for the damage.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Removal of Disabled Aircraft.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Aircraft owners, operators, and Airport tenants shall promptly remove disabled aircraft and their parts from the Airport unless required or directed to delay this action by the Administration or a federal agency.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not allow a disabled aircraft to block a runway unnecessarily. When a disabled aircraft is blocking or delaying the opening or use of any portion of a runway, the owner or operator of the aircraft shall make immediate arrangements to have the aircraft moved as soon as the Administration and all appropriate governmental agencies have cleared the move. If that action to remove the aircraft is not initiated as soon as is reasonably possible, or is not progressing at a reasonable rate, the Airport Director may initiate action to have the aircraft moved at the expense and risk of the owner.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Enplaning and Deplaning. A person may not enplane or deplane passengers or cargo at the Airport, except in specific areas designated by the Administration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Cleaning and Maintaining Aircraft. A person may not clean, paint, wash, polish, or otherwise maintain an aircraft at the Airport except in areas and under the conditions designated for this purpose by the Administration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Refusal of Clearance. The Executive Director may prohibit aircraft operations at the Airport when circumstances are considered likely to endanger persons or property, or for any other justifiable reason. The Executive Director or the Airport Director shall have the authority to issue a Notice to Airmen (NOTAM) to close or open the Airport, or any portion of it.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Aircraft Equipment. Aircraft may not be operated on the Airport, other than a helicopter, unless it is equipped with a tail or nose wheel, and wheel brakes. Any exception shall be authorized by the Airport Director with proper procedural instructions.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Landing and Taking Off.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may not land an aircraft at, or take off an aircraft from, the Airport except on the runway or helipad and in the direction assigned and upon clearance obtained from the control tower. A person operating aircraft not requiring a runway, such as a helicopter, shall strictly conform to the air traffic instructions given by the control tower.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not land an aircraft at, or take off an aircraft from, the Airport other than in conformity with the air traffic instructions given by the control tower.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person may not land an aircraft on, or take off an aircraft from, an unserviceable runway at the Airport or from any ramp area or taxiway.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>All persons operating aircraft in the Airport Class "D" airspace as described in the Airman's Information Manual shall conform to the current established traffic patterns and procedures promulgated jointly by the Federal Aviation Administration (FAA) and the Airport Director.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Simulated emergencies which require special handling by the control tower are prohibited within the Airport Class "D" airspace as described in the Airman's Information Manual.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Airport Marking and Lighting. A person may not operate an aircraft at the Airport, unless he obeys all Airport lighting and pavement marking signals.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Motorless Aircraft. A person may not land at, or take off from, the Airport in a motorless aircraft without first obtaining permission from the Airport Director and clearance from the control tower.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>Experimental Flights, Demonstrations, and Stunt Flying.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may not conduct experimental flights or ground demonstrations of flight equipment on the Airport without the previous approval of the Airport Director.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not perform or conduct stunt flying or air acrobatics at the Airport, except for public displays of aviation flight authorized by the Executive Director or Airport Director.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>Starting and Running Aircraft Engines.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Starting, running, or operating an aircraft at the Airport by any person other than FAA certificated pilots or mechanics, is prohibited.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not start an aircraft engine at the Airport unless blocks or chocks are placed in front of the wheels or the aircraft is provided with adequate brakes and they are in applied position.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person may not operate an aircraft engine at the Airport other than in places designated for these purposes by the Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A person may not warm-up or run-up jet or turboprop engines at the Airport other than in those areas and at those times designated by the Administration. A jet or turboprop engine may not be run-up for maintenance purposes at the Airport between the hours of 8 p.m. and 8 a.m., except in an emergency, and with the previous approval of the Airport Director.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A person may not leave an aircraft unattended with engines running or being tested.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>Radio Ground Control. A person may not taxi or tow an aircraft at the Airport unless that person monitors the ground control frequency being used by the control tower and remains in direct communication with the control tower at all times while so operating anywhere within the Airport movement area under the active control of the control tower.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>P.</num>
      <text>Propeller Slipstream and Jet Blast. A person may not position, start, or run-up engines, or taxi an aircraft in such a manner that propeller slipstream or jet blast could cause injury to persons, scatter debris, or damage property on the Airport or in areas adjacent to the Airport.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>Q.</num>
      <text>Taxiing.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may not taxi an aircraft at the Airport until he has ascertained that there is no danger of collision with any person or object in the immediate area.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not taxi an aircraft at the Airport except at a safe and reasonable speed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person may not taxi an aircraft at the Airport in an aircraft movement area other than according to instructions of the control tower.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>R.</num>
      <text>Aircraft Parking.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may not park an aircraft anywhere on the Airport in such a position as to block access through hangar doors, unless this action is approved by the Airport Director or the operator having jurisdiction over these hangars.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not use any area of the Airport, other than the public aircraft parking and storage areas, for parking and storage of aircraft, except as otherwise specifically approved by lease or otherwise. If a person uses these areas for aircraft parking and storage, the Airport Director shall order the aircraft removed at the risk and expense of the owner.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person may not park an aircraft on a public aircraft parking area at the Airport other than according to the procedures and rate schedule established by the Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A person may not park and leave any aircraft without the aircraft being tied down properly and the landing gear chocked with wheel blocks or other approved devices, except as otherwise approved by the Airport Director.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A person may not load cargo on or unload cargo from an aircraft, except in designated areas or in areas totally contained within an established leasehold approved for this activity.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>S.</num>
      <text>Aircraft Lights. A person may not taxi an aircraft at the Airport in unlighted or poorly lighted areas, during periods of low visibility (less than 3 miles), or between the hours of sunset and sunrise, unless the navigational lights of the aircraft are kept lighted while the aircraft is taxied.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>T.</num>
      <text>Removal of Passengers from Aircraft. A person may not create a nuisance or a threat to persons, property, or aircraft operations while aboard an aircraft at the Airport. At the request of the owner or operator of this aircraft, law enforcement officers may forcibly remove the person from the aircraft.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>U.</num>
      <text>Derelict Aircraft.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may not abandon any aircraft anywhere on the Airport. The Airport Director may remove any abandoned aircraft from the Airport at the sole risk and expense of the owner or operator of the aircraft.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not store or keep aircraft parts or components being held as inventory anywhere on the Airport other than in an enclosed facility approved by the Administration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>V.</num>
      <text>Damage to Airport. The owner or operator of any aircraft which by reason of any type of accident, crash, or fire, or which by reason of malfunction or operation, causes any damage to Airport property, shall be responsible to the Administration for the damage. The amount of the damage shall be ascertained by the Executive Director, who shall make demand upon the owner or operator for payment of the damage.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>W.</num>
      <text>Based Aircraft.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may not base an aircraft, personal or company-owned, at the Airport, unless a written agreement has been obtained from the Administration or a fixed-base operator.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Persons basing aircraft used for hire or other commercial purposes are required to have a written agreement with the Administration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>X.</num>
      <text>Unauthorized Maintenance. Except as provided in <cite path="|11|03|02|.03|C.">Regulation .03C of this chapter</cite>, a person may not perform maintenance on transient, based, or leased aircraft on the Airport premises without a written agreement with the Administration.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|03|02|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Fire Hazards.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Cleaning of Equipment.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The use of flammable or combustible liquids in the cleaning of aircraft, aircraft engines, propellers, or other appliances, equipment, or parts of aircraft is prohibited, unless those cleaning operations are conducted in facilities specifically approved by the Administration for that purpose and are performed in accordance with <cite path="|29.06.01">COMAR 29.06.01</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not use flammable or combustible liquids for cleaning purposes at the Airport, except as provided in <cite path="11|03|02|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person may not store, transport, or use cleaning fluids of a vaporizing nature at the Airport except in containers with dispensing devices which comply with the applicable sections of <cite path="|29.06.01">COMAR 29.06.01</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Open Flame Operations. Open flame operations may be conducted on the Airport only after obtaining a Welding and Burning permit from the Airport Operations office.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Storage of Material.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The storage of combustible materials in hangars at the Airport shall be conducted in accordance with NFPA 1 Uniform Fire Code, Chapter 10 and Chapter 34.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The height of stored material may not exceed that of the lower or bottom side of roof trusses or of a point 18 inches below sprinkler lines or heads, whichever is lower. Storage areas shall have spaces between them as well as aisles throughout the areas of sufficient size to allow passage of fire department personnel and equipment. Sufficient spaces for aisles shall be determined through inspection by the fire marshal in compliance with <cite path="|29.06.01">COMAR 29.06.01</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Storage of Hazardous Material.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Flammable and combustible liquids, gases, explosives, signal flares, or other hazardous materials shall be stored and kept in containers and receptacles and in structures and areas specifically approved by the fire marshal in accordance with <cite path="|29.06.01">COMAR 29.06.01</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All tenants and concessionaires shall ensure that drums and containers are properly marked in accordance with 29 CFR §1910.1200.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>In addition to the labeling requirements of 29 CFR §1910.1200, each tenant and concessionaire shall mark its drums and containers with its company name and date of initial receipt of the item on the Airport premises.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>All tenants and concessionaires shall properly store drums and containers and ensure proper disposal of materials in accordance with <cite path="|26.13.03">COMAR 26.13.03</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>All tenants and concessionaires shall provide adequate documentation regarding the contents of drums and containers to inspectors of the Administration, the Maryland Department of the Environment, or other law enforcement agency.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>If, as a result of a routine inspection of the Airport premises, an improperly marked or stored drum or container is found, the tenant or concessionaire shall be cited. The tenant or concessionaire shall correct the deficiency within 1 working day. This inspection may be conducted by the Fire marshal or representatives of the Administration, the Maryland Department of the Environment, or the Maryland Division of Labor and Industry.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>If a tenant or concessionaire fails to correct the noted deficiency, the Administration may correct the deficiency or cause it to be corrected by a private contractor at the expense of the responsible party.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>All abandoned drums or containers shall be collected by the Administration and placed in storage at the expense of the owner.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Lubricating Oil.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Lubricating oils shall be stored, kept, or transported in containers and receptacles, and in structures and areas, specifically approved by the fire marshal for these purposes in compliance with the applicable sections of <cite path="|29.06.01">COMAR 29.06.01</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The storage of empty lubricating oil drums or cans on the Airport is prohibited, except in approved areas designated by the Administration in compliance with the applicable sections of <cite path="|26.13.03">COMAR 26.13.03</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Petroleum products or objectionable industrial waste matter shall be discharged only into pans or containers provided for that purpose in compliance with the applicable sections of <cite path="|29.06.01">COMAR 29.06.01</cite> and shall be disposed of in a manner approved by the Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A company transporting oil on the Airport shall possess a valid Oil Operations Permit issued by the Waste Management Administration in accordance with <cite path="26.10.01.16">COMAR 26.10.01.16</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Waste. The storage of oily wastes, rags, and other rubbish and trash at the Airport is prohibited unless in suitable metal receptacles with operating self-closing covers as approved by <cite path="|29.06.01">COMAR 29.06.01</cite>. All waste within this general classification shall be removed from the Airport premises daily.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Smoking.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Smoking shall be prohibited within the fuel farm or in any building owned or leased by the Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Smoking or carrying lighted cigars, cigarettes, pipes, matches, or any open flame within the air operations area is prohibited.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Floor Care. The accumulation of oil, grease, or other flammable material on the floors of hangars and other buildings is prohibited. The floors of hangars and other buildings shall be continuously kept free of rags, waste material, trash, rubbish, or other flammable materials.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Care of Aircraft Ramp, Apron, and Parking Areas. Any person, including the operators of aircraft, causing overflowing or spilling of oil, grease, fuel, or any similar material anywhere at the Airport, is responsible for immediately cleaning the spillage. Upon the default of the responsible person to clean this area, the Airport Director may provide the necessary cleaning and charge the responsible person for the expense of it at established rates.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Cleaning of Aircraft. The cleaning of aircraft shall be conducted in accordance with NFPA 410 Aircraft Maintenance, which is incorporated by reference at <cite path="11.03.01.01">COMAR 11.03.01.01</cite>-1B(2)(e). This cleaning shall only be permitted in areas of the Airport approved by the Administration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Doping, Spray Painting, and Paint Striping.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Doping processes, spray painting, or paint stripping operations are permitted only in properly designed, ventilated buildings or areas that are approved by <cite path="|29.06.01">COMAR 29.06.01</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Only persons who are properly clothed for safety and self-protection are permitted to enter or work in a doping or spray painting room while doping and spray painting operations are being conducted.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Fire Extinguishers. All fire extinguishing equipment shall be maintained according to the requirements of <cite path="|29.06.01">COMAR 29.06.01</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>Eye Hazards. The use of a material, such as oil absorbents or similar material, that creates an eye hazard when picked up, swirled, or blown about by the blast from an aircraft engine is prohibited in any passenger loading area or other public area at the Airport.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>Operating Motor Vehicles in Hangars. No tractor, tug, or other vehicle may be operated within any hangar or other building used for aircraft maintenance or storage when an aircraft is present, except in an emergency, unless the exhaust of the tractor, tug, or other motor vehicle is protected by screens or baffles to prevent the escape of sparks or the propagation of flame. The parking of motor vehicles in any hangar with an aircraft is prohibited. The parking of a motor vehicle in aircraft hangars where multiple aircraft are stored is prohibited.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>Grounding or Bonding of Aircraft. Aircraft in hangars shall be grounded or bonded for removal and control of static electrical accumulations on aircraft while aircraft are undergoing service or repair in accordance with NFPA 409 Aircraft Hangars, which is incorporated by reference at <cite path="11.03.01.01">COMAR 11.03.01.01</cite>-1B(2)(d). Aircraft being serviced on the Airport ramp or other designated area shall be grounded or bonded for removal and control of static electrical accumulations in accordance with NFPA 407 Aircraft Fuel Servicing, which is incorporated by reference at <cite path="11.03.01.01">COMAR 11.03.01.01</cite>-1B(2)(c).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>P.</num>
      <text>Motorized Ground Equipment Near Aircraft or Hangars.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Motorized ground equipment may not be parked near any aircraft or hangar at the Airport in a manner that prevents this equipment from being readily driven or towed away in case of an emergency.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The parking of motorized ground equipment near aircraft and hangars at the Airport shall be conducted in accordance with NFPA 407 Aircraft Fuel Servicing, §407-8, which is incorporated by reference at <cite path="11.03.01.01">COMAR 11.03.01.01</cite>-1B(2)(c).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>Q.</num>
      <text>Repairing of Aircraft. The repair of an aircraft or aircraft engine, propeller, or other aircraft apparatus is prohibited in an area of the Airport other than that specifically designated by the Administration for this purpose, except that minor adjustments or repairs may be made while the aircraft is at a tie-down position, on the terminal apron, or being prepared for departure.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>R.</num>
      <text>Operating Aircraft Engines in Hangars. A person may not start or operate aircraft engines inside a hangar at the Airport, other than the air rotation of jet engines without ignition.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>S.</num>
      <text>Heating Systems in Hangars. The installation and operation of any heating system or device is prohibited in any hangar at the Airport, other than systems or devices listed or labeled by an independent testing laboratory or facility as suitable for use in heating aircraft hangars. Those systems and devices shall be installed in the manner prescribed by and standards set forth in NFPA 70, National Electrical Code, which is incorporated by reference at <cite path="11.03.01.01">COMAR 11.03.01.01</cite>-1B(2)(a), and NFPA 409 Aircraft Hangars, which is incorporated by reference at <cite path="11.03.01.01">COMAR 11.03.01.01</cite>-1B(2)(d)). The use of portable aircraft engine heating equipment is prohibited inside any aircraft hangar. Only listed or labeled, and Federal Aviation Administration (FAA) approved, equipment shall be used.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>T.</num>
      <text>Electrical Equipment and Lighting Systems.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All electrical equipment shall be in accordance with NFPA 70 National Electrical Code, which is incorporated by reference at <cite path="11.03.01.01">COMAR 11.03.01.01</cite>-1B(2)(a).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The use of a portable lamp assembly in any maintenance shelter or hangar without a proper protective guard or shield over the lamp assembly to prevent breakage is prohibited.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person may not keep power-operated equipment or electrical devices running at the Airport while not properly supervised.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Gasoline or diesel powered generators, compressors, or other similar equipment shall be properly grounded or bonded and may not be operated in any hangar.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03-1</num>
    <heading>Dangerous Articles.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Explosives, Corrosives, Poisons, and Radiological Materials. The storing, retaining, handling, using, dispensing, or transporting of any Class A explosive or hazardous material (as defined by the "Hazardous Material Regulation of the U.S. Department of Transportation") requires a Special Use permit authorized by the Airport Director and issued by the fire marshal under <cite path="|29.06.01">COMAR 29.06.01</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Control of Explosives.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Detonators such as blasting caps, electric blasting caps, and detonating primers shall be stored in a separate magazine for blasting supplies and may not be stored in a magazine with other explosive materials.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Detonators shall be stored in a Type 1, 2, or 3 magazine, except that electric blasting caps having leg wires at least 4 feet long may be stored in a Type 4 magazine. Whenever specific types of magazines are required by <cite path="|29.06.01">COMAR 29.06.01</cite>, magazines of higher classifications shall be permitted to be substituted.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Explosive materials that are bullet-sensitive shall be stored in a Type 1, 2, or 3 magazine.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Explosive materials that are not cap-sensitive shall be stored in a Type 4 or 5 magazine.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Magazines shall be in the charge of a competent person at all times who shall be at least 21 years old or a member of the Armed Services and who shall be held responsible for enforcement of all safety precautions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Magazine doors shall be kept locked, except during the time of placement and removal of stocks of explosives, or during inspection.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Safety rules governing the operation of magazines shall be posted on the interior of the magazine door.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Aircraft that are involved in loading, unloading, reloading, or temporary retaining of Class A explosives or blasting agents shall be parked on the Airport in areas designated by the Administration. Class B and C explosives shall be handled in the same manner when compliance is deemed necessary by the Airport Director to ensure public safety.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Explosive cargo shall be ground transported to and from the designated parking areas in vehicles equipped in accordance with federal regulations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>A carrier of explosive cargo shall notify the Airport Director at least 12 hours before the scheduled arrival of the aircraft involved. The Airport Director will then issue the appropriate NOTAMs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Explosives may not be stored on an aircraft which has been authorized to park in a designated area. Temporary use of the designated area by an explosive-laden aircraft or temporary use of the designated area for explosives which are ready for air shipment or which have arrived by air for further movement may be permitted for not longer than 12 hours.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03-2</num>
    <heading>Fueling and Defueling.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The provisions of this section govern and control the fueling and defueling of aircraft at the Airport.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not fuel or defuel any aircraft while any engine of the aircraft is running.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The smoking or carrying of lighted cigars, cigarettes, pipes, matches, or any open flame is prohibited within 100 feet of the site at which an aircraft is being fueled or defueled, or within 100 feet of the site of a flammable or combustible liquid spill.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The operation of any electrical appliance in an aircraft is prohibited when the aircraft is being fueled or defueled.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A person may not fuel or defuel an aircraft unless the aircraft and the fuel apparatus both are electrically bonded.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>When a fuel spill occurs at or near a fuel delivery device, the Administration shall be notified immediately. Valves and dome covers shall be shut down, and the fueling vehicle shall remain in place until the arrival of fire department vehicles. If the engine of the fueling vehicle is running at the time of the fuel spill, it shall remain running until orders otherwise are issued by the fire department incident commander at the scene. Conversely, if the engine of the fueling vehicle is shut down at the time of the fuel spill, it shall remain shut down until the fire department incident commander at the scene orders the vehicle removed. Fueling or defueling operations may not resume following a fuel spill until all affected areas are thoroughly cleaned.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>No person, except personnel engaged in the fueling, defueling, servicing, and operation of an aircraft, may be within 100 feet of aircraft during fueling or defueling, excluding passengers and flight crew.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>A person may not be in any aircraft being fueled or defueled.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>A material which may cause a static spark during fueling or defueling of aircraft may not be used within 100 feet of any aircraft being fueled or defueled.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>A person may not engage in aircraft fueling or defueling operations without fire extinguishers within ready reach.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>A person may not start the engine of any aircraft when there is any flammable or combustible liquid on the ground near the aircraft.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>A person may not fuel or defuel an aircraft with fueling hoses and other equipment or apparatus which are not in a safe, sound, and nonleaking condition.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>A person may not use hoses, funnels, and appurtenances in fueling and defueling operations unless the hoses, funnels, and appurtenances are equipped with a grounding or bonding device in good order to prevent ignition of flammable liquids.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>A person may not engage in the fueling and defueling of aircraft or the maintenance of aircraft fueling systems at a distance of less than 50 feet from any hangar or other building, unless conducted in compliance with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>NFPA 410 Aircraft Maintenance, which is incorporated by reference at <cite path="11.03.01.01">COMAR 11.03.01.01</cite>-1B(2)(e); and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>NFPA 407 Aircraft Fuel Servicing, which is incorporated by reference at <cite path="11.03.01.01">COMAR 11.03.01.01</cite>-1B(2)(c).</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>Use of Automotive Fuel in Aircraft Engines.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Except as provided in §A(14)(b), the use of automotive fuel (MOGAS) in an aircraft engine is prohibited. The Administration, acting as the vendor of aviation fuel at the Airport, may not service any aircraft with aviation fuel (AVGAS) if it is determined that the aircraft has been fueled previously with automotive fuel (MOGAS).</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Permissible use of MOGAS shall be extended only to those aircraft owners/operators carrying a Supplemental Type Certificate (STC) from the Federal Aviation Administration which specifically authorizes use of MOGAS in the aircraft or if the aircraft is certified for MOGAS use by the Federal Aviation Administration.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Fueling Vehicles.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may not park a fueling vehicle other than in an area assigned by the Administration, except for the accomplishment of minor adjustments or repairs necessary to move this vehicle to a designated storage area when failure occurs elsewhere on the Airport.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not bring, keep, or store fuel vehicles, empty or otherwise, within any building at the Airport, unless the building is properly equipped for that purpose, or, in those instances under controlled conditions, during approved fueling and defueling operations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person may not back a fueling vehicle anywhere on the Airport, unless an attendant is present outside the fueling vehicle to assist the operator of the fueling vehicle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A person may not operate or ground test airborne radar equipment in any area on the Airport, except in areas approved for these purposes, when the directional beam of high intensity radar is within 300 feet, or the low intensity beam is within 100 feet, of another aircraft, aircraft fueling operation, aircraft fueling truck, or aircraft fuel or flammable liquid storage facility.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall adhere to NFPA 407 Aircraft Fuel Servicing, which is incorporated by reference at <cite path="11.03.01.01">COMAR 11.03.01.01</cite>-1B(2)(c), and NFPA 410 Aircraft Maintenance, which is incorporated by reference at <cite path="11.03.01.01">COMAR 11.03.01.01</cite>-1B(2)(e).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Furnace Rooms. A person may not let rubbish accumulate in the furnace rooms or any hangar or other building at the Airport. Rubbish in furnace rooms shall be collected in metal covered containers and shall be disposed of daily.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Clothes Lockers. A person may not install or use at the Airport a clothes locker constructed of anything besides metal. All clothes lockers shall be either secured to a wall or anchored to the floor.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|03|02|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Control of Vehicular Traffic on the Air Operations Area.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Operating Procedure. The control of all vehicular traffic on the air operations area shall be governed by the regulations of the Administration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Authority to Operate on the Air Operations Area.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may not operate or cause to be operated any motor vehicle on the air operations area, unless this operation is directly related to an aviation activity at the Airport, to the business of the Administration, or to the business of a tenant or authorized subtenant of the Airport engaged in a business activity authorized by the Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not drive a motor vehicle on the air operations area without proper vehicle identification as prescribed by the Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person may not wash, clean, or polish a motor vehicle within the air operations area or at any point on the Airport other than that approved by the Airport Director.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Communication with Control Tower.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may not drive a motor vehicle on or across an active runway or taxiway unless he maintains direct contact with and receives clearance from the control tower. If the vehicle is not equipped with an operable two-way radio on the assigned ground control frequency, it may be used on or across an active runway or taxiway only under the escort or by the instructions of another motor vehicle equipped with two-way radio able to maintain contact with the control tower or, with prior arrangement, in conformance with light signals from the control tower.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Vehicles without radio equipment that have been permitted to operate on the airfield in accordance with light signals may not proceed any closer than 200 feet from the edge of any active runway without clearance from the control tower. It shall be the responsibility of all vehicle operators to recognize and understand the standard light signals used by the control tower.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Operations Near Aircraft.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>No person other than the operator of an aircraft servicing vehicle for a designated aircraft may operate a motor vehicle on the air operations area so as to pass within 20 feet of a parked aircraft.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not operate an aircraft servicing vehicle on the loading ramp unless the aircraft to be serviced has come to a complete stop at its designated loading position.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All vehicles shall pass to the rear of taxiing aircraft.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Speed Limits.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may not operate any motor vehicle, other than an emergency vehicle proceeding in response to an alarm, on the air operations area at a speed exceeding 25 miles per hour, except as otherwise posted.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not operate any motor vehicle on aircraft parking ramps, aprons, or in hangar areas at a speed exceeding 15 miles per hour.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person may not drive a motor vehicle within 20 feet of a parked or taxiing aircraft at a speed exceeding 5 miles per hour.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Careless Driving. A person may not operate a motor vehicle on the air operations area in a careless or reckless manner, but shall have regard for the width, grade, curves, corners, traffic, and use of roadways, weather conditions, and all other attendant circumstances, so as not to endanger the life, limb, or property of any person.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Safety Equipment.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may not operate a motor vehicle on the air operations area unless this vehicle is properly maintained and is equipped with the safety equipment, in operable condition, described in this section.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Motor Vehicle Lights.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A person may not operate a motor vehicle on the air operations area, other than a motor vehicle designed for only one headlight, unless the motor vehicle is equipped with two headlights and one or more red taillights.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A person may not operate a motor vehicle on the air operations area unless the vehicle's headlights and taillights are kept lighted between the hours of sunset and sunrise and at all times when passing through unlighted or poorly lighted areas.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A person may not allow a stalled motor vehicle to remain on the air operations area between the hours of sunset and sunrise unless the parking lights of the vehicle are kept on or warning lights are posted.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A person may not operate a motor vehicle on the air operations area unless headlights of the vehicle are sufficient to meet State requirements.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>A person may not operate a baggage or cargo cart and trailers on the air operations area unless the cart is equipped with at least two yellow reflectors on each side and two red reflectors on the rear.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>A person may not operate a motor vehicle on a taxiway or runway unless the vehicle is equipped with United States Department of Transportation-type clearance lights and mounted to United States Department of Transportation requirements. If a vehicle configuration will not permit installation of ICC clearance lights, a single 50 candle power non-flashing red light may be used.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>All motor vehicles with headlights approved for operating on the air operations area shall be equipped with dimmer switches. If there is no provision for dimming headlights, they must be focused so as to strike the ground not more than 50 feet ahead of the vehicle.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Motor Vehicle Brakes.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A person may not operate a motor vehicle on the air operations area unless he tests the brakes of this vehicle upon approaching an aircraft within the distance necessary to avoid a collision with the aircraft if the brakes on the motor vehicle fail.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A person may not operate a motor vehicle unless it is equipped with an emergency brake capable of holding the motor vehicle on a 30-degree grade.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Motor Vehicle Windows and Mirrors.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A person may not operate a motor vehicle on the air operations area, except specialized Airport and aircraft servicing equipment not licensed for general highway use and having an open cab which provides the driver with unobstructed 360-degree visibility, unless the vehicle is equipped with at least one mirror adjusted so that the operator of the vehicle shall have a clear view of the road behind for a distance of at least 200 feet.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A person may not operate a motor vehicle on the air operations area unless the windows of the vehicle are free of cracks, blisters, discoloration, and any other defect causing distortion or obstruction of the vision of the operator.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A person may not use or place posters, stickers, signs, or other objects on the windows of a motor vehicle operating on the air operations area, other than those required by the Administration or by law.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>All vehicles approved for operating on the air operations area shall carry an approved fire extinguisher of the type and size required by the Airport Director.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Emergency Vehicles and Conditions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person operating a motor vehicle on the air operations area shall immediately yield the right-of-way to a police, ambulance, fire department, or other emergency vehicle giving an audible or visible signal.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Emergency conditions existing on the air operations area will not mitigate or cancel any existing regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Under emergency conditions, such as an aircraft accident or fire, access to the air operations area is barred for all vehicles or persons except those whose duties require their admittance.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Occupants of Motor Vehicles.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>While on the air operations area, a person may not ride on the running board of a moving motor vehicle, stand up in the body of a moving motor vehicle, ride on the outside of the body of a moving motor vehicle, or ride on the vehicle with his arms or legs protruding from the body of the vehicle, unless the motor vehicle is so designed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person operating a motor vehicle on the air operations area may not allow any passengers to ride in the vehicle other than those passengers permitted by these regulations or by other applicable law.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Tugs and Trailers.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may not operate a trailer or semitrailer on the air operations area, unless the trailer or semitrailer is equipped with proper brakes so that when disengaged from a towing vehicle, no propeller slipstream, jet blast, or wind will cause it to become free-rolling.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not operate towed equipment on the air operations area unless the equipment has positive locking couplings.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Yielding Right-of-Way.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person operating a motor vehicle on the air operations area shall yield the right-of-way to aircraft in motion or aircraft with engines running, ready to be put in motion.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person operating a motor vehicle on the air operations area may not cross or enter motor vehicle traffic lanes without yielding the right-of-way to vehicles already in these lanes.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person operating motor vehicles on the air operations area shall observe left-to-left passing of approaching vehicles.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A person operating motor vehicles on the air operations area shall yield right-of-way to emergency vehicles.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Traffic Control. A person may not operate a motor vehicle on the air operations area unless that person obeys all posted regulatory signs and traffic signals and all instructions by the control tower, the Airport Director, or a law enforcement officer.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>Parking.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may not park a motor vehicle, or motorized or other equipment, on the air operations area except at those points designated by the Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not park a motor vehicle or other equipment on the air operations area within 15 feet of any fire hydrant or other fire control apparatus.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person may not park a motor vehicle, or motorized or other equipment, on the air operations area so as to interfere with or prevent the passage or movement of aircraft or emergency or other motor vehicles.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A person may not park an unattended vehicle or other equipment adjacent to a runway, unless those motor vehicles or other equipment are parked parallel to the runway and at least 200 feet from the edge of the runway.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A person may not leave a motor vehicle unattended with the engine running.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A motor vehicle or other equipment on the air operations area, parked in such a manner as to create a nuisance or hazard, or interfere with aircraft operations and emergencies, may be removed to a location designated by the Airport Director, at the expense of the owner.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>Motor Vehicle Accidents.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person operating a motor vehicle on the air operations area who is involved in an accident resulting in injury to any person or damage to any property, shall, if physically able, do the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Stop the vehicle at the scene of the accident or as clearly as possible to it without obstructing traffic more than necessary;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Notify the Airport Director;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Return to and remain at the scene of the accident until he has given a full report of the same to the investigating officer;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Upon request, and if physically able, exhibit to the investigating officer any permit, license, registration, or other document relevant to this accident or the persons or property involved.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person operating a motor vehicle on the air operations area who is involved in an accident as defined in <cite path="11|03|02|.04|N.|(1)">§N(1) of this regulation</cite>, and the owner of the vehicle (if other than the operator), shall, if physically able, make a full written report of this accident to the Airport Director within 24 hours after the accident, and shall include the names and addresses of the persons involved, the description of the property or vehicles involved, the registration and license number of the vehicles involved, and any other information relevant to the accident.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>Repair of Motor Vehicles. A person may not clean, repair, maintain, or overhaul any motor vehicle or motorized or other equipment on the air operations area, other than in an approved shop area, except for those repairs necessary to remove this motor vehicle or equipment from the air operations area.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>P.</num>
      <text>Contractor's Access and Use of Premises.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may not gain access to and egress from the site of construction on the airfield area in a motor vehicle or construction equipment belonging to or under the supervision of a contractor other than by routes and through gates designated by the Administration, and only during those periods of time specified in writing by the Airport Director.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not allow a motor vehicle or construction equipment belonging to or under the supervision of a contractor to remain at the work area at the end of the working day or to be parked overnight in any position or location where it constitutes an actual or potential hazard to aircraft or motor vehicles at the Airport. If, however, the contractor has the written authorization of the Airport Director to leave these motor vehicles or construction equipment parked overnight, they shall be marked and lighted as required.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person may not operate a motor vehicle or construction equipment belonging to or under the supervision of an Airport contractor on or across an active runway at the Airport, unless the vehicle or equipment is escorted by a motor vehicle equipped with a two-way radio in contact with the control tower or is itself so equipped.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>Q.</num>
      <text>Vehicle Identification and Registration.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may not operate a motor vehicle based at the Airport on the air operations area unless the vehicle is registered with the Airport Director, with permission obtained for the operation of the vehicle, and unless the vehicle is clearly marked with the company name, logo, or other means of identification acceptable to the Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not operate a motor vehicle based off the Airport on the air operations area on a regular continuing basis, including but not limited to off-Airport contractor and service company vehicles, unless this person conspicuously displays in a window of the vehicle an "official permit" issued by the Administration, or is escorted by approved Administration or tenant personnel.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person may not operate a motor vehicle based off the Airport on the air operations area for the purpose of making a delivery on a one-time basis, unless the vehicle is escorted by approved Administration or tenant personnel.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A person may not operate roadway-authorized motor vehicles, or vehicles without two-way radios, on the air operations area without notifying the control tower before entry.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A person may not operate a two-wheeled motor vehicle on the air operations area, unless this vehicle has been approved in writing by the Airport Director.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A person may not operate any motor vehicle inside a hangar unless the vehicle is specially equipped and approved by the Airport Director.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>R.</num>
      <text>Driver Licensing and Permits. A person may not drive a motor vehicle on the air operations area without a currently valid driver's license issued by the State or by the jurisdiction where this person resides if other than Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>S.</num>
      <text>Guidemen. A person may not operate a motor vehicle at the Airport without a guideman positioned outside the vehicle if the vision of its operator is restricted in any manner.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>T.</num>
      <text>Parking Regulations.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may not park a motor vehicle or load or unload a motor vehicle at the Airport in violation of any posted parking sign or other traffic regulation, or in such a manner as to obstruct the free movement of traffic.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Vehicles shall be parked in one space only within areas that have marked spaces and lanes. Each vehicle shall leave clear access to adjacent spaces, and may not block driving lanes or create a hazard for other drivers.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An area of the Airport property which has been closed by the use of barricades or other traffic control devices may not be entered by any vehicle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>U.</num>
      <text>Removal of Vehicles.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may not abandon a motor vehicle at the Airport.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Airport tenants are responsible for the prompt removal of abandoned motor vehicles from their leased premises, at the owner's expense.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Administration shall remove, at the owner's expense, any vehicle which remains parked in a limited duration parking space for a period of time which exceeds the posted time limit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Administration may fine violators of posted signs and parking regulations adopted under Transportation Article §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|5-426">5-426</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|5-427">5-427</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland, not to exceed $50.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>V.</num>
      <text>Pedestrians.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person operating a motor vehicle at the Airport shall yield the right-of-way to a pedestrian in a marked pedestrian crosswalk.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not park any vehicle in any marked pedestrian crosswalk.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04-1</num>
    <heading>Control of Landside Traffic.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Governing Law. Motor vehicle operators using the public streets, ramps, roads, and highways on the Airport shall comply with the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr">Transportation Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>General Parking Regulations.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Parking or standing is prohibited on all Airport roads, except in designated parking areas.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An individual may not park a motor vehicle or load or unload a motor vehicle at the Airport in violation of any posted parking sign or other traffic regulation, or in such a manner as to obstruct the free movement of traffic.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Motor vehicles shall be parked in one space only within areas that have marked spaces and lanes. Each motor vehicle shall leave clear access to adjacent spaces and may not block driving lanes or create a hazard for other drivers.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A motor vehicle may not enter any area that is closed to vehicular traffic by the use of barricades or other traffic control devices.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Leaving a motor vehicle unattended in front of the terminal building is prohibited.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>An individual may not abandon a motor vehicle at the Airport.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>An individual operating a motor vehicle at the Airport shall yield the right-of-way to a pedestrian in a marked pedestrian crosswalk.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>An individual may not park a motor vehicle in a marked pedestrian crosswalk.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Airport tenants are responsible for the prompt removal of abandoned motor vehicles from their leased premises, at the owner's expense.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>The Administration shall remove, at the owner's expense, any vehicle which remains parked in a limited duration parking space for a period of time which exceeds the posted time limit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>The Administration may fine violators of posted signs and parking regulations adopted under Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|5-426">5-426</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|5-427">5-427</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland, not to exceed $50.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>In addition to these general regulations, the Airport Director may further regulate parking by posting signs or notices. Parking in violation of any sign or notice is prohibited.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>The responsibility for finding a legal parking space rests with the motor vehicle operator. Lack of space is no excuse for violation of these regulations.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Taxicabs.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Taxicabs shall stand or wait only in designated or approved areas at the Airport and the operator shall remain with the taxicab.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An individual operating a taxicab at the Airport may not block or interfere with the free passage of pedestrians or vehicular traffic to and from the Airport buildings.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An individual may not operate a taxicab at the Airport unless the individual prominently displays within the taxicab a taxicab-driver identification license permit containing a recent discernible photograph of the driver and the telephone number of the taxicab franchise operator, the assigned taxicab number, and the driver's identification number.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Rental Cars.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An individual may not conduct or engage in the business of renting motor vehicles on the Airport without a written contract with the Administration, except, however, a car rental company without a written contract may deliver customers to the Airport and meet prereserved customers at the Airport. Nothing in this regulation is to be construed to prevent delivery of previously reserved rental cars for arriving passengers. Evidence of previous reservation may be requested by any law enforcement officer or authorized representative of the Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An individual other than representatives of rental car agencies holding contracts with the Administration may not, within the boundaries of the Airport, solicit passengers for the rental of motor vehicles.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Parking spaces assigned to car rental companies under written contract with the Administration shall be designated and appropriately marked. These parking spaces shall be used only to park rental cars ready for delivery to customers and for temporarily parked cars being returned by customers. Unauthorized parked motor vehicles, including those that are owned by these car rental companies, shall be cited according to the other provisions of these regulations governing vehicular traffic.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Operations of Motor Vehicles for Hire.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An individual operating a motor vehicle to transport passengers from the Airport may not refuse or neglect to transport to any requested destination any orderly individual willing to pay the prescribed fare.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An individual operating a motor vehicle for hire to transport passengers from the Airport may not charge passengers a fare in excess of the normal and customary fare in effect from the Airport to the destination, as determined by meter or published rate schedule.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Penalties, Fines, and Costs.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Abandoned motor vehicles and vehicles parked in violation of any parking regulation, sign, or notice may be removed by the Administration at the expense and risk of the owner. Towing charges are in addition to any fines.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Parking violations are subject to the following fines:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Obstructing movement of traffic$35;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Obstructing movement of pedestrians$35;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Unattended motor vehicle$50;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Meter or other time limit violation$35;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Parking in other than designated areas$35;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Illegally parked in handicapped area$50;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Illegally parked in leased space$35;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Parked in no parking area$35.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Fines shall be paid or request for trial shall be requested within 15 days of issuance of the parking violation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Motor vehicles with three or more unpaid tickets against them may be impounded until all tickets have been cleared.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Commercial Activity.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Soliciting or Carrying on Business. A person, unless expressly authorized in writing by the Administration, may not engage in any of the following activities in or upon any area of the Airport:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Engage in any business or commercial activity;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Sell or offer for sale any merchandise or service;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Solicit any business or trade, including the carrying of passengers or baggage for hire;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Solicit charitable contributions or funds for any purpose;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Gamble or solicit gambling.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Commercial Photography and Recordings. No person, unless authorized by the Administration, may take still pictures, motion pictures, or sound-motion pictures or sound records or recordings for commercial purposes, other than news coverage, on the public areas of the Airport.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Commercial Advertising. No person, unless authorized by the Administration, may post or distribute commercial signs, advertisements, literature, circulars, pictures, sketches, drawings, handbills, or any other form of printed or written commercial matter or material at the Airport.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Storage of Property. Unless authorized by the Administration or otherwise provided in a lease or other written agreement, a person may not use any area of the Airport for storage of cargo, aircraft, or other property.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Commercial Freight Operators.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may not operate freight-forwarding vehicles within the boundaries of the Airport unless he is authorized by the Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not engage in air freight commercial activity at the Airport unless he is authorized by the Administration; however, an air freight operator without authorization shall be allowed to deliver freight at the Airport.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Maintenance and Repair of Leased Premises.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Administration shall be responsible for the maintenance, repair, and custodial services as specified in each of the tenant lease agreements.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Tenants shall be responsible for repairs to leased premises which are damaged due to improper operation, misuse, or negligence of a tenant or agent, or agents, of the tenant operating under control of the tenant. Repair of the premises shall be made at the tenant's own expense.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Administration shall be notified in writing by the tenant whenever the tenant engages a contractor for the purpose of repairs and reserves the right to disapprove a contractor if there is reason to believe the contractor's performance may be unsatisfactory.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Repair work shall be inspected and approved by the Administration before the release of the tenant from responsibility for the damage and repairs, whether the work was performed by the tenant or a contractor hired by the tenant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Administration shall provide only custodial services which are specifically provided for in the contract/lease agreement between the Administration and the tenant.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Building Permits.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Construction or modifications to existing facilities in or on State-owned property under the jurisdiction of the Administration may not be undertaken without prior issuance of a building permit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The application shall be approved and the permit issued before initiation of any construction or modification activities.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The building permit shall be displayed on the construction site at all times.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>All building, construction, and modifications to existing or new structures shall comply with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The International Building Code, which is incorporated by reference at <cite path="11.03.01.01">COMAR 11.03.01.01</cite>-1B(3);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>NFPA 1 Uniform Fire Code, which is incorporated by reference at <cite path="11.03.01.01">COMAR 11.03.01.01</cite>-1B(1); and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>NFPA 101 Life Safety Code, which is incorporated by reference at <cite path="11.03.01.01">COMAR 11.03.01.01</cite>-1B(2)(b).</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Minimum Standards for Commercial Aeronautical Activities.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Administration shall establish minimum acceptable qualifications to ensure that the level and quality of service, as well as other conditions, shall be adhered to by those conducting commercial activities at the Airport.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Administration may extend the opportunity to engage in commercial aeronautical activities at the Airport to applicants who meet the Administration's published standards for those activities, providing there is available suitable space at the Airport for the conduct of these activities, and if the applicants have an Administration approved credit application.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Documents Needed for Application.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Applicants shall furnish the following documents when submitting a letter of application:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Evidence of organizational and financial capability to provide the proposed activity;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Business and financial references; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A copy of the applicant's annual financial report, and that of the parent company if a wholly owned subsidiary, for the last complete fiscal year showing applicant's assets and liabilities and the value of its unencumbered assets.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The annual report shall be certified by a certified public accountant.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If unable to provide the annual report, the applicant shall provide bank references and other records necessary to substantiate its financial status.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Festivals, Exhibits, and Trade Shows. A public or special event held at the Airport requires a Special Use permit authorized by the Airport Director and issued by the fire marshal in accordance with <cite path="|29.06.01">COMAR 29.06.01</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Environmental Protection and Public Health.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Water Pollution. A person may not introduce or permit to be introduced into any water system or any surface or underground water at the Airport any organic or inorganic matter or deleterious substance which is injurious to human, plant, animal, fish, or other life, or property. The types of permissible quantities of discharge shall be governed by the then applicable water discharge standards as promulgated by the United States Environmental Protection Agency under the Federal Water Pollution Control Act of 1972, or by <cite path="|26.08.03">COMAR 26.08.03</cite>, whichever is the most stringent. At the earliest feasible planning stage, any proposed development shall be coordinated with the Administration in compliance with the Chesapeake Bay Critical Area Commission (<cite path="|27.01">COMAR 27.01</cite>).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Air Pollution.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may not introduce or permit to be introduced into the atmosphere at the Airport any air contaminants or combinations of them by burning or otherwise, which are injurious to human, plant, or animal life, or property, or which in any way interfere with the operation of aircraft on the ground or in the air. The types and permissible quantities of discharge into the air shall be governed by the atmospheric discharge standards applicable at the time, as promulgated by the United States Environmental Protection Agency under the Federal Clean Air Act of 1970, or under any amendment or successor legislation to it, or by <cite path="|26.11.06">COMAR 26.11.06</cite>, whichever is the most stringent.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not operate a motor vehicle, and the owner of a motor vehicle may not permit it to be operated, upon the air operations area unless the engine power and exhaust mechanism is equipped, adjusted, and operated in accordance with <cite path="|11.14.02">COMAR 11.14.02</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Sanitary Sewage, Storm Drainage, and Industrial Waste System Pollution.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person, whether on or off premises under the jurisdiction of the Administration, may not introduce or permit to be introduced into any sanitary sewage and industrial waste or storm sewage system under the jurisdiction of the Administration, any deleterious substance which is injurious to human, plant, or animal life, or property, or which unreasonably interferes with the conduct of business at the Airport, or which in any way interferes with the maintenance or operation of the Airport. The types and permissible quantities of discharge shall be governed by the sewage discharge standards for sanitary sewage and industrial waste and storm sewage systems applicable at the time, as promulgated by the United States Environmental Protection Agency or <cite path="|26.04.01">COMAR 26.04.01</cite>—.03, whichever is the most stringent. This discharge shall be drained only into sewage receptacles provided for this purpose and disposed of in a manner approved by the Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not deposit, discharge, or permit the discharge or disposal of oil in any manner into the storm drainage system at the Airport.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person may not deposit, throw, or discharge garbage or food containers of any kind into the storm drainage system at the Airport.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A person may not place, discharge, or permit the placement or discharge of industrial waste in any manner into the storm drainage system at the Airport.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A person may not apply, discharge, or deposit toxic materials from any source into the storm drainage system at the Airport, unless this application, discharge, or deposit meets all industrial waste requirements of the Water Resources Administration and of the Environmental Protection Agency.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Washing Vehicles and Equipment.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>No person other than an employee of the Administration or an Airport tenant may use the vehicle and equipment wash area at the Airport.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not wash or clean a personal vehicle at the Airport vehicle and equipment wash area.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person may not use the Airport vehicle and equipment wash area unless the following action is taken:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All waste is disposed of in the trash container provided;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>No materials are left on the ramp area;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Mud, dirt, and other refuse washed from a vehicle or equipment are thoroughly flushed down the open drain;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The area is kept neat and presentable at all times.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A person may not deposit, discharge, or permit the discharge or disposal of oil in any manner into the drain system at the Airport vehicle and equipment wash area.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A person may not deposit, throw, or discharge garbage or food containers of any manner into the drain system at the Airport vehicle and equipment wash area.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A person may not place, discharge, or permit the placement or discharge of industrial waste in any manner into the drain system at the Airport vehicle and equipment wash area.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Health Laws. A person, whether on or off the Airport, may not engage in activities affecting the Airport involving food and beverage service, drinking water service, handling, storage, or disposal of water or refuse, or any other activity having a potentially deleterious effect on food quality, water quality, air quality, or sanitary sewage and industrial waste or storm sewage systems, unless this person fully complies with the applicable health laws and regulations of the United States and with Health-General Article, Title 21, Subtitles 2—10, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Food and Beverage Service and Related Activities.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Only fully licensed food and beverage services shall provide service on or for the Airport or any aircraft.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not design or construct any establishment for the conduct of food or beverage service at the Airport other than according to the regulations of the Maryland Department of Health.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Aircraft Drinking Water.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may not operate a water piping system in aircraft servicing areas unless the system is under adequate positive pressure at all times with a vacuum break to prevent siphoning. There may not be cross-connections between the potable water system and a system of questionable quality. All drinking and culinary water used in connection with the operation of aircraft in interstate, intrastate, or foreign commerce shall come from sources approved by the United States Public Health Service and the Maryland Department of the Environment. The installation of all aircraft water piping systems shall comply with the requirements established by these agencies.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not use hoses to deliver potable water to aircraft, unless these hoses are constructed of the material and stored and handled in the manner prescribed by the United States Public Health Service.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Aircraft Toilet Waste.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>No person at the Airport may discharge the sewage accumulated in the fixed waste retention tank aboard an aircraft other than through a flexible hose, with a water-type connection to a portable water-type tank; and no person may flush the retention tank by direct connection to the portable water distribution system at the Airport.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not remove a toilet waste bucket from an aircraft, unless the contents are enclosed or covered while being transported to the Airport sanitary disposal facility for emptying and cleaning.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person may not use a water hydrant at the Airport to service a toilet waste truck or cart.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A person may not operate at the Airport an aircraft soil discharge line or soil tank servicing equipment unless all connections are equipped with positive seals to prevent spillage.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A person may not operate a defective aircraft soil discharge valve or defective soil tank servicing equipment at the Airport. When a defect in the valve or equipment results in soil spillage, the aircraft or equipment owner or operator shall immediately clean and decontaminate the equipment and ground area soiled. The defective components shall be repaired or replaced before the discharge valve or servicing equipment is placed back in service.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A person may not operate a toilet waste tank truck at the Airport unless, upon notification by the Administration, the person makes all alterations to this truck as the Administration deems necessary for the sanitary operation of the aircraft toilet waste disposal system.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Aircraft and Airport Solid Waste.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may not supply or maintain receptacles at the Airport for the storage of aircraft galley paper and liquid waste or for the storage of garbage and solid waste accumulating from operations in aircraft servicing areas, unless these receptacles are covered, leakproof, fly-tight, metal roll-away containers, or other approved types of metal packer loading containers. Containers shall be emptied not less than once daily at the Airport sanitary disposal facility. If the containers are located in aircraft servicing areas, they shall be secured so as not to create a safety hazard.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not supply or maintain garbage and solid waste containers in the terminal building areas unless the same are of a type and design approved by the Administration, with the design compatible to the use and location, so as to preclude odor, insects, and vermin.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person may not use open drums or containers for storage of garbage or solid waste at the Airport.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A person may not improperly use or keep at the Airport any receptacle, including rubber tires, that holds water and is conducive to insect or rodent harborage or breeding.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A person may not dispose of waste paper or other rubbish at the Airport unless precaution is taken to prevent this paper or other rubbish from blowing onto the air operations area.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Waste Removal.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may not conduct waste removal services at the Airport without a permit from the Administration and written approval from the Maryland Department of the Environment as to the suitability of the waste removal vehicle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not operate a vehicle for hauling trash, dirt, or any other waste materials at the Airport unless this vehicle is constructed so as to prevent the contents from dropping, sifting, leaking, or otherwise escaping.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person may not maintain waste, trash, or garbage compactors or containers at the Airport other than at locations approved by the Administration. All these locations shall be kept clean and sanitary at all times by the person in charge.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A person may not place in receptacles provided by the Administration waste originating from other than normal operations of Administrative offices and terminal facilities at the Airport. Used tires, mufflers, tailpipes, and used oil or other liquids are included in this prohibition and will not be removed by Administration personnel. Private waste collection and removal services shall be hired for this purpose, subject to the requirements of §J(1) and (2), above.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Sanitation.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may not dispose of garbage, papers, solid waste, or other forms of trash at the Airport, including cigarettes, cigars, and matches, except in receptacles provided for this purpose.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not dump or dispose of any fill or building material at the Airport, or in any body of water or drainage ditch serving the Airport, unless authorized by the Administration and then only in those areas and under those conditions as are specifically designated by the Airport Director.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person may not place any foreign object in any plumbing fixture of a comfort station, terminal building, hangar, or other building on the Airport.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A person may not enter or work about any building at the Airport with bare feet.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Personal Conduct.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Use and Enjoyment of Airport.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>No person, singly or in association with others, may, by his conduct or by congregating with others, prevent any other lawfully entitled person from the use and enjoyment of the Airport and its facilities or any part of them, or prevent any other lawfully entitled person from passing from place to place, or through entrances, exits, or passageways at the Airport.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not walk, drive a motor vehicle, or ride a bicycle upon the public areas of the Airport other than on roads, walks, or rights-of-way provided for this purpose.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person may not use roller skates or skate boards at the Airport.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Smoking or carrying any lighted tobacco product in any building owned or leased by the Administration is prohibited.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Any outdoor area in which smoking or carrying lighted tobacco products is permitted shall be designated by the Administration and prominently marked.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Preservation of Property.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>No person, unless duly authorized by the Administration, may destroy, injure, deface, disturb, remove, or tamper with any building, sign, equipment, fixture, marker, or any other structure or property at the Airport.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not injure, deface, remove, destroy, or disturb the trees, flowers, shrubs, or other vegetation at the Airport.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person may not walk on a posted lawn or seeded area of the Airport.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A person may not willfully abandon any personal property at the Airport. Any person who causes damage to Airport property shall be liable for this damage, in addition to any other penalties prescribed in these regulations.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Handbills.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may not affix any printed or written material or matter anywhere in the public areas and public phone booths of the Airport, except where otherwise specifically permitted or prescribed by these regulations, or unless authorized by the Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not distribute any printed or written material or matter by placing or leaving it unattended at any location at the Airport, unless authorized by the Administration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Picketing and Demonstrations.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may not conduct picketing or demonstrations anywhere at the Airport unless permitted by the Administration and according to prescribed conditions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Persons engaged in picketing or demonstrations shall conduct these activities only in an area specified by the Airport Director.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Persons engaged in picketing or demonstrations shall conduct themselves in a peaceful and orderly manner contemplated by law, without physical harm, molestation, threat, or harassment of persons, obscenities, violence, breach of peace, or other unlawful conduct.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A person picketing or demonstrating may not obstruct the use of the Airport by others, or interfere with the proper, safe, orderly, and efficient operation of the Airport and activities conducted there.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A person under the influence of alcohol or drugs may not picket or demonstrate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The area specified for the purpose of picketing shall be kept clean and free from all debris.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Private vehicles of pickets will not be permitted to park in the vicinity of the picket line.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>All signs must be carried by persons in the picket line, and the size and type of sign must be approved in advance of a specified picket date, by the Airport Director.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Disorderly Conduct.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may not use the terminal building or any other public area of the Airport for sleeping.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not sit on the floor in the terminal building or any other public area of the Airport instead of using provided accommodations.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Intoxication. A person may not drink any intoxicating liquors upon any portion of the Airport open to the public except in places properly designated for on-premises liquor consumption.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Model Aircraft.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may not operate or release any model aircraft, rocket, kite, balloon, parachute (other than in an emergency), or other similar contrivance at or upon the Airport unless authorized by the Airport Director. This prohibition does not extend to an Airport weather station.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not throw, shoot, or propel any object in any manner that interferes with or endangers the safe operation of any aircraft landing at, taking off from, or operating at the Airport.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Animals.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>No person, other than a blind person with a seeing-eye dog, may enter any building on the Airport with a domestic animal unless the entry is relative to the animal's transportation by air and the animal is kept restrained by a leash or otherwise confined so as to be completely under control.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not enter the air operations area with a domestic animal unless the animal is kept restrained by a leash or otherwise confined so as to be completely under control.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person may not permit a domestic animal to run, roam, or be exercised on any portion of the Airport unless the animal is under the complete control of a competent handler.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A person may not permit any wild animal under his control or custody to enter the Airport, except for wild animals that are to be or have been transported by air and are properly confined for air travel, without the prior approval of the Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A person may not hunt, pursue, trap, catch, injure, or kill any animal at the Airport, except authorized personnel engaged in an official Airport bird or animal control program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A person may not ride horseback at the Airport without authorization from the Airport Director.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>A person may not permit, either willfully or through failure to exercise due care or control, any animal to urinate or defecate upon the sidewalks of the Airport or upon the floor of the terminal building or any other building used in common by the public.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>A person may not feed or do any other act to encourage the congregation of birds or other animals on or in the vicinity of the air operations area or in structures used for the storage or maintenance of aircraft.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Lost Articles. Articles found in public areas at the Airport may be deposited with the Airport Director. Articles unclaimed by their proper owner shall be disposed of by the Administration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Forgery and Counterfeit. A person may not make, possess, use, offer for sale, sell, barter, exchange, pass, or deliver any forged, counterfeit, or falsely altered pass, permit, identification card, certificate, placard, sign, or other authorization purporting to be issued by or on behalf of the Administration.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Airport Security.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Restricted Areas. A person may not enter any part of the air operations area or any other restricted area so established or posted at the Airport, except:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Persons assigned to duty or transacting business there;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Crew members, and passengers under appropriate supervision of a crew member, who enter the aircraft apron for the purpose of enplaning or deplaning an aircraft;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An authorized representative of the State, the Federal Aviation Administration, the National Transportation Safety Board, the Maryland Aviation Administration, or of any other governmental department or agency having proper business there;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>An Airport tenant or invitee of an Airport tenant in a leasehold area.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Security Regulations.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may not tamper or interfere with the lock or closing mechanism of any door, window, gate, or other opening leading to the air operations area or any other restricted area at the Airport.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not breach any other security regulation in effect at the Airport, except under emergency conditions.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Weapons.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may not carry or transport a weapon at the Airport, unless the weapon is properly packaged for shipment, except the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Law enforcement officers of the federal government, of the State, its political subdivisions, and of the Maryland Aviation Administration and any other State agency, if weapons are required in the performance of their duties;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Enplaning and deplaning passengers authorized by 49 CFR §1544.219 to carry weapons aboard aircraft;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Uniformed employees of licensed security or armored transport services under contract to any tenant of the Airport, when actually transporting monies or valuables or performing assigned duties;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Authorized members of the Maryland Air National Guard;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Those persons authorized to wear or carry handguns, or declared exempt, pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="27|36E">Article 27, §36E, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not discharge any weapon at the Airport except in the performance of official duties requiring the discharge or in the lawful defense of life or property.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person may not discharge any weapon at or near the Airport in such a manner as to cause interference with the safe taking off or landing of any aircraft.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Penalties.</heading>
    <text>Any person who violates the provisions of these regulations, except a motor vehicle parking regulation, is guilty of a misdemeanor and upon conviction shall be subject to a fine of not more than $500 or by imprisonment of not more than 90 days or both in the discretion of the court, except that for a violation of a motor vehicle parking regulation, the maximum fine may not exceed $50.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Certified Martin State Airport (MTN) Noise Zone.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definitions. Acoustic terminology definitions used in this regulation have the same meanings as stated in <cite path="11.03.03.01|A.">COMAR 11.03.03.01A</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>MTN Airport Noise Zone.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The MTN Airport Noise Zone is established pursuant to the Maryland Environmental Noise Act of 1974 (Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|5-805">5-805</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|5-806">5-806</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|5-819">5-819</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Executive Director shall update and recertify the Airport Noise Zone as required, by developing contours of equal noise exposure using day-night average sound levels (L<sub>dn</sub>) to determine the extent of impacted land uses.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Martin State Airport — Airport Noise Zone, certified by the Executive Director, and consisting of the 65, 70, and 75 L<sub>dn</sub> contours overprinted on county tax maps as follows, is incorporated by reference at <cite path="11.03.01.01">COMAR 11.03.01.01</cite>-1B(6):</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Airport Noise Zone Map;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Tax Map index;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Baltimore County Tax Maps 90 and 91.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The noise zone is a composite of the 65, 70, and 75 Ldn noise contours for the base year of 2019 and future years of 2025 and 2030.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The noise zone reflects the projected future use of the Airport, including existing and planned projects in the Master Plan or Capital Program that influence future Airport use.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>MTN Noise Abatement Plan.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The MTN Noise Abatement Plan is established pursuant to the Maryland Environmental Noise Act of 1974 (Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|5-805">5-805</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|5-806">5-806</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|5-819">5-819</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Executive Director shall review and update the MTN Noise Abatement Plan as required.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Compliance with the MTN Noise Abatement Plan.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All entities which use the Airport facilities shall comply with the MTN Noise Abatement Plan.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Maryland Air National Guard, the Maryland State Police, and local law enforcement agencies are exempt from the provisions of this regulation when operational necessity dictates noncompliance, or in the event of a State or national emergency.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The elements contained in the MTN Noise Abatement Plan are as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Airport Noise Zone (ANZ);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Control of Incompatible Development;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Noise Concerns;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Maryland Air National Guard (MDANG) Noise Barriers;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Aircraft Maintenance Engine Run-up Areas; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Noise Abatement Procedures including Visual Flight Rules (VFR) and Instrument Flight Rules (IFR) Departures, VFR and IFR Arrivals and Traffic Patterns, Closed Traffic Patterns, and Touch-and-Go or Practice Approaches.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|5-202">5-202</cite>.1, 5-204, 5-208, 5-426, 5-805, 5-806, and 5-819, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1975-10-01">Effective date: October 1, 1975 (2:24 Md. R. 1479)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1977-12-02">Chapter revised effective December 2, 1977 (4:25 Md. R. 1912)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|11.03.05">COMAR 11.03.05</cite> to <cite path="|11.03.02">11.03.02</cite></annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-10-07"><cite path="|11|03|02|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective October 7, 1985 (12:20 Md. R. 1929)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-12-24" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective December 24, 1990 (17:25 Md. R. 2908)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-10-16"><cite path="|11|03|02|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective November 20, 1995 (22:23 Md. R. 1802); October 16, 2000 (27:20 Md. R. 1840)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-01-12"><cite path="|11|03|02|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective January 12, 2009 (36:1 Md. R. 22)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-01-12"><cite path="|11|03|02|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective November 20, 1995 (22:23 Md. R. 1802); January 12, 2009 (36:1 Md. R. 22)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-10-16"><cite path="|11|03|02|.02|N.">Regulation .02N</cite>, Q amended effective October 16, 2000 (27:20 Md. R. 1840)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-01-12"><cite path="|11|03|02|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective October 16, 2000 (27:20 Md. R. 1840); January 12, 2009 (36:1 Md. R. 22)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-01-12"><cite path="|11|03|02|.03-1">Regulation .03-1</cite> amended effective October 16, 2000 (27:20 Md. R. 1840); January 12, 2009 (36:1 Md. R. 22)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-10-16"><cite path="|11|03|02|.03-2">Regulation .03-2</cite> amended effective October 16, 2000 (27:20 Md. R. 1840)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-01-12"><cite path="|11|03|02|.03-2A">Regulation .03-2A</cite> amended effective January 12, 2009 (36:1 Md. R. 22)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-01-12"><cite path="|11|03|02|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective April 11, 1994 (21:7 Md. R. 531); January 12, 2009 (36:1 Md. R. 22)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1991-09-30"><cite path="|11|03|02|.04|V.">Regulation .04V</cite> amended effective September 30, 1991 (18:19 Md. R. 2102)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-04-11"><cite path="|11|03|02|.04-1">Regulation .04-1</cite> adopted effective April 11, 1994 (21:7 Md. R. 531)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-01-12"><cite path="|11|03|02|.04-1B">Regulation .04-1B</cite> amended effective January 12, 2009 (36:1 Md. R. 22)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-10-16"><cite path="|11|03|02|.05|G.">Regulation .05G</cite> amended and I adopted effective October 16, 2000 (27:20 Md. R. 1840)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-01-12"><cite path="|11|03|02|.05|G.">Regulation .05G</cite>, I amended effective January 12, 2009 (36:1 Md. R. 22)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-01-12"><cite path="|11|03|02|.06|K.">Regulation .06K</cite> amended effective January 12, 2009 (36:1 Md. R. 22)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-01-12"><cite path="|11|03|02|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective January 12, 2009 (36:1 Md. R. 22)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-05-23"><cite path="|11|03|02|.07|A.">Regulation .07A</cite> amended effective May 23, 1994 (21:10 Md. R. 845)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-01-12"><cite path="|11|03|02|.08|C.">Regulation .08C</cite> amended effective January 12, 2009 (36:1 Md. R. 22)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-11-20"><cite path="|11|03|02|.10">Regulation .10</cite> repealed and new Regulation .10 adopted effective November 20, 1995 (22:23 Md. R. 1802)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-12-24"><cite path="|11|03|02|.10|B.">Regulation .10B</cite> amended effective October 16, 2000 (27:20 Md. R. 1840); December 24, 2001 (28:25 Md. R. 2192); December 24, 2012 (39:25 Md. R. 1614)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-04-19"><cite path="|11|03|02|.10|B.">Regulation .10B</cite>, C amended effective April 19, 2021 (48:8 Md. R. 310)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
