<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>09</num>
  <heading>Issuance of Citations by Maryland Aviation Administration Personnel</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>The purpose of these regulations is to establish:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Qualifications for employees designated under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|5-212">Transportation Article, §5-212</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland, including prerequisites of character, training, experience, and education; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Standards for the performance of the duties assigned to employees designated under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|5-212">Transportation Article, §5-212</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Administration" means the Maryland Aviation Administration of the Maryland Department of Transportation, established pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|2-102">Transportation Article, §2-102(b)(2), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Airport" means Baltimore/Washington International Thurgood Marshall Airport or Martin State Airport, owned by the State and operated by the Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Motor vehicle" means a device in, upon, or by which a person or property may be propelled, moved, or drawn upon land, except:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A device moved by human or animal power; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Aircraft and devices moved exclusively upon stationary rails or tracks.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Traffic" means pedestrians and vehicles, singly or together, using any airport area.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Traffic control officer" means an Administration employee authorized to issue a citation under these regulations and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|5-212">Transportation Article, §5-212</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|03|09|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Employee Qualifications and Training.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Character.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A traffic control officer shall successfully pass a preemployment background investigation and may not have been convicted of a felony.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A traffic control officer who fails to maintain a good character shall be relieved immediately of the authority to issue citations under these regulations and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|5-212">Transportation Article, §5-212</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Experience and Education. A traffic control officer shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Have a minimum of 1 year of experience as a security officer or in a closely related field; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Possess a high school diploma or a State equivalence certificate.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Training.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An individual designated as a traffic control officer shall be trained in:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All provisions of <cite path="|11.03.01">COMAR 11.03.01</cite> and <cite path="|11.03.02">11.03.02</cite> relating to traffic control and traffic regulations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The preparation of citations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The areas of customer service, conflict resolution, Airport operations, and organization; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Courtroom procedures, including courtroom demeanor and case presentation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The training shall consist of a minimum of 12 hours covering the subject areas in <cite path="11|03|09|.03|C.|(1)">§C(1) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Performance Standards for Traffic Control Officers.</heading>
    <text>A traffic control officer shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Act in a manner to bring credit both to the position of traffic control officer and the Administration;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Act in a reasonable manner so as to avoid any confrontation which may lead to personal injury or embarrassment to the Administration;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Keep abreast of changes to aspects of the law, regulations, and policies which impact on the traffic control officer's duties;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Strictly adhere to and enforce the Airport's security plan;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Assist law enforcement officers when requested in security matters so as to ensure the safety of the public, employees, and airport property;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Safeguard, maintain, and clean all equipment, uniforms, and accessories which are issued;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Be considered in a sensitive classification and be subject to the substance abuse policy of the Administration; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Observe all State laws and personnel policies and regulations applicable to Administration employees.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|5-212">5-212</cite>.1 and 5-426, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-12-21">Effective date: December 21, 1992 (19:25 Md. R. 2206)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-10-16"><cite path="|11|03|09|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective October 16, 2000 (27:20 Md. R. 1840)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-01-12"><cite path="|11|03|09|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective January 12, 2009 (36:1 Md. R. 23)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
