<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>07</num>
  <heading>Medical Day Care Services</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|09|07|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Adult Day Care Assessment and Planning System (ADCAPS)" means a system that is comprised of a comprehensive assessment completed by a registered nurse, which is designed to evaluate the participant’s strengths and needs, and to facilitate the development of a problem list, service plan, and plan of care.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Adult Evaluation and Review Services (AERS)" means an entity within the local health department which, in accordance with the waiver, this chapter, and <cite path="|10.09.30">COMAR 10.09.30</cite>, assesses waiver applicants and participants.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Advance directive" has the meaning stated in Health-General Article, §5-601, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Community Settings Questionnaire" means the participant survey, completed annually or when a participant changes medical day care centers or sites, that is part of the State’s strategy to validate provider compliance with federal requirements on home and community based settings.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Daily attendance record" means a daily attendance account of the physical presence of each medical day care participant that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is designed by the provider;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is signed and dated by the staff designated to take attendance or by the medical day care director; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Includes the name, medical assistance number, date of service, and arrival and departure times, of each participant, including documentation of time of temporary absences.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Department" means the Maryland Department of Health.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Home and community based services waiver" means a program implemented by the Department and approved by the Secretary of Health and Human Services, which authorizes the waiver of certain specified federal statutory requirements limiting coverage for home and community based services under the Maryland Medical Assistance Program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Licensed practical nurse" means an individual licensed to practice licensed practical nursing under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 8, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Licensed social worker" means an individual who is licensed to practice social work under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 19, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Maintenance services" means the periodic monitoring of medically stable patients and the services provided in order to maintain their health care status.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Medical Assistance Program" means the Program administered by Maryland under Title XIX of the Social Security Act, which provides comprehensive medical and other health-related care for categorically eligible and medically needy recipients.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>"Medical day care" means medically supervised, health-related services provided in an ambulatory setting to medically handicapped adults, who, due to their degree of impairment, need health maintenance and restorative services supportive to their community living.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>"Medical day care center" means a facility operated for the purpose of providing medical day care services in an ambulatory care setting to medically handicapped adults who do not require 24-hour inpatient care, but, due to their degree of impairment, are not capable of full-time independent living.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>"Medical director" means an individual who is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Licensed to practice medicine under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 14, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Employed by the medical day care center either as a staff member or by a contractual agreement.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>"Medically handicapped adult" has the meaning stated in Health-General Article, §14-301(c), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>"Medically necessary" means that a service or benefit is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Directly related to diagnostic, preventive, curative, palliative, rehabilitative, or ameliorative treatment of an illness, injury, disability, or health condition;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Consistent with current accepted standards of good medical practice;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The most cost efficient service that can be provided without sacrificing effectiveness or access to care; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Not primarily for the convenience of the consumer, family, or provider.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>"Multidisciplinary team" means the group consisting of members of the medical day care center’s professional staff, the participant, the participant’s authorized representative, health care professionals, and waiver case managers, as appropriate, that establishes and updates the participant’s service plan and plan of care.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>"Occupational therapist" means an individual who practices occupational therapy under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 10, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>"Occupational therapy" means medically prescribed treatment concerned with improving or restoring functions which have been impaired by illness or injury or, when function has been permanently lost or reduced by illness or injury, concerned with improving the individual's ability to perform those tasks for independent functioning.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>"Participant" means an individual:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Who is a medically handicapped adult as defined under <cite path="10|09|07|.01|B.|(14)">§B(14) of this regulation</cite> and who is certified by the Department or its designee as requiring nursing facility services, as defined under <cite path="|10.09.10">COMAR 10.09.10</cite>, but whose condition does not require institutional care if medical day care services or other services that provide alternatives to institutional care are available;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Who is enrolled in a home and community based services waiver that includes medical day care as a waiver service; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Whose disabilities and needs cannot be satisfactorily and totally met in an episodic ambulatory care setting but require participation at least 1 day a week in a day-long rehabilitative or maintenance ambulatory care program which provides a mix of medical and social services and is authorized in the participant’s home and community based services waiver service plan.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>"Personal care services" means assistance with activities of daily living.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>"Physical therapist" means an individual licensed to practice physical therapy under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 13, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>"Physical therapy" means treatment of disease and injury through use of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Therapeutic exercise and modalities of heat, cold, water, light, electricity, massage and radiant energy (other than roentgen rays, radium or use of electricity for cauterization in surgery); or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Administration and interpretation of tests and measurements of neuromuscular and musculoskeletal functions; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Both §B(22)(a) and (b) of this regulation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(24)</num>
        <text>"Plan of care" means a written plan established by the multidisciplinary team in accordance with <cite path="10.12.04.22">COMAR 10.12.04.22</cite>, based upon a medical order and an assessment of the participant’s health status and special care requirements.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(25)</num>
        <text>"Preventive services" means those services designed to prevent the occurrence and/or progression of disease at an early stage before complications and serious disabilities develop.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(26)</num>
        <text>"Primary care provider" means a physician, physician assistant, or nurse practitioner who is the primary coordinator of care for the participant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(27)</num>
        <text>"Program" means the Maryland Medical Assistance Program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(28)</num>
        <text>"Provider" means a facility licensed under <cite path="|10.12.04">COMAR 10.12.04</cite> furnishing medical day care services through an appropriate agreement with the Department and identified as a provider by the issuance of an individual account number.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(29)</num>
        <text>"Provider agreement" means a contract between the Department of Health and the provider of medical day care, specifying the services to be performed, methods of operation, financial and legal requirements which shall be in force before Program participation in medical day care.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(30)</num>
        <text>"Recipient" means a person who is certified for, and is receiving, Medical Assistance benefits.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(31)</num>
        <text>"Referral" means to direct a participant, family member, or caretaker to the appropriate community agency or health care provider, or to contact the agency or provider on the participant's behalf, to facilitate access to needed services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(32)</num>
        <text>"Registered nurse" means an individual licensed to practice as a registered nurse under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 8, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(33)</num>
        <text>"Secretary" means the Secretary of Health.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(34)</num>
        <text>"Service Plan" means an approved document which specifies the type, amount, frequency, and duration of all waiver and other Medicaid services required to safely support the waiver participant in the community.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(35)</num>
        <text>"Significant change in condition" means a change in the participant’s physical, mental, or psychological status as identified by the comprehensive assessment performed by a registered nurse.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(36)</num>
        <text>"Specially equipped vehicles" means those vehicles used to transport participants with severe physical disabilities that limit mobility.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(37)</num>
        <text>"Supervision" means initial direction or periodic monitoring of the actual activity.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Licensing Requirements.</heading>
    <text>The provider shall be licensed under <cite path="|10.12.04">COMAR 10.12.04</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Conditions for Participation.</heading>
    <text>Requirements for providing medical day care services are that the providers shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Meet the licensure requirements as provided in <cite path="|10|09|07|.02">Regulation .02 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Meet the requirements of <cite path="|10.09.36">COMAR 10.09.36</cite>;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Be open to participants at least 6 hours a day, 5 days a week, and post hours of operation;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Verify the licenses and credentials for all professionals employed by or contracting with the medical day care center;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Provide or arrange for the provision of any covered service, as specified in <cite path="|10|09|07|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>, or any other service which is required by a plan of care;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Demonstrate to the satisfaction of the Program that a need exists for medical day care in the service area and that the provider has the necessary expertise to deliver the service;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Have policies and procedures as required under <cite path="|10.12.04">COMAR 10.12.04</cite>;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Maintain medical records for each participant which shall include, as a minimum, the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An application for admission;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The medical day care center's plan of care as required under §M(3)—(4) of this regulation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The current home and community based services waiver service plan or the approved medical day care preauthorization form for the participant;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Medical orders for all services rendered which may include, but is not limited to, the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Type and duration of service;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Frequency of service; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Dosage and frequency of medications when prescribed;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The medical history, chronic illnesses, principal and significant diagnoses, prognoses, prescribed medications, special diets, allergies, and assessments of the recipient's physical and mental status specifying the general types of activities the recipient can and cannot do;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The documentation of daily nursing observations for the first 5 days of attendance, and monthly after the first 5 days of attendance; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The initial social history, ADCAPS assessment, and, when needed, social service and activity progress notes;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Have an emergency plan for each participant which includes, as a minimum, an easily located file on each participant, listing:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The name and telephone number of the participant’s primary care provider;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The advance directive in accordance with Health-General Article, §5-602, if requested or made by the participant;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All allergies identified by the participant or the participant’s primary care provider;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The treatments or medications for a participant's conditions; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The name and telephone number of a family member, caregiver, or friend to be notified in case of emergency;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Provide training for medical day care staff in emergency procedures, including cardiopulmonary resuscitation and first aid;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Have accurate daily attendance records that are easily retrievable and available for review by the Program;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Have accurate daily transportation records that are easily retrievable and available for review by the Program, and shall include, as a minimum, each participant's transportation plan;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>Establish a multidisciplinary team who shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Assess the participant to determine the appropriateness of the medical day care center's care, interventions, and activities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Determine the medical, psychosocial, and functional status of each participant by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Establishing the ADCAPS evaluations on the date of admission; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Completing the assessment with an initial plan of care within 30 days, after which the ADCAPS evaluations shall be conducted every 4 months;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Develop an individual plan of care in conjunction with the service plan;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Review and update with the participant or participant’s representative, the individual plan of care semi-annually, or more frequently when a significant change in condition is identified or reported; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Obtain the signature of the participant or the participant’s representative to document their approval of the individual plan of care semi-annually, or more frequently when a significant change in condition is identified or reported.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>Have a quality assurance program which includes, as a minimum, health care audits and utilization reviews that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Consist of a review of medical records on all participants that evaluate the appropriateness of admissions, the efficiency, adequacy, and coordination of provided services, and the length of stay and discharge practices, as needed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Include the following elements:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Development of outcome criteria for presenting problems common to the medical day care center's participants;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Description of actual outcomes as abstracted from the medical day care center's medical records for all the participants served over a specific time period for each presenting problem for which outcome criteria have been developed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Evaluation of actual outcomes compared with the outcome criteria to identify problem areas or reasons for suboptimal care;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Documented submission of recommended corrective action to the program director; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Reassessment of the appropriateness of the recommended corrective action as revealed by the outcomes of the next audit; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Is signed and dated by the program director or designee; and</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>Have a signed and dated corrective action plan transferring the participant to the appropriate service, if it is determined that the medical day care center's program is not appropriate for an individual participant.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Staffing Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The medical day care center shall have adequate staffing capability to monitor the participants at all times. The composition of the staff depends in part on the needs of the participants and on the number of participants the medical day care center serves. At a minimum, the medical day care center shall meet the requirements of <cite path="10.12.04.14">COMAR 10.12.04.14</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The medical day care center shall also have:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A full-time or part-time licensed social worker, who has at least 1 year of experience providing services to adults in a health care setting; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A full-time, part-time, or contractual medical director who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Has 1 year of experience in the care of impaired adults; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>May function as the primary care provider for those participants who do not have a primary care provider, consult with staff regarding a participant’s condition and medical needs, and assist with the development of the medical day care center’s health care policies.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The medical day care center is required under <cite path="|10.12.04">COMAR 10.12.04</cite> to have a director who has a bachelor's degree or is a registered nurse. When the director is not a registered nurse, the center shall designate a health director who is a registered nurse. The health director shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Establish, develop, and amend the center's health care policies and procedures;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Supervise health care services;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Manage the delivery of all required health care services to ensure that needed services are provided in a timely manner by appropriate personnel consistent with each individual's plan of care; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Consult with other health care providers to coordinate care, services, and referrals.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|09|07|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Covered Services.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Program reimburses for a day of care which includes the following services:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Health care services supervised by the director, medical director, or health director, which emphasize primary prevention, early diagnosis and treatment, rehabilitation and continuity of care, including the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Participation in the development of the individual participant's plan of care;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Participation in the determination of the participant's medical, psychosocial, and functional status;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Consultation with the participant’s primary care provider; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Consultation with staff regarding a participant's condition and health care needs;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Nursing services performed by a registered nurse or by a licensed practical nurse under the supervision of a registered nurse which include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The evaluation of the needs of the participants for nursing care;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The supervision of any nursing staff;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Preventive and maintenance services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Observation and monitoring of participant's condition;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Rehabilitative services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The teaching and training activities in appropriate self-care techniques;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>The supervision of medication normally self-administered;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>The provision of health education;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Discharge planning; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Nursing services that may be delegated to other staff in accordance with the Maryland Nurse Practice Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 8, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Physical therapy services, performed by or under supervision of a licensed physical therapist, which meet the following conditions:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Are of a diagnostic, rehabilitative, therapeutic, or maintenance nature, and are provided with the expectation based on the assessment made by the primary care provider, that a participant will improve significantly in a reasonable and generally predictable period of time, or are necessary for the establishment of a safe and effective maintenance program required in connection with a specific disease state;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Are directly related to the primary care provider’s written plan of care which specifies:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Part or parts to be treated;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Type of modalities or treatments to be rendered;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Expected results of physical therapy treatments;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Frequency and duration of treatment;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The complexity and sophistication of the services, or the condition of a participant, requires the judgment, knowledge, and skills of a licensed physical therapist; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The services are considered within accepted standards of medical practice to be a specified and effective treatment for a participant's condition;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Occupational therapy services, performed by an occupational therapist, that meet the following conditions:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The treatment requires the special skills of an occupational therapist;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The services are directly related to the primary care provider’s written plan of care which specifies the treatment to be rendered, the frequency and duration of treatment, and the expected results of treatment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The treatment is provided with the expectation that there will be a significant practical improvement in a participant's level of functioning within a reasonable period of time; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The services fall within one or more of the following categories:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Evaluation and reevaluation of a participant's level of functioning by administering diagnostic and prognostic tests;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Selection and teaching of task-oriented therapeutic activities designed to restore physical function;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Teaching of compensatory techniques to improve the level of independence in the activities of daily living;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Training in the use of supportive and adaptive equipment, and assistive devices required for independent performance according to <cite path="|10.09.12">COMAR 10.09.12</cite>; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Improvement of mobility skills;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Personal care services which include assistance with activities of daily living such as:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Bathing;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Eating;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Toileting;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Dressing; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Ambulation;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Nutrition services which include the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Meals and snacks as specified under <cite path="10.12.04.20">COMAR 10.12.04.20</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Therapeutic diets as specified under <cite path="10.12.04.20">COMAR 10.12.04.20</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Dietary counseling and education;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Social work services performed by a licensed, certified social worker or licensed social work associate which include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Screening and interviewing or assisting designated staff with screening and interviewing all referrals to determine the general appropriateness of the prospective participant for the full assessment process and medical day care participation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Ongoing services to include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Identifying the emotional and social needs of participants during the rendering of medical day care services;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Maintaining linkages with community support resources for the participant including relatives, friends, and other care providers;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Counseling to improve the participant's response to the plan of care, chronic condition, and prospects for recovery or stabilization, but does not include diagnosing or treating mental disorders;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Counseling a participant and a participant's family in the availability and utilization of public and private community agency services, referral to, and coordination of these services;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Assisting participants in obtaining those health care services which are not available through the medical day care center (such as vision care, podiatry, medical equipment, etc.);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Counseling participants individually to assist with acclimation to the medical day care center's services and to promote active involvement in their plan of care;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Coordinating and implementing group and family counseling in conjunction with plan of care goals;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Writing notes in the participant’s records that reflect the social work activities performed;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ix)</num>
            <text>Participating in the multidisciplinary team meetings; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(x)</num>
            <text>Assisting participants with completing the Community Settings Questionnaire; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Discharge planning and referral services including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Written procedures for discharge, referral, and follow-up;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A discharge summary with post discharge goals;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Recommendations for continuing care; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Referral to appropriate community service agencies and health care providers to facilitate the participant's return to more independent living;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Activity programs in accordance with <cite path="10.12.04.15|C.">COMAR 10.12.04.15C</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Transportation services that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Are in accordance with <cite path="10.12.04.27">COMAR 10.12.04.27</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Are provided or arranged for a participant by the medical day care staff;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Maximize the following types of transportation services in an effort to achieve the least costly, yet appropriate means of transportation for a participant:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Walking, for a person who lives within walking distance of the medical day care center and who is sufficiently mobile;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Family-supplied transportation provided by friends, neighbors, or volunteers; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Public transportation services;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Are procured by the provider after options described in <cite path="10|09|07|.05|A.|(10)|(b)">§A(10)(b) of this regulation</cite> have been exhausted;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Are the responsibility of the provider to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Arrange contractual agreements with transportation providers to meet the transportation needs of the participants; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Group participants, where possible, in the same taxi, van or specially equipped vehicles, to minimize the cost of transportation;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Are provided in accordance with records that clearly indicate both a primary transportation plan and a back-up plan;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Are documented, indicating the type of transportation used by each participant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Are scheduled to ensure that a participant's one-way transit time does not exceed 1 hour as specified under <cite path="10.12.04.27">COMAR 10.12.04.27</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Are included in the day of care for:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Trips and outings which are part of the activities program; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A participant's medical appointment escorted by center staff.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Department shall reimburse for a day of care when this care is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Authorized in the participant's waiver service plan;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Medically necessary;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Adequately described in progress notes in the participant's medical record, signed and dated by the individual providing care;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Provided to a participant certified annually by the Department as requiring nursing facility care as specified under <cite path="|10.09.10">COMAR 10.09.10</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Provided to participants certified present at the medical day care center a minimum of 4 hours a day by an adequately maintained and documented participant register.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Limitations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Medical day care services are not covered for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Individuals who do not meet the definition of "participant" in <cite path="|10|09|07|.01|B.">Regulation .01B of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Individuals younger than 16 years old.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Covered services do not include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Days of service in excess of the frequency specified in the participant’s home and community based services waiver service plan;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Services which are not part of those services listed in <cite path="|10|09|07|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Services for a number of participants that exceeds the provider’s licensed capacity on a given day;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>More than one day of care, per participant, per day; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A day of care provided on the same day that the following services are provided and billed to the Department:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Day habilitation services under <cite path="|10.09.26">COMAR 10.09.26</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Supported employment services under <cite path="|10.09.26">COMAR 10.09.26</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Programs of All-Inclusive Care for the Elderly under <cite path="|10.09.44">COMAR 10.09.44</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Senior center plus services under <cite path="|10.09.54">COMAR 10.09.54</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Adult day care reimbursed under the State of Maryland's human service contracts; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>On-site psychiatric rehabilitation services under <cite path="|10.09.59">COMAR 10.09.59</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Authorization Requirements.</heading>
    <text>The provider is entitled to reimbursement from the Program when:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The participant is enrolled in a home and community based services waiver; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The service is specified in the participant’s home and community based services waiver service plan.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|09|07|.08">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Payment Procedures.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Requests for Payment.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All requests for payment of services rendered shall be submitted in accordance with <cite path="|10.09.36">COMAR 10.09.36</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Billing time limitations for claims submitted pursuant to this chapter are set forth in <cite path="|10.09.36">COMAR 10.09.36</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Payment to a provider shall be limited to the number of days each participant attends the medical day care center, as authorized by a participant’s home and community based services waiver service plan.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Payment shall be made only to a qualified medical day care provider. Payment may not be made to a participant, or to individual nurses, physicians, social workers, activity coordinators, or aides for services rendered in connection with the provision of medical day care.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Per Diem Rate.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Payment to a medical day care services provider shall be as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>For dates of service from January 1, 2021 through October 31, 2021, $88.95 per diem;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For dates of service from November 1, 2021 through June 30, 2022, $93.58 per diem; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>For dates of service on or after July 1, 2022, $104.81 per diem.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Subject to the limitations of the State budget, the per diem rate shall increase on July 1 of each year by 4 percent.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Payment to a provider of medical day care services may not exceed the lesser of the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Per diem rate established under <cite path="10|09|07|.08|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provider's customary charge to the general public for services covered by the Program, unless the service is free to individuals not covered by Medicaid.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If the service is free to individuals not covered by Medicaid:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The provider:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>May charge the Program; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Shall be reimbursed in accordance with <cite path="10|09|07|.08|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The provider’s reimbursement is not limited to the provider’s customary charge.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Recovery and Reimbursement.</heading>
    <text>Recovery and reimbursement shall be in accordance with <cite path="|10.09.36">COMAR 10.09.36</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Cause for Suspension or Removal and Imposition of Sanctions.</heading>
    <text>Cause for suspension or removal and imposition of sanctions shall be in accordance with <cite path="|10.09.36">COMAR 10.09.36</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Appeal Procedures.</heading>
    <text>Appeal procedures shall be in accordance with <cite path="|10.09.36">COMAR 10.09.36</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Interpretive Regulation.</heading>
    <text>State regulations shall be interpreted in accordance with <cite path="|10.09.36">COMAR 10.09.36</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health-General Article, §§2-104(b), 15-103, 15-105, and 15-111, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1980-01-01">Effective date: January 1, 1980 (6:26 Md. R. 2073)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-03-10">Regulations .03B, C and .07D amended effective March 10, 1986 (13:5 Md. R. 543)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1983-01-06"><cite path="|10|09|07|.03|D.">Regulation .03D</cite> adopted effective January 6, 1983 (9:26 Md. R. 2572)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1984-01-30"><cite path="|10|09|07|.03|E.">Regulation .03E</cite> adopted and .07A amended effective January 30, 1984 (11:2 Md. R. 113)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-06-03"><cite path="|10|09|07|.07|A.">Regulation .07A</cite> amended effective June 3, 1985 (12:11 Md. R. 1049)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1983-09-12"><cite path="|10|09|07|.07|F.">Regulation .07F</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 1, 1983 (10:12 Md. R. 1070); adopted permanently effective September 12, 1983 (10:18 Md. R. 1608)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-05-12"><cite path="|10|09|07|.08|A.">Regulation .08A</cite> amended effective May 12, 1986 (13:9 Md. R. 1029)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1981-08-17"><cite path="|10|09|07|.09|A.">Regulation .09A</cite>, B amended effective August 17, 1981 (8:16 Md. R. 1365)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1983-06-06"><cite path="|10|09|07|.10">Regulation .10</cite> amended effective June 6, 1983 (10:11 Md. R. 974)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1982-10-25"><cite path="|10|09|07|.11">Regulation .11</cite> adopted effective October 25, 1982 (9:21 Md. R. 2106)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-05-01" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective May 1, 1989 (16:8 Md. R. 909)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-11-01">Regulations .01B and 07A amended as an emergency provision effective July 17, 1990 (17:16 Md. R. 1984); adopted permanently effective November 1, 1990 (17:20 Md. R. 2427)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-11-01">Regulations .03J and K and .09 amended as an emergency provision effective July 1, 1990 (17:15 Md. R. 1850); adopted permanently effective November 1, 1990 (17:21 Md. R. 2529)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1991-01-28"><cite path="|10|09|07|.09|A.">Regulation .09A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective January 28, 1991 (18:3 Md. R. 301); emergency status expired April 8, 1991 (18:9 Md. R. 1004)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1991-10-07"><cite path="|10|09|07|.09|A.">Regulation .09A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective April 9, 1991 (18:9 Md. R. 1005); amended permanently effective October 7, 1991 (18:18 Md. R. 2004)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-11-24"><cite path="|10|09|07|.09|D.">Regulation .09D</cite> amended effective July 4, 1994 (21:13 Md. R. 1157); November 24, 2003 (30:23 Md. R. 1651)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-02-01"><cite path="|10|09|07|.09-1">Regulation .09-1</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective February 1, 2002 (29:4 Md. R. 412); emergency status expired June 30, 2002</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-01-14" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective January 14, 2008 (35:1 Md. R. 17)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-12-15"><cite path="|10|09|07|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 1, 2008 (35:17 Md. R. 1480); amended permanently effective December 15, 2008 (35:25 Md. R. 2150)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-05-20"><cite path="|10|09|07|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective February 15, 2016 (43:3 Md. R. 272); May 20, 2019 (46:10 Md. R. 485)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-12-15"><cite path="|10|09|07|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 1, 2008 (35:17 Md. R. 1480); amended permanently effective December 15, 2008 (35:25 Md. R. 2150)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-05-20"><cite path="|10|09|07|.03|H.">Regulation .03H</cite>, I amended effective May 20, 2019 (46:10 Md. R. 485)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-02-15"><cite path="|10|09|07|.03|H.">Regulation .03H</cite>, M amended effective February 15, 2016 (43:3 Md. R. 272)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-05-18"><cite path="|10|09|07|.03|M.">Regulation .03M</cite> amended effective April 4, 2011 (38:7 Md. R. 431); May 18, 2020 (47:10 Md. R. 516)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-02-15"><cite path="|10|09|07|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite> amended effective February 15, 2016 (43:3 Md. R. 272)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-12-15"><cite path="|10|09|07|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite>, B amended as an emergency provision effective July 1, 2008 (35:17 Md. R. 1480); amended permanently effective December 15, 2008 (35:25 Md. R. 2150)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-05-20"><cite path="|10|09|07|.04|B.">Regulation .04B</cite> amended effective February 22, 2010 (37:4 Md. R. 340); April 4, 2011 (38:7 Md. R. 431); May 20, 2019 (46:10 Md. R. 485)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-12-15"><cite path="|10|09|07|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 1, 2008 (35:17 Md. R. 1480); amended permanently effective December 15, 2008 (35:25 Md. R. 2150)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-05-18"><cite path="|10|09|07|.05|A.">Regulation .05A</cite> amended effective February 15, 2016 (43:3 Md. R. 272); May 20, 2019 (46:10 Md. R. 485); May 18, 2020 (47:10 Md. R. 516)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-12-15"><cite path="|10|09|07|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 1, 2008 (35:17 Md. R. 1480); amended permanently effective December 15, 2008 (35:25 Md. R. 2150)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-05-20"><cite path="|10|09|07|.06|B.">Regulation .06B</cite> amended effective February 15, 2016 (43:3 Md. R. 272); May 20, 2019 (46:10 Md. R. 485)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-12-15"><cite path="|10|09|07|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 1, 2008 (35:17 Md. R. 1480); amended permanently effective December 15, 2008 (35:25 Md. R. 2150)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-02-15"><cite path="|10|09|07|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective February 15, 2016 (43:3 Md. R. 272)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-12-15"><cite path="|10|09|07|.08">Regulation .08</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 1, 2008 (35:17 Md. R. 1480); amended permanently effective December 15, 2008 (35:25 Md. R. 2150)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-10-10"><cite path="|10|09|07|.08">Regulation .08</cite> amended effective October 10, 2016 (43:20 Md. R. 1110)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-02-15"><cite path="|10|09|07|.08|B.">Regulation .08B</cite> amended effective February 15, 2016 (43:3 Md. R. 272)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-10-16"><cite path="|10|09|07|.08|D.">Regulation .08D</cite> amended effective April 6, 2009 (36:7 Md. R. 523); February 22, 2010 (37:4 Md. R. 340); October 31, 2011 (38:22 Md. R. 1345); May 20, 2019 (46:10 Md. R. 486); May 18, 2020 (47:10 Md. R. 516)​; November 14, 2022 (49:23 Md. R. 995); October 16, 2023 (50:20 Md. R. 886)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-04-01"><cite path="|10|09|07|.08-1">Regulation .08-1</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective April 1, 2008 (35:9 Md. R. 892); emergency status expired August 22, 2008</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-04-04"><cite path="|10|09|07|.09">Regulation .09</cite> amended effective April 4, 2011 (38:7 Md. R. 431)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
