<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>66</num>
  <heading>Assistance in Community Integration Services</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Assistance in Community Integration Services (ACIS)” means the ACIS program, a health related social needs benefit for qualified individuals, which is implemented in accordance with the HealthChoice Section 1115 Waiver approved by the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Compliance activities” means tasks undertaken to ensure that ACIS is delivered in accordance with the HealthChoice Section 1115 Waiver approved by the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Continuum of Care Program” means the regional or local planning body that coordinates housing and services funding for families and individuals experiencing homelessness.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Homelessness” has the meaning stated in 24 CFR §578.3.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Lead entity” means a local health department or local governmental agency, which:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Has been awarded participant spaces in the ACIS program;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is an enrolled provider with the Maryland Medical Assistance Program;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Is responsible for leadership, coordination, oversight, and monitoring of ACIS;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Shall serve as the organizing hub and contact point for ACIS with all collaborators, including the participant’s MCO; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Shall facilitate the financial arrangement and payments with designated subcontractors.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Managed care organization (MCO)”  has the meaning stated in Health-General Article, §15-101, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Participant” has the meaning stated in <cite path="10.09.36.01">COMAR 10.09.36.01</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Program” means the Maryland Medical Assistance Program.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Conditions for Participation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A provider shall meet all conditions for participation as set forth in <cite path="10.09.36.03">COMAR 10.09.36.03</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A lead entity shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Have been awarded participant spaces for ACIS by the Program; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Be a member of its local Continuum of Care Program.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Eligibility for Services.</heading>
    <text>Eligibility for ACIS services under this chapter is limited to individuals who meet the following health and housing criteria:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The individual is a participant that uses Maryland Medical Assistance;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The individual meets at least one of the following health criteria:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Repeated emergency department visits;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Repeated hospital admissions in the past year; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Two or more chronic conditions as defined in §1945(h)(2) of the Social Security Act; and</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The individual meets at least one of the following housing criteria:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is homeless, chronically homeless, or at risk of homelessness as defined in 24 CFR §578.3; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is at risk of institutional placement.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|09|66|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Covered Services.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Program shall cover the following ACIS services:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Compliance activities; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Housing and tenancy-based case management services when three or more services, as specified in <cite path="10|09|66|.04|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, are delivered per month per participant.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Housing and tenancy-based case management services include the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Community integration assessments to identify the participant’s:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Housing preferences;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Needs for support to maintain community integration;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Budgeting needs;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Needs for assistance applying for social services; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Needs for support regarding understanding and meeting obligations of tenancy;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The development of a person-centered community integration plan with enumerated measurable goals inclusive of review and modification of the plan when necessary;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Participation in meetings related to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Housing support;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Crisis management; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Person-centered planning;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Assistance in connecting individuals with social services defined in the integration plan such as:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Housing required to meet the participant’s medical care needs;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Independent living services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Counseling services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Employment support services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Services required to meet the participant’s medical needs;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Transportation for services; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Entitlement programs;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Assistance in communication with property managers or landlord for accommodation needs; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Connecting the participant to training and resource support related to being housed and household management.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Limitations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Under this chapter, the Program does not cover the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Services provided to or for the primary benefit of individuals other than the participant;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Services rendered but not appropriately documented; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Room and board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Providers may not bill for monthly ACIS case-management services if less than three housing and tenancy-based case management services were rendered to the participant for the month.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Providers may not bill for compliance activities more than once per participant per calendar year.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Payment Procedures.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General policies governing payment procedures that are applicable to all providers are set forth in <cite path="10.09.36.04">COMAR 10.09.36.04</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Billing time limitations for claims submitted pursuant to this chapter are set forth in <cite path="10.09.36.06">COMAR 10.09.36.06</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Payments for services rendered to a participant shall be made directly to the qualified lead entity.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Effective January 1, 2025, rates for the services outlined in this chapter shall be as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>$725 per member per month for ACIS housing and tenancy-based case management; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>$100 per member per year for compliance activities.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Recovery and Reimbursement.</heading>
    <text>Recovery and reimbursement regulations are as set forth in <cite path="10.09.36.07">COMAR 10.09.36.07</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Cause for Suspension or Removal and Imposition of Sanctions.</heading>
    <text>Cause for suspension or removal and imposition of sanctions are as set forth in <cite path="10.09.36.08">COMAR 10.09.36.08</cite></text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Appeal Procedures.</heading>
    <text>Providers filing appeals from administrative decisions made in connection with these regulations shall do so according to <cite path="10.09.36.09">COMAR 10.09.36.09</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Interpretive Regulation.</heading>
    <text>Interpretive regulatory requirements shall be as set forth in <cite path="10.09.36.10">COMAR 10.09.36.10</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health-General Article, §§2-104(b), 15-103, and 15-105, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-05-12">Effective date: May 12, 2025 (52:9 Md. R. 405)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
