<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>General</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="14|25|01|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this subtitle, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Authority" means the Maryland Stadium Authority, an independent unit of the Executive Branch of State Government.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Authority Facility.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Authority facility" means:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The Camden Yards Sports Complex, including Oriole Park at Camden Yards and the Ravens' Stadium;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Offices, restaurants, stores, museums, parking facilities, and other facilities located on the Camden Yards Sports Complex; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Facilities located on other Authority property.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Authority facility" includes the grounds and walkways surrounding the facilities listed in <cite path="14|25|01|.01|B.|(2)|(a)">§B(2)(a) of this regulation</cite> and adjacent parking lots or garages owned or controlled by the Authority.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Camden Station” means the building known as Camden Station located within the Camden Yards Sports Complex, but does not include the grounds and walkways surrounding it.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Demonstration” means a person or gathering of persons at an Authority facility for the purpose of expressing an opinion to observers through use of their speech, signs, or express conduct, excluding any expression or conduct prohibited under <cite path="|14.25.02">COMAR 14.25.02</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Director of Facilities Management” means the director of a particular Authority facility.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Director of Security Management” means the director of security management for the Authority.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Distribution of literature" means the distribution of flyers, leaflets, brochures, pamphlets, books, or any other printed or written material.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Emergency” means, as reasonably determined by the Authority or by authorized police or fire officials, an actual or imminent fire, flood, riot, weather, outages of power or public services, terrorism, public disturbance, or other catastrophe that will or is likely to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Endanger the health, safety, or welfare of persons at an Authority facility;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Threaten the destruction, loss, or damage to public or private property located at an Authority facility; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Disturb the normal and peaceful conduct of business, sports, or other activities at an Authority facility.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“Eutaw Way” means the pedestrian area known as Eutaw Way between the playing field and seating bowl of Oriole Park at Camden Yards to the west, the Warehouse to the east, Gate A of Oriole Park to the south, and Gate H of Oriole Park to the north.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Event" means any game, concert, ceremony, banquet, party, or other activity or event at an Authority facility.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Executive Director" means the Executive Director of the Authority.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>“Free speech activities” include a demonstration, distribution of literature, collection of petition signatures, and other activities protected by the First and Fourteenth Amendments to the Constitution of the United States and Articles 10, 13, and 40 of the Declaration of Rights within <cite doc="Md. Const.">the Maryland Constitution</cite>, provided, however, that such activities do not include any activity prohibited under <cite path="|14.25.02">COMAR 14.25.02</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>“Performing Arts Center” means the France-Merrick Performing Arts Center, including the Hippodrome Theatre at the France-Merrick Performing Arts Center.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>“Plazas” means and includes the plazas surrounding Oriole Park at Camden Yards and the Ravens’ Stadium, including the breezeway underneath the Warehouse, but does not include the sidewalks directly adjacent to public streets.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>“Smoking” means the burning of a lighted cigarette, cigar, pipe, or any other matter or substance that contains tobacco.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>“Spine” means the pedestrian walkway that provides a connection between Lee Street at its north end and Hamburg Street at its south end and which lies between the parking lots that are designated as Lot B and Lot C.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>“Stadium structures” means and includes the facades, fences, and admission gates that comprise the outer perimeter of the baseball stadium and the football stadium at the Camden Yards Sports Complex.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>“Tailgating” means the preparing, cooking, serving, or consuming of food or beverages before, during, or after an event on an Authority-owned or operated parking lot or open space.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>“Warehouse” means the building known as the Warehouse at Camden Yards within the Camden Yards Sports Complex, but does not include the grounds and walkways surrounding it or the open breezeway underneath it.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>“Working days” means Monday through Friday excepting all legal holidays and all other days on which the Executive Branch of State Government is generally closed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Economic Development Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gec|10-604">10-604</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gec|10-613">10-613</cite>(a)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gec|4">4</cite>) and (10), and 10-616(b); <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfi|13-708">Financial Institutions Article, §13-708</cite>; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-04-12">Effective date: April 12, 1993 (20:7 Md. R. 642)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-07-27"><cite path="|14|25|01|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective July 27, 1998 (25:15 Md. R. 1194)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-01-05"><cite path="|14|25|01|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective March 4, 2013 (40:4 Md. R. 347); January 5, 2015 (41:26 Md. R. 1570)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
