<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Prohibited Activities</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Disturbing the Public Peace and Disorderly Conduct.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The following conduct is prohibited at any Authority facility:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The use of language meant to incite immediate violence or an immediate breach of the peace;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The description or depiction of erotic or pornographic images or conduct; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Lewd or indecent exposure.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An individual at an Authority facility may not:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Willfully act in a disorderly manner that disturbs the peace of others;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Engage in, instigate, or encourage the continuation or escalation of a fight or other physical violence; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>In any way endanger the life, person, property, health, or safety of others by words, actions, or attempts made directly or by aiding or abetting others to do so.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Commercial Activity.</heading>
    <text>Commercial activity at an Authority facility, including the display of commercial advertising, and the sale of food, beverages, novelties, or tickets, is prohibited, except when conducted by Authority tenants and their employees, licensees, agents, and assignees who have received authorization by the Authority within their leased or assigned areas, or as otherwise authorized by the Authority. This includes the distribution of flyers containing commercial advertising. Flyers may not be placed on vehicles situated on parking lots or garages owned or controlled by the Authority.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Solicitation.</heading>
    <text>Solicitation for the immediate receipt of money or contributions, commercial solicitation, and the collection of private debts at an Authority facility is prohibited. This prohibition does not apply to tenants or their employees, licensees, agents, delegates, and assignees who have received authorization by the Authority within their leased or assigned areas, or as otherwise authorized by the Authority.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Obstruction of Traffic.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Conduct which obstructs sidewalks, walkways, entrances, corridors, stairways, or parking lots, or which otherwise obstructs or hinders normal pedestrian or vehicular traffic and business, is prohibited. In general, a single person engaged in free speech activities does not impermissibly obstruct a sidewalk, unless that person intentionally moves to obstruct or hinder pedestrians or vehicles attempting to pass by such person.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Sidewalks and other walkways located on Authority property are for use by pedestrian traffic only, and the use of bicycles, roller skates, roller blades, skateboards, motorcycles, or any other form of transportation (other than a wheelchair or other transportation reasonably necessary for a person’s mobility) on those sidewalks is prohibited at all times. On event dates, the use of bicycles, roller skates, roller blades, and skateboards is prohibited on parking lots owned or controlled by the Authority.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Tailgating.</heading>
    <text>Tailgating may only take place at:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Those times specifically authorized by the Authority during, before, or after events at Authority facilities, with the approval of the Baltimore Orioles, the Baltimore Ravens, or other team or licensee of the Authority facility where an event is being held; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Locations designated by the Authority within the parking lots owned or controlled by the Authority.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Weapons.</heading>
    <text>The possession, carrying, or transporting, either openly with the intent to injure a person in an unlawful manner, or concealed, or the use or discharge of, a weapon at an Authority facility is prohibited, including those weapons described in Criminal Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|4-101">4-101</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|4-201">4-201</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland, except for official purposes and by authorized personnel. An individual carrying a weapon shall notify the Director of Security for the Authority before entering an Authority facility.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Controlled or Dangerous Substances.</heading>
    <text>The possession, use, or distribution of a controlled or dangerous substance, or prescription drugs, except those prescribed by a physician and permitted by law, is prohibited.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Disobeying Authorities and Signs; Entrances and Exits.</heading>
    <text>An individual may not:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Disobey an order of a police officer acting within the scope of the officer's employment;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Disobey, disregard, or fail to comply with any rule or regulation, warning, prohibition, instruction, or direction, whether posted or displayed by sign, notice, bulletin, card, or poster, or when notified or informed as to its existence by a police officer; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Enter or leave an Authority facility, including any parking lot or garage owned or operated by the Authority, at points not designated as proper entrances or exits.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Open Containers.</heading>
    <text>The possession, in an open container, or the drinking of any alcoholic beverage at an Authority facility is prohibited, except for the following:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Alcoholic beverages consumed by tenants and their employees, licensees, agents, and assignees within their leased areas who have received authorization by the Authority;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Alcoholic beverages sold by the Authority's designated concessionaire or the tenants' designated concessionaire in accordance with their lease; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Alcoholic beverages consumed on parking lots owned or controlled by the Authority on those dates and times and at those locations designated by the Authority for tailgating.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Intoxication.</heading>
    <text>An individual intoxicated by alcoholic beverages or controlled dangerous substances and endangering the safety of that individual or other individuals or property, or disturbing tenants, patrons, or the normal course of Authority business, is not permitted at an Authority facility, and that individual may not operate a vehicle on Authority property.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Animals.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as otherwise specifically permitted by this regulation, a person may not bring any animal onto or into an Authority facility.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>As used in this regulation, the term “service animal” means and includes:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A service animal as defined under the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 and regulations promulgated thereunder;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Pursuant to 28 CFR §35.136(i), a miniature horse used by an individual with a disability if the miniature horse has been individually trained to do work or perform tasks for the benefit of the individual with a disability, is housebroken, and is under the sufficient control of its handler;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A service animal as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ghu|7-701">Human Services Article, §7-701, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and regulations promulgated thereunder.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Service Animals.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Individuals with disabilities and the parents of a minor child with a disability are permitted to bring a service animal onto or into an Authority facility.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Service animal trainers, as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ghu|7-701">Human Services Article, §7-701, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and regulations promulgated thereunder, are permitted to bring an animal being trained or raised as a service animal onto or into an Authority facility, provided, however, that an animal being trained as a service animal and accompanied by a service animal trainer may be excluded from an Authority facility if admitting the animal would create a clear danger of a disturbance or physical harm to any individual at the Authority facility.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>No person hosting an event at an Authority facility may require the purchase of a separate ticket or charge any additional amount for the admission of a service animal or an animal being trained or raised as a service animal.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>An individual with a disability or a parent of a minor child with a disability who is accompanied by a service animal may be liable for any damages to the Authority facility caused by the service animal to the extent permitted under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ghu|7-705">Human Services Article, §7-705, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>. The service animal trainer organization that certifies the service animal may be liable for any personal injuries or damages to the premises or facilities caused by the service animal to the extent permitted under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ghu|7-705">Human Services Article, §7-705, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Nothing in this regulation shall be construed as requiring the Authority to make any physical modification to an Authority facility in order to admit a person accompanied by a service animal or animal being trained or raised as a service animal.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Animals used for governmental security and law enforcement purposes shall be permitted onto and into an Authority facility.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Other animals may be brought onto or into an Authority facility if specifically authorized by the Executive Director, the Director of Security Management, or the Director of Facilities Management for such Authority facility.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Sleeping.</heading>
    <text>Use of an Authority facility for sleeping or other purposes instead of one's home, a hotel, motel, or other public facility is prohibited.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Bicycles.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Bicycles are parked on Authority property at the owner's risk.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Bicycles shall be parked in designated bicycle parking areas. Bicycle racks are provided.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Bicycles chained to any pole or fixed structure other than a bicycle rack or left unattended at a location other than the designated bicycle racks may be removed by the Authority at the owner’s risk. The Authority may treat any bicycle left chained to any pole or fixed structure other than a bicycle rack or left unattended at a location other than the designated bicycle racks as suspicious and may remove, dispose of, or destroy any such bicycle without liability to the owner thereof.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Open Fires.</heading>
    <text>Open fires of any kind are not permitted on Authority property, except for fires contained in a customary cooking device on those dates and times and at those locations designated by the Authority for tailgating.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Refusal to Leave Authority Property Upon Request.</heading>
    <text>Authority property is subject to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|6-409">Criminal Law Article, §6-409, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>. An individual refusing or failing to leave Authority property upon proper request to do so by an authorized agent of the Authority is guilty of a misdemeanor, and upon conviction may be fined not more than $1,000 or imprisoned for not more than 6 months, or both.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Damage to Property; Responsibility for Damage.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An individual may not climb, cut, injure, mutilate, set fire to, deface, displace, remove, or destroy any wall, fence, shelter, seat, statue, or other structure at any Authority facility.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An individual may not cut, destroy, break, prune, set fire to, mutilate, injure, disturb, sever from the ground, or remove any growing thing, including any plant, flower, flower bed, shrub, tree, grass, or any branch, stem, fruit, or leaf.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An individual who injures Authority property in any manner whatsoever is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Responsible for the injury or damage; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Liable for the cost to have the property restored to its original condition.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.17</num>
    <heading>Games.</heading>
    <text>Except for the Authority, its tenants, and licensees, an individual may not throw, cast, catch, kick, play with, or strike any game ball whatsoever or engage in any sport, game, or competition at any Authority facility or on parking lots owned or controlled by the Authority.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.18</num>
    <heading>Trespassing on the Playing Field and Interference with Events or Contests.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This regulation is in addition to, and not in lieu of, <cite path="|14|25|02|.15">Regulation .15 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|6-402">Criminal Law Article §6-402, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, at locations which are reasonably visible to persons within the Stadium Structures, the Authority shall place signs that conspicuously prohibit trespass upon the playing field of such Authority facility. Except for the Authority, its authorized tenants, and the Authority’s and such tenants’ licensees, an individual may not trespass upon the playing field at any Authority facility at any time. In accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|6-402">Criminal Law Article, §6-402, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, a person who violates this regulation is guilty of a misdemeanor and on conviction is subject to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For a first violation, imprisonment not exceeding 90 days or a fine not exceeding $500 or both;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For a second violation occurring within 2 years after the first violation, imprisonment not exceeding 6 months or a fine not exceeding $1,000 or both; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>For each subsequent violation occurring within 2 years after the preceding violation, imprisonment not exceeding 1 year or a fine not exceeding $2,500 or both.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An individual may not loiter, project objects onto the playing field or seating area, or act in such a manner as to interfere with the players of athletic events or contests in any Authority facility.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.19</num>
    <heading>Smoking in Stadiums.</heading>
    <text>Smoking is prohibited by any person located in any of the following areas:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In any spaces within the Stadium structures, whether such spaces are covered or uncovered, walled or exposed, or open or closed to public access; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Within 25 feet of any entry, outdoor air intake, or operable window of the Stadium Structures at the Camden Yards Sports Complex.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Economic Development Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gec|10-604">10-604</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gec|10-613">10-613</cite>(a)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gec|4">4</cite>) and (10), and 10-616(b); <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfi|13-708">Financial Institutions Article, §13-708</cite>; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-04-12">Effective date: April 12, 1993 (20:7 Md. R. 642)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-07-27" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective July 27, 1998 (25:15 Md. R. 1194)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-01-05"><cite path="|14|25|02|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective January 5, 2015 (41:26 Md. R. 1570)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-01-05"><cite path="|14|25|02|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective January 5, 2015 (41:26 Md. R. 1570)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-01-05"><cite path="|14|25|02|.08|C.">Regulation .08C</cite> amended effective January 5, 2015 (41:26 Md. R. 1570)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-01-05"><cite path="|14|25|02|.11">Regulation .11</cite> repealed and new Regulation .11 adopted effective January 5, 2015 (41:26 Md. R. 1570)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-01-05"><cite path="|14|25|02|.13|B.">Regulation .13B</cite>, C amended effective January 5, 2015 (41:26 Md. R. 1570)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-01-05"><cite path="|14|25|02|.15">Regulation .15</cite> amended effective January 5, 2015 (41:26 Md. R. 1570)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-01-05"><cite path="|14|25|02|.18">Regulation .18</cite> amended effective January 5, 2015 (41:26 Md. R. 1570)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-03-04"><cite path="|14|25|02|.19">Regulation .19</cite> adopted effective March 4, 2013 (40:4 Md. R. 347)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
