<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>06</num>
  <heading>Continuing Education</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This regulation governs all acupuncturists licensed to practice in the State of Maryland.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following term has the meaning indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Term Defined. “Board” means the State Board of Acupuncture.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|26|06|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Licensure Renewal.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A licensee applying for renewal shall complete 30 hours of relevant continuing education during the 2-year period preceding the expiration of the license which include the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At least 20 hours in formally organized programs approved by the Board which are relevant to the practice of acupuncture and East Asian medicine;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Not more than 10 hours of formally organized training programs in Western science and medical practices, medical ethics, medical research, or cardiopulmonary resuscitation which are relevant to the practice of acupuncture and East Asian medicine;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Not more than 10 hours of training in approved programs which will assist a licensee to carry out the licensee’s professional responsibilities, including, but not limited to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Management courses for a school administrator;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Foreign language training for translators of relevant texts; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Educational methodology for teachers of acupuncture;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Not more than 10 hours teaching acupuncture and related East Asian medical therapies in an accredited school or in a program approved for acupuncture continuing education;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Not more than 7 hours of pro bono work as outlined in <cite path="10|26|06|.03|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Not more than 7 hours in published writing or articles in acupuncture and East Asian medicine that are:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Peer-reviewed research or peer-reviewed clinically relevant articles in acupuncture and East Asian medicine; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Limited to 4 hours per article;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Not more than 20 hours for passage of the NCCAOM exam within the 2-year period preceding the expiration of the license; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Not more than 10 hours serving on a professional board involving:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Acupuncture; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>East Asian medicine.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Pro Bono Work.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Pro bono work shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Earn 1 credit hour for each 3 hours of pro bono activity up to a maximum of 7 credit hours per renewal cycle; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Be for the provision of acupuncture services provided through an organization offering humanitarian services such as, but not limited to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Domestic or international victims in an emergency situation or disaster area;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Low-income or underserved areas or populations;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Special needs populations; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>United States military personnel.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Upon completion of the pro bono work, the licensee shall obtain from the facility written documentation of completion of pro bono hours, including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The name of the facility;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The address where the pro bono work was provided;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The type of work that was done;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The number of hours of actual work provided for which the licensee desires credit hours; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>A statement guaranteeing that the work provided no financial benefit to the licensee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Licensees shall maintain the documentation of their continuing education credits for 4 years from the date of their acupuncture renewal.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If requested by the Board, a licensee shall provide proof of continuing education attendance by providing documentation of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Name of the program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Date of the program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Number of continuing education hours earned; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Name of the sponsoring organization.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|1A-205">1A-205</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|1A-306">1A-306</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-10-16">Effective date: October 16, 2023 (50:20 Md. R. 887)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
