<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>04</num>
  <heading>Certification and Training for School Security Employees and School Resource Officers</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Center” means the Maryland Center for School Safety.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“School resource officer” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|7-1501">Education Article, §7-1501(j), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“School safety coordinator” means an individual or individuals in a school system, regardless of job title, who serve as:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The head of safety or security for the school system; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The liaison between the Center, local law enforcement, and the local school system as required under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|7-1508">Education Article, §7-1508(a), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>School Security Employee.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“School security employee” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|7-1501">Education Article, §7-1501(k), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>School security employee includes individuals:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Employed by a local school system, either as salaried or contractual employees, to provide safety or security-related services at a public school; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Assigned to a public school, whose job description includes safety or security related services as part of the individual’s primary duties.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>School security employee does not include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A school resource officer;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Local law enforcement providing supplemental coverage to local school systems;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>An employee of the school system not assigned to work in an individual public school as part of their duties; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>A school administrator.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>School Safety Coordinator Certification.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Center shall certify a school safety coordinator upon completion of the following training:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Center’s curriculum for school safety coordinators and any annual updates;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The National Incident Management System, Incident Command System, independent study courses 100, 200, 700, and 800; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Federal Emergency Management Agency (FEMA) independent study course, Multi-Hazard Emergency Planning for Schools.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Supplemental Instruction.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A school safety coordinator shall complete an additional 4 hours of supplemental instruction annually in content areas approved by the Center to maintain certification.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A request for enrollment in a particular course of supplemental instruction shall be made by the school safety coordinator to the Center in advance of enrollment in a course to ensure that the course is approved.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Retroactive requests for approval of a particular course to maintain certification by the Center shall be denied.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A school safety coordinator shall submit certificates of completion to the Center within 30 days of completion of the coursework.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>School Resource Officers and School Security Employees Certification Training.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A school resource officer or school security employee shall complete the Center’s model curriculum or an approved local training, as required under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|7-1508">Education Article, §7-1508, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A school resource officer or school security employee assigned or hired after the start of the school year will register and complete the model curriculum prior to the next school year and may begin work in a school:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Following notification to the Center; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Following completion of the preliminary curriculum prescribed by the Center.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>School resource officers and school security employees shall complete additional hours of training annually in content areas approved by the Center, including:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Updated legislative and regulatory changes affecting the work of school resource officers and school security employees;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Expanded training in existing content areas;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any training identified or approved by the Center; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Any other mandates under State, federal, or local law.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Each year, the local school superintendent shall certify to the Center’s Executive Director that school security employees assigned to the jurisdiction’s schools have completed the training required under this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|7-151">7-151</cite>(k), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|7-1503">7-1503</cite>(g), and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|7-1508">7-1508</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-08-24">Effective date: August 24, 2020 (47:17 Md. R. 797)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-12-11"><cite path="|14|40|04|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective December 11, 2023 (50: 24 Md. R. 1042)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-12-11"><cite path="|14|40|04|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective December 11, 2023 (50: 24 Md. R. 1042)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-12-11"><cite path="|14|40|04|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective December 11, 2023 (50: 24 Md. R. 1042)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
