<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Enforcement of the Plumbing Law by the Board</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Qualifications of Plumbers—How Certificates May Be Issued.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>All plumbing work shall be performed, or supervised and approved, by a licensed master plumber who is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Familiar with its design and purpose; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Available to direct and control all journey and apprentice plumbers.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The license of a master plumber will be issued in the name of the master plumber.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>All plumbing work performed, or supervised and approved, by a licensed master plumber shall be of ordinary worker-like skill and quality and shall conform both to the regulations promulgated by the Board and to applicable local laws and regulations.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Required Training for Apprentice Plumbers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Before an apprentice plumber may be examined for a license as a journey plumber, the apprentice plumber shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Receive at least 7,500 working hours of instruction and experience in the installation and repair of plumbing material and systems, under the direction and control of a master plumber; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Be registered with the Board for the duration of the apprenticeship training.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>To avoid undue hardship, the Board may give credit for hours worked in the installation and repair of plumbing material and systems by an unregistered apprentice plumber.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>It is recommended that the instruction and experience include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Installation of piping for waste, soil, sewerage, vent and rain leader lines in copper,</text>
        <text>steel, cast iron, and plastic pipe: 	1,400 hrs.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Name and size of sewer fittings, wyes, tees, bend, packing, pouring, caulking joints;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Use of proper fittings in making connections;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Proper pitch in sewer lines;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Regulations on cesspools and septic tanks;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Local codes governing plumbing.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Installation of piping for hot and cold water for domestic purposes:	1,400 hrs.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Rough-in water and gas piping for fixtures;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Cut holes in floors and joist;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Measure up piping;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Run pipe in copper, steel, or plastic;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Installation of domestic water boilers and hot water heaters;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Install tankless or tank-type copper coil heaters in boilers;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Automatic gas water heaters with vent to chimney;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Measure up piping and connect to hot and cold water lines;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Use of pipe cutters and reamers;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Cut threads with stocks and dies, or with pipe threading machines;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Use of joint compound on threads and screw up fittings on pipe with pipe wrenches;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>Local codes governing plumbing.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Installation of lead pipe, tin pipe, sheet lead, and solder work: 	180 hrs.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Proper use of tools;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Kinds of materials and fluxes;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Correct heating temperatures.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Assembly in position and connection of fixtures and appliances used in the plumbing</text>
        <text>and drainage system:	950 hrs.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Rough-in waste, soil, and vent lines for fixtures;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Pack, pour, and caulk fittings and pipe;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Make up fittings, run piping, and hook up main sewer;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Lay out water lines, hot and cold;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Place and connect various plumbing fixtures;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Local codes governing plumbing.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Service work—maintenance and repair of plumbing:	480 hrs.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Leaks;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Renewals;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Stoppage of lines;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Alterations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Trouble shooting plumbing systems.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Operation, care, safety, and use of all tools and materials connected with the trade:	 850 hrs.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Pipe and fittings, tees, ells, 45-degree ells and nipples;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Black, galvanized, wrought iron, wrought steel, copper, and plastic pipe;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Use and care of tools;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Pipe cutters, reamers, stocks and dies, size of wrenches, caulking irons, lead pots,</text>
          <text>lead burners, lead runners, cleaning of tools, and storage after working hours;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Types of tubs—corner or recess, left or right;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Lavatories—cast iron, vitreous china, and stainless steel;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Closet combinations—vitreous china, closed couples, siphon action, flushometer types.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Gas installation: 	750 hrs.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Types of gas installations—natural and LPG;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Venting gas systems;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Gas appliances and controls;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Local codes governing gas fitting.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Special purpose installations: 	180 hrs.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Swimming pools;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Fountains and planters;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Lawn sprinkling and vacuum systems;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Local codes governing plumbing.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Plan reading:	 375 hrs.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Sketching;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Sleeve drawing and deck layout;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Drawing coordination.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Builders level transit: 	275 hrs.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Layout of sewer and water lines;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Shoot grades and elevations.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Welding connected with the trade: 	480 hrs.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Gas, metallic arc, and heliarc welding;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Use of torch;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Proper flame, fluxes, and solder;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Pipe welding;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Proper welding procedures and techniques;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Identification of welding rods and materials;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Flame cutting;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Brazing.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Rigging: 	375 hrs.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Materials;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Equipment.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Examinations for Journey Plumber Certificates.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each applicant for the journey plumber's examination shall provide certification that the applicant has accrued at least 7,500 working hours, that is, 4 years of apprenticeship instruction and experience in the installation and repair of plumbing material and systems, under the direction and control of a master plumber. The following conditions apply:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Up to 1,500 hours of accredited, approved school study may be applied towards the 7,500-hours requirement, which may be composed of classroom plumbing work or study under a vocational or technical program accredited by the State Department of Education or under the apprenticeship agreement registered with the Maryland Apprenticeship and Training Council;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The applicant shall furnish the certification, made under penalty of perjury, with the examination application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Hours accrued may not be credited to an individual serving under an apprenticeship agreement registered with the Maryland Apprenticeship and Training Council unless the individual is also licensed with the Board as an apprentice plumber.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Examinations.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board shall examine qualified applicants by written examination.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the applicant satisfactorily documents that the applicant has a disability as defined under The Americans With Disabilities Act (ADA), the Board will make those accommodations necessary for the administration of the examination.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An applicant shall attain a passing grade of 70 to qualify for licensure as a journey plumber.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Out-of-State Applicants.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A nonresident applicant or an applicant whose work experience has not been in Maryland shall provide certification that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The applicant has accrued at least 7,500 working hours, that is, 4 years of apprenticeship instruction and experience in the installation and repair of plumbing material and systems, under the direction and control of a licensed master plumber; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The master plumber under whom the applicant trained received a license by passing a written competency examination.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Up to 1,500 hours of accredited, approved school study may be applied towards the 7,500-hour requirement.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The applicant shall furnish the certification as to accrued work experience and the qualifications of the supervisory master plumber, under penalty of perjury, with the examination application.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|20|02|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Examinations for Master Plumber Certificates.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each applicant for the master plumber's examination shall provide certification, under penalty of perjury, that the applicant has accrued at least 2 years, that is, 3,750 working hours of practical experience as a journey plumber, in the installation and repair of plumbing material and systems under the direction and control of a master plumber.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The candidate shall be examined on:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>General knowledge of the regulations as may be provided by the Board;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Knowledge of physics and hygiene as may deal with the proper and safe methods of supplying water to a building, and of removing water and sewage from it; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Drainage, hydraulics, pneumatics, and hydrostatics insofar as they relate to the proper construction of work required in providing plumbing services.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Applicants shall also be required to demonstrate their ability to comprehend and interpret plans and drawings, showing the arrangements of plumbing fixtures and other related parts of the plumbing system.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Unless specifically provided for, each applicant shall answer all examination questions in writing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If the applicant satisfactorily documents that the applicant has a disability as defined under The Americans With Disabilities Act (ADA), the Board will make those accommodations necessary for the administration of the examination.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If an applicant successfully completes the examination under <cite path="09|20|02|.04|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>, the Board shall grant to the applicant a license as a master plumber upon a showing that the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Applicant's ability to function as a master plumber is not significantly impaired by the dyslexia or other reading disability; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Applicant is otherwise competent and qualified to become a master plumber.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Out-of-State Applicants.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A nonresident applicant or an applicant whose work experience has not been in Maryland shall accrue a total of at least 11,250 working hours, that is, 6 years of practical experience in the installation and repair of plumbing material and systems.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The applicant shall furnish information about the applicant's work experience, under penalty of perjury, as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Certification of at least 4 years of the required total number of years, that is, 7,500 working hours spent in the installation and repair of plumbing material and systems under the direction and control of a licensed master plumber;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Certification of at least 2 years, that is, 3,750 hours of work in the plumbing trade as a journey plumber;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Certification that the journey plumber's license was received by passing a written competency examination; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Certification that the master plumber for whom the applicant worked received a license by passing a written competency examination.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the nonresident applicant is from an area that does not require licensure of journeyperson plumbers, and the applicant holds a master plumber's license, the applicant shall provide certification with the application that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The applicant accrued at least 7,500 hours of practical experience in the plumbing trade under the direction and control of a licensed master plumber;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The master plumber for whom the applicant worked received a license by passing a written competency examination;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The applicant's master plumber license was received by passing a written competency examination; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The applicant has accrued at least 2 years, that is, 3,750 working hours in the installation and repair of plumbing material and systems since receiving the master plumber's license.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Passing Grade Required for a Master's License.</heading>
    <text>An applicant shall attain a passing grade of 70 to quality for a license as a master plumber.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Applicants Failed.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Any applicant who failed the examination for either a master or journey license may apply and pay the prescribed fee for another examination. A period of 1 month shall elapse before a failed applicant may retake an examination.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Applicants who have failed an examination may review their examination papers upon written request to the Board. This request shall be made within 30 days after the applicant has been notified that the applicant failed to attain the required grade.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Applicants for Renewal of License.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>All apprentice, journey, and master plumbers eligible for renewal shall renew their licenses every 2 years.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>All applicants for renewal, after submitting their written application for renewal accompanied by the required fee, shall be issued a new license by the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Any applicant for renewal who has for 5 consecutive years failed to renew a license is subject to examination before being issued a new license.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Issuing of License on a Reciprocal Basis.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board shall issue a master or journey plumber license on a reciprocal basis to applicants living in Baltimore County or the Washington Suburban Sanitary District who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Have passed the master or journey plumber examination in either jurisdiction;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Are in good standing in that jurisdiction; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Intend to do business in Maryland outside of Baltimore County or Washington Suburban Sanitary District.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board shall give examinations for journey or master plumber licenses to applicants living outside the State who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Demonstrate that they have served an apprenticeship, or had practical experience, under supervision equivalent to that required in Maryland; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Demonstrate the same level of proficiency and study required of applicants serving an apprenticeship or gaining practical experience in Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Advertisements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definitions. In this regulation, the following terms have the meanings indicated:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Current master plumber" means the individual responsible for supervising and controlling the work of all individuals providing or assisting in providing plumbing services in a business.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Current natural gas fitter" means the individual responsible for supervising and controlling the work of all individuals providing or assisting in providing natural gas services in a business.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Current propane gas fitter" means the individual responsible for supervising and controlling the work of all individuals providing or assisting in providing propane gas services in a business.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"License number" means the license registration certificate number displayed on the license document or propane gas fitter certificate issued to a licensee or certificate holder by the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Requirements for Plumbers.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The license number of the current master plumber shall be displayed on all documents used by any person holding themselves out to the public as providing plumbing services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Each vehicle that advertises plumbing services shall display the words "MD Licensed Plumber" and the license number of the current master plumber on both sides of the vehicle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Requirements for Licensed Natural Gas Fitters.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The license number of the current natural gas fitter shall be displayed on all documents used by any person holding themselves out to the public as providing natural gas services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Each vehicle that advertises natural gas services shall display the words "MD Licensed Natural Gas Fitter" and the license number of the current natural gas fitter on both sides of the vehicle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Requirements for Propane Gas Fitters.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The license number of the current propane gas fitter shall be displayed on all documents used by any persons holding themselves out to the public as providing propane gas services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Each vehicle that advertises propane gas services shall display the words "MD Certified Propane Gas Fitter" and the license number of the current propane gas fitter on both sides of the vehicle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Additional Requirements for Licensees and Certificate Holders.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each vehicle that advertises plumbing, natural gas, or propane gas services shall display the information required by this regulation on both sides of the vehicle. Display of wording shall be not less than 1-1/2 inches in height.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Each printed, audio, video, or computerized advertisement of any type, including all estimate forms, contract forms, and final statements of payment, shall clearly contain the words "MD Licensed Plumber", "MD Licensed Natural Gas Fitter", or "MD Certified Propane Gas Fitter" and the license number as required by §§B(2), C(2), and D(2) of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Qualifications for Plumbing Inspectors.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Plumbing inspectors hired by the State, a county, or a local government after October 1, 1988, shall meet minimum standards that are established by the county or local government in consultation with the State Board, or, if there is no standard established by the county or local government, the minimum standards established by the State Board. The minimum standards established by the State Board are as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The plumbing inspector shall be a licensed master or journey plumber;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The plumbing inspector shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Have at least 4 years experience as an inspector or craftsman in a building and construction trade, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Pass a written examination prepared and administered by the State Board, or prepared and administered by the county or local government, provided that the examination is approved by the State Board, and certified copies of all results are provided to the State Board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Each plumbing inspector shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Attend, at least once each year, continuing education pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|12-503">Business Occupations and Professions Article, §12-503(a)(1), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, to be conducted by the State Board, or a course which is consistent in content with the State Board's course and which is conducted by a county or local government; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|12-503">Business Occupations and Professions Article, §12-503(a)(1), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, obtain a cumulative 8 hours of qualifying continuing education each calendar year.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Passing Grade for License and Certificate Examinations.</heading>
    <text>In accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|12-304">Business Occupations and Professions Article, §12-304(d)(1), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and as set forth in Regulations .03B(3) and .05 of this chapter, an applicant for any license or certificate issued by the Board shall attain a passing score of 70 to qualify for the license or certificate.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Business Occupations and Professions Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|12-205">12-205</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|12-207">12-207</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|12-302">12-302</cite>(d), (e), (g)(2), and (h)(3), 12-304(d)(1), and 12-503(a), <br/>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date: 1971</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1976-01-07"><cite path="|09|20|02|.02">Regulation .02</cite>, .13 amended effective January 7, 1976 (3:1 Md. R. 41)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1980-02-08"><cite path="|09|20|02|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective February 8, 1980 (7:3 Md. R. 263)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1976-05-26"><cite path="|09|20|02|.15">Regulation .15</cite> amended effective May 26, 1976 (3:11 Md. R. 592)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1975-12-24"><cite path="|09|20|02|.17">Regulation .17</cite> amended effective December 24, 1975 (2:29 Md. R. 1735)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1981-10-26" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective October 26, 1981 (8:21 Md. R. 1706)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-08-12"><cite path="|09|20|02|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective August 12, 1985 (12:16 Md. R. 1605)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-04-21"><cite path="|09|20|02|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite> amended effective April 21, 1986 (13:8 Md. R. 898)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-04-21"><cite path="|09|20|02|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective April 21, 1986 (13:8 Md. R. 898)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-03-25"><cite path="|09|20|02|.05|D.">Regulation .05D</cite> adopted effective March 25, 1985 (12:6 Md. R. 595)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1983-09-26"><cite path="|09|20|02|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 1, 1983 (10:14 Md. R. 1257); adopted permanently effective September 26, 1983 (10:19 Md. R. 1690)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-04-21"><cite path="|09|20|02|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective April 21, 1986 (13:8 Md. R. 898)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-03-25"><cite path="|09|20|02|.06|G.">Regulation .06G</cite> adopted effective March 25, 1985 (12:6 Md. R. 595)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1984-02-13"><cite path="|09|20|02|.10|A.">Regulation .10A</cite> amended effective February 13, 1984 (11:3 Md. R. 199)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-08-12"><cite path="|09|20|02|.12|A.">Regulation .12A</cite> amended effective August 12, 1985 (12:16 Md. R. 1605)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-07-28"><cite path="|09|20|02|.12|D.">Regulation .12D</cite> adopted effective July 28, 1986 (13:15 Md. R. 1734)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-06-26"><cite path="|09|20|02|.15">Regulation .15</cite> adopted effective June 26, 1989 (16:12 Md. R. 1335)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-06-22" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective June 22, 1992 (19:12 Md. R. 1133)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-03-01"><cite path="|09|20|02|.11">Regulation .11</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective March 1, 1995 (22:6 Md. R. 471); emergency status expired September 1, 1995</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1996-03-25"><cite path="|09|20|02|.11">Regulation .11</cite> adopted effective March 25, 1996 (23:6 Md. R. 475)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1997-10-20" discontinuity="true">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|09.20.26">COMAR 09.20.26</cite> to <cite path="|09.20.02">COMAR 09.20.02</cite> effective October 20, 1997 (24:21 Md. R. 1448)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-05-22"><cite path="|09|20|02|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective May 22, 2017 (44:10 Md. R. 472)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-06-17">Regulations .03B amended effective October 20, 1997 (24:21 Md. R. 1448); June 17, 2019 (46:12 Md. R. 536)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1997-10-20">Regulations .04E amended effective October 20, 1997 (24:21 Md. R. 1448)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-06-17"><cite path="|09|20|02|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective June 17, 2019 (46:12 Md. R. 536)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-06-24"><cite path="|09|20|02|.06|A.">Regulation .06A</cite> amended effective June 24, 2002 (29:12 Md. R. 927)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-05-22"><cite path="|09|20|02|.07|A.">Regulation .07A</cite> amended effective May 22, 2017 (44:10 Md. R. 472)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-03-18"><cite path="|09|20|02|.09">Regulation .09</cite> amended effective November 29, 1999 (26:24 Md. R. 1857); March 18, 2002 (29:5 Md. R. 503)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-02-04"><cite path="|09|20|02|.10|B.">Regulation .10B</cite> amended effective February 4, 2013 (40:2 Md. R. 72)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-12-01"><cite path="|09|20|02|.11">Regulation .11</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective December 1, 2005 (32:26 Md. R. 1993); emergency status expired April 28, 2006</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-07-03"><cite path="|09|20|02|.11">Regulation .11</cite> amended effective July 3, 2006 (33:13 Md. R. 1063)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-05-22"><cite path="|09|20|02|.11">Regulation .11</cite> repealed effective May 22, 2017 (44:10 Md. R. 472)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-06-17"><cite path="|09|20|02|.11">Regulation .11</cite> adopted effective June 17, 2019 (46:12 Md. R. 536)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
