<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>General Regulations</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Responsibilities of Licensees.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A licensee shall undertake to provide plumbing services only if the licensee is qualified by education, training, and experience to provide the required services.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A licensee shall undertake to provide plumbing services related to gas only if the licensee is qualified by education, training, and experience with the specific gas, gas system, gas utilization equipment, and associated accessories to provide the required services.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A licensee may not use or allow the use of a license issued by the Board for the purpose of obtaining or attempting to obtain a permit or other authority to provide plumbing services from a county or local government agency unless the licensee is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Familiar with the design and purpose of the plumbing services to be provided, and, when any portion of the services provided is to be outside of a permanent structure, the ground conditions of the area;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Available to direct and control all journey and apprentice plumbers who will provide or assist in the providing of the plumbing services; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Responsible for the services performed or to be performed pursuant to a contract.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A licensee shall maintain appropriate insurance covering any plumbing service the licensee provides. Insurance provided by an employer does not satisfy the insurance requirements of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|12-501">Business Occupations and Professions Article, §12-501, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, if a licensee provides plumbing services outside the scope of employment with the insured person or business entity.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Street Address Required.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This regulation applies to all applications, both original and renewal, received on or after January 1, 2014.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An applicant for a license shall provide to the Board the actual street address of the individual’s residence or principal business office. An applicant may not provide a post office box or private mail drop as the applicant's business address of record.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Failure to Respond.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If an applicant or licensee receives from the Board a written communication requesting a response, the applicant or licensee shall respond in writing within 30 days of the date of the mailing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board shall send a written communication by first-class mail to the last address furnished to the Board by the applicant or licensee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>It is the responsibility of an applicant or licensee to notify the Board in writing if there has been a change in an applicant’s or licensee’s address.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Failure to respond as required by this regulation may be considered by the Board to be a violation of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|12-312">Business Occupations and Professions Article, §12-312(a)(1)(xiii), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Business Occupations and Professions Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|12-205">12-205</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|12-207">12-207</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|12-303">12-303</cite>(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|1">1</cite>), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|12-311">12-311</cite>(c), and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|12-312">12-312</cite>(a)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|1">1</cite>)(xiii), Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-11-29">Effective date: November 29, 1999 (26:24 Md. R. 1857)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-03-18"><cite path="|09|20|03|.01|D.">Regulation .01D</cite> adopted effective March 18, 2002 (29:5 Md. R. 503)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-12-12"><cite path="|09|20|03|.02">Regulation .02</cite> adopted effective December 12, 2013 (40:24 Md. R. 2016)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-12-31"><cite path="|09|20|03|.03">Regulation .03</cite> adopted effective December 31, 2018 (45:26 Md. R. 1241)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
