<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>04</num>
  <heading>Cross Connection/Backflow Prevention Certification Training Program</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meaning indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Certified instructor” means an individual who possesses a master plumber or a journey plumber license issued by the Board or a reciprocating jurisdiction and has successfully completed an instructional certification program sponsored by an organization recognized by the Board, including, but not limited to, the University of Florida Treeo Center (TREEO), American Society of Sanitary Engineering (ASSE) Instructor Accreditation Certification, and University of Southern California Foundation for Cross Connection Control.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Certified provider” means a person or organization who provides Board-approved cross connection/backflow prevention certification training in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|12-306">Business Occupations and Professions Article, §12-306(c), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and meets the requirements of Regulation .02A—C of this chapter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Certified technician” means an individual who is certified to install, test, repair, and make reports on a mechanical cross connection/backflow prevention device or assembly after successful completion of a 32-hour cross connection/backflow prevention certification program approved by the Board in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|12-306">Business Occupations and Professions Article, §12-306(c), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|20|04|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Approved Cross Connection/Backflow Prevention Certification Program.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|12-306">Business Occupations and Professions Article, §12-306(c), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, a cross connection/backflow prevention certification program may be eligible for approval by the Board if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The certified provider submits to the Board an application on the form that the Board provides, identifying the course provider and the provider’s credentials to offer cross connection/backflow prevention certification training;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Each program instructor is a certified instructor in accordance with <cite path="|09|20|04|.01|B.|(1)">Regulation .01B(1) of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The course materials include a cross connection/backflow prevention training manual prepared by an organization identified in <cite path="|09|20|04|.01|B.|(1)">Regulation .01B(1) of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>In the opinion of the Board, the course curriculum provides, at a minimum, adequate training in:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Introduction to backflow prevention;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Hazards of cross connection/backflow;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Laws of backflow prevention;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Responsibilities of certified technician;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The methods, mechanisms, and installation techniques used for the prevention of backflow;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Field testing;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Field reports;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Troubleshooting;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Repair of a backflow occurrence; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Recertification;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The program is conducted at a facility that provides adequate space and a suitable training environment in the opinion of the Board that is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Accessible for inspection by an authorized representative or agent of the Board during normal business and class hours without prior notice; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Equipped with adequate apparatus necessary for adequate training in the opinion of the Board including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A test kit;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>One of each mechanical cross connection control device and assembly necessary for compliance with ASSE 1011, 1012, 1013, 1015, 1019, 1020, 1022, 1024, 1035, and 1056; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Mechanical cross connection control assembly set up for field testing;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The certified provider issues to an individual who successfully completes the program a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Certificate that includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The name of the certified provider;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The name of the certified technician to whom it is issued;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A statement that the course constitutes a 32-hour cross connection/backflow prevention certification program approved by the Maryland State Board of Plumbing;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>The date of completion of the certification program;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>The name and signature of the course instructor; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>The certification technician number; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Pocket identification card that includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The name of the certified technician to whom it is issued;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The title “Certified Backflow Prevention Technician”;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The dates for which the certification is valid; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The certified provider notifies the Board within 10 days of any change of a certified course instructor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In order for a cross connection/backflow prevention certification program to be and remain eligible for approval by the Board in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|12-306">Business Occupations and Professions Article, §12-306(c), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the program must be able to demonstrate adequate recertification credentials including the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Offer of recertification training for technicians every 5 years; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Requirement that course instructors maintain instructor certification by meeting the requirements of, but not limited to, the University of Florida Treeo Center (TREEO), American Society of Sanitary Engineering (ASSE) Instruction Accreditation Certification, and University of Southern California Foundation for Cross Connection Control, which shall include completion of recertification training at a minimum of once every 5 years.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In addition to the requirements of <cite path="09|20|04|.02|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, in order for a cross connection/backflow prevention certification program to remain eligible for approval by the Board in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|12-306">Business Occupations and Professions Article, §12-306(c), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, every 3 years, the program provider shall provide the Board with updated information about the program which shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A current list of certified instructors; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Notification from the certified provider of changes to the course curriculum or the location of the training facility.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Board may rescind its approval of a cross connection/backflow prevention certification program at any time if, in the opinion of the Board:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The certified provider demonstrates misconduct or incompetence in the performance of supervisory duties over the program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A certified course instructor demonstrates misconduct or incompetence in the provision of applicable training; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The certified provider fails to meet any of the requirements of §§A—C of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>In accordance with Business Occupations and Professions Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|12-306">12-306</cite>(c)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|3">3</cite>) and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|12-503">12-503</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland, an individual appointed, designated, or employed by a county or local government as an inspector of mechanical cross connection/backflow prevention devices shall have completed a cross connection/backflow prevention certification program approved by the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Completion of an approved cross connection/backflow prevention certification program does not authorize an individual to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Install, test, or certify a mechanical cross connection/backflow prevention device unless the individual is licensed by the Board as a master or journey plumber in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|12-101">Business Occupations and Professions Article, §12-101(g) </cite>or (l), Annotated Code of Maryland; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Assist in installing, testing, or certifying a mechanical cross connection/backflow prevention device unless the individual is licensed by the Board as an apprentice plumber in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|12-101">Business Occupations and Professions Article, §12-101(c), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Business Occupations and Professions Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|12-207">12-207</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|12-306">12-306</cite>(c), Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-07-22">Effective date: July 22, 2013 (40:14 Md. R. 1174)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
