<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Educational Requirements</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|19|02|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Eligibility to Take Examination or Obtain Original Trainee License.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Licensed Real Estate Appraisers. Except as provided in <cite path="|09.19.04">COMAR 09.19.04</cite>, to be eligible to sit for the licensed real estate appraisers examination, an applicant shall hold a valid trainee appraiser license and shall have successfully completed 150 classroom hours of study in accordance with the Appraiser Qualifications Board core curriculum as set forth in <cite path="|09|19|02|.03|B.">Regulation .03B of this chapter</cite> that includes:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The 15-hour National USPAP Course or an equivalent course approved by the Appraisal Qualifications Board; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>75 hours in:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Residential market analysis and highest and best use — 15 hours;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Residential appraiser site valuation and cost approach — 15 hours;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Residential sales comparison and income approaches — 30 hours; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Residential report writing and case studies — 15 hours.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Residential Real Estate Appraisers. To be eligible to sit for the certified residential real estate appraisers examination, an applicant shall have successfully completed:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>200 classroom hours of study; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>One of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A bachelor’s degree or higher from an accredited college or university;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An associate’s degree, or higher, from an accredited college, junior college, or community college in a field of study related to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Business administration;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Accounting;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Finance;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Economics; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Real estate;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>30 semester credit hours of college-level courses that cover 3 semester hours in each of the following specific topic areas:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>English composition;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Microeconomics;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Macroeconomics;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Finance;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Algebra;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Statistics;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Computer science;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Business or real estate law; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ix)</num>
            <text>2 elective courses in any of the topics listed in §B(2)(c)(i)—(viii) of this regulation or in accounting, geography, agricultural economics, business management, or real estate;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Successful completion of at least 30 semester hours of college-level examination program (CLEP) examinations from each of the following subject matter areas:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>College algebra — 3 semester hours;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>College composition — 6 semester hours;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>College composition modular — 6 semester hours;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>College mathematics — 6 semester hours;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Principles of macroeconomics — 3 semester hours;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Principles of microeconomics — 3 semester hours;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Introductory business law — 3 semester hours; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Information systems — 3 semester hours; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Any combination of §B(2)(c) or (d) of this regulation that ensures coverage of all topics and hours identified in <cite path="09|19|02|.01|B.|(2)|(c)">§B(2)(c) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>As an alternative to the requirements of <cite path="09|19|02|.01|B.|(2)|(c)">§B(2)(c) of this regulation</cite>, an individual who has held a real estate appraiser license for a minimum of 5 years may qualify for a residential real estate appraiser certificate by satisfying all of the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>No record of any adverse, final, and non-appealable disciplinary action affecting the licensee’s legal eligibility to engage in appraisal practice within the 5 years immediately preceding the date of application for a residential real estate appraiser certificate; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Successful completion of the required Appraiser Qualifications Board core curriculum as set forth in <cite path="|09|19|02|.03|B.">Regulation .03B of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Successful completion of the additional required qualifying education as set forth in <cite path="09|19|02|.01|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An individual holding valid trainee appraiser license may satisfy the educational requirements for a residential appraiser certificate by successful completion of Appraiser Qualifications Board core curriculum as set forth in <cite path="|09|19|02|.03|B.">Regulation .03B of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An individual holding a valid real estate appraiser license may satisfy the educational requirements for a residential real estate appraiser certificate by successful completion of the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Appraiser Qualifications Board core curriculum as set forth in <cite path="|09|19|02|.03|B.">Regulation .03B of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Additional qualifying education including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Statistics, modeling, and finance — 15 hours;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Advanced residential applications and case studies — 15 hours; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Appraisal subject matter electives — 20 hours.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>An individual holding a valid trainee appraiser license may qualify for a real estate appraiser license by satisfying the college-level education requirements as set forth in <cite path="09|19|02|.01|B.|(2)">§B(2) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>An individual holding a valid real estate appraiser license who does not meet the requirements set forth in <cite path="09|19|02|.01|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> may qualify for a residential appraiser certificate by satisfying the college-level education requirements as set forth in <cite path="09|19|02|.01|B.|(2)">§B(2) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>General Real Estate Appraisers. To be eligible to sit for the certified general real estate appraisers examination, an applicant shall have completed:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>300 classroom hours of study; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A bachelor’s degree or higher from an accredited college or university.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>To be eligible for a real estate appraiser trainee license, an applicant, within the 5 year period prior to the date of submission of an application for a real estate appraiser trainee license, shall have completed:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>75 hours of classroom study which comply with this regulation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A Commission-approved course oriented toward trainee appraiser expectations and responsibilities.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Minimum Requirements for Approved Courses.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A course hour may not be considered as part of the 90-hour, 120-hour, or 180-hour, or on and after January 1, 2008, the 150-hour, 200-hour, or 300-hour, requirement of <cite path="|09|19|02|.01">Regulation .01 of this chapter</cite> unless it has been approved by the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A course may not be approved by the Commission unless the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Course is at least 15 hours in length; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Individual passes an examination at the completion of the course.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In determining whether a course is 15 hours in duration, the time during which the required examination is given is counted as part of the 15 hours.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A classroom hour is 50 minutes out of each 60-minute segment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An individual may be given up to one half of an individual's continuing education requirement for participation, other than as a student, in appraisal educational processes and programs. Credit for instructing any given course or seminar may be awarded only once during a continuing education cycle.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Commission may approve courses taken at any time. All courses, however, whether taken before or after July 1, 1990, shall meet the requirements of this regulation, including but not limited to the 15-hour and examination requirements.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Required Courses.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Effective January 1, 2008, in order to meet the 150-hour requirement set forth in <cite path="|09|19|02|.01">Regulation .01 of this chapter</cite>, an applicant shall, at a minimum, have completed the required Appraiser Qualifications Board core curriculum for the licensed education requirements, as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Basic appraisal principles — 30 hours;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Basic appraisal procedures — 30 hours;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The 15-hour national Uniform Standards of Professional Appraisal Practice course or its equivalent — 15 hours;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Residential market analysis and highest and best use — 15 hours;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Residential appraiser site valuation and cost approach — 15 hours;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Residential sales comparison and income approaches — 30 hours; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Residential report writing and case studies — 15 hours.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Effective January 1, 2008, in order to meet the 200-hour requirement set forth in <cite path="|09|19|02|.01">Regulation .01 of this chapter</cite>, an applicant shall, at a minimum, have completed the required Appraiser Qualifications Board core curriculum for the certified residential education requirements, as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Basic appraisal principles — 30 hours;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Basic appraisal procedures — 30 hours;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The 15-hour national Uniform Standards of Professional Appraisal Practice course or its equivalent — 15 hours;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Residential market analysis and highest and best use — 15 hours;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Residential appraiser site valuation and cost approach — 15 hours;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Residential sales comparison and income approaches — 30 hours;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Residential report writing and case studies — 15 hours;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Statistics, modeling and finance — 15 hours;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Advanced residential applications and case studies — 15 hours; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Appraisal subject matter electives — 20 hours.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Effective January 1, 2008, in order to meet the 300-hour requirement set forth in <cite path="|09|19|02|.01">Regulation .01 of this chapter</cite>, an applicant shall, at a minimum, have completed the required Appraiser Qualifications Board core curriculum for the certified general education requirements, as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Basic appraisal principles — 30 hours;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Basic appraisal procedures — 30 hours;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The 15-hour national Uniform Standards of Professional Appraisal Practice course or its equivalent — 15 hours;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>General appraiser market analysis and highest and best use — 30 hours;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Statistics, modeling and finance — 15 hours;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>General appraiser site comparison approach — 30 hours;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>General appraiser site valuation and cost approach — 30 hours;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>General appraiser income approach — 60 hours;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>General appraiser report writing and case studies — 30 hours; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Appraisal subject matter electives — 30 hours.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Effective January 1, 2015, in order to meet the 75-hour requirement and the Trainee Appraiser Expectation and Responsibilities Course set forth in <cite path="|09|19|02|.01|D.">Regulation .01D of this chapter</cite>, an applicant shall, at a minimum, have completed the required Appraiser Qualifications Board core curriculum for the trainee education requirements, as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Basic appraisal principles — 30 hours;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Basic appraisal procedures — 30 hours;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The 15-hour national Uniform Standards of Professional Appraisal Practice course or its equivalent — 15 hours; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Trainee appraiser and responsibilities course.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Continuing education credit may be granted for educational offerings that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Are consistent with the purpose of ensuring that appraisers participate in a program that maintains and increases their skill, knowledge, and competency in real property appraising; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Cover real property related appraisal topics, including, but not limited to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Ad valorem taxation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Arbitration and dispute resolution;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Courses related to the practice of real estate appraisal or consulting;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Development cost estimating;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Ethics and standards of professional practice under the Uniform Standards of Professional Appraisal Practice;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Land use planning and zoning;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Management, leasing, and timesharing;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Property development and partial interests;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Real estate law, easements, and legal interests;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Real estate litigation, damages, and condemnation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Real estate financing and investment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>Real estate appraisal related computer applications;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>Real estate securities and syndication;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(n)</num>
          <text>Developing opinions of real property value in appraisal that also include personal property and/or business value;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(o)</num>
          <text>Seller concessions and impact on value; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(p)</num>
          <text>Energy efficient items and “green building” appraisals.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Requirement for Appraisal Standards of Conduct and Ethics.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Effective January 1, 2003, individuals seeking to meet the educational requirement under this regulation shall successfully complete the 15-hour national Uniform Standards of Professional Appraisal Practice (USPAP) course or its equivalent for qualifying education, as determined by the Appraiser Qualifications Board (AQB) of the Appraisal Foundation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The course shall be taken from an instructor who is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An AQB certified USPAP instructor; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A State certified residential appraiser or State certified general appraiser.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|19|02|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Continuing Education.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Renewal Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In order to be considered for renewal as a certified general real estate appraiser, certified residential real estate appraiser, licensed real estate appraiser, or appraiser trainee, the applicant shall have completed 14 hours of continuing education for each year or portion thereof the applicant has been certified or licensed, since the initial issuance of the license held or, if appropriate, the most recent renewal. These courses shall be approved by the Commission as set forth in this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A total of not less than 42 hours of continuing education during each license term is required for renewal.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A licensee or certificate holder shall complete the continuing education required by §A(1)—(2) of this regulation prior to filing any application for renewal of a license or certificate, notwithstanding the expiration date for the license or certificate to be renewed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Failure to complete the continuing education required by §A(1) — (2) of this regulation in advance of filing any application for renewal of a license or certificate may be considered by the Commission to be a violation of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|16-701">Business Occupations and Professions Article, §16-701(a)(1)(i), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, among other potential violations related to failure to complete the required continuing education hours.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Required Subject Matter for Continuing Education.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Required Continuing Education in Professional Appraisal Standards, Ethics, Fair Housing, Discrimination, and Bias.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Effective January 1, 2003, all currently licensed appraisers, certified appraisers, and appraiser trainees, at least once every 2 calendar years, shall successfully complete the 7-hour national Uniform Standards of Professional Appraisal Practice (USPAP) update course, or its equivalent as determined by the Appraiser Qualifications Board (AQB) of the Appraisal Foundation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Effective November 1, 2023, any currently licensed appraiser, certified appraiser, and appraiser trainee applying for license or certificate renewal shall successfully complete during the preceding 3-year license cycle a minimum of 3 hours of appraisal education related to racial discrimination and implicit bias.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The course required by <cite path="09|19|02|.04|B.|(1)|(a)">§B(1)(a) of this regulation</cite> shall be taken from an instructor who is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An AQB certified USPAP instructor; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A State certified residential appraiser or State certified general appraiser.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A classroom hour is 50 minutes out of each 60-minute segment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Commission may not approve a continuing education course unless the course:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is at least 2 hours in duration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is taught by an approved educational provider; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Covers real estate appraisal-related topics, including but not limited to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Ad valorem taxation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Arbitration and dispute resolution;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Courses related to real estate appraisal or consulting;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Development cost estimating;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Ethics and standards of professional practice (USPAP);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Land use planning and zoning;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Management, leasing, and timesharing;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Property development and partial interests;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Real estate law, easements, and legal interests;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Real estate litigation, damages, and condemnation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Real estate financing and investment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>Real estate appraisal related computer applications;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>Real estate securities and syndication;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(n)</num>
          <text>Developing opinions of real property value in appraisals that also include personal property and/or business value;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(o)</num>
          <text>Seller concessions and impact on value;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(p)</num>
          <text>Energy efficient items and “green building” appraisals;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(q)</num>
          <text>Training in racial discrimination; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(r)</num>
          <text>Training in implicit bias or appraisal bias.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Commission may approve up to one half of an individual’s continuing education credit for participation, other than as a student, in appraisal educational processes and programs. Examples of activities for which credit may be granted are teaching, program development, authorship of textbooks, or similar activities which are determined to be equivalent to obtaining continuing education.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Commission may grant a licensee or certificate holder no more than 8 hours of credit for instruction per day for courses of continuing education.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The Commission may not grant a licensee or certificate holder credit for completion of the same continuing education course offering within the appraiser’s continuing education cycle, with the exception of the 7-Hour National USPAP Update Course, or its AQB-approved equivalent.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Approved Educational Providers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A course may not be credited towards the hours necessary to satisfy either the educational prerequisites for examination or for continuing education unless the course has been taught by a provider approved by the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Accredited universities and colleges, including community and junior colleges, are approved.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Other providers will be approved by the Commission if the Commission is satisfied that the provider is capable of providing courses which meet the educational requirements of this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Business Occupations and Professions Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|16-208">16-208</cite>(a), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|16-216">16-216</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|16-220">16-220</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|16-302">16-302</cite>(d)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|1">1</cite>) and (3) and (g), 16-308,<br/>16-309, 16-503(b)(1)(iii), (3), and (4), (e), and (f), 16-511, and 16-5A-01, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1991-09-30">Effective date: September 30, 1991 (18:19 Md. R. 2099)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-01-27"><cite path="|09|19|02|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective January 14, 2008 (35:1 Md. R. 17); January 1, 2015 (41:23 Md. R. 1372); January 27, 2020 (47:2 Md. R. 62)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-08-24"><cite path="|09|19|02|.01|A.">Regulation .01A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective January 1, 1998 (25:2 Md. R. 73); emergency status expired June 30, 1998; amended permanently effective August 24, 1998 (25:17 Md. R. 1360)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-09-12"><cite path="|09|19|02|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective September 12, 1994 (21:18 Md. R. 1509)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-08-24"><cite path="|09|19|02|.01|C.">Regulation .01C</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective January 1, 1998 (25:2 Md. R. 73); emergency status expired June 30, 1998; amended permanently effective August 24, 1998 (25:17 Md. R. 1360)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-02-18"><cite path="|09|19|02|.01|D.">Regulation .01D</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective December 1, 2000 (27:25 Md. R. 2277); emergency status expired June 1, 2001; adopted permanently effective February 18, 2002 (29:3 Md. R. 219)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-01-14"><cite path="|09|19|02|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective January 14, 2008 (35:1 Md. R. 17)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-09-12"><cite path="|09|19|02|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended effective September 12, 1994 (21:18 Md. R. 1509)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-08-24"><cite path="|09|19|02|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective January 1, 1998 (25:2 Md. R. 73); emergency status expired June 30, 1998; amended permanently effective August 24, 1998 (25:17 Md. R. 1360)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-01-14"><cite path="|09|19|02|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective January 14, 2008 (35:1 Md. R. 17)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-08-24"><cite path="|09|19|02|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective January 1, 1998 (25:2 Md. R. 73); emergency status expired June 30, 1998; amended permanently effective August 24, 1998 (25:17 Md. R. 1360)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-09-12"><cite path="|09|19|02|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite> amended effective September 12, 1994 (21:18 Md. R. 1509)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-08-24"><cite path="|09|19|02|.03|C.">Regulation .03C</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective January 1, 1998 (25:2 Md. R. 73); emergency status expired June 30, 1998; amended permanently effective August 24, 1998 (25:17 Md. R. 1360)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-01-01"><cite path="|09|19|02|.03|D.">Regulation .03D</cite>, E amended effective January 1, 2015 (41:23 Md. R. 1372)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-02-18"><cite path="|09|19|02|.03|E.">Regulation .03E</cite>, F adopted as an emergency provision effective December 1, 2000 (27:25 Md. R. 2277); emergency status expired June 1, 2001; adopted permanently effective February 18, 2002 (29:3 Md. R. 219)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-03-31"><cite path="|09|19|02|.03|G.">Regulation .03G</cite> adopted effective March 31, 2003 (30:6 Md. R. 420)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-02-18"><cite path="|09|19|02|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective December 1, 2000 (27:25 Md. R. 2277); emergency status expired June 1, 2001; adopted permanently effective February 18, 2002 (29:3 Md. R. 219)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-03-17"><cite path="|09|19|02|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite> amended effective March 17, 2014 (41:5 Md. R. 343)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-08-24"><cite path="|09|19|02|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite>, B amended as an emergency provision effective January 1, 1998 (25:2 Md. R. 73); emergency status expired June 30, 1998; amended permanently effective August 24, 1998 (25:17 Md. R. 1360)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-03-31"><cite path="|09|19|02|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite>, B amended effective March 31, 2003 (30:6 Md. R. 420)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-05-15"><cite path="|09|19|02|.04|B.">Regulation .04B</cite>, D amended effective May 15, 2023 (50:9 Md. R. 378)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-01-01"><cite path="|09|19|02|.04|D.">Regulation .04D</cite>, E amended effective January 1, 2015 (41:23 Md. R. 1372)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-01-07"><cite path="|09|19|02|.04|F.">Regulation .04F</cite> adopted effective January 7, 2013 (39:26 Md. R. 1663)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-01-01"><cite path="|09|19|02|.04|G.">Regulation .04G</cite> adopted effective January 1, 2015 (41:23 Md. R. 1372)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
