<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>04</num>
  <heading>Supervising Appraisers and Appraiser Trainees</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Supervising Appraisers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>To be eligible to serve as a supervising appraiser, an individual:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall be in good standing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>May not have been subject to any disciplinary action within the immediately preceding 3 years; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Shall have held a certified residential or certified general real estate appraisal license for at least 3 years.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A supervising appraiser may supervise a maximum of three appraiser trainees at one time.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A supervising appraiser must complete a Commission-approved course that, at a minimum, complies with the specifications for course content established by the AQB and is oriented toward the requirements, expectations and responsibilities of supervisory appraisers.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A supervising appraiser shall notify the Commission on a form prescribed by the Commission of the commencement or termination of a supervisory relationship with a real estate appraiser trainee no later than 10 days after the commencement or termination.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A supervising appraiser shall approve, sign and accept responsibility for each appraisal report prepared by a trainee under the supervision of the supervising appraiser.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Appraiser Trainees.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A real estate appraiser trainee shall notify the Commission on form prescribed by the Commission of the commencement or termination of a supervisory appraiser relationship with a supervising appraiser no later than 10 days after the commencement or termination.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>To obtain experience credit for appraisals, the real estate appraiser trainee must sign the appraisal report, sign the certification of the appraisal report, or have their name and significant appraisal assistance conspicuously identified in the appraisal report.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Business Occupations and Professions Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|16-101">16-101</cite>(r) and (s), 16-216, 16-220, and 16-5A-03, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1991-09-30">Effective date: September 30, 1991 (18:19 Md. R. 2099)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-11-09" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|09|19|04|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|09|19|04|.02">.02</cite> repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|09|19|04|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|09|19|04|.02">.02</cite> adopted effective November 9, 2015 (42:22 Md. R. 1377)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
