<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>11</num>
  <heading>Volunteer Expert Review Appraiser Roster</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Composition.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Commission may assemble and maintain a roster of licensed and certified real estate appraisers who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Possess, in the opinion of the Commission, specific expertise and knowledge; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Are willing to provide appraisal report reviews for the Commission on a volunteer basis pursuant to <cite path="25.02.01.02|B.|(8)">COMAR 25.02.01.02B(8)</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Application/Complaint Committee of the Commission may request the assistance of an appraiser from this roster to conduct research, gather data, and review and evaluate appraisal reports for compliance with the Uniform Standards of Professional Appraisal Practice (USPAP).</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Responsibilities of Volunteer Expert Appraisers.</heading>
    <text>The volunteer expert review appraiser (VERA) roster participants shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Be licensees selected by the Commission who are State-certified or State-licensed appraisers;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Agree to provide their services on a voluntary basis;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Act in conformance with the Maryland Real Estate Appraisers Act and this chapter;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Keep a detailed log of the volunteer activities conducted as a participant of the VERA roster;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Submit a copy of this log to the Application/Complaint Committee at the end of each month during which volunteer activity occurred;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Provide the Committee with written results of the review based on information obtained through services provided pursuant to <cite path="|09|19|11|.01">Regulation .01 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Appear at an administrative proceeding and provide testimony pertaining to the volunteer services rendered to the Committee pursuant to <cite path="|09|19|11|.01">Regulation .01 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Review Process.</heading>
    <text>When an appraisal report is submitted to a roster participant for review and evaluation for compliance with USPAP:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The assignment of the appraisal review will be based on the geographic location of the subject property, the type of property appraised, and the expertise and qualifications of the VERA roster participant;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The appraiser reviewing the report will be given specific written instructions by the Application/Complaint Committee as to the scope of the assignment;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The appraiser will have 30 days in which to complete a review for residential properties and 45 days for all other properties;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Extensions of the time for review may be granted upon written request from the appraiser to the Application/Complaint Committee;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The appraiser shall provide the Application/Complaint Committee with written results of the review;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Confidential information, such as the identities of the appraiser who prepared a report and the lender/client, will not be disclosed to the appraiser reviewing the report; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The appraiser reviewing the report will keep all information and documents submitted as part of the review confidential.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Application Process.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A licensed or certified appraiser may apply to serve as a volunteer expert review appraiser by submitting to the Commission a resume, a letter of interest reflecting the applicant's qualifications, including education, experience, geographic location, and property type expertise and any other information which may support selection to the VERA roster.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Commission may appoint a committee to review applications and make recommendations to the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Commission will select applicants to be included in the VERA roster from among those applicants deemed qualified by the Commission based on the applicant's education, knowledge, and experience.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>All applicants will be notified of the decision of the Commission in writing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Appraisers selected to be included in the VERA roster shall serve for a 5-year term.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Upon 30 days notice, the Commission may remove an individual from the VERA roster for any reason.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Upon request, a list of appraisers then serving on the VERA roster will be made available to members of the public.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Business Occupations and Professions Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|16-208">16-208</cite>(a), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|16-216">16-216</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|16-220">16-220</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|16-503">16-503</cite>(f), Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-06-26">Regulations <cite path="|09|19|11|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|09|19|11|.04">.04</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective January 5, 2000 (27:2 Md. R. 140); adopted permanently effective June 26, 2000 (27:12 Md. R. 1139)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
