<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>28</num>
  <heading>Cross-State Air Pollution Rule to Control Annual Nitrogen Oxides Emissions, Annual Sulfur Dioxide Emissions, and Ozone Season Nitrogen Oxides Emissions</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“CSAPR” means the federal Cross-State Air Pollution Rule promulgated under §110 of the federal Clean Air Act.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“CSAPR NO<sub>x</sub> Annual Trading Program” means a multi-state NO<sub>x</sub> air pollution control and emission reduction program established in accordance with 40 CFR Part 97, Subpart AAAAA, as published July 1, 2017, and 40 CFR §52.38(a) (including such a program that is revised in a SIP revision approved by the Administrator under 40 CFR §52.38(a)(3) or (4) or that is established in a SIP revision approved by the Administrator under 40 CFR §52.38(a)(5)), as a means of mitigating interstate transport of fine particulates and NO<sub>x</sub>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“CSAPR NO<sub>x</sub> Ozone Season Group 2 Trading Program” means a multi-state NO<sub>x</sub> air pollution control and emission reduction program established in accordance with 40 CFR Part 97, Subpart EEEEE, as published July 1, 2017, and 40 CFR §52.38(b)(1), (2)(iii), (7)—(11), and (13) (including such a program that is revised in a SIP revision approved by the Administrator under 40 CFR §52.38(b)(7) or (8) or that is established in a SIP revision approved by the Administrator under 40 CFR §52.38(b)(9)), as a means of mitigating interstate transport of ozone and NO<sub>x</sub>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“CSAPR SO2 Group 1 Trading Program” means a multi-state SO2 air pollution control and emission reduction program established in accordance with 40 CFR Part 97, Subpart CCCCC, as published July 1, 2017, and 40 CFR §52.39(a), (b), (d)—(f), and (j)—(l) (including such a program that is revised in a SIP revision approved by the Administrator under 40 CFR §52.39(f)), as a means of mitigating interstate transport of fine particulates and SO2.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“CSAPR Update” means the federal Cross-State Air Pollution Update Rule promulgated under §110 of the federal Clean Air Act.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Existing unit” for the purpose of allocation means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A unit under the CSAPR NO<sub>x</sub> Annual Trading Program or the CSAPR SO2 Group 1 Trading Program that commenced commercial operation prior to January 1, 2010.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A unit under the CSAPR NO<sub>x</sub> Ozone Season Group 2 Trading Program that commenced commercial operation prior to January 1, 2015.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“New unit” for the purpose of allocation means any unit that is not an existing unit.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter incorporates by reference the U.S. EPA CSAPR and the CSAPR Update, including the definitions, criteria, and procedures therein.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Trading Program Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>This chapter incorporates by reference provisions of the CSAPR NO<sub>x</sub> Annual Trading Program set forth in 40 CFR Part 97, Subpart AAAAA, as published July 1, 2017, and associated reference methods, performance specifications, and other test methods referenced by these standards, as applicable to existing and new units in Maryland, except the provisions at 40 CFR §97.411(b)(2) and (c)(5)(iii), 97.412(b), and 97.421(h) and (j).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>This chapter incorporates by reference provisions of the CSAPR NO<sub>x</sub> Ozone Season Group 2 Trading Program set forth in 40 CFR Part 97, Subpart EEEEE, as published July 1, 2017, and associated reference methods, performance specifications and other test methods referenced by these standards, as applicable to existing and new units in Maryland, except the provisions at 40 CFR §§97.811(b)(2) and (c)(5)(iii), 97.812(b), and 97.821(h) and (j).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>This chapter incorporates by reference provisions of the CSAPR SO2 Group 1 Trading Program set forth in 40 CFR Part 97, Subpart CCCCC, as published July 1, 2017, and associated reference methods, performance specifications and other test methods referenced by these standards, as applicable to existing and new units in Maryland, except the provisions at 40 CFR §§97.611(b)(2) and (c)(5)(iii), 97.612(b), and 97.621(h) and (j).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Environmental Article, §§1-404, 2-103, and 2-301—2-303, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-03-23">Effective date: Effective March 23, 2020 (47:6 Md. R. 342)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
