<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>29</num>
  <heading>Control of NO<sub>x</sub> Emissions from Natural Gas Pipeline Compression Stations</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Natural gas pipeline compression station” means a main line natural gas transmission station, consisting of one or more internal combustion engines, used to compress natural gas, thereby sustaining flow of natural gas through the pipeline.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Parametric optimization” means the adjustment of an internal combustion engine, such as adjustment of the air-to-fuel ratio, that maximizes engine efficiency and minimizes emissions.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="26|11|29|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Applicability and General Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Applicability. This chapter applies to stationary internal combustion engines used to compress natural gas located at natural gas pipeline compression stations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>NO<sub>x</sub> Emission Limits. A person who owns or operates a stationary internal combustion engine to which this chapter applies shall perform either parametric optimization or engine rebuild to meet the following NO<sub>x</sub> emission limits:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Facilities with five or fewer internal combustion engines shall meet a combined maximum hourly emission limit of 300 pounds per hour or less.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Facilities with more than five engines shall meet a combined maximum hourly emission limit of 566 pounds per hour or less.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>NO<sub>x</sub> Emission Rates.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The NO<sub>x</sub> emission rates in <cite path="26|11|29|.02|C.|(2)">§C(2) of this regulation</cite> apply to a stationary internal combustion engine used to compress natural gas at a natural gas pipeline compression station if the engine is one of the types and corresponding sizes identified in <cite path="26|11|29|.02|C.|(2)">§C(2) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Emission Rates.</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th>Type Engine</th>
                <th>Size (Brake HP)</th>
                <th>NO<sub>x</sub> Emission Rate<br/>(15 Percent Oxygen)</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Spark ignited rich burn</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">2400 HP or greater</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">110 ppmv</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Spark ignited lean burn</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">2400 HP or greater</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">125 ppmv</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Diesel engines</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">3100 HP or greater</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">175 ppmv</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Dual fuel engines</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">4400 HP or greater</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">125 ppmv</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The NO<sub>x</sub> emission rates in <cite path="26|11|29|.02|C.|(2)">§C(2) of this regulation</cite> shall apply on and after May 1, 2003.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="26|11|29|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Monitoring Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A person who owns or operates a stationary internal combustion engine subject to <cite path="|26|11|29|.02|C.">Regulation .02C of this chapter</cite> shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Continuously monitor NO<sub>x</sub> emissions with a continuous emissions monitor (CEM) certified in accordance with 40 CFR Part 60 or use an alternative method approved by the Department and the EPA;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>On or before May 1, 2002, and every year thereafter, collect NO<sub>x</sub> emissions data that was obtained pursuant to <cite path="26|11|29|.03|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Submit emissions data collected pursuant to <cite path="26|11|29|.03|A.|(2)">§A(2) of this regulation</cite> to the Department for the previous calendar year by April 1 of each year.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The NO<sub>x</sub> emissions data collected pursuant to <cite path="26|11|29|.03|A.|(2)">§A(2) of this regulation</cite> shall be used to demonstrate compliance with the emission reduction requirements in Regulation .02C of this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Demonstrating Compliance.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Internal Combustion Engines Equipped with a CEM.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The owner or operator of an internal combustion engine subject to this chapter that is equipped with a CEM shall demonstrate compliance with the NO<sub>x</sub> emissions limits and rates in Regulation .02B, C of this chapter using CEM data.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The sum of the NO<sub>x</sub> emissions from all affected engines at the facility shall be used to demonstrate compliance with Regulation .02B.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Internal combustion engines not equipped with a CEM.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The owner or operator of an internal combustion engine subject to this chapter that is not equipped with a CEM shall demonstrate compliance with the NO<sub>x</sub> emissions limits and rates in Regulation .02B, C of this chapter as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Compliance shall be established by stack tests using EPA Method 7 or other test methods approved by the Department and the EPA; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Compliance shall be established by an alternative emissions test approved by the Department.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The results of the stack tests or alternative emissions test for each engine and fuel consumption records submitted to the Department pursuant to <cite path="|26|11|29|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite> shall be used to calculate NO<sub>x</sub> emissions for each affected engine.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The sum of the NO<sub>x</sub> emissions from all of the stationary internal combustion engines at a natural gas pipeline compression station that are subject to this chapter shall be used to demonstrate compliance with Regulation .02B.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Stack test schedule. The owner or operator of an internal combustion engine subject to this chapter that is not equipped with a CEM shall conduct a stack test or an alternative emissions test approved by the Department to determine NO<sub>x</sub> emissions for each affected engine not less than once each 12-month period.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Maintaining Records.</heading>
    <text>Results from the previous calendar year of the stack tests, emissions tests, or CEM data and fuel consumption records for each internal combustion engine subject to this chapter shall be submitted to the Department as part of the annual emissions report due April 1 of each year.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Environment Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|1-101">1-101</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|1-404">1-404</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|2-101">2-101</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|2-103">2-103</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|2-301">2-301</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|2-303">2-303</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-05-01">Effective date: May 1, 2000 (27:8 Md. R. 799)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-11-24"><cite path="|26|11|29|.09">Regulation .09</cite> amended effective November 24, 2003 (30:23 Md. R. 1654)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-05-31" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|26|11|29|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|26|11|29|.15">.15</cite> repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|26|11|29|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|26|11|29|.05">.05</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective January 1, 2010 (37:4 Md. R. 336); adopted permanently effective May 31, 2010 (37:11 Md. R. 766)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-07-20" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|26|11|29|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|26|11|29|.05">.05</cite> under NO<sub>x</sub> Reduction Requirements for Non-Electric Generating Units, repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|26|11|29|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|26|11|29|.05">.05</cite> under Control of NO<sub>x</sub> Emissions from Natural Gas Pipeline Compression Stations, adopted effective July 20, 2015 (42:14 Md. R. 885)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
