<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>41</num>
  <heading>Control of Methane Emissions from the Natural Gas Industry</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Affected facilities” means any one of the following facilities:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Cove Point Liquefied Natural Gas Facility;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Myersville Natural Gas Compressor Station;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Accident Natural Gas Compressor Station and Storage;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Rutledge Natural Gas Compressor Station;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Ellicott City Natural Gas Compressor Station; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Any new, modified, or reconstructed natural gas compressor station, natural gas underground storage facility, or liquefied natural gas facility.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Audio, visual, and olfactory inspection” means sensory monitoring to detect natural gas leaks utilizing a human ear, eyes, and nose.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Blowdown.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Blowdown” means the release of pressurized natural gas from a station, equipment, or pipelines into the atmosphere conducted with the intent to lower the pressure in a vessel or pipeline.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Blowdown” does not include natural gas pneumatics emissions, fugitive components emissions, or compressor seal leakage.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Bubble test” means the alternative screening procedure as described at EPA Method 21 (40 CFR 60, Appendix A-7, §8.3.3).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Component” means a valve, fitting, flange, threaded-connection, process drain, stuffing box, pressure-vacuum valve, pressure-relief device, pipes, seal fluid system, diaphragm, hatch, sight-glass, meter, open-ended line, well casing, natural gas powered pneumatic device, natural gas powered pneumatic pump, reciprocating compressor rod packing/seal, metal to metal joint or seal of nonwelded connection separated by a compression gasket, screwed thread (with or without thread sealing compound), metal to metal compression, or fluid barrier through which natural gas or liquid can escape to the atmosphere.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Continuous bleed” means the continuous venting of natural gas from a gas-powered pneumatic device to the atmosphere.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Difficult-to-monitor” means fugitive emissions components that cannot be monitored for natural gas leakage without the monitoring personnel needing specialized equipment to reach components above the grade.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Direct measurement” means use of high volume sampling, calibrated bagging, a calibrated flow measuring instrument, or a temporary meter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“Fuel gas system” means components and equipment that collect and transfer natural gas to be used as a fuel source to on-site natural gas-powered equipment other than a vapor control device.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Fugitive Emissions Component.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Fugitive emission component” means any component that has the potential to emit fugitive emissions of natural gas, including but not limited to valves, connectors, pressure relief devices, open-ended lines, flanges, covers, and vapor collection systems.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Fugitive emission component” does not include devices that vent as a part of normal operations, such as natural gas-driven pneumatic devices or annulus vents, insofar as the natural gas discharged from the device’s vent is not considered a fugitive emission.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>“Fugitive emission component” includes thief hatches or other openings on a storage vessel, compressor, instrument, natural gas-powered pneumatic device, or meter that are not venting.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>“Intermittent bleed” means a pneumatic controller that is designed to vent noncontinuously.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>“Leak detection and repair” or “LDAR” means the inspection of fugitive emissions components to detect leaks of total methane and the repair of components with leaks above the standards specified in this chapter and within the time frames specified in this chapter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>“Leak or fugitive leak” means any visible emission from a fugitive emissions component observed by optical gas imaging or an instrument reading of 500 ppm or greater of methane using U.S. EPA Method 21 (40 CFR 60, Appendix A-7) or any emissions discovered from a fugitive emissions component observed using an auditory, visual, and olfactory inspection.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>“Liquefied natural gas” or “LNG” means natural gas or synthetic gas having methane as its major constituent which has been changed to a liquid.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>“LNG facility” means a pipeline facility that is used for liquefying natural gas or synthetic gas or transferring, storing, or vaporizing liquefied natural gas, and includes all components and stationary equipment within the fence line.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>“Natural gas” means a naturally occurring mixture or process derivative of hydrocarbon and nonhydrocarbon gases, which has methane as its major constituent.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>“Natural gas compressor station” means all equipment and components located within a facility fence line associated with moving natural gas from production fields or natural gas processing plants through natural gas transmission pipelines, or within natural gas storage fields.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>“Natural gas storage well” means a well located and used in a natural gas storage reservoir for injection or withdrawal purposes, or an observation well.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>“Natural gas underground storage” means all equipment and components associated with the temporary subsurface storage of natural gas in depleted crude oil or natural gas reservoirs or salt dome caverns, not including gas disposal wells.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>“Observation well” means a well used to monitor the operational integrity and conditions in a natural gas storage reservoir, the reservoir protective area, or the strata above or below the gas storage horizon.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>“Optical gas imaging” or “OGI” means an instrument that makes emissions visible to the naked eye that may otherwise be invisible.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>“Pneumatic device” means an automation device that uses natural gas or compressed air to control a process.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>“Process gas system” means components and equipment that collect and transfer the natural gas to be used through the intended process of the facility, including storage, transmission, or liquefaction.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(24)</num>
        <text>“Reciprocating natural gas compressor” means equipment that increases the pressure of natural gas by positive displacement of a piston in a compression cylinder and is powered by an internal combustion engine or electric motor with a horsepower rating designated by the manufacturer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(25)</num>
        <text>“Reciprocating natural gas compressor rod packing” means a seal composed of a series of flexible rings in machined metal cups that fit around the reciprocating compressor piston rod to create a seal limiting the amount of compressed natural gas that leaks into the atmosphere.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(26)</num>
        <text>“Reciprocating natural gas compressor seal” means any device or mechanism used to limit the amount of natural gas that leaks from a compression cylinder into the atmosphere.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(27)</num>
        <text>“Successful repair” means tightening, adjusting, or replacing equipment or a component for the purpose of stopping or reducing fugitive leaks below the minimum leak threshold or emission flow rate standard specified in this chapter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(28)</num>
        <text>“Unsafe-to-monitor” means fugitive emissions components that cannot be monitored for natural gas leakage because monitoring personnel would be exposed to immediate danger while conducting a monitoring survey.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(29)</num>
        <text>“Vapor collection system” means equipment and components installed on pressure vessels, separators, tanks, sumps, piping, connections, reciprocating compressors, natural gas-powered pneumatic devices, and flow-inducing devices used to collect and route emission vapors to a processing gas system, fuel gas system, or vapor control device.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(30)</num>
        <text>“Vapor control device” means destructive or nondestructive equipment used to control otherwise vented emissions.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Applicability.</heading>
    <text>The provisions of this chapter apply to an affected facility as that term is defined in <cite path="|26|11|41|.01|B.">Regulation .01B of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="26|11|41|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Leak Detection and Repair Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Affected facilities that are natural gas compressor stations or natural gas underground storage facilities and that use natural gas-powered equipment to compress natural gas shall comply with the following leak detection and repair requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Owners and operators of affected facilities subject to this section shall develop and submit to the Department an initial methane emissions monitoring plan that includes a technique for determining fugitive emissions (for example, EPA Method 21 at 40 CFR part 60, appendix A–7, or optical gas imaging).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If an affected facility uses optical gas imaging for leak detection, the following information shall be included in the initial methane emissions monitoring plan:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A list of the unsafe-to-monitor components;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Procedures and time frames for identifying and repairing fugitive emissions components;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A defined observation path throughout the site to confirm all components can be viewed and recorded;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Manufacturer and model number of fugitive emissions detection equipment to be used; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Equipment specifications and procedures as specified in 40 CFR §60.5397a(c)(7), as published in July 2017.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If an affected facility uses EPA Method 21 (40 CFR 60, Appendix A-7) for leak detection, the following information shall be included in the initial methane emissions monitoring plan:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A list of all fugitive emission components, difficult-to-monitor components, and unsafe-to-monitor components at an affected facility;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Procedures and time frames for identifying and repairing fugitive emission components; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Equipment specifications and procedures as specified in 40 CFR §60.5397a(c)(8), as published in July 2017.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Each difficult-to-monitor and unsafe-to-monitor component shall be identified in the written initial methane monitoring plan explaining the location and why the fugitive emissions components are difficult-to-monitor and unsafe-to-monitor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Initial Methane Emissions Monitoring Plan Submission.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Except for a new natural gas compressor station or natural gas underground storage facility, owners and operators of the affected facilities subject to this section shall submit the initial methane emissions monitoring plan required in §A(1)—(4) of this regulation to the Department within 90 days of the adoption of this regulation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Owners and operators of a new natural gas compressor station or natural gas underground storage facility subject to this section shall submit the initial methane emissions monitoring plan required in §A(1)—(4) of this regulation to the Department within 60 days of startup.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Owners and operators of affected facilities that modify or reconstruct a natural gas compressor station or underground storage facility shall submit an initial monitoring plan with the elements in §A(1)—(4) of this regulation within 90 days of the facility startup operation for each new collection of fugitive emissions components at the modified or reconstructed compressor station or underground storage facility.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Owners or operators of affected facilities subject to this section shall conduct an audio, visual, and olfactory inspection of all fugitive emission components for leaks or indications of leaks at least once per calendar week except for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Unsafe-to-monitor components; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Natural gas storage wells and observations, which shall conduct audio, visual, and olfactory inspections according to <cite path="26|11|41|.03|A.|(10)">§A(10) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Leak Monitoring Survey.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Owners and operators of affected facilities shall follow the initial monitoring methane plan and shall inspect all fugitive emission components, except for unsafe-to-monitor components, for leaks using OGI or EPA Method 21 within 180 days of the adoption of this chapter and quarterly thereafter.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Owners and operators of affected facilities that install any new, modified, or reconstructed natural gas compressor station or underground storage facility that uses natural gas-powered equipment to compress natural gas shall meet the requirements of <cite path="26|11|41|.03|A.|(8)|(a)">§A(8)(a) of this regulation</cite> within 180 days of the startup of the facility’s operations.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>At least annually, all difficult-to-monitor fugitive emissions components shall be inspected for leaks using an OGI camera.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Repair Requirements.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Any leaking fugitive emissions component identified during a leak monitoring survey or audio, visual, and olfactory inspection shall be successfully repaired, replaced, or removed from service as soon as practicable, but no later than 30 calendar days after leak detection.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Fugitive Emissions Component Resurvey.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Each repaired or replaced fugitive emissions component shall be resurveyed within 30 days after being repaired or replaced using either OGI or EPA Method 21 (40 CFR 60, Appendix A-7).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Owners and operators of facilities subject to this section that use EPA Method 21 (40 CFR 60, Appendix A-7) to resurvey the repaired or replaced fugitive emissions component shall consider the fugitive emissions component repaired when the EPA Method 21 (40 CFR 60, Appendix A-7) instrument indicates a concentration of less than 500 ppm of methane or when no soap bubbles are observed during a bubble test.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Owners and operators of affected facilities subject to this section that use OGI to resurvey the repaired or replaced fugitive emissions component shall consider the fugitive emissions component repaired when the OGI instrument shows no indication of visible emissions or when no soap bubbles are observed during a bubble test.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A delay of repair may occur when, upon request, the owner or operator provides documentation to the Department that supports the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The parts or equipment required to make necessary repairs will take longer than 30 days to be ordered and delivered, but the repair may not exceed 1 year;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The repair is unsafe to perform during the operation of the unit; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The repair requires a blowdown or facility shutdown in order to complete.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Leaking fugitive emission components awaiting repair or replacement under a delay of repair shall be clearly marked or identified in the facility’s records.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Leaking fugitive emission components under a delay of repair according to <cite path="26|11|41|.03|A.|(9)|(c)|(i)">§A(9)(c)(i) of this regulation</cite> shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Be repaired or replaced within 7 days after the owner or operator receives parts or equipment; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Be repaired or replaced at the next vent or compressor station blowdown if the owner or operator has identified this fugitive emission component as needing a vent or compressor station blowdown.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Fugitive emission components under a delay of repair according to §A(9)(c)(ii) and (iii) of this regulation shall be repaired or replaced within 1 year, at the next vent blowdown or facility shutdown, whichever occurs first.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>If a repair of a leak cannot be successfully completed according to this subsection, the owner or operator of the affected facility shall prepare a plan, for Department approval, that includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>An explanation of the technical difficulty;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A timeline to successfully repair the fugitive emission components;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A calculation of the additional methane that is expected to be released while on delay of repair; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Upon written request from the Department, any other information that the Department determines is necessary to evaluate the plan.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>The owner or operator of the affected facility shall submit any plan required under <cite path="26|11|41|.03|A.|(9)|(g)">§A(9)(g) of this regulation</cite> to the Department within 30 days from identifying the leak.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Natural Gas Storage Field Inspections.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Owners and operators of natural gas underground storage facilities shall conduct an audio, visual, and olfactory inspection of every natural gas storage well and observation well in the natural gas storage field at least once each month.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For each inspection according to <cite path="26|11|41|.03|A.|(10)|(a)">§A(10)(a) of this regulation</cite>, owners and operators shall record:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The well-head pressure or water level measurement, as appropriate;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The open flow on the annulus of the production casing or the annulus pressure if the annulus is shut in;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A measurement of gas escaping the well if there is evidence of a gas leak; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Evidence of progressive corrosion, rusting, or other signs of equipment deterioration.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>For each natural gas storage well with emissions that exceed 1,440 cubic feet per day, owners and operators shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Notify the Department within 1 business day of discovering the emission rate exceedance; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>File a written report within 10 days which shall include an explanation of the problem and corrective action taken or planned.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>For each audio, visual, and olfactory inspection that detects a leaking fugitive emission component, the owner and operator shall comply with the repair requirements specified in <cite path="26|11|41|.03|A.|(9)">§A(9) of this regulation</cite>, as applicable.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Affected facilities that are natural gas compressor stations and natural gas underground storage facilities, that exclusively use electric-powered equipment to compress natural gas, shall comply with the following leak detection and repair requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Owners and operators of facilities in this section shall meet the requirements of §A(1)—(6), (9), and (10) of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Except for unsafe-to-monitor components, owners or operators of facilities in this section shall conduct an audio, visual, and olfactory inspection of all fugitive emission components for leaks or indications of leaks at least once per calendar month.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Leak Monitoring Survey.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Except for unsafe-to-monitor components, owners and operators of affected facilities subject to this section shall inspect all fugitive emission components, including difficult-to-monitor components, for leaks using OGI or EPA Method 21 (40 CFR 60, Appendix A-7) within 180 days of the adoption of this chapter and annually thereafter.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Owners and operators of affected facilities that install any new, modified, or reconstructed natural gas compressor station or underground storage facility that uses electric-powered equipment to compress natural gas shall meet the requirements of <cite path="26|11|41|.03|B.|(3)|(a)">§B(3)(a) of this regulation</cite> within 180 days of the startup of the facility’s operations.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Cove Point Liquefied Natural Gas facility shall comply with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The leak detection and repair requirements as specified by the Climate Action Plan, which is defined, prepared, and approved under <cite path="26.09.02.06">COMAR 26.09.02.06</cite>.B—E; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The leak detection and repair plan defined and approved under the Certificate of Public Convenience and Necessity, issued by the Maryland Public Service Commission on May 30, 2014, Order No. 86372, Case No. 9318, as amended on February 6, 2018, with Order No. 88565, and Errata on February 23, 2018, Order No. 88565, as amended.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Any new liquefied natural gas facility that begins operations or repairs after the effective date of this chapter shall comply with <cite path="26|11|41|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If an owner requests approval, the Department may approve a new technology or alternative practice to identify leaking fugitive emissions components as an equivalent substitution for the requirements in §A or B of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="26|11|41|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Natural Gas-Powered Pneumatic Devices Methane Emission Control Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Beginning January 1, 2021, each continuous and intermittent bleed natural gas-powered pneumatic device shall comply with the leak detection and repair requirements specified in <cite path="|26|11|41|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>, as applicable, when the device is idle and not controlling.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>By January 1, 2022, continuous bleed natural gas-powered pneumatic devices shall not vent natural gas at a rate greater than 6 standard cubic feet per hour.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>By January 1, 2023, all continuous bleed natural gas-powered pneumatic device shall be converted to use compressed air or electricity to operate unless an exemption is provided in <cite path="26|11|41|.04|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Exemption. Continuous bleed natural gas-powered pneumatic devices may be used if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The owner and operator collect all vented natural gas from the pneumatic device with the use of a vapor collection system according to <cite path="|26|11|41|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The owner and operator submit justification for approval to the Department which demonstrates the need for the continuous bleed pneumatic device for safety or process purposes, as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Each continuous bleed pneumatic device that is approved for use shall be tagged with the month and year of installation, reconstruction, or modification and shall also have a permanent tag that identifies the natural gas flow rate as less than or equal to 6 standard cubic feet per hour; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The owner and operator shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Inspect each continuous bleed pneumatic device on a monthly basis;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Perform necessary maintenance (including cleaning, tuning, and repairing leaking gaskets, tubing fittings, and seals and tuning to operate over a broader range of proportional band to eliminate unnecessary valve positioners);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Maintain the pneumatic device according to manufacturer specifications to ensure that the device’s natural gas emissions are minimized;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>By April 1, test each pneumatic device annually using a direct measurement method (high volume sampling, bagging, calibrated flow measuring instrument, etc.); and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Successfully repair any device with a measured emissions flow rate that exceeds 6 standard cubic feet per hour within 14 calendar days from the date of the exceedance.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="26|11|41|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Reciprocating Natural Gas Compressor Methane Emission Control Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>All reciprocating natural gas compressor components at an affected facility shall comply with the leak detection and repair requirements in <cite path="|26|11|41|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite> where applicable.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Control Measures for Reciprocating Natural Gas Compressor.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>By January 1, 2021, compressor vent stacks used to vent rod packing/seal emissions shall be controlled with the use of a vapor collection system as specified in <cite path="|26|11|41|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>By April 1, the reciprocating natural gas compressor rod packing/seal emission flow rate through the rod packing/seal vent stack shall be measured annually through direct measurement (high volume sampling, bagging, calibrated flow measuring instrument, etc.) while the compressor is operating at normal operating temperature.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Direct measurements shall use one of the following methods:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Vent stacks shall be equipped with a meter or instrumentation to measure the rod packing or seal emissions flow rate; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Vent stacks shall be equipped with a clearly identified access port to measure individual or combined rod packing or seal emission flow rates.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the measurement is not obtained because the compressor is not operating for the scheduled test date, testing shall be conducted within 7 calendar days of resumed operation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A reciprocating natural gas compressor with a rod packing/seal with a measured emission flow rate that exceeds 1 standard cubic foot per minute, or a combined rod packing or seal emission flow rate that exceeds the number of compression cylinders multiplied by 1 standard cubic foot per minute shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be successfully repaired or replaced within 30 calendar days from the date of the exceedance; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Conduct natural gas compressor rod packing/seal emission flow rate measurements every 6 months or when the compressor resumes operation, whichever is later.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A reciprocating natural gas compressor with a measured emission flow rate that exceeds 2 standard cubic feet per minute, or a combined rod packing or seal emission flow rate that exceeds the number of compression cylinders multiplied by 2 standard cubic feet per minute, shall be successfully repaired or replaced within 30 calendar days from the date of the exceedance.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Delay of Repair for Reciprocating Natural Gas Compressor.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A delay of repair may occur provided the owner or operator provides documentation, upon request from the Department, that the delivery of parts or equipment required to make necessary repairs will take more than 30 days from the last emission flow rate measurement and that the parts have been ordered.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A delay of repair to obtain parts or equipment may not exceed 60 days from the date of the last emission flow rate measurement unless the owner or operator notifies the Department, in writing, of the extended delay and provides an estimated time by which the repairs will be completed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A reciprocating natural gas compressor with a rod packing/seal emission flow rate measured above the standard specified in <cite path="26|11|41|.05|B.|(4)">§B(4) of this regulation</cite>, and which has leaking parts deemed unsafe to monitor or requiring a facility shutdown, shall be successfully repaired by the end of the next planned process shutdown or within 12 months from the date of the flow rate measurement, whichever is sooner.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="26|11|41|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Vapor Collection System and Vapor Control Devices.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Owners or operators of affected facilities that utilize vapor collection systems and vapor control device to comply with this chapter shall follow the requirements as specified in §§B and C of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If a vapor collection system does not route all gases, vapors, and fumes to either a process gas system or a fuel gas system by January 1, 2021, a vapor control device shall be installed which meets the requirements of <cite path="26|11|41|.06|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The vapor collection system shall have no detectable emissions, as determined using auditory, visual, and olfactory inspections as specified in <cite path="|26|11|41|.03|A.|(7)">Regulation .03A(7) of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The vapor collection system shall comply with the leak monitoring survey and repair requirements as specified in <cite path="|26|11|41|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>, where applicable.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Vapor control devices shall meet one of the following requirements:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A nondestructive vapor control device manufacturer-designed to achieve at least 95 percent vapor control efficiency of methane emissions and may not result in emissions of nitrogen oxides (NOx); or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A destructive vapor control device manufacturer-designed to achieve at least 95 percent vapor control efficiency of methane emissions and does not generate more than 15 parts per million volume (ppmv) NOx when measured at 3 percent oxygen; or require the use of supplemental fuel gas, other than gas required for a pilot burner, to operate.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="26|11|41|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Record-Keeping and Reporting Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Owners or operators of affected facilities shall maintain, submit as described in this section, and make available upon request by the Department a copy of records necessary to verify compliance with the provisions of this chapter, as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For each leak monitoring survey and audio, visual, and olfactory inspection conducted according to <cite path="|26|11|41|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>, owners and operators shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Submit a report to the Department within 60 days of each leak monitoring survey with the following information:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Date of the survey;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A list of each fugitive emission and repair;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Any deviations from the initial methane monitoring plan or a statement that there were no deviations from the initial methane monitoring plan;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Number and type of components for which fugitive emissions were detected;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Number and type of difficult-to-monitor fugitive emission components monitored;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Instrument reading of each fugitive emissions component that requires repair when EPA Method 21 (40 CFR 60, Appendix A-7) is used for monitoring;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Number and type of fugitive emissions components that were not repaired;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Number and type of fugitive emission components placed on delay of repair and explanation for each delay of repair;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ix)</num>
            <text>The date of successful repair of the fugitive emissions component; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(x)</num>
            <text>Instrumentation used to resurvey a repaired fugitive emissions component that could not be repaired during the initial fugitive emissions finding;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Maintain, for a minimum of 5 years, record of each leak monitoring survey along with the following information:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Reports submitted according to <cite path="26|11|41|.07|A.|(1)|(a)">§A(1)(a) of this regulation</cite>;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Beginning and end time of the survey;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Name of operator(s) performing survey;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Monitoring instrument used, including the manufacturer, model number, serial number, and calibration documentation;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>When optical gas imaging is used to perform the survey, one or more digital photographs or videos, captured from the optical gas imaging instrument used for conduct of monitoring, of each required monitoring survey being performed;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Fugitive emissions component identification when EPA Method 21 (40 CFR 60, Appendix A-7) is used to perform the monitoring survey;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Ambient temperature, sky conditions, and maximum wind speed at the time of the survey;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Any deviations from the initial methane monitoring plan or a statement that there were no deviations from the initial methane monitoring plan;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ix)</num>
            <text>Proof that parts or equipment required to make necessary repairs, as required by this chapter, have been ordered;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(x)</num>
            <text>If a fugitive emissions component is not tagged, a digital photograph or video of each fugitive emissions component that could not be repaired during the leak monitoring survey at the time the fugitive emissions were initially found; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xi)</num>
            <text>Repair methods applied in each attempt to repair the fugitive emissions components;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Post a quarterly report summary to a publicly available website of each leak monitoring survey, including the information required in <cite path="26|11|41|.07|A.|(1)|(a)">§A(1)(a) of this regulation</cite>, 60 days after the leak monitoring survey; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Maintain records of audio, visual, and olfactory inspections for at least 5 years from the date of inspection.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For each natural gas-powered continuous bleed pneumatic device, owners and operators shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Maintain a record of the emission flow rate measurement and report annually beginning April 1, 2021, for at least 5 years from the date of each emissions flow rate measurement;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Maintain records of the date, location, and manufacturer specifications for each continuous bleed pneumatic device constructed, modified, or reconstructed and report annually beginning April 1, 2021;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Maintain records of the manufacturer’s specifications indicating that the device is designed such that natural gas bleed rate is less than or equal to 6 standard cubic feet per hour, if applicable;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Maintain records of deviations in cases where the pneumatic device was not operated in compliance with the requirements specified in <cite path="|26|11|41|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite> and report annually beginning April 1, 2021;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Maintain purchase orders, work orders, or any in-house or third-party reports produced or provided to the affected facility relating to the device for at least 5 years; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Maintain a record of each continuous bleed pneumatic inspection and any corrective or maintenance action taken for at least 5 years.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>For each reciprocating natural gas compressor, owners and operators shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Maintain a record of each rod packing leak concentration measurement found above the minimum leak threshold and report annually beginning April 1, 2021, for at least 5 years from the date of each leak concentration measurement;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Maintain a record of each rod packing or seal emission flow rate measurement and report annually beginning April 1, 2021, for at least 5 years from the date of each emissions flow rate measurement;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Maintain a record that documents the date(s) and hours of operation a compressor is operated in order to demonstrate compliance with the rod packing leak concentration or emission flow rate measurement in the event that the compressor is not operating during a scheduled inspection for at least 1 calendar year;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Maintain records that provide proof that parts or equipment required to make necessary repairs required by this chapter have been ordered;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Report annually the cumulative number of hours of operation or the number of months since initial startup or the previous reciprocating compressor rod packing replacement, whichever is later, beginning April 1, 2021;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>If applicable, submit a statement that emissions from the rod packing are being routed to applicable vapor control system under <cite path="|26|11|41|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Report records of deviations from this chapter that occurred during the reporting period annually, beginning April 1, 2021; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Maintain a record of purchase orders, work orders, or any in-house or third-party reports produced or provided to the affected facility necessary to demonstrate compliance with the delay of repair provisions of this chapter for at least 5 years.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Blowdown Events and Reports.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within 90 days of the effective date of this chapter, affected facilities shall submit a blowdown notification plan to the Department for approval of any blowdown event in excess of 1,000,000 standard cubic feet.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The blowdown notification plan according to <cite path="26|11|41|.07|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite> shall include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The notification format (for example, website, email, robocall, text message, social media announcement, etc.) to local authorities, the Department, and interested parties for blowdown emissions in excess of 1,000,000 standard cubic feet;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A public outreach plan to inform interested parties of the availability to be notified of blowdown events in excess of 1,000,000 standard cubic feet;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The affected facility’s responsible personnel for blowdown notifications; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A sitemap of the facility with clearly marked designated area(s) for blowdown emissions in excess of 1,000,000 standard cubic feet.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>For any blowdown event in excess of 1,000,000 standard cubic feet, affected facilities shall make information publicly available in accordance with the facility’s approved blowdown notification plan, including notification to the Department, at least 7 days prior.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>For any blowdown event in excess of 1,000,000 standard cubic feet that is scheduled less than 7 days prior to the blowdown event, affected facilities shall, as soon as practicable:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Make information publicly available in accordance with the facility’s approved blowdown notification plan; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Provide an explanation to the Department of the reason for the blowdown event.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>For any emergency or unplanned blowdown event in excess of 1,000,000 standard cubic feet, affected facilities shall make information publicly available in accordance with the facility’s approved blowdown notification plan and notify the Department within 1 hour of the emergency or unplanned blowdown event.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>When safety concerns preclude a facility from providing prior notification of an emergency or unplanned blowdown under <cite path="26|11|41|.07|B.|(5)">§B(5) of this regulation</cite>, the facility shall send notice to the Department within 24 hours of the blowdown event indicating the reason(s) why prior notice was not possible.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Affected facilities shall report the following information to the Department of blowdown emissions in excess of 50 cubic feet within the facility’s fence line annually by April 1 of each year:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Date and type (that is, planned or emergency) of each blowdown event;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Methane emissions in metric tons released from each blowdown event; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Annual methane emissions in metric tons from all blowdown events.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Methane emissions shall be calculated according to procedures in 40 CFR Part 98, Subpart W, §98.233.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Greenhouse Gas Emissions Reporting.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Owners and operators of affected facilities shall report methane, carbon dioxide, and nitrous oxide mass emissions to the Department annually by April 1 of each year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Owners and operators of affected facilities shall follow the procedures for emission calculation, monitoring, quality assurance, missing data, record keeping, and reporting that are specified in 40 CFR Part 98, Subpart C, and 40 CFR Part 98, Subpart W.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>When reporting to the Department, owners and operators of affected facilities shall expand the fugitive emissions reporting requirements of 40 CFR Part 98, Subpart W, to include a Microsoft Excel format list providing calculations summarized by category under 40 CFR §98.232(e)—(h) as applicable.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The reporting threshold in 40 CFR §§98.2, <cite path="|98.31">98.31</cite> and 98.231 of 25,000 metric tons of CO2 equivalent does not exempt an affected facility from following the requirements of this section.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>All required reports shall be submitted to the Industrial Compliance Division in written or electronic format and mailed to Maryland Department of the Environment, Air Quality Compliance Program, 1800 Washington Boulevard, 7th Floor, Baltimore, MD 21230, Attention: Industrial Compliance Division.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Environment Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|1-404">1-404</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|2-103">2-103</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|2-1202">2-1202</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|2-1205">2-1205</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-11-16">Effective date: November 16, 2020 (47:23 Md. R. 978)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
