<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Handgun Permit Unit</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Board” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|5-301">Public Safety Article, §5-301(b), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Central Repository” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|5-117">Public Safety Article, §5-117</cite>.1(f)(1), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Designated security personnel” means an individual who receives a handgun permit for employment purposes and is a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Holder of a special police commission;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Uniformed security guard;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Special railway police;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Watchman;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Private detective; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Guard in the employ of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>An armored car company;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A bank;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A savings and loan association;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>A building and loan association; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>An express agency.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Handgun Permit Training Certificate” means a certificate, letter, or other documentation verifying satisfactory completion of a Handgun Permit Training Course.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Handgun Permit Training Course” means a firearms training course that satisfies the requisite minimum requirements of <cite path="|29|03|02|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Mental disorder” has the meaning stated in Health—General Article, §10-101(f), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Mental health facility” has the meaning stated in Health—General Article, §10-101(e), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Permit” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|5-301">Public Safety Article, §5-301(d), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“Qualified Handgun Instructor” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|5-101">Public Safety Article, §5-101(q), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="29|03|02|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Generally.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|5-306">Public Safety Article, §5-306(a), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the Secretary shall issue handgun permits under specified conditions.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Unless otherwise provided by law, a person shall have a valid permit in their possession to carry, wear, or transport a handgun.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A valid permit must satisfy all the requirements set forth in this chapter, including any limitations or restrictions imposed by the Secretary.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A permit holder may not wear, carry, or transport a handgun while under the influence of alcohol or drugs.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="29|03|02|.02|F.">§F of this regulation</cite>, all valid permits must be issued by the Secretary.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>An armored car driver’s permit from another state is valid if the driver is on duty in Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Eligibility.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Qualifications. In accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|5-306">Public Safety Article, §5-306, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, a person is eligible for issuance of a handgun permit only if the person:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is an adult;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is not prohibited from possessing a handgun under <cite path="29.03.01.03">COMAR 29.03.01.03</cite> or otherwise prohibited from purchasing or possessing a handgun under federal or State law;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Has not been convicted of a felony or misdemeanor for which a sentence of imprisonment for more than 1 year has been imposed, unless the person has been pardoned or the United States Attorney General has granted relief;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Has not been convicted of a crime involving the possession, use, or distribution of a controlled dangerous substance;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Is not presently an alcoholic, addict, or habitual user of a controlled dangerous substance, unless the habitual use of a controlled dangerous substance is under legitimate medical direction;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Has not exhibited propensity for violence or instability that may reasonably render the person’s possession of a handgun a danger to the person or another;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Has a good and substantial reason to wear, carry, or transport a handgun; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>If younger than 30 years old, has not been committed to a detention, training, or correctional institution for juveniles for longer than 1 year after an adjudication of delinquency by a juvenile court.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Investigation Criteria. The following areas will be a part of the investigation of every applicant and will be considered by the Secretary in determining whether a permit will be issued:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Age of the applicant;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Occupation, profession, or employment of the applicant;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Verification of the applicant’s qualifications;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Verification of the information supplied by the applicant in the application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Information received from personal references and other persons interviewed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Information received from business or employment references as may be necessary in the discretion of the investigator;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Criminal record of applicant, including any juvenile record for an applicant younger than 30 years old;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Medical history of applicant as it may pertain to the applicant’s fitness to carry, wear, or transport a handgun;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Psychiatric or psychological background of the applicant as it may pertain to the applicant’s fitness to carry, wear, or transport a handgun;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>The applicant’s propensity for violence or instability which could reasonably render the applicant’s wearing, carrying, or transporting of a handgun a danger to the applicant or to others;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>The applicant’s use of intoxicating beverages and drugs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>The reasons given by the applicant for carrying, wearing, or transporting a handgun, and whether those reasons are good and substantial; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Whether the permit is necessary as a reasonable precaution for the applicant against apprehended danger.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="29|03|02|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Application.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The handgun permit application shall be submitted in the format prescribed by the Secretary.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The permit application shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The applicant’s name, address, driver’s license or photographic identification soundex number, place and date of birth, height, weight, race, sex, eye and hair color, occupation, and home and work telephone numbers;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Proof of the applicant’s completion of, or exemption from, a Handgun Permit Training Course with at least 16 hours of instruction within the previous 2 years, in the manner prescribed by the Secretary on the permit application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A complete set of the applicant’s fingerprints, taken and submitted in the manner prescribed by the Secretary on the application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Authorization by the applicant to the Maryland Department of Health, or any other similar agency or department of another state, to disclose to the Department of State Police information as to whether the applicant:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Suffers from a mental disorder and has a history of violent behavior;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has been voluntarily admitted for more than 30 consecutive days to a mental health facility or an institution that provides treatment or services for individuals with mental disorders; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Has been involuntarily committed to a mental health facility or an institution that provides treatment or services for individuals with mental disorders; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A declaration by the applicant, under the penalty of perjury, that the applicant is not prohibited under federal or State law from possessing a handgun; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A declaration by the applicant, under the penalty of perjury, that all information in the application is true and accurate.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="29|03|02|.04|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>, the application must be accompanied by a nonrefundable payment of $75.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Secretary shall not charge a fee to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A State, county, or municipal public safety employee who is required to carry, wear, or transport a handgun as a condition of governmental employment; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A retired law enforcement officer of the State or a county or municipal corporation of the State.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A handgun permit expires on the last day of the holder’s birth month following 2 years from the date of issuance.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="29|03|02|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Training Requirement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="29|03|02|.05|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, a person applying to obtain or renew a handgun permit shall complete a Handgun Permit Training Course and submit a Handgun Permit Training Certificate issued by a Qualified Handgun Instructor. The submission of the Handgun Permit Training Certificate shall constitute proof that the applicant satisfactorily completed a Handgun Permit Training Course.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An applicant does not need to complete a Handgun Permit Training Course if the applicant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is a law enforcement officer or has retired in good standing from service with a law enforcement agency of the United States, the State, or any local law enforcement agency in the State;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is an active member, retired member, or honorably discharged member of the armed forces of the United States or the National Guard;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Is a Qualified Handgun Instructor in accordance with <cite path="29.03.01.37">COMAR 29.03.01.37</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Has satisfactorily completed a firearms training course approved by the Secretary as an exemption from the Handgun Permit Training Course.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A Handgun Permit Training Course shall consist of a minimum of 16 hours of instruction by a Qualified Handgun Instructor for initial applicants or eight hours of instruction by a Qualified Handgun Instructor for renewal applicants, and shall include the following minimum curricula.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>State Firearm Law. Overview of the State firearm laws, including discussion of what constitutes a regulated firearm, how to properly purchase or transfer a firearm, where allowed to carry or transport a firearm, when necessary to possess a carry permit, and who is prohibited from possessing firearms.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Home Firearm Safety. Overview of handgun and firearm safety in the home, including discussion of access to minors, locking and storing of firearms, and use of safety devices, such as secure lock boxes.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Handgun Mechanisms and Operation. Overview of the proper operation and safe handling of a handgun, including cleaning and maintenance, the loading and unloading of ammunition, and the differences between revolvers and semi-automatic handguns, as well as training in nomenclature, sight alignment, position shooting, dry-firing, and range practice.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Proficiency and Use Demonstration. Overview of handgun and firearm safety on the range, off the range, and while transporting or on duty. Orientation that demonstrates the applicant’s proficiency in the operation and use of a firearm, including a shooting component in which the applicant fires live ammunition and obtains a qualifying score of 70 percent as prescribed by the Secretary. Instruction on safety shall be integrated into every phase of the training.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Except as provided in <cite path="29|03|02|.05|C.|(4)|(b)">§C(4)(b) of this regulation</cite>, the shooting component shall be at least 25 rounds and an applicant may not be required to fire in excess of 15 yards from the target during qualifications.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For designated security personnel, the shooting component shall be conducted on a practical police course as approved by the Secretary. The shooting component shall be at least 50 rounds and an applicant may not be required to fire in excess of 25 yards during qualifications.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>False or Omitted Information.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant shall not provide false information on an application for a permit, or omit significant information on the application, or cause false information to be given in connection with the verification investigation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Any knowing material omission or false statement may be considered grounds for denial of a permit or for criminal prosecution.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Investigation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Upon receipt of a properly completed application, the Secretary shall conduct an investigation of the applicant for the purpose of determining whether the applicant possesses the qualifications for a permit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Information discovered during the investigation may be used against an applicant who has provided false or misleading information or has omitted information on the application.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Issuance and Denial.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|5-306">Public Safety Article, §5-306(a), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the Secretary shall issue a permit or provide a written denial of the application within a reasonable time after receiving a properly completed application.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A properly completed application must satisfy all the requirements prescribed by the Secretary.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A written denial provided by the Secretary shall contain the reasons the application was denied and a statement of the applicant’s appeal rights.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Secretary may limit the geographic area, circumstances, or times of the day, week, month, or year in which a permit is valid or effective.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Change of Address or Employment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If a permit holder’s address or employment changes, the permit holder shall provide written notification to the Secretary within 10 days of the change.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Failure to notify the Secretary within ten days may be grounds for revocation of the permit by the Secretary.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Lost or Stolen Permit.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If a handgun permit is lost or stolen, the permit holder shall provide written notification to the Secretary within 10 days after discovery of the loss or theft.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The written notification shall be accompanied by a notarized affidavit, under oath, stating that the permit has been lost or stolen.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Failure to notify the Secretary within 10 days may be grounds for revocation of the permit by the Secretary.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Replacement or Modification.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A person may submit a request to the Secretary for a replacement permit if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The permit was lost or stolen; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The permit needs to be modified.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A request for a replacement permit must be accompanied by a nonrefundable fee of $10, unless the replacement permit is a result of action by the Handgun Permit Review Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Upon receipt of a properly submitted request, the Secretary shall issue a replacement permit within a reasonable time if the applicant is not otherwise disqualified from possessing a handgun permit.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Renewal.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A permit may be renewed for successive periods of 3 years.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The permit renewal application shall be submitted in the format prescribed by the Secretary.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The permit renewal application shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The applicant’s name, address, driver’s license or photographic identification soundex number, place and date of birth, height, weight, race, sex, eye and hair color, occupation, and home and work telephone numbers;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The identification number from the applicant’s prior permit;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Proof of the applicant’s completion of, or exemption from, a Handgun Permit Training Course with at least 8 hours of instruction within the previous 2 years, in the manner prescribed by the Secretary on the permit renewal application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A complete set of the applicant’s fingerprints, taken and submitted in the manner prescribed by the Secretary on the application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Authorization by the applicant to the Maryland Department of Health, or any other similar agency or department of another state, to disclose to the Department of State Police information as to whether the applicant:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Suffers from a mental disorder and has a history of violent behavior;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has been voluntarily admitted for more than 30 consecutive days to a mental health facility or an institution that provides treatment or services for individuals with mental disorders; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Has been involuntarily committed to a mental health facility or an institution that provides treatment or services for individuals with mental disorders; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A declaration by the applicant, under the penalty of perjury, that the applicant is not prohibited under federal or State law from possessing a handgun; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>A declaration by the applicant, under the penalty of perjury, that all information in the application is true and accurate.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The renewal application must be accompanied by a nonrefundable payment of $50.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Upon receipt of a properly submitted renewal application, the Secretary shall issue a renewed permit within a reasonable time if the applicant is not otherwise disqualified from possessing a permit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>To ensure adequate time for processing, a renewal application should be filed at least 90 days before the expiration date of the permit which is to be renewed.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Revocation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Secretary may revoke a permit on a finding that the permit holder:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>No longer satisfies the qualifications set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|5-306">Public Safety Article, §5-306, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Failed to carry the permit in the holder’s possession whenever the holder carried, wore, or transported a handgun.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Secretary shall provide written notification to a person whose permit is revoked.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A written notice of revocation shall contain the reasons the permit was revoked and a statement of the person’s appeal rights.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A person whose permit is revoked shall return the permit to the Licensing Division, Department of State Police within 10 days after receipt of the notice of revocation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Appeal.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Informal Review.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person whose original or renewal permit application is denied or whose permit is revoked or limited may submit a written request to the Secretary for an informal review within 10 days after receipt of the notice of denial, revocation, or limitation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Upon receipt of a valid request, the Secretary shall review the action under informal review and may include a personal interview of the person requesting the informal review.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Secretary shall sustain, reverse, or modify the action under informal review and provide written notification to the person who requested the informal review within 30 days after receipt of the request for informal review.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>An informal review is not subject to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 10, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Handgun Permit Review Board.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person whose original or renewal permit application is denied or whose permit is revoked or limited may submit a written request to the Board to review the decision of the Secretary within 10 days after receipt of the notice of denial, revocation, or limitation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person whose original or renewal permit application is not acted on by the Secretary within 90 days after submitting the application to the Secretary may submit a written request to the Board for a hearing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Public Safety Article, Title 5, Subtitle 3; <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|4-202">Criminal Law Article, §4-202</cite>; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1976-05-26">Effective date: May 26, 1976 (3:11 Md. R. 592)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1984-01-02"><cite path="|29|03|02|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective January 2, 1984 (10:25 Md. R. 2270)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1984-01-02"><cite path="|29|03|02|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective November 17, 1978 (5:23 Md. R. 1741); January 2, 1984 (10:25 Md. R. 2270)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1984-01-02"><cite path="|29|03|02|.08">Regulation .08</cite> amended effective January 2, 1984 (10:25 Md. R. 2270)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-10-29"><cite path="|29|03|02|.11">Regulation .11</cite> repealed and new Regulation .11 adopted effective October 29, 1990 (17:21 Md. R. 2530)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-10-29"><cite path="|29|03|02|.12">Regulation .12</cite> amended effective October 29, 1990 (17:21 Md. R. 2530)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-10-29"><cite path="|29|03|02|.13">Regulation .13</cite> repealed and new Regulation .13 adopted effective October 29, 1990 (17:21 Md. R. 2530)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-10-29"><cite path="|29|03|02|.14">Regulation .14</cite> amended effective January 2, 1984 (10:25 Md. R. 2270); October 29, 1990 (17:21 Md. R. 2530)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" discontinuity="true">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|12.06.07">COMAR 12.06.07</cite> to <cite path="|29.03.02">29.03.02</cite>, July 1994</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-07-17">Regulations .01, .02, .06—.09, .11, .13, and .14 amended effective July 17, 1995 (22:14 Md. R. 1053)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-03-19"><cite path="|29|03|02|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective October 1, 2000 (27:20 Md. R. 1836); amended permanently effective March 19, 2001 (28:5 Md. R. 552)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-09-30"><cite path="|29|03|02|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective September 30, 2002 (29:19 Md. R. 1527)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-03-19"><cite path="|29|03|02|.04|D.">Regulation .04D</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective October 1, 2000 (27:20 Md. R. 1836); amended permanently effective March 19, 2001 (28:5 Md. R. 552)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-09-30"><cite path="|29|03|02|.08|A.">Regulation .08A</cite> amended effective September 30, 2002 (29:19 Md. R. 1527)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-09-30"><cite path="|29|03|02|.10|G.">Regulation .10G</cite> amended effective September 30, 2002 (29:19 Md. R. 1527)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-03-19"><cite path="|29|03|02|.14">Regulation .14</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective October 1, 2000 (27:20 Md. R. 1836); amended permanently effective March 19, 2001 (28:5 Md. R. 552)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-12-23" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|29|03|02|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|29|03|02|.14">.14</cite> repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|29|03|02|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|29|03|02|.14">.14</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective October 1, 2013 (40:21 Md. R. 1772); adopted permanently effective December 23, 2013 (40:25 Md. R. 2072)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
