<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>11</num>
  <heading>Electronic Contributions</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter applies to all electronic contributions received by a political committee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>For the purposes of this regulation, a credit card contribution made by a person to a political committee is not an electronic contribution.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this subtitle, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Common short code” means a unique text message number that may be accessed by an individual through the use of SMS on a wireless communication device or computer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Short message service” or “SMS” means a service that allows the exchange of short text messages between or among wireless communication devices or computers.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="33|13|11|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Electronic Contributions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Electronic Contribution Requirements. As provided in <cite path="33|13|11|.03|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, a person may make an electronic contribution to a political committee if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A record of the name and address of the person is provided to the receiving political committee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The person approves and authorizes the contribution;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The contribution is made using one of the secure methods in <cite path="33|13|11|.03|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>For contributions made using a common short code:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The contribution amount is not greater than $10.00 for each transaction;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The common short code is directly associated with the political committee receiving the contribution; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The person receives a confirmation that the transaction occurred.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Method of Electronic Contributions. A political committee may receive an electronic contribution if made by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Electronic funds transfer authorized by the contributor and transferred directly from the contributor’s account in a financial institution into the political committee’s campaign account;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Wire transfer authorized by the contributor and transferred directly from the contributor’s account in a financial institution into the political committee’s campaign account;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A financial-institution-issued debit card withdrawal authorized by the contributor and transferred directly from the contributor’s account in a financial institution into the political committee’s campaign account by the political committee or by a processing agent of the political committee; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>An authorized payment for a common short code message associated with a political committee authorized by the contributor through the use of a wireless communication device owned by the contributor and transferred into the political committee’s campaign account by the political committee or by a processing agent of the political committee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Campaign Finance Reporting.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Reporting Electronic Contribution. A political committee may not report on a campaign finance report any electronic contribution received by a political committee as a lump sum contribution.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Contribution Reporting Requirements. A political committee shall meet the contribution reporting requirements of <cite path="33.13.02.02|A.">COMAR 33.13.02.02A</cite> for any electronic contribution received.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|2-102">Election Law Article, §2-102(b)(4), </cite>13-234, and 13-304(b), Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-04-30">Effective date: April 30, 2012 (39:8 Md. R. 537)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
