<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>General Regulations</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Rules of Order.</heading>
    <text>All proceedings of the Board in regular session shall be governed by Robert's Rules of Order.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Board Officers, Members, and Staff.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board shall, as the appointing authority, direct the operation of the staff through the executive director.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Board members may not have monetary, pecuniary, or other interest in the affairs of any:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Staff member; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Organization engaged in business with the Board, including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Businesses;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Enterprises; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Other for-profit organizations.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A Board member or Board staff may not serve for compensation as an instructor in a continuing education course or program under Board cognizance over which that Board member or staff member serves in an approval capacity.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Preliminary Educational Qualifications Credits.</heading>
    <text>Preliminary educational qualifications credits acceptable to the Board are:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Certificates or diplomas issued by public and private high schools accredited by the National Council of Secondary Educational Institutions or as recognized by the state or city issuing them.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Certificates issued by the department of education of the states and possessions of the United States to applicants having 15 or more units to their credit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Applicants presenting foreign credits of preliminary education shall have them certified by the consul or the embassy of the country in which they were acquired.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Bachelor's degree accredited by the State.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Examination Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board shall accept examination results only from the National Board of Chiropractic Examiners for applicants for a chiropractic license, including applicants seeking to practice chiropractic with physical therapy privileges.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board shall set the minimum passing score for each section of the National Board of Chiropractic Examiners' examination.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Board shall administer a jurisprudence examination at least twice a year at times and places to be announced by the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An applicant for the jurisprudence examination shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Have first successfully completed all required parts of the National Board of Chiropractic examination to the satisfaction of the Board; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Submit all documentation and fees at least 45 days before the examination date as determined by postmark.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The examination shall begin promptly at a time announced by the Board and shall be proctored by a Board member or Board staff member.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The applicant shall present a letter of admission and at least one form of personal, valid, current, U.S. government or state issued photo identification. There is no excuse, waiver, or exception for this requirement.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The application shall be executed, verified, and submitted to the Board at least 45 days before the date of examination.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The applicant shall follow all directions of the examination proctor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>The examination paper shall be retained by the Board as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Passing examination papers shall be retained for 30 days;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Failing examination papers shall be retained for 90 days;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All examination papers shall be destroyed after the expiration of the time periods established under §I(1) and (2) of this regulation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Retained examination papers may not be reviewed by the applicant following the completion of the applicant's examination.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>The Board shall administer the jurisprudence examination in the English language with no provisions made by the Board to accommodate the examination in any foreign language.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>An applicant who fails the jurisprudence examination three times may not retake the examination until the Board has reviewed the applicant's file and approved a retake.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|43|01|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Licenses.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Temporary Licenses. The Board may not issue any temporary license to practice chiropractic in Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An individual practicing chiropractic without a license shall be prosecuted and subject to penalties as prescribed in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 3, Subtitle 5, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Board shall issue a license only upon an applicant's successful completion of the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>National Board of Chiropractic Examiners' examination, Parts I, II, III, and IV;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Jurisprudence examination; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>National Board of Chiropractic Examiners' Physiotherapy examination, if applicable.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Board may waive educational or examination requirements for any licensed chiropractor applying to practice exclusively with a visiting organization for not more than 30 days per calendar year if the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Chiropractor practices in a Board-approved, recognized jurisdiction with an active license in good standing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Practice is limited exclusively to members of the visiting organization; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Chiropractor submits a timely request by application in accordance with Board procedures.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Display of License in Office. A license holder shall display conspicuously at all times at the license holders' place of business the license granted by the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The license holder shall notify the Board of any change in the name or address of the license holder, in writing, within 60 days after the change occurs.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Licensure by Credential.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An application for licensure by credential shall be based on a written SPEC examination administered by the National Board of Chiropractic Examiners, a jurisprudence examination administered by the Board, and the education and professional qualifications of the applicant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>At the Board's discretion, an applicant for licensure by credential shall appear before the Board in person before the license is granted.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Renewals.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A license holder failing to renew a license shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be notified by the Board by certified mail of the delinquency; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Have the license lapse into non-renewed status if the license holder does not renew by September 30th of the renewal year.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Continuing Education.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Upon renewal, when audited by the Board, a license holder shall submit written evidence of the successful completion of the number of continuing education hours and cardiopulmonary resuscitation (CPR) certification required by the Board for renewal.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The license holder shall have completed the required credit hours by the time of renewal.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>This evidence may include a photocopy of the official transcript or a report of the completion of the course.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Only a course program approved by the Board may be used to meet the continuing education requirement of <cite path="10|43|01|.05|H.|(2)">§H(2) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The requirement may be waived by the Board upon proof of unusual and extreme hardship or disability, and upon application to the Board at least 60 days before September 1.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Reinstatements. An applicant for reinstatement of a license that has lapsed for a period of more than 2 years shall be admitted only after satisfying the Board as to the applicant's efficiency by examination and the payment of fees due.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Types of Licenses.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board shall issue two types of licenses:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A license covering the practice of chiropractic and physical therapy, as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|3-101">Health Occupations Article, §3-101(f) </cite>and (g), Annotated Code of Maryland; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A license permitting the holder to practice chiropractic as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|3-101">Health Occupations Article, §3-101(f) </cite>and (g), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An individual holding the chiropractic license and wishing to qualify for the license to practice physical therapy in conjunction with a practice of chiropractic may do so by passing the National Board of Chiropractic Examiners Physiotherapy examination with a minimum score of 75 percent.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Disclosure for Compelling Public Purpose.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board may find that a compelling public purpose warrants disclosure of information in an application, certification, licensing, or investigative file, regardless of whether there has been a request for the information, if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The information concerns possible criminal activity and the disclosure is to a federal, state, or local law enforcement or prosecutorial official or authority;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The information concerns a possible violation of law and the disclosure is to a federal, state, or local authority that has jurisdiction over the individual whose conduct may be a violation, and the information disclosed is limited to information relevant to the possible violation by that individual; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The information concerns conduct by an individual that the Board reasonably believes may pose a risk to the public health, safety, or welfare, and the disclosure is to a law enforcement authority, administrative official, or agency that regulates the individual, or to a hospital or other health care facility where the individual has privileges.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Other Disclosures. This regulation does not prohibit or limit the Board's ability to disclose general licensing information as provided in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-333">General Provisions Article, §4-333, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or any information that the Board may otherwise disclose by law.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health Occupations Article, Title 3, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1969-02-01">Effective date: February 1, 1969</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-11-25"><cite path="|10|43|01|.02-1">Regulation .02-1</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective November 25, 1985 (12:25 Md. R. 2469); emergency status expired May 24, 1986 (Emergency provisions are temporary and not printed in COMAR)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1991-01-21"><cite path="|10|43|01|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective January 21, 1991 (18:1 Md. R. 30)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1977-04-27"><cite path="|10|43|01|.06|E.">Regulation .06E</cite> amended effective April 27, 1977 (4:9 Md. R. 719)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1983-10-24"><cite path="|10|43|01|.08">Regulation .08</cite> repealed effective October 24, 1983 (10:21 Md. R. 1902)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-08-06" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective August 6, 2001 (28:15 Md. R. 1398)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-06-09"><cite path="|10|43|01|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective June 9, 2003 (30:11 Md. R. 735)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-06-13"><cite path="|10|43|01|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended effective June 13, 2011 (38:12 Md. R. 705)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-01-06"><cite path="|10|43|01|.04|D.">Regulation .04D</cite> amended effective June 13, 2011 (38:12 Md. R. 705); January 6, 2014 (40:26 Md. R. 2164)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-06-13"><cite path="|10|43|01|.04|G.">Regulation .04G</cite> amended effective June 13, 2011 (38:12 Md. R. 705)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-10-22"><cite path="|10|43|01|.04|F.">Regulation .04F</cite> amended effective October 22, 2007 (34:21 Md. R. 1915)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-01-06"><cite path="|10|43|01|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective October 22, 2007 (34:21 Md. R. 1915); January 6, 2014 (40:26 Md. R. 2164)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-04-13"><cite path="|10|43|01|.05|F.">Regulation .05F</cite> amended effective April 13, 2015 (42:7 Md. R. 570)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-01-02" discontinuity="true">Subtitle and Chapter name amended to be, Board of Chiropractic Examiners, General Regulations, effective January 2, 2017 (43:26 Md. R. 1446)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
