<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>General</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In addition to the terms defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-101">State Government Article, §9-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and in <cite path="36.01.01.01">COMAR 36.01.01.01</cite>, which have the same meanings in this subtitle, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Activate” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>To make a book of instant tickets ready for sale in the Lottery Central System; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>To make a ticket ready for sale.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Announced end of game” means the date set by the Agency after which retailers may not activate instant tickets for that game.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Bonus Drawing.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Bonus drawing” means a game the Agency designates as a bonus drawing that may have a claiming period other than 182 days after the drawing in which the prize is won.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Bonus drawing” does not include a daily or weekly lottery drawing.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Bonus Game.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Bonus game” means a game the Agency designates as a bonus game that may have a claiming period other than 182 days after the drawing in which the prize is won.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Bonus game” does not include a:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Daily or weekly lottery game; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Specific play features on a ticket.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Claim form” means a paper or computer-generated document that identifies a prize claimant, prize amount, game and ticket characteristics.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Coupon” means a paper or computer-generated code that a player may apply to purchase a ticket.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Daily game” means a draw game for which the Agency offers a drawing at least once every day.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Designated cutoff time” means the time after which a ticket may no longer be purchased for the next drawing of a specified lottery game.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Draw Game.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Draw game” means a lottery game for which a winning result is determined by a drawing for which a ticket:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Is sold and redeemed through a subscription or through a terminal at retailer locations; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>May be generated by a terminal and is a record of a transaction for a draw game.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Draw game” includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A jackpot game including a multi-jurisdictional jackpot game;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A nonjackpot game including a multi-jurisdictional jackpot game;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A monitor game; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Any other Agency-authorized lottery game designated as a draw game.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>“Draw ticket” means a ticket purchased from a terminal or through a subscription for a draw game.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>“Drawing” means a random selection event used for determining winning numbers game data of certain lottery games.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>“Drawing date” means the day, days of the week, or times of day on which the winning game data a lottery game are selected.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>“Entry” means a qualifying purchase or action by which a player may participate in a promotion or special activity.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>“ePlayslip” means an on-screen display or two-dimensional code, that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Contains player-selected or randomly generated game data; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is electronically generated by a website or mobile application authorized by the Agency.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>Fast Play Game.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Fast Play game” means a game issued by the Lottery Central System where predetermined game results are obtained from a finite pool of randomly generated results for that game and are available through the terminal.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Fast Play game” does not include a draw game.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>“Game data” means any item or symbol used to identify:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A winner of a lottery game, including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Numerals;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Letters;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Symbols, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Icons including branded logos;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The cost of a ticket; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Number of draws and which draws on a ticket.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>“In-lane ticket” means a ticket that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is purchased by a player;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>May only be purchased at a retailer that is a commercial establishment; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Is activated for play or produced when it is processed through a third-party point of sale terminal or cash register.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>Instant Game.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Instant game” means a lottery game for which a ticket has a covered area that the player exposes in accordance with the game instructions, and includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Scratch-off tickets; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Tickets using other methods of revealing a hidden area with pre-determined results.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Instant game” does not include an in-lane ticket for a draw game.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>“Instant ticket” means a ticket issued in an instant game.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>“Instant ticket pack” or “instant ticket book” means group of tickets in sequential order bundled together.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>“Jackpot game” means a lottery game for which the top prize amount varies:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Based on sales; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the top prize was won in the preceding drawing.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>“Lottery Central System” means an integrated computer service and equipment that the Agency authorizes and procures for the purposes of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Producing lottery tickets at retailer locations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Facilitating lottery ticket transactions;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Providing tools and the means by which retailers:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Determine sales;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Cash tickets;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Confirm receipt and activate an instant ticket book;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Display of animations of winning numbers;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Process a ticket, ePlayslip, or playslip;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Print special reports and tickets;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Order instant tickets;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Order supplies; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ix)</num>
            <text>Coordinate the distribution of tickets;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Providing random number generating equipment to conduct and offer monitor games, Cash Pop and Fast Play games;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Communicating with lottery retailers; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Performing any other function, the Agency identifies as necessary to the operation of the State lottery and accounting for its proceeds.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>“Lottery Central System contractor” means the person under contract with the Agency to provide all the goods and services required under the contract for the Lottery Central System.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(24)</num>
        <text>“Monitor” means a television screen or similar type of screen used to display monitor game results and other Agency communications.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(25)</num>
        <text>“Monitor game” means a draw game for which:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Tickets are generated by a terminal;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Lottery Central System generates the winning result; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Drawing results may be graphically displayed on a monitor.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(26)</num>
        <text>“Multi-jurisdictional game” means a lottery game offered by the Agency and:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Any other political entity outside Maryland or outside the United States;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Any private licensee of a state or a foreign nation; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Both §B26(a) and (b) of this regulation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(27)</num>
        <text>“Nonjackpot game” means a lottery game where the top prize remains static.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(28)</num>
        <text>“Odds” means the likelihood of an outcome to occur or not occur.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(29)</num>
        <text>“Pari-mutuel” means dividing the prize money available for winners of a certain prize level in a lottery game equally among all plays winning the prize in a particular drawing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(30)</num>
        <text>Player-Activated Terminal or PAT.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Player-activated terminal” or “PAT” means a machine through which a player may purchase a ticket or claim a prize under an applicable tax reporting or taxable prize threshold without intervention by a retailer.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Player-activated terminal or PAT does not mean a machine that dispenses cash.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(31)</num>
        <text>“Playslip” means a document issued by the Agency and used by a player to select the player’s game data.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(32)</num>
        <text>“Probability” means the long-run ratio of the number of winning outcomes to the number of all outcomes.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(33)</num>
        <text>“Progressive jackpot” means a jackpot offered in a lottery game that may increase in value based on sales of that game.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(34)</num>
        <text>Promotion.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Promotion” means:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>An activity or game offered by the Agency to increase awareness of the Agency and its products and services;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A contest that uses a second-chance drawing to determine a winner; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A cooperative marketing project under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|11-203">State Finance and Procurement Article, §11-203, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Promotion” may include a lottery game if additional consideration is required for a player to participate.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(35)</num>
        <text>“Retailer” means a person licensed by the Agency to sell lottery tickets.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(36)</num>
        <text>Special Bonus.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Special bonus” means an extra payment to a retailer or its employees that the Agency authorizes;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Special bonus” may not exceed one-half of 1% of the gross receipts from ticket sales for the year for which the bonuses are awarded;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>“Special bonus” does not include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A bonus drawing; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Game play features on a ticket.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(37)</num>
        <text>“Special license” means a retailer license issued by the Director for a conditional or limited purpose as determined by the Director.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(38)</num>
        <text>“Subscription” means a method of playing a lottery game by which a player completes an application to play a specific number of lottery games using the same game data for a period of consecutive drawings.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(39)</num>
        <text>Terminal.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Terminal” means a computerized unit or software program that operates through the Lottery Central System and is specifically designed for:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Issuing, processing or printing a ticket;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Processing an ePlayslip;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Processing a playslip.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Printing a report;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Confirming and activating a retailer’s receipt of an instant ticket book;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Accepting payment for a ticket;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Processing the validation and redemption of a ticket;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Carrying out functions available to the retailer; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ix)</num>
            <text>Any other process the Agency identifies as necessary for the State lottery and within the scope of the Lottery Central System contract.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Terminal” includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A player-activated terminal or PAT; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A retailer-activated terminal; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Associated lottery equipment.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(40)</num>
        <text>Unusual Claim.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Unusual claim” means a claim of a prize, or multiple claims for prizes, over $600 that is abnormal in amount, frequency, pattern, or type.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Unusual claim” includes a claim made by a claimant under circumstances indicating that a law or regulation may be violated and that the Director has a reasonable belief to be, based on the totality of the circumstances.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(41)</num>
        <text>“Validate” or “validation” means the process of verifying through the Lottery Central System, whether a ticket is a valid winning ticket.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(42)</num>
        <text>“Valid winning ticket” means a lottery ticket that has been validated.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(43)</num>
        <text>Winner.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Winner” means a person that holds a winning ticket.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Winner” includes the claimant of a prize.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Sponsorship Request.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Scope. This regulation sets out procedures under which a person may submit a sponsorship request to the Agency pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-111">State Government Article, § 9-111(d)(1), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite> to promote the Maryland State Lottery.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A person holding an event in Maryland may submit a request to the Agency to sponsor the event.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Form and Content of Request.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A requestor for Agency sponsorship shall submit a request in writing to the Assistant Director of Communications.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The sponsorship request shall describe the event and include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The date, time, and location;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A description;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The expected number of people in attendance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The number of years it has taken place in Maryland;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The types of sponsorship opportunities that are available;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The cost associated with each type of sponsorship opportunity; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>An explanation with examples as to why the event may be a good fit for the Agency.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The decision to sponsor an event is within the sole discretion of the Agency and is not subject to review.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-103">9-103</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-104">9-104</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-109">9-109</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-111">9-111</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|9-122">9-122</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-05-13">Effective date: May 13, 2013 (40:9 Md. R. 790)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-05-26"><cite path="|36|02|01|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective December 2, 2019 (46:24 Md. R. 1104); May 26, 2025 (52:10 Md. R. 439)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-09-21"><cite path="|36|02|01|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective January 7, 2016 (42:26 Md. R. 1597); January 14, 2019 (46:1 Md. R. 13); September 21, 2020 (47:19 Md. R. 850)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-05-26"><cite path="|36|02|01|.02">Regulation .02</cite> adopted effective May 26, 2025 (52:10 Md. R. 439)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
