<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Economic Stabilization</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>The Economic Stabilization Act regulations provide voluntary guidelines for employers faced with a major reduction in the work force.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Exceptions.</heading>
    <text>This law does not apply to reductions in operations if the reduction:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Results solely from labor disputes;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Occurs in a commercial, industrial, or agricultural enterprise operated by this State or its political subdivisions;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Occurs at construction sites or other temporary work places;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Results from seasonal factors that are determined to be customary in the industry; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Results when an employer files for bankruptcy under federal bankruptcy laws.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>"Employer" means a person, corporation, or other entity that employs at least 50 individuals and operates an industrial, commercial, or business enterprise in the State. "Employer" does not mean the State or its political subdivisions. "Employer" does not include any employer who has been doing business in the State for less than 1 year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>"Reduction in operations" means the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Relocation of a part of an employer's operation from one work place to another site; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shutting down of a work place or a portion of the operations of a work place that reduces the number of employees by at least 25 percent or 15 employees, whichever is greater, over any 3-month period.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Work Place.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Work place" means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A factory;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A plant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>An office; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Other facility where employees produce goods or provide services.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Work place" does not mean a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Construction site; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Temporary work place.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Voluntary Guidelines for Employers Anticipating a Permanent Reduction in Work Force.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Employers facing a reduction in operations should:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Meet with employee representatives regarding concessions or alternatives, or both, to closure in order to save the place and save jobs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Notify all impacted employees if a reduction in operation is required:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>At least 90 days before the termination date; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>By written notice to each employee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Termination Phase-In.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If no collective bargaining agreement is in force, the employer should plan for a phase-in of the termination developing a staggered schedule of layoffs spread over the maximum time practical.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If collective bargaining agreements are in force, then the employer shall implement the provisions of the agreement as the agreement pertains to termination and seniority.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Post Termination Benefits.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Employers should consider continuing non-work-related benefits for as long as feasible following termination.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Employers should consider offering laid-off employees the following benefits:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Health care coverage or the option of continuing, at the employee's own expense, the employee's current health care coverage:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>For at least 6 months following termination, or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Until other employment is secured;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Participation rights in employee credit unions; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Other special company benefits.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Special Termination Benefits.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Employers should consider providing the following special benefits:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Retraining allowances, which:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Could range from $1,000 to $1,800, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Can be utilized by any employee who both enrolls and completes a retraining program or career-related educational program;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A severance pay package tied to the employee's wage level or length of employment, or both;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Job search assistance or job clubs which include instruction on how to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Market employment skills,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Complete resumes/applications,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Interview,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Look for work, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Utilize labor market information.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Employers may implement on-site displaced worker centers to provide a central place for the dissemination of all termination services and information.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Assistance from the Maryland Department of Labor.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Maryland Department of Labor shall make the Quick Response Program available to employers consisting of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>On-site unemployment insurance bulk claims registration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Registration of federal trade readjustment services;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Labor market and retraining information;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Job placement services;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Job seeking and finding information; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Referral to retraining opportunities.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Maryland Department of Labor shall assist employers in planning for and implementing a program to provide reemployment services for displaced or soon to be displaced workers by attempting to provide:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Assistance with planning for reemployment services to the work force;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Assistance with planning for and implementing an on-site displaced worker assistance center; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Financial resources, as available, to assist with a wide range of employment and training services.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Mechanisms to Start Assistance Programs from the Maryland Department of Labor.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Employers may contact the Assistant Secretary for the Division of Employment and Training.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Secretary of the Maryland Department of Labor shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Monitor layoffs to identify employers who are likely to experience a reduction in operations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Identify employers likely to experience a reduction in operations; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Contact all employers in the State who appear to be faced with or planning a permanent reduction in operations. This contact shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Made by telephone;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Confidential;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Directed to the chief executive of the business; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>For the purpose of offering:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Planning assistance, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Assistance in providing services, if needed.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the employer approves, the Maryland Department of Labor shall contact the Department of Housing and Community Development to provide whatever assistance is deemed appropriate.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container">Labor and Employment Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gle|11-301">11-301</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gle|11-304">11-304</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-05-19">Effective date: May 19, 1986 (13:10 Md. R. 1158)</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|24.03.03">COMAR 24.03.03</cite> to <cite path="|24.03.02">COMAR 24.03.02</cite></annotation>
    <annotation type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|24.03.02">COMAR 24.03.02</cite> to <cite path="|09.33.02">COMAR 09.33.02</cite>, May 1996</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
