<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>08</num>
  <heading>Crematories — Cremation Procedures</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter governs the procedures to be followed by a permit holder in performing a cremation in this State.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Removal, Identification, and Transportation of Human Remains.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Upon receipt of human remains, a permit holder, in the presence of the authorizing agent or representative of the funeral establishment engaging crematory services, shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Verify that the information on the wrist tag of the human remains is consistent with the documentation accompanying the human remains and consistent with the visual observation of the human remains;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Use a metal detector wand to inspect for the presence of any battery operated, implanted devices including pacemakers, defibrillators, or pain relief devices;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Refuse to accept human remains for cremation if an inspection of the human remains indicates the presence of any battery operated, implanted device;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Remove and properly dispose of any hazardous object or any other materials that the permitted designee of the crematory authority deems should be removed from the human remains or cremation container in order to prevent harm to the public health or damage to the cremator;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Remove any jewelry on the human remains or in the cremation container;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Return any removed jewelry to the authorizing agent or representative of the funeral establishment engaging cremation services; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Obtain a signed, itemized receipt from the authorizing agent or representative of the funeral establishment engaging cremation services for the removed jewelry and retain the receipt as a permanent record.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Foreign objects removed from the human remains:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall be treated as medical waste and disposed of accordingly; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>May not be donated until a sterilization process through a third party, recognized by the Office, to dispose properly of medical waste has been performed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Materials identifying the human remains placed in the custody of a crematory authority shall contain the following information:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Name;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Date of birth;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Date of death;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Name of funeral establishment or authorizing agent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Gender; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Name and relationship of authorizing agent to the decedent.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A crematory authority shall not accept unidentified human remains for cremation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Cremation Container.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A cremation container:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall be a readily combustible, rigid container suitable for cremation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shall provide a completely enclosed covering for the human remains;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Shall be resistant to leakage or spillage;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Shall be of sufficient strength and rigidity for ease of handling;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Shall provide protection to the health and safety of crematory establishment personnel;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Shall comply with all local, State, and federal governmental emissions regulations; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>May not be composed of metal or polyethylene material.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A cremation container which appears to be heavily coated with varnish, lacquer, or any other highly combustible substance shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Placed in a cold cremator within which no cremation has occurred in the prior 4 hours; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Coated completely with water before being placed in the cremator.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Holding Facilities.</heading>
    <text>A holding facility shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Comply with applicable public health laws;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Preserve the dignity of human remains;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Recognize the integrity, health, and safety of crematory establishment personnel; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Be secure from access by unauthorized persons.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Holding Remains.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Unless prevented by emergency circumstances, human remains that have been designated for cremation shall be cremated by a crematory authority within 48 hours after receipt.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A crematory authority may not hold human remains for cremation unless the human remains are contained within an individual, rigid, stackable, closed cremation container.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A crematory authority may not accept a cremation container from which there is any evidence of leakage of the body fluids from the human remains therein.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Whenever a crematory authority is unable to cremate human remains within 48 hours of taking custody thereof due to emergency circumstances, the crematory authority shall maintain the human remains in a refrigerated holding facility, either on or off site, at 40° F or less, unless the remains have been embalmed.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Identification of Human Remains Immediately Prior to Cremation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Immediately prior to being placed within the cremator, a designee of the crematory authority shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Verify the identification of the human remains; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Place in the cremator the circular, hard metal identification disc of the human remains being cremated where it shall remain in place until the cremation process is complete.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The designee of the crematory authority who is operating the cremator may not leave the immediate area of the cremator during the cremation process.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Cremation Authorization.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as otherwise provided in this regulation, a crematory authority may not cremate human remains until:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The body has been identified as required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|7-411">Health Occupations Article, §7-411, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The crematory has received:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A cremation authorization on a form approved by the Office and signed by an authorizing agent;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If applicable, a written delegation document or facsimile; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Any other documentation required by federal, State, or local law; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The crematory authority has documented that at least 12 hours have elapsed from the time of death of the individual whose remains are to be cremated.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The cremation authorization form shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be provided by the crematory authority to the authorizing agent, and signed by the authorizing agent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Contain the following information:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The identity of the human remains;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Date of death;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The name and address of the crematory where the cremation will occur;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The name and address of the authorizing agent and the relationship between the authorizing agent and the deceased;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Authorization for the crematory authority to cremate the human remains;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Authorization to verify that the following have been removed prior to cremation:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Implanted pacemaker or defibrillator; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Any other materials that the crematory authority deems should be removed to prevent harm to the public health or damage to equipment;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>A representation by the authorizing agent that radiological implant treatment has not occurred to the human remains within 5 days before cremation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>A representation that the authorizing agent is aware of no objection to the human remains being cremated by any person who has a right to control the disposition of the human remains; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>The name and address of the person authorized to claim the cremated remains from the crematory authority or accept the cremated remains via registered mail; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Be signed by the authorizing agent.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If an authorizing agent is not available to execute the cremation authorization form, the authorizing agent may delegate that authority to another individual:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In writing; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If located outside the area, by transmitting to the crematory authority:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A signed, notarized statement, electronically or by facsimile device, that contains the name, address, and relationship of the sender to the deceased and the name and address of the individual to whom authority is delegated; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Once the authorizing agent is located in the area, a notarized statement, through the United States Postal Service attesting to the delegation of authority.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Upon receipt of the written delegation document or a copy of the delegation statement transmitted electronically or by facsimile device, the crematory authority shall allow the named individual to serve as the authorizing agent. The documents shall be signed by the authorizing agent in the presence of a notary.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A person signing a cremation authorization form is deemed to warrant the truthfulness of any facts set forth in the cremation authorization form, including the identity of the deceased whose remains are sought to be cremated and the authority of that person to order such a cremation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A crematory authority shall notify and obtain the written consent of the authorizing agent before the cremation of human remains at a location other than the location named on the cremation authorization form.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A crematory authority shall maintain a copy of every cremation authorization form required under this regulation as permanent records.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Cremation authorization records are subject to inspection and copying by the Office.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Record of Receipt of Remains.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A crematory authority shall provide to an individual who delivers human remains for cremation a receipt signed by both the crematory authority and the person who delivered the human remains, that includes the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Name of the individual from whom the human remains were received and the name of the individual's employer, if any;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Name and address of the crematory authority;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Name and address of the deceased;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Gender of the deceased;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Date of death of deceased; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Verification of authorized burial transit permit.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The crematory authority shall maintain a record of each cremation which shall include the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Name of the deceased;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Date of birth of the deceased;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Date of death of the deceased;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Gender of the deceased;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Name and address of the authorizing agent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Date, time, and location of cremation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Name of the individual who performed the cremation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The crematory authority shall provide a certificate of disposition of cremated human remains to the authorizing agent or funeral establishment that arranged for the cremation that contains the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Name of the deceased;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Name of the authorizing agent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Date, time, and location where cremation occurred;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Name of the individual who performed the cremation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Name and address of the person who received the cremated human remains from the crematory authority; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>If ascertainable, the location, including the name of the cemetery and plot location if the remains are interred, the manner, and the date of the disposition of the cremated human remains.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The crematory authority shall maintain a copy of every record and receipt required by this regulation as permanent records.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>All records required to be maintained by a crematory authority by this chapter are subject to inspection and copying by the Office.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|34|08|.09">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Use of a Casket; Embalming.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="09|34|08|.09|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, a crematory authority may not:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Require that human remains be placed in a casket before cremation or that human remains be cremated in a casket;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Refuse to accept human remains for cremation because the remains are not in a casket; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Refuse to accept human remains for cremation because the remains are in a suitable, combustible wooden casket, but may request the authorizing agent or funeral establishment engaging the services of the crematory authority to remove the metal mattress holder in the casket.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Human remains delivered to a crematory authority may not be removed from the cremation container and the cremation container shall be cremated with the human remains unless the authorizing agent for the deceased requests that the human remains be placed in the cremator without enclosure in a cremation container.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The cremation container shall be cremated with the human remains unless the authorizing agent for the deceased requests a more natural environment for the deceased. A crematory authority is not required to accept this manner of disposition.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A crematory authority may not require that human remains be subjected to embalming before cremation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Disposition of Cremated Human Remains.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Upon completion of the cremation, insofar as is possible:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All of the recoverable residue of the cremation process shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Removed from the cremator:</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Except for medical devices remaining after cremation, processed; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Placed in a container; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The identification disc required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|7-411">Health Occupations Article, §7-411, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Removed from the cremator; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Placed in the container with the cremated human remains.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Medical devices which remain after the completion of the cremation process shall be treated as medical waste and disposed of accordingly.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>After pulverization, all of the processed human remains, together with the identification disc, shall be placed in a sealable container.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the cremation container opening is not of adequate dimensions to accommodate an identification disc, it shall be affixed to the container and a record of the cremation number shall be place in the container.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If all of the processed human remains and the identification tag will not fit within the dimensions of a sealable container, the remainder of the processed human remains shall be returned to the authorizing agent, or the agent's representative, in a separate, sealable container. Container seams shall be taped.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If the processed human remains and identification tag do not adequately fill the container's interior dimensions, the extra space may be filled with packing material that will not become intermingled with the processed human remains and then securely closed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>If a sealable container containing processed human remains is to be shipped, the sealable container shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be placed within a separate sturdy box with all box seams securely taped closed; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Have the name of the deceased person whose processed human remains are contained therein legibly written on the outside of the container.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>If processed human remains have been in the possession of a crematory authority, as originally authorized by the authorizing agent, without instructions for disposition, for a period of 10 days or more from the date of cremation, the crematory authority may send the processed human remains, using the current mailing standard approved by the U.S. Postal Service, to the authorizing agent.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Tools.</heading>
    <text>A crematory shall maintain, at its own expense, the following tool inventory:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Safety placement tool measuring a minimum of 49 inches in length;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Wire brushes for cleaning cremators;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Brush with fine bristles for cleaning pulverizers;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Mortar and pestle;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Funnel;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>High temperature protective gloves and heat resistant leather gloves;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Hand magnet and metal detector wand to detect and remove metal from cremated human remains;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Tweezers to remove nonmetal objects from cremated human remains; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Dust masks.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|34|08|.12">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Visitors.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The crematory permit holder or registered crematory operator shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Submit to the Office the number of persons not affiliated with the operation of the crematory who can safely be within the same room and within 10 feet of the cremator door; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Verify to the Office that the crematory permit holder has submitted the information required in <cite path="09|34|08|.12|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite> to their liability insurance carrier.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Crematories that begin operation after July 1, 2014, shall construct a viewing room the area of the cremator if the crematory authority intends to permit more than two visitors present in the area of the cremator during a cremation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|5-204">Business Regulation Article, §5-204, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-03-31">Effective date: March 31, 2014 (41:6 Md. R. 378)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
