<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Electronic Control Device Training</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Annual in-service training curriculum" means a course of study approved by the Commission that meets the requirements established for electronic control device classroom instruction, written examination, and practical exercise and is conducted as part of mandated employee in-service training and firearms qualification under <cite path="12.10.01.16">COMAR 12.10.01.16</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Commission" means the Correctional Training Commission or a representative authorized to act on behalf of the Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Correctional officer" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|8-201">Correctional Services Article, §8-201, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Correctional unit" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|8-201">Correctional Services Article, §8-201, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Electronic control device" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|4-109">Criminal Law Article, §4-109, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Initial training course curriculum" means a course of study approved by the Commission that meets the requirements established for electronic control device classroom instruction, written examination, and practical exercise that an individual shall successfully complete before the individual may be authorized to carry or use an electronic control device.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Minimum Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter establishes minimum correctional officer training requirements related to the use of an electronic control device.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A correctional unit may adopt correctional officer training requirements related to use of an electronic control device in addition to Commission requirements under this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A correctional officer may not carry or use an electronic control device as part of the correctional officer's official duties before the correctional officer's correctional unit has:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Approved each specific manufacturer's model of an electronic control device used as part of the correctional officer's duties;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Certified to the Commission, on forms or in a manner determined by the Commission, that the correctional officer has successfully completed Commission training requirements established under this chapter for each specific manufacturer's model of an electronic control device approved by the correctional unit, which, at a minimum, include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Classroom instruction;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A written examination; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Practical exercises demonstrating proficiency in the use of the specific manufacturer's model of an electronic control device; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Determined that the correctional officer has received adequate training demonstrating the ability to safely and effectively use each specific manufacturer's model of an electronic control device the correctional officer is authorized to carry or use.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="12|10|05|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Correctional Officer Electronic Control Device Initial Training Course Curriculum.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A correctional officer is not required to complete an electronic control device initial training course curriculum under this regulation if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The correctional officer's authorization to use a specific manufacturer's model of an electronic control device is in effect on September 30, 2009 and the correctional unit has determined the correctional officer has:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Received adequate training on the specific manufacturer's model of an electronic control device; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Demonstrated the ability to safely and effectively use the specific manufacturer's model of an electronic control device; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The correctional officer has been authorized to carry or use a specific manufacturer's model of an electronic control device under <cite path="12|10|05|.03|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite> and is seeking authorization to carry or use a different manufacturer's model of an electronic control device that the correctional officer's correctional unit has approved and determined:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>There are no significant operational differences between the current and new manufacturer's model of an electronic control device; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>That the correctional officer has:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Received adequate training; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Demonstrated the ability to safely and effectively use the new manufacturer's model of an electronic control device.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Except under <cite path="12|10|05|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, a correctional officer shall successfully complete a Commission-approved initial training course curriculum for the specific manufacturer's model of an electronic control device before the officer is authorized to carry or use a specific manufacturer's model of an electronic control device as part of the correctional officer's official duties.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A correctional officer is required to complete an initial training course curriculum if after successfully completing an initial training course curriculum, the correctional officer has not been authorized to carry or use the specific manufacturer's model of an electronic control device:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within 2 years of completing an initial training course curriculum for the specific manufacturer's model of an electronic control device; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For 2 or more years and the correctional officer has not met the annual in-service training curriculum requirement for the specific manufacturer's model of an electronic control device under <cite path="|12|10|05|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Initial training course curriculum requirements may be completed:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>As part of correctional officer entrance-level training under <cite path="12.10.01.09">COMAR 12.10.01.09</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Independent of correctional officer entrance-level training.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Electronic Control Device Annual In-Service Training Curriculum.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A correctional officer authorized to use or carry a specific manufacturer's model of an electronic control device shall successfully complete annual in-service training curriculum for the specific manufacturer's model of an electronic control device.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A correctional officer who successfully completes an initial training course curriculum for a specific manufacturer's model of an electronic control device during a calendar year is not required to complete an annual in-service training curriculum for the same specific manufacturer's model of an electronic control device until the next calendar year.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="12|10|05|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Electronic Control Device Training Content Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Minimum Commission-Approved Classroom Instruction Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Only a Commission-certified electronic control device instructor may conduct Commission-approved electronic control device classroom training.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Initial training course curriculum and annual in-service curriculum electronic control device classroom instruction, at a minimum, shall include the following topics related to the specific manufacturer's model of an electronic control device for which the correctional officer is to be authorized to carry or use:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Electronic control device:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Nomenclature;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Characteristics;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Capabilities;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Limitations;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Maintenance; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Operational principles and technology; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Proper electronic control device use addressing:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Correctional unit policy and procedures;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Agency and other protocols;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Judgment and decision making;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Legal considerations;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Physiological and psychological effects;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Target zones;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Side effects and individuals with an elevated risk;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>After-care measures;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ix)</num>
            <text>Defensive measures;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(x)</num>
            <text>Potential collateral occurrences; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xi)</num>
            <text>Safety of transport, storage, and use.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A correctional officer shall achieve a minimum passing score of 70 percent on a written examination that tests a correctional officer's comprehension of the topics required under <cite path="12|10|05|.05|A.|(2)">§A(2) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Minimum Commission-Approved Practical Exercise Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Only a Commission-certified electronic control device instructor may conduct Commission-approved electronic control device practical exercises.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Initial and annual in-service electronic control device practical exercise, at a minimum, requires that a correctional officer demonstrate skills related to the proper use of the specific manufacturer's model of an electronic control device the correctional officer carries or uses as part of official duties.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If applicable to the specific manufacturer's model of an electronic control device, a correctional officer, at a minimum, shall demonstrate proficiency related to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Operational and functionality checks of the device;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Transition between a firearm and other tactical equipment and the electronic control device;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Proper carrying and handling;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Loading and reloading;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Restraint of an individual subjected to the device; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Discharge, if the device is capable of discharging a projectile.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Discharge Requirement.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>During an initial training course curriculum with the specific manufacturer's model of an electronic control device, each correctional officer shall discharge the device.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>During annual in-service training curriculum with the specific manufacturer's model of an electronic control device, the discharge requirement may be met by the instructor discharging the device to demonstrate to two or more correctional officers, rather than each correctional officer personally discharging the device.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Correctional Services Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|2-109">2-109</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|8-208">8-208</cite>; <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|3-207">Public Safety Article §3-207</cite>; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-01-01">Effective date: January 1, 2010 (36:26 Md. R. 1996)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-01-01"><cite path="|12|10|05|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective September 6, 2010 (37:18 Md. R. 1214); January 1, 2013 (39:16 Md. R. 1081)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-12-11"><cite path="|12|10|05|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended effective December 11, 2014 (41:24 Md. R. 1428)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-02-17"><cite path="|12|10|05|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective February 17, 2014 (41:3 Md. R. 202)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-09-02"><cite path="|12|10|05|.06">Regulation .06</cite> repealed effective September 2, 2013 (40:17 Md. R. 1420)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
