<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>06</num>
  <heading>Instructor Training and Certification</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Commission" means the Maryland Correctional Training Commission or a representative authorized to act on behalf of the Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Correctional unit" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|8-201">Correctional Services Article, §8-201, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Course of Fire.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Course of fire" means a sequence of activities related to the actual discharge of a firearm on a firing line for training or qualification.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Course of fire” does not include firearm classroom instruction.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Day fire” has the meaning stated under <cite path="12.10.04.02">COMAR 12.10.04.02</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Department of Juvenile Services” means the State agency established under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ghu|9-201">Human Services Article, §9-201, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Deputy Director" means the Deputy Director of the Police and Correctional Training Commissions, or the Deputy Director’s designee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Executive Director” means the Executive Director of the Police and Correctional Training Commissions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Firearm” means a pistol, revolver, or long gun.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Firearm Classroom Instruction.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Firearm classroom instruction” means training conducted in a traditional educational setting; for example, in a room with desks, chairs, books, paper, and other educational tools or equipment.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Firearm classroom instruction" does not include training conducted on a firing line.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Firing line" means an area and position from which an individual actually discharges a firearm with live ammunition for firearms training or qualification, or both, as part of a course of fire.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Firearms Training.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Firearms training” means a demonstration or an exercise, in addition to firearm classroom instruction, that is provided:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>By an individual certified under <cite path="|12|10|06|.11">Regulation .11 of this chapter</cite> or <cite path="|12.04.06">COMAR 12.04.06</cite> to perform firearm classroom instruction, conduct firearms training or qualification; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>To enhance understanding, proficiency, marksmanship, and other skills related to proper firearm use and tactics, such as movement, multiple targets, judgmental or decision training, and use of cover and concealment.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Firearms training” may include drills that involve discharging rounds of ammunition.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>“Firearm type” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The following handguns:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Revolver; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Pistol; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The following long guns:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Shotgun; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Long gun other than a shotgun.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Handgun.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Handgun” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|5-101">Public Safety Article, §5-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Handgun” includes a:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Pistol; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Revolver.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>Inactive Status.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Inactive status” means a situation in which an individual, who continues to be employed by or under the supervision of a correctional unit, academy certified under <cite path="12.10.01.14">COMAR 12.10.01.14</cite>, or the Department of Juvenile Services, is temporarily relieved of duties with the correctional unit, academy certified under <cite path="12.10.01.14">COMAR 12.10.01.14</cite>, or Department of Juvenile Services for 30 consecutive days or more for:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A medical or administrative reason that prevents the individual from completing Commission-required training; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The purpose of suspending Commission-required training.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Inactive status” does not affect an individual’s instructor certification or eligibility for provisional certification or certification.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>“Judgmental or decision training” means instruction and skills development conducted in the classroom, using firearms simulation, or on a firing line, to enable an individual to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Differentiate between threat levels; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Respond appropriately to an identified threat.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>Optical Sighting Device.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Optical sighting device" means a mechanism that assists an individual in sighting a firearm.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Optical sighting device" does not include an iron sight.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>"Pistol" means a handgun that operates semi-automatically:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Discharging a single round of ammunition with a pull of the trigger;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Clearing the chamber of the spent casing; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Loading the next round of ammunition in the chamber.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>"Power" means a measurement used to describe levels of visual magnification, with a number representing the level of magnification above the normal visual range.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>“Qualification” as used in Regulations .11, .14, and .15 of this chapter means proficiency testing by discharging a firearm on a Commission-approved course of fire to receive a score that the Commission measures against established requirements to determine if the individual meets provisions required under this chapter for certification as a Firearms Provisional Instructor, Line Instructor, or Firearms Instructor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>Reduced Light.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Reduced light” means the normal outdoor lighting conditions that exist between dusk and dawn.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Reduced light” includes simulated natural outdoor lighting conditions such as:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Artificial light; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Goggles, headgear, or an apparatus worn to cover the eyes designed to reduce the availability of light to simulate natural reduced lighting conditions.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>“Revolver” means a handgun that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Fires a single round of ammunition with each pull of the trigger; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has a cylinder containing additional rounds of ammunition that rotates to position the next round of ammunition for firing.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>“Term of certification” means the dates during which an individual’s certification for an instructor classification is in effect.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>“Training authority” means an individual of a correctional unit, academy certified under <cite path="12.10.01.14">COMAR 12.10.01.14</cite>, or the Department of Juvenile Services who is authorized by the correctional unit, academy certified under <cite path="12.10.01.14">COMAR 12.10.01.14</cite>, or the Department of Juvenile Services to submit under provisions of this chapter an application for any of the following for another individual:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Instructor certification;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Renewal of instructor certification;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Termination of certification;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Exemption from instructor certification; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Waiver of certain requirements for instructor certification.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(24)</num>
        <text>“Training provider” means an entity that has Commission approval to conduct a training course.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(25)</num>
        <text>“Type 1 long gun” means a long gun with an optical sighting device greater than 4 power intended for use as a counter-sniper firearm.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(26)</num>
        <text>"Type 2 long gun" means a long gun with an optical sighting device greater than 4 power intended for use other than as a counter-sniper firearm.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(27)</num>
        <text>"Type 3 long gun" means a long gun without an optical sighting device, or with an optical device of 4 power or less.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(28)</num>
        <text>Type 4 Long Gun.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Type 4 long gun" means a long gun manufactured and sold as a shotgun that is designed to discharge a single projectile or multiple projectiles from a single round of ammunition.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Type 4 long gun" includes a long gun manufactured and sold as a shotgun regardless of the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Action; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Use of an optical sighting device.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Instructor Certification Classifications.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Commission provides instructor certification in accordance with this chapter for the following instructor classifications:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Academic Provisional Instructor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Academic Instructor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Defensive Tactics Provisional Instructor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Defensive Tactics Instructor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Electronic Control Device Instructor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Firearms Provisional Instructor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Line Instructor; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Firearms Instructor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Certification Required.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Unless exempt under <cite path="|12|10|06|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>, an individual who provides instruction for a Commission-approved training course that is credited toward the Commission’s requirements for mandated employee certification under <cite path="|12.10">COMAR 12.10</cite> shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Certified by the Commission or the Police Training Commission as an instructor for the type of instruction the individual is providing; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>In compliance with applicable Commission regulations.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An individual’s instructor certification for a specific instructor classification limits the individual to providing the type of instruction prescribed for the instructor classification established under <cite path="|12|10|06|.15">Regulation .15 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Selection Standards and Application.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Selection Standards for Instructor Certification. If an application is submitted to the Commission requesting certification of an individual for an instructor classification, at a minimum, the individual shall meet the following standards:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Possess a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>High school diploma issued by a high school or recognized by the State Board of Education; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>General Education Development (GED) certificate or diploma issued by Maryland or other state, or recognized by the State Board of Education.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Be currently employed by or providing instruction under the supervision of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A correctional unit;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An academy certified under <cite path="12.10.01.14">COMAR 12.10.01.14</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Department of Juvenile Services;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Satisfies requirements of this chapter for the instructor classification for which instructor certification is requested; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Be in compliance with applicable Commission regulations.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Application for Instructor Certification.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An individual applying for instructor certification shall complete and sign a Commission instructor certification application for the requested instructor classification and submit the completed application to the training authority for the correctional unit, academy certified under <cite path="12.10.01.14">COMAR 12.10.01.14</cite>, or Department of Juvenile Services that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Employs the individual; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Supervises where the individual provides instruction.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A training authority may not approve or sign the training authority’s own instructor certification application.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If a training authority approves an individual making application for instructor certification and determines that the individual requesting certification meets requirements under this chapter for instructor certification for the instructor classification requested, the training authority shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Sign the application and submit the application to the Commission; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Provide, with the application, documentation required by the Commission establishing that the individual requesting certification meets requirements under this chapter for the instructor classification for which certification is requested.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Instructor Previously Certified by the Police Training Commission. If an application for instructor certification is submitted to the Commission by a training authority for an individual who was previously certified as an instructor by the Police Training Commission no more than three years before the date of the application, the Commission may certify the individual as an instructor for the instructor classification formerly certified by the Police Training Commission, if the individual meets:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The selection standards under this regulation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The applicable instructor renewal requirements under <cite path="|12|10|06|.13">Regulation .13 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Additional criteria that the Commission may require.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="12|10|06|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Exemptions from Instructor Certification.</heading>
    <text>Instructor Certification Exemptions.</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An individual who provides 3 hours or less of instruction for a Commission-approved training course is exempt from the requirement to have instructor certification required under this chapter if the individual does not provide instruction that is a part of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Defensive tactics training;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Electronic control device training; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Firearms training.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Deputy Director, upon a written request from a training authority or training provider, may exempt the following from the instructor certification requirements under this chapter:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An individual currently licensed or certified by the State or a nationally recognized organization, for the purpose of providing instruction in the subject matter related to the discipline in which the individual is licensed or certified;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A faculty member employed by an accredited college or university, for the purpose of providing instruction in the subject matter area for which the faculty member is employed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A currently certified emergency medical care or advanced first aid instructor, for the purpose of providing instruction related to emergency medical care or first aid; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Other individual who the Deputy Director determines to possess specialized skills or expertise for the purpose of providing instruction related to those skills or expertise.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A training authority may not submit the training authority’s own request for an exemption from instructor certification required under this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An exemption granted to an individual:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Permits the individual receiving the exemption to provide instruction for Commission-approved training for the purpose under <cite path="12|10|06|.04|A.|(2)">§A(2) of this regulation</cite> for which the exemption was granted;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Expires upon termination of the certification, license, or employment that is the basis for the exemption; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>May be permanently revoked or temporarily suspended by the Deputy Director, as provided under <cite path="|12|10|06|.16">Regulation .16 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Time Limits — Extension for Inactive Status.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The following time limits may be extended by the amount of time that equals the length of time an individual is on inactive status:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The time for completion of an applicant’s evaluations prior to submitting an application for certification or renewal of certification;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The time for completion of an applicant’s training program, instructor’s course or instruction prior to submitting an application for provisional certification, certification, or renewal of certification;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The time of an individual’s term of certification; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The time for completing a required firearms qualification course of fire.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Reporting Inactive Status to the Commission.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At the request of an instructor, the training authority shall report the individual’s inactive status to the Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A training authority shall include in the report the date the individual is placed on inactive status and the date the inactive status ends.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Instructor Evaluation Procedures.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An evaluation of an individual required by this chapter for an instructor classification shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Conducted on a separate occasion from other evaluations of the individual who is being evaluated;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Conducted by an individual who meets the requirements of this chapter or <cite path="|12.04.06">COMAR 12.04.06</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Conducted while the individual being evaluated provides instruction for a course that is approved by the Commission or the Police Training Commission;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Based on the personal observations, for a minimum of one hour, of the individual conducting the evaluation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Recorded, by the individual conducting the evaluation, on a form approved by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An individual may not conduct the individual’s own instructor classification evaluation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Commission may consider an unsatisfactory evaluation or commentary by an evaluator as grounds to deny instructor certification.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="12|10|06|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Academic Instructor — Training Program, Evaluation Requirements and Waiver of Training Program.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A correctional unit, academy certified under <cite path="12.10.01.14">COMAR 12.10.01.14</cite>, the Department of Juvenile Services, or training provider may conduct an Academic Instructor training program if the program is approved by the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Not later than 20 working days before the proposed date for the start of an Academic Instructor training program, the correctional unit head, academy training director, Department of Juvenile Services official, or the training provider’s official supervising the Academic Instructor training program shall submit to the Commission the proposed Academic Instructor training program for approval.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The following are minimum Academic Instructor training program requirements:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An individual providing the Academic Instructor training shall be an Academic Instructor certified under this chapter or <cite path="|12.04.06">COMAR 12.04.06</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Academic Instructor training program shall include instruction on the following topics:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An introduction to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The basic concepts of learning and teaching;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The role of training in the criminal justice profession; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Classroom management techniques;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Effective speech techniques;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Preparation and use of audiovisual training aids;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Development of training objectives;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Development of testing strategies;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Identification of the purpose of a lesson plan and its components; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Practical preparation of mock classroom lesson plans.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An evaluation required for an Academic Instructor training program shall be conducted by an:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Academic Instructor, if the individual’s application is for Academic Instructor certification; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Instructor who meets the requirements of this chapter to perform evaluations for the instructor classification for which the individual is applying for certification.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Waiver for an Individual to Complete the Academic Instructor Training Program Requirement.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Upon receiving a written application from a training authority, the Deputy Director may waive the requirement for an individual to complete the Academic Instructor training program if the individual:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is certified or licensed as an instructor by an agency of government or a non-governmental organization to provide instruction;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is currently a Provisional Instructor for one of the instructor classifications under <cite path="|12|10|06|.02">Regulation .02 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Has received at least two acceptable Academic Instructor evaluations conducted in accordance with <cite path="|12|10|06|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite> and <cite path="12|10|06|.07|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A training authority may not submit the training authority’s own application for a waiver of the Academic Instructor training program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A training authority requesting a waiver of the Academic Instructor training program for an individual shall submit to the Deputy Director:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A completed Commission’s Application for Instructor Certification;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A written request that the requirement to complete the Academic Instructor training program be waived for the individual;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Academic Instructor training program evaluations for the individual completed in accordance with <cite path="|12|10|06|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite> and <cite path="12|10|06|.07|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Other information the Deputy Director may request.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Certification — Academic Provisional Instructor and Academic Instructor.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Academic Provisional Instructor. A training authority may submit an application to the Commission for certification of an individual as an Academic Provisional Instructor when the individual:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Has 1 year of employment experience in the public safety community; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Meets the selection standards under <cite path="|12|10|06|.03|A.">Regulation .03A of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Academic Instructor. A training authority may submit an application to the Commission for certification of an individual as an Academic Instructor when the individual has:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A minimum of 2 years employment experience in the public safety community;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Successfully completed, within 2 years before the date of the application, an approved Academic Instructor training program meeting the requirements of <cite path="|12|10|06|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Received a minimum of two favorable instructor evaluations:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Completed by an individual specified by <cite path="|12|10|06|.07|D.">Regulation .07D of this chapter</cite> within 2 years of the date of the application for certification:</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Conducted in accordance with <cite path="|12|10|06|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Conducted while the individual was providing instruction as an Academic Provisional Instructor.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="12|10|06|.09">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Certification and Training Program — Defensive Tactics Provisional Instructor and Defensive Tactics Instructor.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Defensive Tactics Provisional Instructor Certification. A training authority may submit an application to the Commission for certification of an individual as a Defensive Tactics Provisional Instructor if the individual has:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Acquired a minimum of 2 cumulative years of criminal justice related defensive tactics skills experience during the 5-year period immediately before the date of the application; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Successfully completed a Commission-approved Defensive Tactics Instructor training program not more than 2 years before the date of the application for Defensive Tactics Provisional Instructor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Defensive Tactics Instructor Certification. A training authority may submit an application to the Commission for certification of an individual as a Defensive Tactics Instructor when the individual:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is a Defensive Tactics Provisional Instructor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Has successfully completed the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A Commission-approved Academic Instructor training program that meets the requirements under <cite path="|12|10|06|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Except if granted a waiver under <cite path="12|10|06|.09|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, a Commission-approved Defensive Tactics Instructor training program before the date of the application for Defensive Tactics Instructor certification; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>As a Defensive Tactics Provisional Instructor provided a minimum total of 12 hours of defensive tactics classroom and skills instruction under the direction of a Defensive Tactics Instructor that included a minimum of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Four hours of classroom instruction in the concepts and principles of defensive tactics;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Eight hours of defensive tactics practical skills instruction; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>One satisfactory evaluation for each of the following, in accordance with <cite path="|12|10|06|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>, performed by a Defensive Tactics Instructor certified under this chapter or <cite path="|12.04.06">COMAR 12.04.06</cite>, while the individual was providing defensive tactics:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Classroom instruction; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Skills instruction.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Upon application by a training authority, the Deputy Director may waive the requirement under §§A(2) and B(2)(b) of this regulation that an individual complete the Defensive Tactics Instructor training program of this regulation if the individual:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Successfully completed a program that was a minimum of 35 hours in length and the equivalent of a Defensive Tactics Instructor training program that meets the requirements of <cite path="12|10|06|.09|F.|(1)|(c)">§F(1)(c) of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provides supporting evidence, such as copies of certifications or course curriculums, to document the applicant’s extensive knowledge and abilities in the skill areas specified in <cite path="12|10|06|.09|F.|(1)|(c)">§F(1)(c) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A training authority may not submit the training authority’s own application for a waiver of the requirement to complete the Defensive Tactics Instructor training program required under <cite path="12|10|06|.09|A.|(2)">§A(2) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Deputy Director may limit the subject matter taught in a Defensive Tactics Training program by an individual who receives certification as a Defensive Tactics Instructor based on a waiver under <cite path="12|10|06|.09|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> of the Defensive Tactics Instructor training program requirement under this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Defensive Tactics Instructor Training Program.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A Defensive Tactics Instructor training program, at a minimum, shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be approved by the Commission;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Be a minimum of 35 hours in length; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Include the following topics:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Balance, awareness, and self-control;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Impact weapons;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Weapon retention;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Disarming;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Vital points of the human anatomy;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Control holds;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Take-downs;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Handcuffing and searching;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ix)</num>
            <text>Escorting and Transporting an inmate or detainee;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(x)</num>
            <text>Use of force continuum;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xi)</num>
            <text>Multiple adversaries; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xii)</num>
            <text>Ground-level defenses.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Successful completion of a Defensive Tactics Instructor training program, at a minimum, requires:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A minimum score of 80 percent on all written examinations; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Satisfactory demonstration of practical skill elements required in the program.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Commission may approve a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Defensive Tactics Instructor training program that meets the requirements under this regulation; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A combination of defensive tactics training program courses that:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>As determined by the Deputy Director, satisfactorily address the topics required under <cite path="12|10|06|.09|F.|(1)|(c)">§F(1)(c) of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Is a minimum of 35 hours in length.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Certification — Electronic Control Device Instructor.</heading>
    <text>A training authority may submit an application to the Commission for certification of an individual as an Electronic Control Device Instructor if the individual seeking certification:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Is a correctional officer who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is authorized by the correctional officer’s employing agency to carry or use the specific manufacturer’s model of an electronic control device for which the individual, if granted certification, would provide instruction; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Has successfully completed a Commission-approved Academic Instructor training program that meets requirements under <cite path="|12|10|06|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Is not a correctional officer, but has:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Successfully completed a Commission-approved training course for the specific manufacturer’s model of an electronic control device for which the individual, if authorized, would provide instruction; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Been determined by the Deputy Director to be qualified to provide electronic control device instruction based on the individual’s knowledge, skills, and abilities with the specific manufacturer’s model of electronic control device for which the individual, if authorized, would provide instruction.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="12|10|06|.11">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Certification — Firearms Provisional Instructor, Line Instructor, and Firearms Instructor.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Certification Requirements — General. A training authority may submit an application to the Commission for certification of an individual as a Firearms Provisional Instructor, Line Instructor, or Firearms Instructor when the individual meets the certification requirements established under this regulation for the particular instructor classification and has:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Two or more years employment as a correctional officer or law enforcement officer within the last 5 years, during which employment the individual was authorized to use or carry a firearm for a minimum of 2 years; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Within 60 days immediately before the date of the application for instructor certification, successfully completed the qualification course of fire required by <cite path="12|10|06|.11|D.|(5)">§D(5) of this regulation</cite> for the firearm type for which the individual is requesting instructor certification.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Certification Requirements for Firearms Provisional Instructor, Line Instructor, and Firearms Instructor.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Firearms Provisional Instructor Certification Requirements. Before an individual may be certified as a Firearms Provisional Instructor, the Commission requires, at a minimum, that the individual:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Meets requirements established under <cite path="12|10|06|.11|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Within 2 years of the date of the application for Firearms Provisional Instructor, successfully completed classroom instruction, training, and the qualification course of fire required under §§D(2) and (3) of this regulation that was provided by:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The Commission;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A Commission-approved program;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The United States Government or Armed Forces;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>National Rifle Association; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>A firearms instructor school approved by the Deputy Director.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Line Instructor Certification Requirements. Before an individual may be certified as a Line Instructor, the Commission requires, at a minimum, that the individual:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Meets requirements established under <cite path="12|10|06|.11|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Successfully completed the requirements for Firearms Provisional Instructor certification established under <cite path="12|10|06|.11|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Received at least two satisfactory evaluations performed by a Firearms Instructor for the individual while providing firearms firing line training and qualification; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Provided firearms firing line training and qualification instruction that is:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A minimum of 8 hours;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Provided for Commission-approved courses;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Supervised by a Line Instructor or Firearms Instructor; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Provided for the firearm type for which the individual is requesting Line Instructor certification.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Firearms Instructor Certification Requirements. Before an individual may be certified as a Firearms Instructor, the Commission requires, at a minimum, that the individual:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Meets requirements established under <cite path="12|10|06|.11|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Successfully completed a Commission-approved Academic Instructor training program;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Received at least two satisfactory evaluations performed by a Firearms Instructor for the individual providing firearms classroom instruction during the Academic Instructor training program;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Successfully provided at least 4 hours of firearms classroom instruction;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Received at least two satisfactory evaluations performed by a Firearms Instructor for the individual while providing firearms firing line training and qualification; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Is currently a Commission-certified Line Instructor, or a Commission-certified Firearms Provisional Instructor who has successfully provided firearms firing line training and qualification instruction that has been:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A minimum of 8 hours;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Provided for a Commission-approved course;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Supervised by a Line Instructor or Firearms Instructor; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Provided for the firearm type for which the individual is requesting Firearms Instructor certification.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Experience Accepted by the Commission for Training Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Commission may accept documented firearms-related experience toward meeting the minimum training requirements for Firearms Provisional Instructor, Line Instructor, or Firearms Instructor certification.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Examples of documented firearms-related experience that the Commission may accept include military training or counter sniper training.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Classroom Instruction, Firearms Training, and Firearms Qualification Course of Fire Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Firearms classroom instruction and firearms training and qualification course of fire required by this regulation shall be approved by the Commission before being conducted.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The following establishes minimum requirements for classroom instruction and firearms training and qualification course of fire for the certification of instructor classifications under this regulation:</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th>Requirement</th>
                <th>Handgun</th>
                <th>Type 1 Long Gun</th>
                <th>Type 2 <br/>Long Gun</th>
                <th>Type 3 <br/>Long Gun</th>
                <th>Type 4 <br/>Long Gun</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="2">(a) Total minimum hours for classroom instruction, training and course of fire for qualification</td>
                <td rowspan="2" data-text-align="center">35 hours</td>
                <td rowspan="2" data-text-align="center">35 hours</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">35 hours</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">14 hours</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">7 hours</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="2">56 hours when also seeking certification for one handgun type and also a Type 4 long gun;<br/>65 hours when also seeking certification for two handgun types and also one long type, of a Type 2, 3, or 4 long gun</td>
                <td>35 hours when also seeking certification for one handgun type;<br/>49 hours when also seeking certification for two handgun types</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(b) Training and qualification courses of fire total minimum rounds to be discharged</td>
                <td>350 rounds for one handgun type; 250 rounds each for two handgun types</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">150 rounds</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">350 rounds</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">350 rounds</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">50 rounds</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(c) Qualification course of fire minimum rounds to be discharged</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">30 rounds</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">20 rounds</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">30 rounds</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">30 rounds</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">10 rounds</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(d) Minimum passing score Commission-approved instructor qualification course of fire</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">90 percent</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">100 percent</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">90 percent</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">90 percent</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">90 percent</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(e) Minimum passing score each written test</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">80 percent</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">80 percent</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">80 percent</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">80 percent</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">80 percent</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Firearms Provisional Instructor classroom instruction shall meet the requirements established under <cite path="12|10|06|.11|D.|(2)">§D(2) of this regulation</cite>, and at a minimum include instruction on:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Firearms safety;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Firearms nomenclature;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Firearms fundamentals and marksmanship;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Firearms cleaning and maintenance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The problem shooter;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Target analysis;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Ballistics;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Legal issues concerning the use of force;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Deadly force policy;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Judgmental or decision training;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Reduced light discipline;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>Emotional, mental, and psychological issues related to critical incidents;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>Commission policy and procedures;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(n)</num>
          <text>Malfunctions; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(o)</num>
          <text>Exposure to or practical application of, or both:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Designing a course of fire;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Lesson plan development; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Classroom presentations.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Firearms training shall meet the requirements established under <cite path="12|10|06|.11|D.|(2)">§D(2) of this regulation</cite>, and at a minimum, include exposure to and practical application of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Firing line operations, that include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Instruction on the firing line; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Instruction from a location overseeing the firing line;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Malfunction drills;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Stress training;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Judgmental or decision training;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Range preparation and cleanup;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Scoring;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Target analysis;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Safety; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Marksmanship fundamentals.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>An individual seeking instructor certification under this regulation shall successfully complete one firearms qualification course of fire that meets the requirements established under <cite path="12|10|06|.11|D.|(2)">§D(2) of this regulation</cite> for each firearm type for which the individual is seeking instructor certification.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>An individual seeking instructor certification under this regulation shall successfully meet:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>For a handgun, requirements 3 — 9 of the “Handgun Day-Fire Required Course of Fire for Qualification” in the table under <cite path="12.10.04.05">COMAR 12.10.04.05</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For a particular type long gun, requirements 3 — 7 of the table under <cite path="12.10.04.07">COMAR 12.10.04.07</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Expiration of Instructor Certification.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An individual’s instructor certification expires:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At the conclusion of the individual’s term of certification established under <cite path="|12|10|06|.15|B.">Regulation .15B of this chapter</cite> for the individual’s instructor classification;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When the individual leaves employment with the correctional unit, academy certified under <cite path="12.10.01.14">COMAR 12.10.01.14</cite>, or the Department of Juvenile Services on behalf of which the training authority submitted the application for the individual’s instructor certification; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the training authority for the correctional unit, academy certified under <cite path="12.10.01.14">COMAR 12.10.01.14</cite>, or the Department of Juvenile Services that submitted the application for the individual’s instructor certification requests that the individual’s instructor certification be terminated.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An individual’s term of certification may not expire while the individual is on inactive status.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Renewal of Instructor Certification.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Renewal of provisional instructor certification for an instructor classification may be granted by the Deputy Director as provided under <cite path="|12|10|06|.15">Regulation .15 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Except for provisional instructor, renewal of instructor certification for an instructor classification may be granted by the Commission as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If an individual’s instructor certification has been expired for more than 3 years, the individual:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Shall successfully complete the instructor certification requirements of this chapter for the instructor classification applied for in order to receive certification for that instructor classification; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Upon approval by the Commission, may receive certification renewal for the expired instructor classification if the individual successfully completes a program of selected aspects of the instructor classification’s certification requirements designated by the Commission.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If an individual’s instructor certification expires because the individual leaves employment or ceases to provide instruction under the supervision of a correctional unit, academy certified under <cite path="12.10.01.14">COMAR 12.10.01.14</cite>, or the Department of Juvenile Services that submitted the application for the individual’s instructor certification and subsequently is employed by or provides instruction under the supervision of another correctional unit, academy certified under <cite path="12.10.01.14">COMAR 12.10.01.14</cite>, or the Department of Juvenile Services whose training authority submits an application for renewal of the individual’s instructor certification:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>More than 90 days before the date that the individual’s term of certification expires, the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Individual is not required to meet the requirements of <cite path="|12|10|06|.14">Regulation .14 of this chapter</cite> to receive the certification; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Commission shall establish a new term of certification for the individual that does not exceed 12 months from the expiration date of the individual’s most recent term of certification.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>90 days or less before expiration of the term of certification or 3 years or less after the expiration of the term of certification, the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Individual shall meet requirements established under <cite path="|12|10|06|.14">Regulation .14 of this chapter</cite> to receive renewal of certification for the instructor classification; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Certification renewal, if granted, shall be for a new term of certification established under <cite path="|12|10|06|.15|B.">Regulation .15B of this chapter</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If an instructor certification is due to expire or has expired at the conclusion of the term of certification, the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Training authority shall submit an application for renewal of the instructor certification to the Commission not sooner than 90 days before the term of certification expires and, if certification has expired, not later than 3 years after the term of certification expired;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Individual is required to meet the instructor certification requirements under <cite path="|12|10|06|.14">Regulation .14 of this chapter</cite> to renew instructor certification; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Individual’s instructor certification shall be renewed for a new term of certification established under <cite path="|12|10|06|.15|B.">Regulation .15B of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Instructor Certification Renewal Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Commission may renew an individual’s certification for an instructor classification if the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Individual meets requirements under this chapter for instructor certification renewal and other applicable Commission regulations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Individual completes the Commission’s renewal application and submits the completed application to the training authority for the individual’s employer; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Training authority for the individual’s employer has reviewed and approved the renewal application and submits the approved application to the Commission within the time established under this regulation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A training authority may not review, approve, or submit to the Commission the training authority’s own application for instructor certification renewal.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="12|10|06|.14">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Instructor Certification Renewal Requirements for Instructor Classifications.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If a provisional instructor certification for an instructor classification expires, the individual is not required to meet the requirements of this section to renew the same provisional instructor certification classification.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The training authority for a correctional unit, academy certified under <cite path="12.10.01.14">COMAR 12.10.01.14</cite>, or the Department of Juvenile Services submitting an application for instructor certification or renewal of instructor certification that the Commission last approved during the individual’s most recent term of instructor certification shall affirm that the individual meets the certification requirements specified for the instructor classification under <cite path="12|10|06|.14|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Renewal for each instructor classification requires that the individual for which a training authority has submitted an application for instructor certification renewal is recommended for instructor certification renewal by the individual’s correctional unit, academy certified under <cite path="12.10.01.14">COMAR 12.10.01.14</cite>, or the Department of Juvenile Services.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The following table provides the minimum requirements for an individual’s certification renewal of the instructor classifications indicated:</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Instructor Classification</th>
              <th>Minimum Requirements for Certification Renewal</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>(1)  Academic Instructor</td>
              <td>During the most recent term of certification the individual is required  to: <br/>   (a) Have provided classroom instruction for a training course approved by the Commission or Police Training Commission; and <br/>   (b) Demonstrate competence in providing classroom instruction while conducting classroom instruction for a training course approved by the Commission or Police Training Commission.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Defensive Tactics Instructor</td>
              <td>During the most recent term of certification the individual is required: <br/>   (a) To demonstrate competence in providing classroom and skills instruction which a Defensive Tactics Instructor is authorized to provide under this chapter; and <br/>   (b) While conducting instruction for a training course approved by the Commission or the Police Training Commission, to have received a minimum of: <br/>      (i) One satisfactory evaluation for defensive tactics classroom instruction; and <br/>      (ii) One satisfactory evaluation for defensive tactics practical skills instruction.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(3)  Electronic Control Device Instructor</td>
              <td>During the most recent term of certification the individual is required: <br/>   (a) To demonstrate competence in providing classroom and skills instruction which an Electronic Control Device Instructor is authorized to provide under this chapter; and <br/>   (b) While conducting instruction for a training course approved by the Commission or the Police Training Commission, to have received a minimum of: <br/>      (i) One satisfactory evaluation for electronic control device classroom instruction; and <br/>      (ii) One satisfactory evaluation for electronic control device practical skills instruction.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(4)  Line Instructor</td>
              <td>The individual is required: <br/>   (a) Within 60 days immediately preceding submission of the application for renewal to the Commission, to have successfully completed the firearms qualification course of fire requirements under <cite path="|12|10|06|.11">Regulation .11 of this chapter</cite> for the firearm type for which the individual is seeking certification renewal; and <br/>   (b) During the most recent term of instructor certification to have: <br/>      (i) Demonstrated competence in providing skills instruction which a Line Instructor is authorized to provide  under this chapter; and <br/>      (ii) Received a minimum of one satisfactory evaluation while providing firearms firing line operations and skills instruction for a training course approved by the Commission or the Police Training Commission.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(5) Firearms Instructor</td>
              <td>The individual is required: <br/>   (a)  Within 60 days immediately preceding submission of the application for renewal to the Commission, to have successfully completed the firearms qualification course of fire requirements under <cite path="|12|10|06|.11">Regulation .11 of this chapter</cite> for the firearm type for which the individual is seeking certification renewal; and <br/>   (b) During the most recent term of instructor certification to have: <br/>      (i) Demonstrated competence in providing classroom and  skills instruction which a Firearms Instructor is authorized to provide under this chapter; and <br/>      (ii) While conducting a training course approved by the Commission or the Police Training Commission, received a minimum of one satisfactory evaluation for firearms classroom instruction, and one satisfactory evaluation for firearms firing line operations and skills instruction.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Term of Instructor Certification and Limitations on Instruction.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An individual may not conduct any part of the individual’s own training or instruction required by the Commission to meet instructor certification requirements under this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The following table establishes for each instructor classification:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Limitations on instruction that may be provided; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Term of instructor certification.</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th>Instructor Classification</th>
                <th>Term of Certification</th>
                <th>Limitations on Instruction that may be provided</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td>(1) Academic Provisional Instructor</td>
                <td>One year, and may be renewed with the approval of the Deputy Director.</td>
                <td>The individual may provide instruction only while in the presence of a supervising Academic Instructor.  In addition, the individual may not instruct any aspect of: <br/>   (a) Defensive Tactics Training; <br/>   (b) Electronic Control Device Training; or <br/>   (c) Firearms classroom instruction, training or qualification course of fire.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(2) Academic Instructor</td>
                <td>Up to 4 years, and may be renewed.</td>
                <td>May not instruct any aspect of: <br/>   (a) Defensive Tactics Training; <br/>   (b) Electronic Control Device Training; or <br/>   (c) Firearms classroom instruction, training or qualification course of fire.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(3) Defensive Tactics Provisional Instructor</td>
                <td>One year, and may be renewed with the approval of the Deputy Director.</td>
                <td>Instructional authority is limited to providing the following, while in the presence of a supervising Defensive Tactics Instructor: <br/>   (a) Classroom instruction on defensive tactics; <br/>   (b) Assist with practical defensive tactics skills training; and <br/>   (c) Assist in skill assessment.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(4) Defensive Tactics Instructor</td>
                <td>Up to 4 years, and may be renewed.</td>
                <td>Instructional authority is limited to providing instruction in defensive tactics classroom and skills training.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(5) Electronic Control Device Instructor</td>
                <td>Up to 4 years, and may be renewed.</td>
                <td>Instructional authority is limited to providing electronic control device instruction for the specific manufacturer’s model of an electronic control device for which the individual has been granted Electronic Control Device Instructor certification.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(6) Firearms Provisional Instructor</td>
                <td>One year, and may be renewed with the approval of the Deputy Director.</td>
                <td>(a) Instructional authority is limited to providing, for the firearm type with which the individual is qualified under <cite path="|12|10|06|.11">Regulation .11 of this chapter</cite>, while in the presence of a supervising Firearms Instructor: <br/>      (i) Firearms classroom instruction; <br/>      (ii) Firearms training; and <br/>      (iii)Qualification course of fire. <br/>(b) May not conduct the individual’s own firearms training or qualification.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(7) Line Instructor</td>
                <td>Up to 4 years, and may be renewed.</td>
                <td>(a) Instructional authority is limited to providing, for the firearm type with which the individual is qualified under <cite path="|12|10|06|.11">Regulation .11 of this chapter</cite>, firearms training and qualification course of fire. In addition, the individual may provide, for the firearm type with which the individual is qualified under <cite path="|12|10|06|.11">Regulation .11 of this chapter</cite>, firearms classroom instruction while in the presence of a supervising Firearms Instructor. <br/>(b) May not conduct the individual’s own firearms qualification course of fire.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(8) Firearms Instructor</td>
                <td>Up to 4 years, and may be renewed.</td>
                <td>(a) Instructional authority is limited to providing firearms classroom instruction, firearms training and qualification course of fire for the firearm type with which the individual is qualified under <cite path="|12|10|06|.11">Regulation .11 of this chapter</cite>. <br/>(b) May not conduct the individual’s own qualification course of fire.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="12|10|06|.16">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Suspension and Revocation of Instructor Certification and Exemptions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Deputy Director, in accordance with this regulation may temporarily suspend or permanently revoke an individual’s instructor certification if the individual:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Does not comply with Commission regulations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Falsifies or fails to maintain reports, forms, rosters, and other records required by the Commission;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Facilitates or condones cheating on an examination, skills exercise, or other aspect of a training provider’s course for which instruction is provided;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Compromises the integrity of a training provider’s training program or course;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Misuses the authority granted by the instructor certification;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Fails to provide required instruction or provides instruction that is erroneous or inadequate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Fails to cooperate with Commission audits or inquiries;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Provides false or misleading information to the Commission; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Violates or fails to meet Commission requirements.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the Commission has knowledge that an instructor has allegedly engaged in conduct specified under <cite path="12|10|06|.16|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, the Deputy Director shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provide written notice of the allegations to the instructor’s supervising authority at the correctional unit, Department of Juvenile Services, law enforcement agency, training provider, or academy certified under <cite path="12.10.01.14">COMAR 12.10.01.14</cite> or <cite path="12.04.01.10">COMAR 12.04.01.10</cite> that employs or supervises the instructor who is the subject of the allegation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Ensure the allegation is thoroughly investigated; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Conduct a hearing to allow the allegation to be presented and the instructor to respond to the allegation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>After reviewing the information resulting from the investigation and conducting a hearing under <cite path="12|10|06|.16|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, the Deputy Director shall decide if the allegation is supported by fact.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the Deputy Director decides the allegation is supported by fact, the Deputy Director may order that the instructor’s certification be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Permanently revoked; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Temporarily suspended.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Deputy Director shall submit a written report of findings to support a decision under <cite path="12|10|06|.16|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> and any order under <cite path="12|10|06|.16|D.">§D of this regulation</cite> to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The instructor’s supervising authority at the correctional unit, Department of Juvenile Services, law enforcement agency, training provider, or academy certified under <cite path="12.10.01.14">COMAR 12.10.01.14</cite> or <cite path="12.04.01.10">COMAR 12.04.01.10</cite> that employs or supervises the instructor who is the subject of the allegation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Correctional Training Commission or Police Training Commission that granted the instructor’s certification.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The instructor who is the subject of the allegation may appeal the Deputy Director’s decision under <cite path="12|10|06|.16|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> and any order under <cite path="12|10|06|.16|D.">§D of this regulation</cite> to the Executive Director.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Revoking or Suspending an Instructor Certification Exemption.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Deputy Director may permanently revoke or temporarily suspend an exemption from instructor certification granted under <cite path="|12|10|06|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite> if the individual to whom the exemption was granted engages in conduct specified by <cite path="12|10|06|.16|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If Deputy Director considers revoking or temporarily suspending an exemption as provided by <cite path="12|10|06|.16|G.|(1)">§G(1) of this regulation</cite>, the Deputy Director shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Comply with the requirements of <cite path="12|10|06|.16|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, and may order that the exemption be revoked or temporarily suspended as provided by <cite path="12|10|06|.16|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Provide a written report on the findings and order under <cite path="12|10|06|.16|G.|(2)|(a)">§G(2)(a) of this regulation</cite> to the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Individual to whom the exemption was granted; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Training authority or training provider that requested the exemption.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An exemption from instructor certification granted under <cite path="|12|10|06|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite> may be revoked or temporarily suspended by the Deputy Director if the Deputy Director determines the individual no longer possesses the specialized skills or expertise to warrant the exemption.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Correctional Services Article, Title 8, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-01-01">Effective date: January 1, 2013 (39:16 Md. R. 1081)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-05-26"><cite path="|12|10|06|.06|A.">Regulation .06A</cite> amended effective May 26, 2014 (41:10 Md. R. 561)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
