<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Administration of Services for Students with Disabilities</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>The purpose of this chapter is to implement administrative procedures related to Part B of the Individuals with Disabilities Education Act (IDEA), 34 CFR 300, and Education Article, Title 8, Subtitles 3 and 4, Annotated Code of Maryland, which assure a free appropriate public education (FAPE) for students with disabilities, birth through the end of the school year in which the student turns 21 years old, in accordance with the student's individualized education program (IEP).</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter applies to public agencies that provide educational services to students with disabilities, 3 years old through the end of the school year in which the student turns 21 years old, in accordance with the student's Individualized Education Program (IEP), including the Department, local school systems, the SEED School, Maryland Department of Health, Department of Juvenile Services, the Maryland School for the Blind, the Maryland School for the Deaf, and the Maryland Department of Labor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Early intervention services to eligible infants and toddlers, birth through 2 years old, and their families are provided in accordance with Part C of IDEA, 34 CFR 303, and COMAR 13A.13.01.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the definitions in COMAR 13A.05.01 apply, and the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Local care team (LCT)” means the interagency committee established in each jurisdiction in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ghu|8-405">Human Services Article §8-405, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Identify interagency resources to assist students with special needs;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Facilitate the provision of interagency services to students with disabilities; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Review requests for State funding of residential placements of students with disabilities in accordance with <cite path="|14.31.01">COMAR 14.31.01</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Local management board" means the entity established or designated in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ghu|8-301">Human Services Article, §8-301, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, to ensure the implementation of a local interagency service delivery system for children, youth, and families in each local jurisdiction.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Service provider" means an individual who provides special education or related services to students with disabilities, including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A general educator;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A special educator;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A related service provider; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Another individual, determined appropriate.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"State Coordinating Council (SCC)" means the interagency committee established in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ghu|8-401">Human Services Article, §8-401, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Technology-based instructional products" means instructional software, on-line resources, and computer-based equipment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|05|02|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>State Administration.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Assurance.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Department shall ensure that all students, birth through the end of the school year in which the student turns 21 years old residing in the State, who have disabilities, regardless of the severity of the disability, and who are in need of special education and related services, are located, identified, evaluated, and provided with services consistent with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The student's IEP;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>20 U.S.C. §§1400—1419;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>34 CFR 300;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-401">8-401</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-415">8-415</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>COMAR 13A.05.01.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Students under <cite path="13A|05|02|.04|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite> include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Students with disabilities attending private schools;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Highly mobile students;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Migrant students;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Homeless students, as defined in COMAR 13A.05.09;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Wards of the State, as defined in COMAR 13A.05.01; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Students who are suspected of being a student with a disability under 34 CFR §300.8 and in need of special education, even though they are advancing from grade to grade in accordance with 34 CFR §300.101.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Oversight Responsibility. The Department shall have in effect policies and procedures to ensure that a FAPE is available to all students with disabilities residing in the State in accordance with <cite path="13A|05|02|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>State Implementation. To receive funds under Part B of the Act, the Department shall submit information that includes the requirements of 20 U.S.C. §1411 to the United States Department of Education at the time and in the manner specified by the Secretary of the U. S. Department of Education.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>State Performance Plan.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Department shall have a performance plan that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Evaluates the State's efforts to implement the requirements and purposes of the Act in accordance with 20 U.S.C. §1416(b) and 34 CFR §300.601; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Describes how the Department shall improve implementation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Department shall establish measurable rigorous targets for the indicators established in accordance with 20 U.S.C. §1416(a)(3).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Department shall collect information to report annually to the Secretary of the U. S. Department of Education in accordance with 20 U.S.C. §1416(b)(2)(B), 34 CFR §300.602, and <cite path="|13A|05|02|.11">Regulation .11 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Department shall use the targets described in <cite path="13A|05|02|.04|D.|(2)">§D(2) of this regulation</cite> to analyze and report annually on the performance of each public agency in the State in accordance with 20 U.S.C. §1416(b)(2)(C) and 34 CFR §300.602.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If the Department receives notice that the Secretary of the U.S. Department of Education is proposing to take or is taking an enforcement action pursuant to 34 CFR §300.604, the Department shall notify the public in the manner described in 34 CFR §300.606.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Access to Instructional Materials. The Department shall adopt the National Instructional Materials Standards (NIMAS) and coordinate with the National Instructional Materials Access Center (NIMAC) to provide instructional materials in specialized formats to blind students and students with print disabilities in accordance with 34 CFR §300.172 and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-408">Education Article, §8-408, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Significant Disproportionality.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Department shall collect and examine data to determine if significant disproportionality based on race and ethnicity is occurring in each public agency in the State in accordance with 34 CFR §300.646.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In making determinations of significant disproportionality, the Department shall use:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A risk ratio threshold of 2.0;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A minimum cell size of 5; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A minimum n-size of 20.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Department shall determine that significant disproportionality is occurring in a public agency that has:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Exceeded the risk ratio threshold for 2 consecutive years; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Failed to demonstrate reasonable progress under <cite path="13A|05|02|.04|F.|(4)">§F(4) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Demonstrating reasonable progress means that a public agency has:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Decreased its risk ratio by 0.15 and the current risk ratio is 2.0 to 4.0; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Decreased its risk ratio by 0.50 and the current risk ratio is above 4.0.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>State Advisory Committee.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The State Superintendent of Schools shall appoint a State Advisory Committee for Special Education.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Membership shall represent the population and geographic diversity of the State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The term of appointment for each member shall be 3 years. Members may be reappointed for one term.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The State Advisory Committee shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Parents of students, ages birth through 26 years old, with disabilities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Individuals with disabilities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Special education and general education teachers;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Representatives from institutions of higher education that prepare special education and related services personnel;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>State and local school system officials, including general education administrators and officials responsible for the implementation of COMAR 13A.05.09;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Administrators of programs for students with disabilities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Representatives from other State agencies involved in financing or delivering related services to students with disabilities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Representatives from nonpublic schools and public charter schools;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Not less than one representative of a vocational, community, or business organization concerned with the provision of transition services to students with disabilities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Representatives from the State juvenile and adult corrections agencies;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>A representative of the Maryland Department of Human Services (DHS); and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>A representative of the State Parent Training and Information Center.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A majority of the members shall be individuals with disabilities or parents of students, ages birth through 26 years old, with disabilities.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The State Advisory Committee shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Advise the Department of unmet needs within the State in the education of students with disabilities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Comment publicly on any regulations proposed by the Department regarding the education of students with disabilities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Advise the Department in developing evaluations and reporting data to the Secretary of the U. S. Department of Education under 20 U.S.C. §1418;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Advise the Department in developing corrective action plans to address findings identified in federal monitoring reports under Part B of the Act; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Advise the Department in developing and implementing policies relating to the coordination of services for students with disabilities.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Meetings.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The State Advisory Committee shall meet at least four times per year, or as often as necessary, to conduct its business.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Official minutes shall be kept on State Advisory Committee meetings and shall be made available to the public on request.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>State Advisory Committee meetings, including agendas, shall be publicly announced before the meetings and the meetings shall be open to the public consistent with 20 U.S.C. §1412(a)(21).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Interpreters and other necessary services shall be provided for Advisory Committee members or participants.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>State Advisory Committee members shall serve without compensation, but the State shall reimburse the members for reasonable and necessary expenses for attending meetings and performing duties.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Annual Report.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Not later than July 1 of each year, the State Advisory Committee shall submit an annual report of Committee activities and suggestions to the Department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The report shall be made available to the public in a manner consistent with other public reporting requirements under the Act.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>The State may use Part B funds allocated under 20 U.S.C. §1411 for the services in §F(4) and (5) of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Department Procedural Safeguards.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Department shall establish and maintain procedures to ensure that students with disabilities and their parents are guaranteed procedural safeguards with respect to the provisions of FAPE consistent with 34 CFR §§300.500—300.537 and Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-407">8-407</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-412">8-412</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-413">8-413</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Mediation.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Department shall maintain a list of qualified mediators who are knowledgeable in laws and regulations relating to the provision of special education and related services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Department shall bear the cost of the mediation process.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Impartial Due Process Hearing. The Office of Administrative Hearings shall ensure the appointment of an individual to serve as the impartial hearing officer to conduct a due process hearing in accordance with 20 U.S.C. §1415(f), 34 CFR §300.511, State Government Article, Title 10, Subtitle 2, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-413">Education Article, §8-413, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, COMAR 13A.05.01.15C, and <cite path="|28.02.01">COMAR 28.02.01</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|05|02|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Compliance Review Activities.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Department is responsible for the development and implementation of policies and procedures for compliance review of public agencies to ensure implementation of the requirements of 20 U.S.C. 1400—1419, Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-401">8-401</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-415">8-415</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland, COMAR 13A.05.01, and <cite path="|13A|05|02|.13">Regulation .13 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the Department identifies a violation of federal or State law or regulation by a public agency, the Department shall require the public agency to submit documentation verifying the implementation of a corrective action.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Department shall develop policies and procedures to address the provision of technical assistance, monitoring, and enforcement of corrective actions implemented by a public agency as a result of a violation under <cite path="13A|05|02|.07|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> and consistent with 20 U.S.C. §1416(a)(1)(C) and 34 CFR §300.600.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If a public agency has not implemented the corrective actions in the time and manner specified by the Department, the Department shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Advise the public agency in writing that the corrective actions shall be implemented within a specified time frame to avoid further enforcement action; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Offer additional technical assistance to the public agency to assist in the implementation of the corrective actions.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If, after the implementation of <cite path="13A|05|02|.07|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>, a public agency has not implemented the corrective actions or made good faith efforts to correct substantial violations, the Department may initiate sanctions, including, but not limited to the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Redirect or target the use of funds allocated under IDEA Part B Discretionary funds;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Reduce or eliminate the use of funds allocated under IDEA Part B Discretionary funds;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Redirect or target the use of funds allocated under IDEA Part B Passthrough funds;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Withhold or reduce Part B Passthrough funds pending completion of the corrective actions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Withhold or reduce State funds for special education services pending the completion of corrective actions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Assign Department staff on-site to assist in the completion of the corrective actions; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Assign a monitor to oversee the public agency's special education programs, with the responsibility for the costs of monitoring to be determined by the Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Prior to reducing or withholding funds, all requirements regarding proper notice by the Department to the public agency shall be met, consistent with 20 U.S.C. §1413(c) and (d).</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Funding.</heading>
    <text>The Department may use available State, federal, and private sources of support, including public or private third-party reimbursements which do not result in cost to parents of students with disabilities, to meet the requirements of 20 U.S.C. §§1400—1419.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Interagency Collaboration.</heading>
    <text>The Department shall establish, implement, and maintain interagency planning and program implementation agreements for students with disabilities, consistent with federal and State law.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>State Complaint Procedures.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Department shall develop and implement State complaint investigation procedures consistent with COMAR 13A.05.01.15A.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The complaint investigation procedures and guidelines shall be disseminated on request.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Reports.</heading>
    <text>The Department shall submit reports at the time and in the manner specified by the Secretary of the U.S. Department of Education.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|05|02|.12">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Nonpublic School Approval.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An in-State nonpublic school offering special education and related services may have the program approved if the nonpublic school:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Has a certificate of approval from the Department for the school's special education program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Meets the requirements of COMAR 13A.09.10.18A—C;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Meets the requirements of COMAR 13A.09.10.14A—B;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Employs teachers who meet the highest standard of the Department and the requirements of 34 CFR §300.18; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Has written policies and procedures regarding the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>School's participation in the development, review, or revision of a student's IEP with the local school system that referred the student,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Notification of a local school system when a student's IEP needs to be reviewed or revised,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Notification of a local school system before dismissing a student with a disability, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Maintenance of a student's placement during mediation or due process hearings in accordance with COMAR 13A.05.01.15B and C, unless the local school system and parent agree to an alternative placement.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An out-of-State nonpublic school that offers special education and related services may have its program approved if there is a demonstrated need for the services of the nonpublic school, and the nonpublic school program:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is approved by the state education agency of the state where the school is located;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is determined by the Department to substantially meet the requirements of COMAR 13A.09.10;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Meets the requirements of COMAR 13A.09.10.09B and C, or equivalent standards as established by the state education agency of the state where the nonpublic school is located; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Has written policies and procedures consistent with <cite path="13A|05|02|.12|A.|(4)">§A(4) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|05|02|.13">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Local Public Agency Administration.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Assurance.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A local school system shall ensure that all students with disabilities, 3 years old through the end of the school year in which the student turns 21 years old, residing within the jurisdiction of the local school system are located, identified, evaluated, and provided services consistent with 20 U.S.C. §§1400—1419, 34 CFR 300 and 301, Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-401">8-401</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-415">8-415</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland, and COMAR 13A.05.01.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Students under <cite path="13A|05|02|.13|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite> include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Students with disabilities attending private schools within the jurisdiction of the local school system;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Highly mobile students;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Migrant students;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Homeless students, as defined in COMAR 13A.05.09;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Wards of the State, as defined in 34 CFR §300.45 and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-412">Education Article §8-412, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Students who are suspected of being a student with a disability under 34 CFR §300.8 and in need of special education, even though they are advancing from grade to grade, in accordance with 34 CFR §300.101.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Interagency Collaboration. A local school system shall establish and maintain interagency planning and program implementation agreements for students with disabilities in the manner specified by the Department or <cite doc="Md. Code" path="49D">Article 49D, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Local Application for Federal Funds.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A public agency shall submit a local application for Part B funds annually, in the manner specified by the Department, consistent with 20 U.S.C. §1413(a), including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Grant budgets;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Policies and procedures for the implementation of FAPE for students with disabilities, consistent with federal and State laws and regulations; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A staffing plan consistent with <cite path="13A|05|02|.13|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Department shall review the local application, as described in <cite path="13A|05|02|.13|C.|(1)">§C(1) of this regulation</cite>, and issue a written decision to the public agency.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Department shall prohibit a public agency from reducing maintenance of effort for any fiscal year, consistent with 20 U.S.C. §1413(a)(2), 34 CFR §300.203, and COMAR 13A.02.05, and in accordance with 20 U.S.C. §1416(f), if the Department determines a public agency is not meeting the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Requirements of the Act; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Targets in the State performance plan.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Early Intervening Services. A local school system may use not more than 15 percent of the federal funds received under the Act to develop and implement coordinated early intervening services in accordance with 20 U.S.C. §1413(f) and 34 CFR §300.226.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Disproportionality. A local school system shall reserve 15 percent of the federal funds in accordance with 20 U.S.C. §1418(d)(2)(B) and 34 CFR §300.646 to provide comprehensive, coordinated early intervening services consistent with 20 U.S.C. §1413(f) and 34 CFR §300.226 to serve students identified in those groups where significant disproportionality exists.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A public agency shall make available all documents relating to the eligibility of the public agency in accordance with 20 U.S.C. §1413(a)(8) and 34 CFR §300.212.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Staffing Plan.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A public agency shall develop a staffing plan consistent with the procedures provided by the Department to ensure that personnel and other resources are available to provide FAPE to each student with a disability in the least restrictive environment as determined by an IEP team.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The local board shall approve the staffing plan.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Procedural Safeguards.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A public agency shall establish and maintain procedures consistent with 20 U.S.C. §1415, 34 CFR §§300.500—300.536, and COMAR 13A.05.01.11—15 and .16C to ensure that students with disabilities and their parents are guaranteed procedural safeguards with respect to the provision of a FAPE.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Parent Surrogates. A public agency shall appoint a parent surrogate for a student with a disability, as described in COMAR 13A.05.01.11G and in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-412">Education Article, §8-412, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Continuum of Alternative Placements. A public agency shall ensure a continuum of alternative placements is available for students with disabilities who require special education and related services, consistent with COMAR 13A.05.01.10B.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Reports. A public agency shall submit reports at the time and in the manner specified by the Department.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Accessibility of Technology-Based Instructional Products.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A public agency shall ensure that a request for bid, request for proposal, and local public agency guidelines for the selection and evaluation of technology-based instructional products used by students include the requirements governing equivalent access consistent with Subpart B, Technical Standards, Section 508 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973, as amended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A public agency shall ensure that technology-based instructional products provide students with disabilities equivalent access unless doing so would:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Fundamentally alter the nature of the instructional activity;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Result in undue financial and administrative burdens on the public agency; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Not meet all other specifications.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If a technology-based instructional product meets the criteria described in <cite path="13A|05|02|.13|H.|(2)">§H(2) of this regulation</cite> or is not available, the public agency shall implement an alternative method of instruction designed to enable a student with a disability to access the general curriculum and meet the student's IEP goals and objectives as specified in COMAR 13A.05.01.09A.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Local Special Education Citizens Advisory Committee.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each local school system shall establish a special education citizens advisory committee to advise the local school system on the needs of students with disabilities within the jurisdiction.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Department shall annually allocate federal funds to each local school system to support the activities of the local special education citizen advisory committee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Each local school system shall submit a budget for the use of federal funds, consistent with <cite path="13A|05|02|.13|C.|(1)|(a)">§C(1)(a) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Charter Schools. A local school system shall serve students with disabilities attending charter schools in the same manner as the public agency serves students with disabilities in its other schools, in accordance with 20 U.S.C. §1413(a)(5) and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged">Education Article, Title 9, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Medications. Public agencies may not require a student with a disability to obtain a prescription for a substance covered by the Controlled Substances Act, as described in 20 U.S.C. §1412(a)(25), as a condition of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Attending school;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Receiving an evaluation; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Receiving special education and related services in accordance with COMAR 13A.05.01.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Personnel Development. A public agency shall ensure all personnel necessary to implement the Act are prepared in accordance with 20 U.S.C. §1412(a)(14), 34 CFR §300.207, and §2122 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>Purchase of Instructional Materials. A public agency may coordinate with the National Instructional Materials Access Center (NIMAC) when purchasing print instructional materials in the same manner and subject to the same conditions as the Department as described in <cite path="|13A|05|02|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite> and in accordance with 34 CFR §300.210 and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-408">Education Article, §8-408(d), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>Reimbursement of Licensing Fee.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A local school system shall provide an amount equal to the initial licensing fee or renewal of license fee to an audiologist or speech-language pathologist, in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|6-112">Education Article, §6-112</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland, who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Provides audiology and speech language services on a third-party billing basis in schools; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is licensed by the State Board of Audiologists, Hearing-Aid Dispensers, and Speech-Language Pathologists.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An audiologist or speech-language pathologist shall reimburse the local school system the full amount of aid received if the audiologist or speech-language pathologist does not:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Complete all the requirements for renewal of a license; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Provide audiology or speech-language pathology services on a third-party billing basis in a school.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>Transition from a Local Infants and Toddlers Program. The public agency shall ensure that a representative of the public agency attends the local infants and toddlers transition planning meeting as described in 20 U.S.C. §1437(a)(9)(A)(ii)(II).</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|05|02|.14">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Nonpublic Placements by Local School Systems.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General. A local school system shall consider the placement of a student with a disability in a nonpublic program when:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The local school system cannot implement the student's IEP; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The nonpublic school program to which the student has been referred:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Has been approved by the Department;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Can implement the student's IEP; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Is the least restrictive environment.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>State Contributions for Funding In-State Nonpublic Placements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A State contribution for funding the costs of a placement for a student with a disability in an approved nonpublic school program is available for placements which meet the requirements of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-406">Education Article, §8-406, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and <cite path="|13A|05|02|.12">Regulation .12 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A local school system requesting a State funding contribution in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-414">Education Article, §8-414, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, shall apply to the Department for approval of the funding contribution for the placement of the student at the time and in the manner specified by the Department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The local school system shall provide written notice to the parents of a student with a disability when an application for a State contribution for funding a nonpublic school placement is submitted to the Department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the Department disapproves a request for State funding of a nonpublic school placement recommended by a local school system for a student with a disability, the Department shall identify an available appropriate alternative placement.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>State Contribution for Funding an In-State Residential Placement.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A local school system shall obtain approval from the LCT  before a local school system requests a State funding contribution of an in-State residential placement for a student with a disability.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A local school system shall notify the Department of the LCT approval when the request for a State funding contribution is submitted to the Department.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>State Contribution for Funding Out-of-State Nonpublic Placements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A local school system shall participate as a member of the LCT and the LMB, in accordance with <cite path="|14.31.01">COMAR 14.31.01</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A local school system shall obtain approval from the LCT  to request a State contribution for funding an out-of-State nonpublic placement for a student with a disability whose educational needs cannot be met in an in-State nonpublic placement consistent with <cite path="13A|05|02|.14|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The LCT shall review the funding request for an out-of-State nonpublic placement in accordance with <cite path="|14.31.01">COMAR 14.31.01</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the LCT approves the out-of-State nonpublic placement funding request, the local school system shall forward the funding request and supporting documentation at the time and in the manner specified by the SCC.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>On approval of the State contribution for funding the out-of-State residential nonpublic placement, the SCC shall notify the Department and the local school system.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Limitations on Local School System and State Funding Contributions to Nonpublic Placements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If the LCT determines that a student with a disability requires a nonpublic placement for noneducational reasons, the local school system may agree to be responsible for the educational cost not to exceed the local share of the basic cost of the local school system education program, as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-415">Education Article, §8-415, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The local school system is not responsible for the cost of the educational component of a nonpublic placement if the placement:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is not required to provide a student FAPE consistent with COMAR 13A.05.01.06 and <cite path="13A|05|02|.14|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is made by another agency without local school system approval for funding.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Notwithstanding <cite path="13A|05|02|.14|D.|(2)">§D(2) of this regulation</cite>, the local school system shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Assist the placing agency with the transfer of educational records as set forth in Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-501">8-501</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-506">8-506</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Review student progress at least annually, in accordance with COMAR 13A.05.01.07 —10.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>When another public agency places a student with a disability in a residential placement as defined in <cite path="14.31.01.02|B.|(18)">COMAR 14.31.01.02B(18)</cite>, for noneducational reasons, the nonpublic school shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Immediately enroll the student;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Allow the student to access the full array of instructional opportunities offered by the nonpublic school; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Provide special education and related services as outlined in the student's IEP.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>In accordance with the fiduciary responsibilities for public funds, the Department may audit the records of nonpublic schools to which the Department has contributed funding for placements.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|2-205">2-205</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-301">8-301</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-319">8-319</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-3">8-3</cite>A-01—8-3A-11, and 8-401—8-419;<br/>Human Services Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ghu|8-401">8-401</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ghu|8-409">8-409</cite>;<br/>Labor and Employment Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gle|11-801">11-801</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gle|11-901">11-901</cite> et seq.; Annotated Code of Maryland<br/>Federal Statutory Reference: 20 U.S.C. §§1408, 1412, 1413, and 1437;<br/>Federal Regulatory References: 34 CFR 300 and 303</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-07-01">Effective date: July 1, 1999 (26:8 Md. R. 616)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-05-07"><cite path="|13A|05|02|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective January 21, 2002 (29:1 Md. R. 24); May 7, 2007 (34:9 Md. R. 826)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-10-05"><cite path="|13A|05|02|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended effective January 21, 2002 (29:1 Md. R. 24) ; May 7, 2007 (34:9 Md. R. 826); October 5, 2009 (36:20 Md. R. 1530)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-07-31"><cite path="|13A|05|02|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite> amended effective January 21, 2002 (29:1 Md. R. 24); July 31, 2017 (44:15 Md. R. 760)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-05-07"><cite path="|13A|05|02|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite> amended effective June 23, 2003 (30:11 Md. R. 789) ; May 7, 2007 (34:9 Md. R. 826)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-01-21"><cite path="|13A|05|02|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite>, B amended effective January 21, 2002 (29:1 Md. R. 24)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-05-07"><cite path="|13A|05|02|.04|D.">Regulation .04D</cite> adopted effective May 7, 2007 (34:9 Md. R. 826)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-10-05"><cite path="|13A|05|02|.04|D.">Regulation .04D</cite> amended effective October 5, 2009 (36:20 Md. R. 1530)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-06-18"><cite path="|13A|05|02|.04|F.">Regulation .04F</cite> adopted effective June 18, 2018 (45:12 Md. R. 618)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-05-07"><cite path="|13A|05|02|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective May 7, 2007 (34:9 Md. R. 826)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-05-16"><cite path="|13A|05|02|.05|D.">Regulation .05D</cite> amended effective May 16, 2011 (38:10 Md. R. 615)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-06-23"><cite path="|13A|05|02|.05|F.">Regulation .05F</cite> amended effective January 21, 2002 (29:1 Md. R. 24); June 23, 2003 (30:11 Md. R. 789)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-05-07"><cite path="|13A|05|02|.06|A.">Regulation .06A</cite>, C amended effective May 7, 2007 (34:9 Md. R. 826)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-05-07"><cite path="|13A|05|02|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective May 7, 2007 (34:9 Md. R. 826)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-05-07"><cite path="|13A|05|02|.10">Regulation .10</cite> amended effective May 7, 2007 (34:9 Md. R. 826)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-05-07"><cite path="|13A|05|02|.12|A.">Regulation .12A</cite> amended effective May 7, 2007 (34:9 Md. R. 826)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-05-07"><cite path="|13A|05|02|.13">Regulation .13</cite> amended effective May 7, 2007 (34:9 Md. R. 826)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-06-23"><cite path="|13A|05|02|.13|A.">Regulation .13A</cite> amended effective June 23, 2003 (30:11 Md. R. 789)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-01-21"><cite path="|13A|05|02|.13|H.">Regulation .13H</cite> adopted effective January 21, 2002 (29:1 Md. R. 24)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-11-08"><cite path="|13A|05|02|.13|I.">Regulation .13I</cite> adopted effective November 8, 2004 (31:22 Md. R. 1596)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-10-05"><cite path="|13A|05|02|.13|O.">Regulation .13O</cite> adopted effective October 5, 2009 (36:20 Md. R. 1530)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-07-31"><cite path="|13A|05|02|.14|B.">Regulation .14B</cite>—D amended effective July 31, 2017 (44:15 Md. R. 760)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-05-07"><cite path="|13A|05|02|.14|D.">Regulation .14D</cite> amended effective May 7, 2007 (34:9 Md. R. 826)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-01-21"><cite path="|13A|05|02|.14|E.">Regulation .14E</cite> adopted effective January 21, 2002 (29:1 Md. R. 24)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
