<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Maryland Register, Volume 52, Issue 18" codify:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">
  <num>52-18</num>
  <meta>
    <stub/>
    <effective>2025-09-15</effective>
    <citations>
      <citation type="register" url="./52-18.pdf">52:18</citation>
    </citations>
    <history>
      <published>2025-09-05</published>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <container name="regulations">
    <container name="final">
      <container>
        <num>25-060-F</num>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="08|18|01|.08" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="08|18|01|.08">
          <section cache:ref-path="08|18|01|.08">
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.08</num>
            <heading>Boating on White Water Portions of Designated Stream Segments.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>The provisions of this regulation apply to boating on any white water portion of stream segments designated in this regulation, but do not apply to stream segments not designated in this regulation.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>For purposes of this regulation, “white water portion” means any portion of a designated stream segment which has any of the criteria characteristics described in <cite path="08|18|01|.08|C." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">§C of this regulation</cite>.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>C.</num>
              <text>The Department of Natural Resources shall designate white water stream segments in accordance with the following criteria:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Class III (Intermediate). Rapids with moderate irregular waves occur, which may be difficult to avoid and which can swamp an open canoe. Complex maneuvers in fast current, and good boat control in tight passages or around ledges are often required. Large waves or strainers may be present but are easily avoided. Strong eddies and powerful current effects can be found, particularly on large volume rivers. Scouting is advisable for inexperienced parties. Injuries while swimming are rare. Self-rescue is usually easy, but group assistance may be required to avoid long swims.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Class IV (Advanced). Intense, powerful but predictable rapids occur, requiring precise boat handling in turbulent water. Depending on the character of the river, it may feature large, unavoidable waves and holes or constricted passages demanding fast maneuvers under pressure. A fast, reliable eddy turn may be needed to initiate maneuvers, scout rapids, or rest. Rapids may require moves above dangerous hazards. Scouting is necessary the first time down. Risk of injury to swimmers is moderate to high and water conditions may make self-rescue difficult. Group assistance for rescue is often essential, but requires practiced skills. A strong Eskimo roll is highly recommended.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>Class V (Expert). Extremely long, obstructed, or very violent rapids occur, which expose a paddler to above average endangerment. Drops may contain large, unavoidable waves and holes or steep, congested chutes with complex, demanding routes. Rapids may continue for long distances between pools, demanding a high level of fitness. What eddies exist may be small, turbulent, or difficult to reach. At the high end of the scale, several of these factors may be combined. Scouting is mandatory but often difficult. Swims are dangerous, and rescue is difficult even for experts. A very reliable Eskimo roll, proper equipment, extensive experience, and practiced rescue skills are essential for survival.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>Class VI (Extreme). One grade more difficult than Class V. These runs often exemplify the extremes of difficulty, unpredictability, and danger. The consequences of errors are very severe and rescue may be impossible. For teams of experts only at favorable water levels, after close personal inspection and taking all precautions. This class does not represent drops thought to be unrunnable, but may include rapids which are only occasionally run.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>D.</num>
              <text>The Department of Natural Resources is designating the following stream segments for purposes of this boating safety regulation only, and intends no determination whether there is any right of public access to, navigation along, landing along, or egress from, any of these designated stream segments. This regulation does not apply to the use of vessels on non-white water portions of designated stream segments for any purpose other than access to white water. The designated stream segments are:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Class III — stream segments:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>North Branch Casselman River — Dung Hill Road to Md. Rte. 495;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Potomac River — Dam No. 3, Harpers Ferry to Knoxville Falls;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>Evitts Creek — Maryland line (Hazen Road) to North Branch Potomac River (Md. Rte. 51 bridge);</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <text>Flintstone Creek — Flintstone Creek Road to Town Creek (Old Rte. 40 bridge);</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <text>Fifteen Mile Creek — U.S. Rte. 40 to Potomac River (bridge at Orleans Rd.);</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <text>Middle Creek — Pennsylvania line to Toms Creek (Keysville Rd.);</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <text>Northwest Branch Anacostia River — U.S. Rte. 29 to Hyattsville (38th Avenue);</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <text>Patapsco River—Woodstock (Md. Rte. 125) to Gun Road;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <text>South Branch Patapsco River — Woodbine (Md. Rte. 94) to Woodstock (Md. Rte. 125);</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <text>Gunpowder Falls — Prettyboy Dam to Md. Rte. 45;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <text>Little Falls — Parkton (Md. Rte. 45) to Gunpowder Falls (Blue Mount Road);</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <text>Little Gunpowder Falls — Md. Rte. 147 to U.S. Rte. 40;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(m)</num>
                  <text>Deer Creek — Fawn Grove Road to Stafford Road;</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Class IV — stream segments:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Bear Creek — U.S. Rte. 219 to Friendsville (Friendsville — Addison Road);</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Georges Creek — Md. Rte. 36 bridge halfway between Midland and Lonaconing to Westernport (Md. Rte. 135 bridge);</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>Jennings Run — Barrelville (Rte. 36) to Wills Creek (Md. Rte. 36 bridge);</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <text>Middle Patuxent River — Md. Rte. 107 to Savage (Foundry Street);</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <text>Rock Creek — East-West Highway to D.C. line (Rock Creek Park);</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <text>Gunpowder Falls — Lower Loch Raven Dam to U.S. Rte. 40;</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>Class V — stream segments:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Youghiogheny River:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <text>Millers Run (bridge on Oakland — Sang Run Road) to Sang Run Road,</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <text>Sang Run Road to Friendsville (Rte. 42);</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Potomac River — Great Falls (foot of falls) to Washington, D.C. (Chain Bridge Rd.);</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>North Branch Potomac River — Henry, W.Va. (W.Va. Rte. 90) to Bloomington, Md. (mouth of Savage River);</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <text>Savage River — Savage River Dam to North Branch Potomac River (Md. Rte. 135 bridge);</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <text>Wills Creek — Pennsylvania line near Ellerslie to North Branch Potomac River (levee at Md. Rte. 48 bridge);</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <text>Conowingo Creek — Oakwood to Susquehanna River (launching ramp — Conowingo Lake);</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>Class VI — stream segments: All the waters of the Potomac River — Great Falls area from the base of aqueduct dam to a line from the foot of the main falls on the Virginia shoreline to the Maryland shoreline below Olmstead Island.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>E.</num>
              <text>Required Equipment.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>An individual using a vessel, raft, or tube upon any white water portion of any designated stream segment shall wear a U.S. Coast Guard approved Type III or V personal flotation device (PFD) at all times. An individual taking part in supervised training or in International Canoe Federation (ICF) — American Canoe Association (ACA) sanctioned events may substitute a lifedeck personal flotation device (PFD) if it provides a minimum buoyancy of 6 kilograms (13.5 pounds).</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>An individual who is in charge of guiding a commercially hired vessel or vessels shall have in possession, at all times while navigating any designated stream segment, a first aid kit, such as the kit recommended by Eastern Professional River Outfitters, equipped for severe bleeding, shock or concussion, and fractures.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>An individual in charge of a vessel being used on a white water portion of a designated white water stream segment shall have, at all times, grab loops or safety lines attached to the vessel.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>An individual using a kayak or covered canoe vessel on a white water portion of a designated stream segment shall wear a safety helmet.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>F.</num>
              <text>Voluntary Registration of Commercial White Water Outfitters and Guides.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>A person who directly or indirectly receives any consideration for furnishing equipment, facilities, or services, or all of these, for white water boating, may register with the Department as a commercial white water outfitter.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>A person who directly or indirectly receives any consideration for guiding vessels containing passengers on white water stream segments, may register with the Department as a commercial white water guide.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>A person desiring to register as a commercial white water outfitter or guide shall apply annually on forms provided by the Department.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>Criteria for Registration. Before registering a person as a commercial white water outfitter or guide, the Department shall determine that the person:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Carries sufficient liability insurance covering death or personal injury for the number of individuals who will use the outfitter's or guide's equipment on white water stream segments;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>If registering as a guide, holds a CPR certificate or equivalent, or a Red Cross Advanced First Aid certificate or equivalent;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>If registering as a guide, provides proof of degree of experience with specific types of vessels, which proof then shall be included on the State registration list.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(5)</num>
                <text>The Department of Natural Resources shall make available to each registered commercial white water outfitter and guide information concerning white water boating safety.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(6)</num>
                <text>The Department of Natural Resources shall make available to the public a list of the registered commercial white water outfitters and guides.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="08|18|01|annos" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="08|18|01|annos">
          <annotations>
            <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Natural Resources Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|8-101">8-101</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|8-703">8-703</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|8-704">8-704</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-02-03">Effective date: February 3, 1992 (19:2 Md. R. 153)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-03-13"><cite path="|08|18|01|.03|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .03B</cite> amended effective October 14, 2002 (29:20 Md. R. 1587); October 29. 2012 (39:21 Md. R. 1377); April 1, 2013 (40:6 Md. R. 472): March 28, 2016 (43:6 Md. R. 405); March 13, 2017 (44:5 Md. R. 291)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-03-22"><cite path="|08|18|01|.04|A." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .04A</cite> amended effective March 22, 2021 (48:6 Md. R. 237)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-06-20"><cite path="|08|18|01|.06" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective September 28, 1992 (19:19 Md. R. 1704); June 20, 1994 (21:12 Md. R. 1060)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-12-25"><cite path="|08|18|01|.08" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .08</cite> amended effective December 25, 2000 (27:25 Md. R. 2281)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-15"><cite path="|08|18|01|.08|D." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .08D</cite> amended effective May 24, 1993 (20:10 Md. R. 849); September 15, 2025 (52:18 Md. R. 923)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-09-29"><cite path="|08|18|01|.08|E." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .08E</cite> amended effective September 29, 2003 (30:19 Md. R. 1330)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container"><cite path="|08|18|01|.09" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .09</cite> adopted effective October 29. 2012 (39:21 Md. R. 1377)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container"><cite path="|08|18|01|.10" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .10</cite> adopted effective October 29. 2012 (39:21 Md. R. 1377)</annotation>
          </annotations>
        </codify:replace>
      </container>
      <container>
        <num>25-096-F</num>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|32|05|.02" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|32|05|.02">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.02</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>Terms Defined.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>“Asynchronous” means not occurring in real time.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>“In-person” means within the physical presence of the patient.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>“Interpretive services” means reading and analyzing images, tracings, or specimens through telehealth or giving interpretations based on visual, auditory, thermal, or ultrasonic patterns or other patterns as may evolve with technology.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>“Synchronous” means occurring in real time.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(5)</num>
                <text>Telehealth.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>“Telehealth” means a mode of delivering health care services through the use of telecommunications technologies by a health care practitioner to a patient at a different physical location than the telehealth practitioner.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>“Telehealth” includes synchronous and asynchronous interactions.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>“Telehealth” does not include the provision of health care services solely through:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <text>Audio–only calls;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <text>E–mail messages; or</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <text>Facsimile transmissions.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(6)</num>
                <text>“Telehealth practitioner” means a Maryland licensed physician or licensed allied health practitioner performing telehealth services within their respective scope of practice.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|32|05|.03" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|32|05|.03">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.03</num>
            <heading>Licensure.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>Except as specified in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|14-302">Health Occupations Article, §14-302, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, a telehealth practitioner shall be licensed when providing telehealth services to a patient located in the State.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>Telehealth practitioners licensed in the State are subject to the jurisdiction of the State and shall abide by the telehealth requirements of this chapter if either the practitioner or patient is physically located in this State.</text>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|32|05|.04" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|32|05|.04">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.04</num>
            <heading>Specific Telehealth Requirements.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>Before performing telehealth services, a telehealth practitioner shall develop and follow a procedure to:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Verify the identification of the patient receiving telehealth services within a reasonable degree of certainty through use of:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Government issued photograph identification;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Insurance, Medicaid, or Medicare card; or</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>Documentation of the patient’s:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <text>Date of birth; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <text>Home address;</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>For an initial patient encounter, disclose the telehealth practitioner’s name, contact information, license type, and medical specialty, if any;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>Except for interpretive services, obtain oral or written consent from a patient or the patient’s parent or guardian if State law requires the consent of a parent or guardian including informing patients of the risks, benefits, and side effects of prescribed treatments;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>Securely collect and transmit a patient’s medical information, clinical data, clinical images, laboratory results, and self–reported medical history, as necessary and prevent access to data by unauthorized persons through encryption or other means;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(5)</num>
                <text>Notify patients in the event of a data breach;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(6)</num>
                <text>Ensure that the telehealth practitioner provides a secure and private telehealth connection that complies with federal and state privacy laws; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(7)</num>
                <text>Establish safety protocols to be used in the case of an emergency.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>Except when providing asynchronous telehealth services, a telehealth practitioner shall:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Obtain or confirm an alternative method of contacting the patient in case of a technological failure;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Confirm whether the patient is in Maryland and identify the practice setting in which the patient is located; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>Identify all individuals present at each location and confirm they are allowed to hear personal health information.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>C.</num>
              <text>The requirements set forth under §§A and B of this regulation may be delegated.</text>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|32|05|.05" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|32|05|.05">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.05</num>
            <heading>Patient Evaluation.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>A telehealth practitioner shall perform a synchronous or asynchronous clinical patient evaluation that is appropriate for the patient and the condition with which the patient presents before providing treatment or issuing a prescription through telehealth.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>A telehealth practitioner shall, if clinically appropriate for the patient, provide or refer a patient to in-person health care services or another type of telehealth service.</text>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|32|05|.06" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|32|05|.06">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.06</num>
            <heading>Standard Related to Telehealth.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>A telehealth practitioner shall be held to the same standards of practice and documentation as those applicable in in-person health care settings.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>A telehealth practitioner may not treat a patient or prescribe medication based solely on a static online questionnaire.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>C.</num>
              <text>A telehealth practitioner may not prescribe an opiate described in the list of Schedule II substances under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|5-403">Criminal Law Article, §5-403, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite> for the treatment of pain through telehealth unless:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>The patient is in a health care facility as defined in Health-General Article, §19-114(d)(1), Annotated Code of Maryland; or</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>The Governor has declared a state of emergency due to a catastrophic health emergency.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>D.</num>
              <text>A telehealth practitioner shall comply with all State and federal laws and regulations related to dispensing including the prohibition on mail order dispensing.</text>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|32|05|annos" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|32|05|annos">
          <annotations>
            <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|1-903">1-903</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|1-1001">1-1001</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|1-1006">1-1006</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|14-205">14-205</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|14-301">14-301</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|14-601">14-601</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-12-28">Effective date: December 28, 2009 (36:26 Md. R. 1995)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-08-12" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|10|32|05|.01" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|32|05|.07" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">.07</cite>, Telemedicine, repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|10|32|05|.01" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|32|05|.07" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">.07</cite>, Telehealth, adopted effective August 12, 2019 (46:16 Md. R. 688)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-15"><cite path="|10|32|05|.02|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective September 15, 2025 (52:18 Md. R. 923)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-15"><cite path="|10|32|05|.03" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective September 15, 2025 (52:18 Md. R. 923)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-15"><cite path="|10|32|05|.04" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective September 15, 2025 (52:18 Md. R. 923)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-15"><cite path="|10|32|05|.05" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective September 15, 2025 (52:18 Md. R. 923)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-15"><cite path="|10|32|05|.06" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .06</cite> B, C amended effective September 15, 2025 (52:18 Md. R. 923)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-15"><cite path="|10|32|05|.06|D." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .06D</cite> adopted effective September 15, 2025 (52:18 Md. R. 923)</annotation>
          </annotations>
        </codify:replace>
      </container>
      <container>
        <num>25-130-F-I</num>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|50|01|.03" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|50|01|.03">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.03</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>Terms Defined.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>“Adverse outcome” means an undesirable effect or untoward complication in a recipient as a result of or reasonably related to a transfusion or transplantation of cells, tissue, or both.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>“Allogeneic tissue” means tissue from a human donor intended for use within or upon the body of an individual other than the donor.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>“Allograft” means cells, tissue, or both intended for transplantation into another individual of the same species.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>“Approval of the removal plan” means that the OHCQ has determined that the tissue bank's removal plan, if implemented appropriately, will remove the likelihood that serious harm will occur, or recur.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(5)</num>
                <text>“Autogeneic tissue” means tissue from a human donor intended for use within or upon the body of that same donor.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(6)</num>
                <text>“Cardiovascular tissue” means:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Human heart valves;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Aorta and great vessels;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>Pericardium;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <text>Saphenous vein;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <text>Umbilical vein; or</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <text>Other tissues of the cardiovascular system.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(7)</num>
                <text>Collection.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>“Collection” means an activity involved in obtaining allogeneic or autogeneic tissue for the purpose of transplantation, transfusion, or transfer into or upon a human being.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>“Collection” includes the removal, acquisition, recovery, harvesting, or retrieval of donor tissue by any means, including:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <text>Phlebotomy;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <text>Hemapheresis;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <text>Surgical excision; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <text>Biopsy.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(8)</num>
                <text>“Designated qualified employee” means an employee who has been delegated one or more responsibilities by the technical director or medical director and who possesses the training and experience to perform the delegated responsibility.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(9)</num>
                <text>“Department” means the Maryland Department of Health.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(10)</num>
                <text>“Distribution” means the removal of tissue or tissue products from the tissue bank originally collecting, storing, or processing the tissue for shipment to another person or facility for processing, storage, or a diagnostic, therapeutic, or prophylactic purpose.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(11)</num>
                <text>“Donor” means a human being, living or dead, who is the source of tissue for:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Transplantation;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Transfer;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>Transfusion; or</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <text>Implantation.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(12)</num>
                <text>“Eye” means a human cornea or other ocular tissue.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(13)</num>
                <text>“Hematopoietic progenitor cells” means human precursor stem or progenitor hematopoietic cells derived from bone marrow, peripheral blood, or other tissue sources.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(14)</num>
                <text>“Immediate corrective action” means all actions the tissue bank has taken or will take to immediately address the noncompliance that resulted in or made serious harm or death likely.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(15)</num>
                <text>“Immediate jeopardy” means a situation in which immediate corrective action is necessary because the tissue bank's noncompliance with one or more licensure requirements has already caused, is causing, or is likely to cause, at any time, serious harm or death, to individuals served by the tissue bank or to the health or safety of the general public.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(16)</num>
                <text>“Informal dispute resolution (IDR)” means an informal process that provides a tissue bank the opportunity to dispute one or more deficiencies cited in a written statement of deficiencies issued by the Department or the Department’s designee related to a recent survey.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(17)</num>
                <text>Leukocyte.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>“Leukocyte” means a nucleated white blood cell or a colorless blood corpuscle that:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <text>Is found throughout the human body, including the blood, lymphatic system, and lymphoidal tissue;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <text>Is produced and derived from hematopoietic progenitor cells in the bone marrow; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <text>Functions to protect the body against infectious microorganisms that cause disease by phagocytosis of the microorganisms and by producing antibodies.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>“Leukocyte” includes any of the various white blood cells classified as a granulocyte or agranulocyte that collectively make up the human immune system, including:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <text>Neutrophils, also known as polymorphonuclear leukocytes;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <text>Eosinophils;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <text>Basophils;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <text>Monocytes;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(v)</num>
                    <text>Lymphocytes; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(vi)</num>
                    <text>Thrombocytes, also known as platelets.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(18)</num>
                <text>Leukocyte-Poor Tissue.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>“Leukocyte-Poor tissue” means tissue that does not contain a significant or substantial number of potentially viable leukocytes.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>“Leukocyte-Poor tissue” includes but is not limited to:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <text>Corneas;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <text>Sclera;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <text>Skin;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <text>Heart valves;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(v)</num>
                    <text>Dura mater;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(vi)</num>
                    <text>Oocytes; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(vii)</num>
                    <text>Musculoskeletal tissue, including bone, tendons, ligaments, and cartilage oocytes, if cleansed, washed, and rendered leukocyte-reduced.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(19)</num>
                <text>Leukocyte-Rich Tissue.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>“Leukocyte-Rich tissue” means tissue that may contain a significant or substantial number of potentially viable leukocytes.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>“Leukocyte-Rich tissue” includes but is not limited to:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <text>Blood, blood components, and products prepared after blood collection;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <text>Hematopoietic progenitor cells, also known as stem cells;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <text>Bone marrow;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <text>Musculoskeletal tissue containing blood or marrow elements, including unprocessed, fresh or frozen, or whole or partial bone;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(v)</num>
                    <text>Musculoskeletal tissue allografts in which the bone end and subchondral bone element have not been cleansed, washed, and rendered leukocyte-reduced; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(vi)</num>
                    <text>Semen.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(20)</num>
                <text>“Medical director” means a physician who:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Meets the requirements set forth in <cite path="|10|50|01|.10" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .10 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Is responsible for all medical aspects of the tissue bank's operations, unless the technical director meets the qualifications  stated in <cite path="|10|50|01|.10|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .10B of this chapter</cite>.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(21)</num>
                <text>“Milk” means human milk for ingestion by a child other than the milk donor's child.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(22)</num>
                <text>“Musculoskeletal tissue” means:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Bone;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Tendon;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>Ligament;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <text>Muscle;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <text>Fascia;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <text>Cartilage; or</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <text>Other tissue in the musculoskeletal system.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(23)</num>
                <text>“Need for immediate corrective action” means immediate corrective action is necessary to remove the jeopardy.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(24)</num>
                <text>“Noncompliance” means the tissue bank is not compliant with one or more licensure requirements.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(25)</num>
                <text>“OHCQ” means the Office of Health Care Quality in the Department.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(26)</num>
                <text>“Owner” means a person with an ownership interest in a tissue bank.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(27)</num>
                <text>Permit.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>“Permit” means a license issued by the Secretary to:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <text>Operate a tissue bank in this State; or</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <text>Represent or service in this State a tissue bank that is in this State or outside this State.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>“Permit” includes a provisional permit, except as otherwise indicated in <cite path="|10|50|01|.06" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(28)</num>
                <text>“Plan of correction” means a written plan submitted by the tissue bank to the OHCQ which documents steps the tissue bank will take to come into compliance with the licensure requirements.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(29)</num>
                <text>“Processing” means an activity necessary to:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Prepare or preserve a tissue for storage;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Remove a tissue from storage; or</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>Conduct testing to assure the potency, quality, or sterility of a tissue.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(30)</num>
                <text>“Recipient” means an individual who receives a tissue through:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Transplantation;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Transfusion;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>Transfer; or</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <text>Implementation.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(31)</num>
                <text>“Removal plan” means the tissue bank's written plan that documents:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>The immediate corrective action a tissue bank will take to prevent serious harm from occurring or recurring;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>All actions to remove past, present, and future jeopardy; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>The date by which the entity asserts the likelihood for serious harm to any recipient no longer exists.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(32)</num>
                <text>“Represent or service” means a mechanism, system, method, or activity that provides or offers to provide a tissue bank service to a person in the State.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(33)</num>
                <text>Reproductive Tissue.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>“Reproductive tissue” means tissue from the reproductive tract intended for use in artificial insemination or another assisted reproductive procedure.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>“Reproductive tissue” includes, but is not limited to:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <text>Semen;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <text>Oocytes;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <text>Embryos;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <text>Spermatozoa;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(v)</num>
                    <text>Spermatids;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(vi)</num>
                    <text>Ovarian tissue;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(vii)</num>
                    <text>Testicular tissue;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(viii)</num>
                    <text>Epididymal aspirates; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(ix)</num>
                    <text>Other tissue in the reproductive system.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(34)</num>
                <text>Quality Control.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>“Quality control” means the daily analysis of procedures and materials to assure sterility, accuracy, and reproducibility of tissue and tissue bank products.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>“Quality control” includes a documented system to assure that instruments, equipment, reagents, and supplies function properly.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(35)</num>
                <text>“Secretary” means the Secretary of the Department.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(36)</num>
                <text>“Serious harm” means the situation has already caused, is causing, or is likely to cause, at any time, serious injury, serious impairment, or death, to individuals served by the tissue bank or to the health or safety of the general public.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(37)</num>
                <text>“Storage” means holding tissue for subsequent:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Transplantation;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Transfusion;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>Transfer; or</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <text>Implantation.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(38)</num>
                <text>“Statement of Deficiencies” means the written notification that the OHCQ issues to the provider that contains a listing of deficiencies cited that require correction.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(39)</num>
                <text>“Technical director” means an individual who:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Meets the requirements set forth in <cite path="|10|50|01|.10" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .10 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Will oversee and be responsible for all technical aspects of the tissue bank's operations..</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(40)</num>
                <text>Tissue.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>“Tissue” means a visceral or nonvisceral collection of human cells and their associated intracellular substances.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>“Tissue” includes, but is not limited to, human:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <text>Blood, blood components, and products prepared after collection;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <text>Cardiovascular tissue;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <text>Cornea and other ocular tissue;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <text>Hematopoietic progenitor cells;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(v)</num>
                    <text>Milk;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(vi)</num>
                    <text>Musculoskeletal tissue;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(vii)</num>
                    <text>Reproductive cells and tissue; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(viii)</num>
                    <text>Skin.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(41)</num>
                <text>Tissue Bank.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>“Tissue bank” means an establishment that obtains, stores, processes, distributes, or sells human blood or other human tissue for use in the human body.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>“Tissue bank” includes a person or facility that provides or engages in one or more services involving tissue from living or cadaveric donors for:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <text>Transplantation;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <text>Transfusion;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <text>Transfer; or</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <text>Implementation purposes.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>“Tissue bank” includes, but is not limited to, the following classes:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <text>Blood bank;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <text>Cardiovascular tissue bank;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <text>Eye bank;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <text>Hematopoietic progenitor cell bank;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(v)</num>
                    <text>Human milk bank;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(vi)</num>
                    <text>Musculoskeletal tissue bank;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(vii)</num>
                    <text>Reproductive tissue bank; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(viii)</num>
                    <text>Skin bank.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(42)</num>
                <text>Tissue Bank Service.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>“Tissue bank service” means an activity or pursuit that involves tissue intended for human:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <text>Transplantation;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <text>Transfusion;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <text>Transfer; or</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <text>Implementation.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>“Tissue bank service” includes, but is not limited to, an activity or means of donor selection or tissue:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <text>Collection;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <text>Preparation;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <text>Preservation;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <text>Storage;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(v)</num>
                    <text>Allocation;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(vi)</num>
                    <text>Transportation; or</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(vii)</num>
                    <text>Distribution.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
              </para>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|50|01|.04" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|50|01|.04">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.04</num>
            <heading>Incorporation by Reference.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>In this chapter, the following documents are incorporated by reference.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>Documents Incorporated.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Standards for Tissue Banking (American Association of Tissue Banks, 14th Edition), Sections C, D, E, F, G, H, J, K, L, and M1-8 only;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Standards for Blood Banks and Transfusion Services [(American Association of Blood Banks, 29th Edition);] (Association for the Advancement of Blood &amp; Biotherapies), 34th Edition;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>International Quality Plasma Program (IQPP) (Plasma Protein Therapeutics Association):</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Community-based Donor Standard V5 (2020);</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Cross Donation Management Standard V3 (2014);</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>Recording Donor Adverse Events V2 (2018);</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <text>Donor Education Standard V3 (2014);</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <text>Donor Fluid Administration Standard V1 (2014);</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <text>Use of National Donor Deferral Registry Standard V3 (2008);</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <text>Qualified Donor Standard V5 (2020);</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <text>Viral Marker Standard V5 (2022);</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <text>Personnel Education and Training Standard V5 (2019);</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <text>Plasma Collection Facility Standard V4 (2019);</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <text>Quality Assurance Standard V5 (2020); and</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>42 U.S.C. §§1320d et seq., as amended;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(5)</num>
                <text>42 U.S.C. §§17921 et seq., as amended; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(6)</num>
                <text>45 CFR Parts 160, 162, and 164, as amended.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|50|01|.05" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|50|01|.05">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.05</num>
            <heading>Responsibilities of the OHCQ. — Repealed.</heading>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|50|01|.06" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|50|01|.06">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.06</num>
            <heading>Permitting Procedure.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>Application. An application is not complete until the OHCQ has received the completed permit application and all required documents.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>Initial Inspection. The OHCQ shall inspect or have an inspection conducted by an accreditation organization for each tissue bank when an initial Maryland permit to operate is sought.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>C.</num>
              <text>Issuance of a Permit. The Secretary shall issue a permit to an applicant who meets the requirements of this chapter to:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Operate a tissue bank in the State; or</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Represent for service in the State a tissue bank that is inside the State or outside the State.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>D.</num>
              <text>Issuance of a Permit and Provisional Permit.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Permit and Provisional Permit Content. A permit and provisional permit shall state:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>The name of the tissue bank;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>The name of the tissue bank's medical director;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>The name of the tissue bank's owner or owners; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <text>The class or classes of the tissue bank.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Provisional Permit.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>The Secretary may issue a provisional permit before or after an initial inspection.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>A provisional permit:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <text>Is valid for 180 calendar days or a lesser period as determined by the Secretary;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <text>May not be renewed; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <text>Shall automatically expire without notice upon the sooner of the date set for its expiration or upon issuance of a permit.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>E.</num>
              <text>Permit Requirement. A person shall hold a permit issued by the Secretary before the person may:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Operate a tissue bank in this State; or</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Represent or service in this State a tissue bank that is:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>In this State; or</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Outside this State.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>F.</num>
              <text>Operating Without a Permit.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Unless a person has a permit issued by the Secretary to operate, represent, or service a tissue bank in this State, a person may not:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Operate a tissue bank in this State; or</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Represent or service in this State a tissue bank that is in this State or outside this State.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>A permit holder may not operate, represent, or service a tissue bank class other than that authorized in the permit.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>G.</num>
              <text>Cessation of Operations.  If a tissue bank ceases operation for 180 calendar days, then:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>The OHCQ will void the permit to operate a tissue bank in the State; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>The tissue bank shall return the permit to the OHCQ.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>H.</num>
              <text>Permit Application Administratively Closed.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>After 180 calendar days from the date of initial receipt, the OHCQ may deem an incomplete permit application inactive and administratively close the application.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>An applicant whose application is administratively closed may reapply for a permit by submitting a new application.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>I.</num>
              <text>Change of Medical Director, Name, or Location of a Tissue Bank. A tissue bank undergoing a change in medical director, name, or location shall:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Notify the OHCQ 10 calendar days before a change occurs; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Apply to the OHCQ for an amended permit or provisional permit within 30 calendar days after a change takes place.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>J.</num>
              <text>Nontransferability. A permit or provisional permit may not be transferred from one owner of a tissue bank to another.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>K.</num>
              <text>Denial, Suspension, Revocation — Causes. The Secretary may deny, suspend, or revoke a permit or provisional permit if the tissue bank or the tissue bank's technical director, medical director, or both fail to meet requirements of this chapter, including, but not limited to:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Failure within a specified time to correct a cited deficiency identified during an inspection;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Repetitive or consistent errors;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>Deliberate falsehood; or</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>Failure to apply for an amended permit or provisional permit within 30 calendar days after a tissue bank undergoes a change in tissue bank class, medical director, name, or location.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>L.</num>
              <text>Denial, Suspension, and Revocation — Hearing Requirement.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>When the Secretary denies an application for a permit, the Secretary shall inform the permit applicant in writing:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Of the date the denial takes effect;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Of the reason for the denial; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>That the permit applicant has an opportunity for a hearing on the matter in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-226">State Government Article, §10-226, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Unless the Secretary finds that a danger to public health, safety, or welfare summarily requires that emergency action be taken to correct a deficiency, the Secretary shall inform the permit holder or provisional permit holder, in writing:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Of the date a suspension or revocation of the permit or provisional permit takes effect;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Of the reason for the suspension or revocation; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>That the permit holder or provisional permit holder has an opportunity for a hearing on the matter before the suspension or revocation takes effect, in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-226">State Government Article, §10-226, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>When a finding is made that the public health, safety, or welfare summarily requires that emergency or immediate corrective action be taken, the Secretary shall inform the permit holder or provisional permit holder in writing:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Of the date a suspension or revocation of the permit or provisional permit takes effect;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Of the reason for the suspension or revocation; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>That the permit holder or provisional permit holder has an opportunity for a hearing on the matter, after the suspension or revocation takes effect, in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-226">State Government Article, §10-226, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>Reapplication After Revocation. A tissue bank that has had its permit or provisional permit revoked may apply for a new permit 30 calendar days after revocation and upon presentation to the Secretary of evidence of capability and intention to comply with the standards and requirements of this chapter.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>M.</num>
              <text>Return of Permit. If a tissue bank's permit is amended, suspended, or revoked, the original permit is void and the tissue bank's technical director shall return the permit to the OHCQ.</text>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|50|01|.07" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|50|01|.07">
          <section cache:ref-path="10|50|01|.07">
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.07</num>
            <heading>Accredited Tissue Bank and Accrediting Organization.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>Accredited Tissue Bank — Determination. The Secretary may accept as compliance with the inspection requirements of this chapter a tissue bank accredited by an organization approved by the Secretary, as set forth in <cite path="10|50|01|.07|C." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">§C of this regulation</cite>, if the OHCQ determines that the standards of the tissue bank accrediting organization are equivalent to those under this chapter.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>Accredited Tissue Bank — Requirements. In addition to meeting the requirements for accreditation, as set forth by a tissue bank's accrediting organization, an accredited tissue bank shall:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Obtain and maintain a valid permit issued by the Secretary; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Be subject to inspection by the OHCQ to:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Determine if the tissue bank is operating in a manner that does not constitute an imminent and serious risk to public health;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Investigate complaints;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>Determine whether a permit holder is operating a tissue bank beyond the scope of the permit;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <text>Validate findings of a tissue bank's accrediting organization; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <text>Verify compliance with licensure requirements.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>C.</num>
              <text>Accrediting Organization.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>A private, nonprofit tissue-bank accrediting organization may inspect and accredit tissue banks in the State for the purpose of a State permit only after applying for and receiving approval of the OHCQ.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>The OHCQ may approve a tissue bank accrediting organization based on a review of that organization, if the review includes (but need not be limited to) an evaluation of:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Accreditation policies and standards;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Copies of inspection forms and guidelines;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>Inspection and deficiency writing policies;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <text>Inspector qualifications; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <text>Complaint investigation policies.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>In addition to other requirements set forth in this chapter, an accrediting organization shall provide to the OHCQ:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Annually, an updated list containing the names, addresses, and accreditation expiration dates of all tissue banks in the State accredited by the accrediting organization;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Within 30 days after conducting an inspection, a certified written or electronic copy of each inspection report covering each tissue bank applying for or maintaining accreditation in the State;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>At least 30 days before the effective date of the change, written notice of any proposed change to requirements for tissue bank accreditation;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <text>Within 30 days after a tissue bank's accreditation expires, written or electronic notice if the tissue bank does not renew its accreditation;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <text>Documentation of a complaint and complaint investigation; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <text>On request, a copy of:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <text>Inspector qualifications; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <text>Other information the Secretary may require relating to the regulation of a tissue bank.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>When the Secretary denies accreditation to a tissue-bank accrediting organization, the Secretary shall inform the accrediting agency in writing that it has an opportunity for a hearing under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-226">State Government Article, §10-226, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>D.</num>
              <text>Change in Accreditation Status. Tissue banks shall report all changes in accreditation status to the OHCQ within seven calendar days of becoming aware of the change.</text>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|50|01|.08" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|50|01|.08">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.08</num>
            <heading>Inspection by OHCQ.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>Open for Inspection.  A permit holder shall allow an on-site inspection by the OHCQ, or any designee by OHCQ, at any time during the tissue bank's regular hours of operation, to evaluate the tissue bank's compliance with the applicable requirements, conditions, and standards of this chapter.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>Content of Inspection.  An inspection may include, but is not limited to, observation and examination of:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Tissue bank facilities and physical security;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Equipment;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>Quality assurance and quality control policies and records;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>Operating procedures, policies, and records;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(5)</num>
                <text>Personnel and personnel records;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(6)</num>
                <text>Donor documentation and records; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(7)</num>
                <text>Other records and files pertinent to this chapter.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>C.</num>
              <text>Access to Records. Tissue bank employees shall make data and records accessible within a reasonable time during an inspection by OHCQ or any designee by OHCQ.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>D.</num>
              <text>Permitted Tissue Bank. A permit holder operating a tissue bank under a provisional permit or a permit shall be subject to:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>An initial inspection conducted by the OHCQ;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Periodic inspections by the OHCQ; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>Other inspections by the OHCQ to determine if the tissue bank is in compliance with licensure requirements.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>E.</num>
              <text>Accredited Tissue Bank. An accredited tissue bank is subject to:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>An initial inspection by an accreditation organization or the OHCQ;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Periodic inspections by an accreditation organization or the OHCQ; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>Other inspections by the OHCQ to determine if the tissue bank is in compliance with licensure requirements.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>F.</num>
              <text>Notice of Deficiencies. If a survey identifies noncompliance with a requirement, the Department shall:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Issue a written Statement of Deficiencies that cites each deficiency;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Require the tissue bank to submit an acceptable plan of correction within 10 calendar days of receipt of the Statement of Deficiencies;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>Notify the tissue bank of any sanctions imposed or that failure to correct the violation may result in sanctions; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>Offer the tissue bank the opportunity for informal dispute resolution (IDR).</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>G.</num>
              <text>Plan of Correction.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>The tissue bank shall submit a written plan of correction to the OHCQ in response to a Statement of Deficiencies documenting the steps the permit holder will take to come into compliance, including:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>How the tissue bank will correct each deficiency;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>The date by which each deficient practice will be corrected;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>How the tissue bank will prevent the deficient practice from recurring; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <text>Who will be responsible for ensuring the deficiency will not reoccur.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Failure of the tissue bank to return an acceptable plan of correction within 10 calendar days after receipt of a Statement of Deficiencies may result in a sanction.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>A tissue bank’s request for an IDR does not change the tissue bank's requirement to submit a plan of correction for all deficiencies within 10 calendar days after receipt of the Statement of Deficiencies.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>If an immediate jeopardy is identified during a survey, the tissue bank’s plan of correction shall completely correct all noncompliance associated with the immediate jeopardy.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>H.</num>
              <text>Immediate Jeopardy.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Declaration of Immediate Jeopardy.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>When the Department identifies a situation in which immediate corrective action is necessary because the tissue bank's noncompliance with one or more licensure requirements has already caused, is causing, or is likely to cause, at any time, serious harm or death, to individuals served by the tissue bank or to the health or safety of the general public, an immediate jeopardy will be declared.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>The Department shall provide the tissue bank a written notice that includes a description of the situation that constitutes an immediate jeopardy.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Removal Plan.  The tissue bank shall submit a written removal plan to the Department that includes:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>The immediate corrective action a tissue bank will take to prevent serious harm from occurring or recurring;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>All actions to remove past, present, and future jeopardy; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>The date by which the entity asserts the likelihood for serious harm to any recipient or the general public will no longer exist.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>The Department’s Review of the Removal Plan.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>The OHCQ staff shall review the tissue bank's removal plan to determine if the removal plan, if implemented appropriately, will remove the likelihood that serious harm will occur, or recur.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>The OHCQ shall verify that the tissue bank has implemented the removal plan.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>The Department’s Approval of the Removal Plan. The Department shall approve the removal plan after verifying that all actions the tissue bank took were effective in removing the likelihood that serious harm or death would occur or recur.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>I.</num>
              <text>Informal Dispute Resolution (IDR).</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>A tissue bank may request an IDR to dispute one or more deficiencies in a Statement of Deficiencies.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>The tissue bank shall submit the request for an IDR to the OHCQ within 10 calendar days of receiving the Statement of Deficiencies.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>The written request for an IDR shall:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Fully describe the disagreement with the Statement of Deficiencies; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Include all accompanying evidence for the OHCQ’s consideration.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>At the discretion of the OHCQ, the IDR may be held in person, by telephone, by video conference, or in writing.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(5)</num>
                <text>IDRs are informal in nature and may not be attended by legal counsel representing the tissue bank or the Department.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(6)</num>
                <text>The IDR process may not delay the effective date of any enforcement action.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(7)</num>
                <text>In the event a tissue bank requests an IDR for a Statement of Deficiencies written by a designee of the Department, the Department shall request the designee to participate in the IDR process.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(8)</num>
                <text>There is no appeal of the Department’s decision in an IDR.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>J.</num>
              <text>Process of Filing a Complaint. The tissue bank shall have a written process that describes how donors and recipients of tissue bank services are notified of how to file a complaint with the OHCQ and, if applicable, an accreditation organization.</text>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|50|01|.09" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|50|01|.09">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.09</num>
            <heading>Tissue Bank Standards — General.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>Applicable Laws. A tissue bank shall comply with all requirements and standards in this chapter as well as with other applicable federal, State, and local laws, regulations, and rules.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>Governing Body. Unless provided by the institution of which it is a part, a tissue bank shall have a governing body consisting of individuals from various professions, that determines the scope of activities to be pursued by the tissue bank and is responsible for issues of:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Liability;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Ethical considerations;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>Fiduciary responsibility; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>Compliance with the standards and requirements of this chapter and those of the tissue bank's standard operating procedure manual.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>C.</num>
              <text>Facilities.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>General. The physical facilities of a tissue bank shall meet all applicable federal, State, and local laws, including but not limited to:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Engineering;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Fire;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>Safety;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <text>Health; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <text>Sanitation.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Physical Plant. The physical plant of a tissue bank shall be designed or arranged to meet operational needs with plumbing, drainage, lighting, ventilation, space, and handwashing facilities for personnel and donors if applicable.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>Designated Space. Personnel of a tissue bank shall perform the following critical tissue bank procedures in designated areas:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Processing;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Quarantine storage of in-process materials;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>Other quarantining;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <text>Labeling;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <text>Storage of distributable inventory;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <text>Quality assurance and control functions;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <text>Receipt and storage of containers, supplies, and reagents;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <text>Storage of medical waste;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <text>Irradiation and other sterilization procedures; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <text>Final product inspection and distribution activities.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|50|01|.10" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|50|01|.10">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.10</num>
            <heading>Tissue Bank Standards — Personnel.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>General Requirements. A tissue bank shall employ a technical director, medical director, and sufficient staff to:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Provide accurate and reliable services;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Meet all operational needs; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>Meet all statutory and regulatory requirements and standards.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>Medical Director.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Qualifications. The medical director:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Shall be a physician licensed to practice medicine by the:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <text>Maryland Board of Physicians; or</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <text>Appropriate agency in the state where the tissue bank is located; and</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Shall be qualified by training and experience in evaluating and determining donor suitability, particularly with regard to infectious diseases.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Serving as Technical Director. The medical director may serve also as the technical director if the medical director remains at the tissue bank site during the tissue bank's regular hours of operation.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>Responsibilities. The medical director shall be responsible for all medical aspects of the tissue bank's operations and shall retain overall responsibility when a task is delegated to a designated qualified employee. The medical director or the designated qualified employee shall:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Establish donor suitability criteria;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Evaluate and determine each donor's acceptability;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>Review and approve the standard operating procedures, quality assurance policies, and quality control records for medical efficacy;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <text>Approve exceptional or extraordinary releases of tissue as specified in the tissue bank's standard operating procedure manual;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <text>Establish policies and procedures regarding adverse outcomes that include requiring that all potential adverse outcomes are:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <text>Investigated;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <text>Documented;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <text>Reviewed; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <text>Reported as required by applicable federal, State, or local law;</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <text>Notify the living donor or, for a cadaveric donor, the cadaveric donor's physician for any legally allowed counseling of next of kin, of confirmed positive infectious disease test results;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <text>Notify the OHCQ in writing or electronically of each fatal adverse outcome related to:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <text>Transplantation;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <text>Transfusion;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <text>Transfer; or</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <text>Implementation of tissue; and</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <text>Establish look back and recall procedures when tissue is determined to:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <text>Be defective; or</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <text>May potentially cause an adverse outcome.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>C.</num>
              <text>Technical Director.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Qualifications. The technical director shall be qualified by training and experience for the scope of activities being pursued and have:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>A bachelor's or higher degree in medical technology or a biological science from an accredited college or university and be qualified by training and experience for the scope of activities conducted by the tissue bank;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>A bachelor’s degree in a discipline other than medical technology or a biological science from an accredited college or university and have 5 years of experience overseeing all technical aspects of tissue bank operations under the supervision of a medical director; or</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>Licensure as a registered nurse in the state that the tissue bank is operating.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Responsibilities. The technical director shall oversee and be responsible for all technical aspects of the tissue bank's operations and shall retain overall responsibility when a task is delegated to a designated qualified employee. The technical director or designated qualified employee shall:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Provide on-site supervision of tissue bank operations and personnel during the tissue bank's regular hours of operation; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Participate in and actively supervise the tissue bank's:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <text>Planning;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <text>Organization;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <text>Staffing;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <text>Training and continuing education;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(v)</num>
                    <text>Staff competency;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(vi)</num>
                    <text>Quality control and quality assurance;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(vii)</num>
                    <text>Standard operating procedures (SOPs);</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(viii)</num>
                    <text>Facilities;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(ix)</num>
                    <text>Donor selection;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(x)</num>
                    <text>Equipment;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(xi)</num>
                    <text>Products;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(xii)</num>
                    <text>Records;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(xiii)</num>
                    <text>Services; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(xiv)</num>
                    <text>Compliance with the requirements and standards of this chapter.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>D.</num>
              <text>Technical Staff.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Qualifications.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Technical staff shall possess the education, experience, and training necessary and sufficient to assure that assigned tasks are performed in accordance with the tissue bank's established procedures and the standards set forth in this chapter.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>The technical director or the designated qualified employee, and medical director or the designated qualified employee shall train individual staff to accurately and reliably:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <text>Perform tissue bank services such as collection, retrieval, processing, packaging, and cryopreservation; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <text>Document that training in the individual's employee training file.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Responsibilities.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Technical staff shall implement, maintain, and follow the policies and procedures established by the medical director and technical directors.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>A technical director or the designated qualified employee shall list and describe the duties and responsibilities of technical staff in written job descriptions.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>Technical staff shall initially, and at least annually thereafter, demonstrate documented competency in the tasks to which the staff person is assigned.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <text>Technical staff shall participate in documented training and continuing education to maintain technical competency in the duties described in their written job descriptions.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|50|01|.11" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|50|01|.11">
          <section cache:ref-path="10|50|01|.11">
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.11</num>
            <heading>Tissue Bank Standards — Testing to Minimize Disease Transmission.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>Required Testing.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>General — All Donors. A permit holder shall ensure that a prospective donor of tissue, including both leukocyte-rich and leukocyte-poor cell and tissue, intended to be used as an allograft is tested for biochemical, immunological, or serological evidence of:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Hepatitis B virus (HBV);</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Hepatitis C virus (HCV);</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>Human immunodeficiency virus type 1 (HIV-1);</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <text>Human immunodeficiency virus type 2 (HIV-2); and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <text>Treponema pallidum (syphilis).</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Specific — Donors of Specific Tissue or Cell Types.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>In addition to those tests set forth in <cite path="10|50|01|.11|A.|(1)" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">§A(1) of this regulation</cite>, a permit holder shall ensure that a prospective donor of specific types of tissue are tested in accordance with the requirements set forth in §A(2)(b)—(c) of this regulation.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Donors of Leukocyte-Rich Tissue. A permit holder shall ensure that a prospective donor of a leukocyte-rich tissue, as defined in <cite path="|10|50|01|.03|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .03B of this chapter</cite>, intended to be used as an allograft, is tested for biochemical, immunological, or serological evidence of:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <text>Human T-lymphotropic virus type I (HTLV-I);</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <text>Human T-lymphotropic virus type II (HTLV-II); and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <text>Cytomegalovirus (CMV).</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>Donors of Reproductive Tissue including Oocytes and Semen. In addition to those applicable tests set forth in §A(1) and (2)(a) of this regulation, a permit holder shall ensure that a prospective donor of reproductive tissue, as defined in <cite path="|10|50|01|.03|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .03B of this chapter</cite>, intended to be used as an allograft, is tested for biochemical, immunological, or serological evidence of:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <text>Chlamydia trachomatis; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <text>Neisseria gonorrhoeae.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>Required Laboratory Licensure.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>In-House Testing Services. A tissue bank that conducts its own testing on human specimens shall possess a Maryland license to operate a medical laboratory and comply with all applicable standards as set forth in <cite path="|10.10.01" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">COMAR 10.10.01</cite>—10.10.08.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Contractual Testing Services. A tissue bank that contracts for laboratory testing services shall obtain and maintain:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>The name and address of a contracted facility and documentation of the inclusive dates of the contract period; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Proof of the contracted facility's current:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <text>Federal certification;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <text>Required State laboratory licensure; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <text>Accreditation.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>Other Testing Services. A tissue bank that obtains test results from a noncontracted laboratory, for example, another tissue bank or an organ retrieval organization, shall obtain and maintain the name, address, and licensing and accreditation information for each laboratory from which test results are obtained for the purpose of donor assessment.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>C.</num>
              <text>Confidentiality and Release of Test Results. A technical director of a tissue bank may release results of laboratory tests performed by the tissue bank holding a medical laboratory license or performed for the tissue bank by another licensed laboratory only:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>To:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>The medical director of the tissue bank;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>An authorized person who requested the test; or</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>Another laboratory that requested the test as set forth under <cite path="10.10.06.04" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">COMAR 10.10.06.04</cite>; and</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>As allowed under the:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Maryland Confidentiality of Medical Records Act, Health-General Article, Title 4, Subtitle 3, Annotated Code of Maryland; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Federal:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <text>Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act (HIPAA), 42 U.S.C. §§1320d et seq.;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <text>Health Information Technology for Economic and Clinical Health (HITECH) Act, 42 U.S.C. §§17921 et seq.; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <text>Implementing rules and regulations for HIPAA and the HITECH Act set forth at 45 CFR Parts 160, 162, and 164.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
              </para>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|50|01|annos" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|50|01|annos">
          <annotations>
            <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health-General Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1970-07-01">Effective date: July 1, 1970</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-05-05">Regulations <cite path="|10|50|01|.01" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|50|01|.12" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">.12</cite> repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|10|50|01|.01" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|50|01|.06" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">.06</cite> adopted effective May 5, 1986 (13:9 Md. R. 1030)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-03-20"><cite path="|10|50|01|.03" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective March 20, 1989 (16:5 Md. R. 629)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-06-11"><cite path="|10|50|01|.06|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .06B</cite> amended effective June 11, 1990 (17:11 Md. R. 1343)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-06-11"><cite path="|10|50|01|.06|D." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .06D</cite> amended effective March 20, 1989 (16:5 Md. R. 629); amended and recodified to Regulation .07 effective June 11, 1990 (17:11 Md. R. 1343)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-06-11"><cite path="|10|50|01|.06|E." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .06E</cite> adopted effective March 20, 1989 (16:5 Md. R. 629); recodified to Regulation .06D effective June 11, 1990 (17:11 Md. R. 1343)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-06-11"><cite path="|10|50|01|.08" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .08</cite> adopted effective June 11, 1990 (17:11 Md. R. 1343)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-12-13" discontinuity="true"><cite path="|10.10.02" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">COMAR 10.10.02</cite> recodified to <cite path="|10.50.01" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">COMAR 10.50.01</cite> effective December 13, 1999 (26:25 Md. R. 1897)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-03-15" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|10|50|01|.01" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|50|01|.08" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">.08</cite> repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|10|50|01|.01" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|50|01|.12" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">.12</cite> adopted effective March 15, 2004 (31:5 Md. R. 449)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-15"><cite path="|10|50|01|.03|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .03B</cite> amended effective April 4, 2011 (38:7 Md. R. 432); September 15, 2025 (52:18 Md. R. 923)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-15"><cite path="|10|50|01|.04|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .04B</cite> amended effective April 4, 2011 (38:7 Md. R. 432); August 15, 2016 (43:16 Md. R. 901); September 15, 2025 (52:18 Md. R. 923)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-15"><cite path="|10|50|01|.05" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .05</cite> repealed effective September 15, 2025 (52:18 Md. R. 923)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-11-25"><cite path="|10|50|01|.06" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective November 25, 2013 (40:23 Md. R. 1934)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-15"><cite path="|10|50|01|.06" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .06</cite> repealed and new Regulation .06 adopted effective September 15, 2025 (52:18 Md. R. 923)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-15"><cite path="|10|50|01|.07|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .07B</cite> amended effective September 15, 2025 (52:18 Md. R. 923)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-15"><cite path="|10|50|01|.07|D." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .07D</cite> adopted effective September 15, 2025 (52:18 Md. R. 923)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-15"><cite path="|10|50|01|.08" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .08</cite> recodified to be Regulation .09 effective September 15, 2025 (52:18 Md. R. 923)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-15"><cite path="|10|50|01|.08" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .08</cite> adopted effective September 15, 2025 (52:18 Md. R. 923)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-15"><cite path="|10|50|01|.09" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .09</cite> repealed effective September 15, 2025 (52:18 Md. R. 923)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-15"><cite path="|10|50|01|.09" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .09</cite> recodified from Regulation .08 effective September 15, 2025 (52:18 Md. R. 923)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-15"><cite path="|10|50|01|.10" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .10</cite> amended effective September 15, 2025 (52:18 Md. R. 923)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-01-09"><cite path="|10|50|01|.10|C." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .10C</cite> amended effective January 9, 2012 (38:27 Md. R. 1764)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-15"><cite path="|10|50|01|.11|A." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .11A</cite> amended effective September 15, 2025 (52:18 Md. R. 923)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-04-04"><cite path="|10|50|01|.11|A." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .11A</cite>, C amended effective April 4, 2011 (38:7 Md. R. 432)</annotation>
          </annotations>
        </codify:replace>
      </container>
      <container>
        <num>25-124-F</num>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|53|09|.04" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|53|09|.04">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.04</num>
            <heading>Sterilization.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>Except as provided in <cite path="|10|53|09|.02|C." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .02C of this chapter</cite>, critical items, transfer forceps, and soaking receptacles shall be placed on a steel tray or rack in the center of an autoclave or heat sterilizer, separating instruments and keeping them away from the walls of the unit, and shall be sterilized according to manufacturer specifications or by:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Autoclave at the temperatures listed for the following minimum time periods after completing a heat-up period:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>15—20 minutes at 121°C (250°F), 15 psi (pounds per square inch) for unpackaged instruments; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>30 minutes at 121°C (250°F), 15 psi (pounds per square inch) for packaged instruments; or</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Dry heat, at the temperatures listed for the following minimum time periods after completing a heat-up period:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>170°C (340°F) for 1 hour; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>160°C (320°F) for 2 hours.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>Sterile critical items, transfer forceps, and soaking receptacles shall be stored in sterile covered containers until used.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>C.</num>
              <text>Transfer forceps and holding containers shall be cleaned and sterilized daily or more frequently if visibly contaminated.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>D.</num>
              <text>Unused instruments in containers and containers that have been opened shall be resterilized after a 24-hour period.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>E.</num>
              <text>Dry heat ovens and autoclaves shall be of a type registered with the federal Food and Drug Administration (FDA) and shall be cleaned, used, and maintained according to manufacturers' instructions.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>F.</num>
              <text>Sterilizers shall have visible temperature and time indicators.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>G.</num>
              <text>Chemical indicators using color change materials shall be used on or in each package to assure that each package or container has been processed through the sterilization cycle.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>H.</num>
              <text>Biological indicators shall be used no less than once a month according to manufacturers’ instructions to assure that the sterilizer is functioning properly.</text>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|53|09|annos" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|53|09|annos">
          <annotations>
            <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-205">8-205</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-6">8-6</cite>B-01—8-6B-29, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1984-01-16">Effective date: January 16, 1984 (11:1 Md. R. 45)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1991-08-05"><cite path="|10|53|09|.01" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective August 5, 1991 (18:15 Md. R. 1727)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-06-20" discontinuity="true"><cite path="|10|53|09|.01" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .01</cite>, Requirements for Instructor's License, repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|10|53|09|.01" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|53|09|.03" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">.03</cite> adopted under new chapter, Sterilization Procedures, effective June 20, 2005 (32:12 Md. R. 1047)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-08-05" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective August 5, 2024 (51:15 Md. R. 710)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-15">Regulation.04A amended effective September 15, 2025 (52:18 Md. R. 923)</annotation>
          </annotations>
        </codify:replace>
      </container>
      <container>
        <num>25-121-F</num>
        <codify:insert history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="13A|01" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="13A|01|10|.01|annos">
          <container>
            <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
            <num>10</num>
            <heading>Language Access</heading>
            <section>
              <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
              <num>.01</num>
              <heading>Scope.</heading>
              <text>The purpose of this chapter is to establish as a matter of policy and priority that parents, guardians, and caregivers are provided with a meaningful opportunity to participate in and have access to programs and services critical to their child’s education, regardless of their dominant language.</text>
            </section>
            <section>
              <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
              <num>.02</num>
              <heading>Scope.</heading>
              <text>This chapter applies to all local school systems.</text>
            </section>
            <section>
              <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
              <num>.03</num>
              <heading>Definitions.</heading>
              <para>
                <num>A.</num>
                <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>B.</num>
                <text>Terms Defined.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>“Covered languages” means the most common dominant languages other than English spoken by persons living in the county in which the local school system is located.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>“Interpretation” means the process of converting a spoken language from one language to another in a way that is culturally and linguistically appropriate, while preserving the original meaning.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <text>“Language access plan” means a document that describes how the local school system will provide services to individuals whose dominant language is not English.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <text>“Translation” means the process of converting text from one language to another while preserving the original meaning.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
            </section>
            <section>
              <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
              <num>.04</num>
              <heading>Requirements.</heading>
              <text>Each local school system shall:</text>
              <para>
                <num>A.</num>
                <text>Develop and implement a language access plan to:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>Determine the covered languages for which language services will be provided;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>Establish a process to identify, translate, and disseminate documents containing critical information regarding students’ education;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <text>Establish a process to provide interpretation services for meetings and communication with parents and guardians;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <text>Establish a plan to provide language access for families whose dominant language is not a covered language; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <text>Provide regular training sessions for translators, interpreters, school staff, and administrators;</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>B.</num>
                <text>Establish a process for users of language access services to provide feedback on the implementation of the language access plan;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>C.</num>
                <text>Track and report on the effectiveness of their language access services;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>D.</num>
                <text>Develop annual goals to improve the effectiveness of language access services;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>E.</num>
                <text>Review and revise their language access plan every two years; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>F.</num>
                <text>Update covered languages annually.</text>
              </para>
            </section>
            <annotations>
              <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|2-205">Education Article §2-205, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; Federal Statutory Reference: 42 U.S.C. § 2000d</annotation>
              <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-15">Effective date: September 15, 2025 (52:18 Md. R. 924)</annotation>
            </annotations>
          </container>
        </codify:insert>
      </container>
      <container>
        <num>25-118-F</num>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="13A|03|07|.02" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="13A|03|07|.02">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.02</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>Terms Defined.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>“Multilingual learner” has the meaning stated in COMAR 13A.05.07.02.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>“World language” means any natural language, including American Sign Language, native American languages, and languages no longer spoken (e.g., Latin and ancient Greek).</text>
              </para>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="13A|03|07|.03" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="13A|03|07|.03">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.03</num>
            <heading>Local School System Participation and Student Eligibility.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>Local School System Participation.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Participation in the program by a local public school system is voluntary.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>An individual school may not opt out of participation in a local school system program.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>Student Eligibility.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>The pool of students eligible to apply includes any public school student in a participating local school system who demonstrates proficiency in one or more languages in addition to English.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>The pool of students shall include multilingual learners and any student who has acquired or is acquiring a world language at school, home, or in the community.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="13A|03|07|.04" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="13A|03|07|.04">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.04</num>
            <heading>Demonstrating Proficiency in English and World Languages.</heading>
            <text>To receive a Maryland Seal of Biliteracy, the student shall:</text>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>Meet one of the assessment requirements from the Department’s approved list of English language arts/literacy assessments for the Maryland Seal of Biliteracy; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>Meet one of the assessment requirements from the Department’s approved list of world language assessments for the Maryland Seal of Biliteracy.</text>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:insert history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="13A|03|07" before="annos" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="13A|03|07|.06">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.06</num>
            <heading>Data Collection.</heading>
            <text>The local school system shall collect and provide data to the Department on implementation of the program, including:</text>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>The number of Seals awarded;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>The languages of the Seals awarded;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>C.</num>
              <text>The race, ethnicity, gender, and multilingual learner status of each Seal recipient; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>D.</num>
              <text>Any other demographic factors for each Seal recipient as identified by the Department.</text>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:insert>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="13A|03|07|annos" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="13A|03|07|annos">
          <annotations>
            <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">
              <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|7-208">Education Article, §7-208, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>
            </annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-02-13">Effective date: February 13, 2017 (44:3 Md. R. 189)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-15"><cite path="|13A|03|07|.02|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective September 15, 2025 (52:18 Md. R. 924)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-15"><cite path="|13A|03|07|.03" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective September 15, 2025 (52:18 Md. R. 924)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-15"><cite path="|13A|03|07|.04" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective September 15, 2025 (52:18 Md. R. 924)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-15"><cite path="|13A|03|07|.06" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .06</cite> adopted effective September 15, 2025 (52:18 Md. R. 924)</annotation>
          </annotations>
        </codify:replace>
      </container>
      <container>
        <num>25-119-F</num>
        <codify:replace history="false" path="13A|05|07|heading" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="13A|05|07">
          <heading>Programs for Multilingual Learners</heading>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" path="13A|05|07|.01" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="13A|05|07|.01">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.01</num>
            <heading>Scope.</heading>
            <text>These regulations pertain to all programs for multilingual learners (MLs) that provide instructional assistance and services to enable MLs to attain English Proficiency, develop high levels of academic language, and achieve at high levels in academic subjects so that all MLs can meet the same challenging Maryland College and Career Ready Standards that all students are expected to meet.</text>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="13A|05|07|.02" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="13A|05|07|.02">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.02</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>Terms Defined.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>“Maryland Home Language Survey” means one or more Department-approved questions posed to all parents and students upon entering a local school system in order to determine the language or languages spoken in the home.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>“Multilingual learner (ML)” has the same meaning as “English learner” as defined in 20 U.S.C. §7801(20).</text>
              </para>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="13A|05|07|.03" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="13A|05|07|.03">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.03</num>
            <heading>Programs for Multilingual Learners.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>Each local school system shall establish an English language development program for those students who have been identified as MLs by:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>The Maryland Home Language Survey; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>The Department-approved English language proficiency placement assessment.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>The English language development programs shall contain the following components:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Goals;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Student identification;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>Student placement;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>Curriculum and instruction;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(5)</num>
                <text>Certified English for Speakers of Other Languages (ESOL) teachers;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(6)</num>
                <text>Materials of instruction;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(7)</num>
                <text>Facilities;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(8)</num>
                <text>Program delivery models;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(9)</num>
                <text>Parent and community involvement;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(10)</num>
                <text>Support services;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(11)</num>
                <text>Exit criteria; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(12)</num>
                <text>Program evaluation.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>C.</num>
              <text>A student who has been identified as an ML shall:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Be placed in an English language development program; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Be evaluated each year on the appropriate Department-approved summative English language proficiency assessment in listening, speaking, reading, and writing to determine ML status.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>D.</num>
              <text>The English language development program shall include the following standards:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Multilingual learners communicate for Social and Instructional purposes within the school setting.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Multilingual learners communicate information, ideas, and concepts necessary for academic success in the content area of Language Arts.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>Multilingual learners communicate information, ideas, and concepts necessary for academic success in the content area of Mathematics.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>Multilingual learners communicate information, ideas, and concepts necessary for academic success in the content area of Science.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(5)</num>
                <text>Multilingual learners communicate information, ideas, and concepts necessary for academic success in the content area of Social Studies.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>E.</num>
              <text>Local school systems shall adopt policies and procedures to ensure that there is an English language development program and that the program meets the requirements of this chapter.</text>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="13A|05|07|.04" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="13A|05|07|.04">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.04</num>
            <heading>Funding.</heading>
            <text>The amount of State funding shall be determined annually on the basis of the number of MLs who are reported on the Enrollment Survey as of October 31.</text>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="13A|05|07|.05" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="13A|05|07|.05">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.05</num>
            <heading>Reporting Requirements.</heading>
            <text>Local school systems shall annually report to the Department their goals, objectives, and strategies regarding the performance of multilingual learners along with timelines for implementation and methods for measuring progress.</text>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="13A|05|07|annos" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="13A|05|07|annos">
          <annotations>
            <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|2-205">2-205</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|4-111">4-111</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-12-04">Effective date: December 4, 1995 (22:24 Md. R. 1901)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-15"><cite path="|13A|05|07|.01" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective October 24, 2016 (43:21 Md. R. 1168); September 15, 2025 (52:18 Md. R. 924)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-15"><cite path="|13A|05|07|.02|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective October 24, 2016 (43:21 Md. R. 1168); September 15, 2025 (52:18 Md. R. 924)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-15"><cite path="|13A|05|07|.03" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective October 24, 2016 (43:21 Md. R. 1168); September 15, 2025 (52:18 Md. R. 924)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-15"><cite path="|13A|05|07|.04" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective October 24, 2016 (43:21 Md. R. 1168); September 15, 2025 (52:18 Md. R. 924)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-15"><cite path="|13A|05|07|.05" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective October 24, 2016 (43:21 Md. R. 1168); September 15, 2025 (52:18 Md. R. 924)</annotation>
          </annotations>
        </codify:replace>
      </container>
      <container>
        <num>25-055-F</num>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="13A|12|05|.05" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="13A|12|05|.05">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.05</num>
            <heading>Supervisors of Instruction, Assistant Principals, and Principals.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>Application of Regulation.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>This regulation applies to obtaining licensure as an Administrator.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>If a principal transfers to become a principal in a special education school, the principal shall hold a Supervisor of Special Education license as set forth in <cite path="|13A|12|05|.10" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .10 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>Administrator Requirements.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>This license qualifies an individual to be assigned as a supervisor of instruction, assistant principal, or principal.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>The applicant shall have:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>A master’s degree, or higher, from an accredited institution of higher education;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Twenty-seven months of effective teaching performance or effective performance as a specialist as defined in COMAR 13A.12.04;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>Three semester hours or State-approved CPD credits in special education coursework; and</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>The applicant shall meet one of the following pathways:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>A Department-approved program which leads to licensure as a supervisor of instruction, assistant principal, or principal;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>An approved out-of-State program that leads to licensure as a supervisor of instruction, assistant principal, or principal and includes a supervised clinical practicum;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>Eighteen semester hours of graduate coursework taken at an institution of higher education, to include coursework in the following categories:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <text>Curriculum, instruction, and assessment;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <text>Supervision, evaluation, and supporting instructional improvement;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <text>Legal issues and ethical decision-making;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <text>Program/school administration;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(v)</num>
                    <text>Culturally responsive leadership and/or equity in leadership; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(vi)</num>
                    <text>Supervised clinical practicum that is a minimum of 240 clock hours; or</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <text>Holds a valid professional state license in administration from another state or country and has verification of 5 years of effective performance as an administrator in a PK-12 school setting.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>Applicants who qualify based on §3(b) or (c) of this regulation must present a qualifying score as established by the State Superintendent of Schools on a school leader licensure assessment approved by the State Board of Education.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="13A|12|05|annos" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="13A|12|05|annos">
          <annotations>
            <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|2-205">2-205</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|2-303">2-303</cite>(g), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|6-701">6-701</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|6-708">6-708</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-3">8-3</cite>A-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|03">03</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-701">8-701</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-708">8-708</cite>; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-01-01">Effective date: January 1, 1989 (15:26 Md. R. 2998)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-01-06"><cite path="|13A|12|05|.01" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective December 25, 1989 (16:25 Md. R. 2714); September 17, 1990 (17:18 Md. R. 2201); January 6, 1992 (18:26 Md. R. 2831)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-01-06"><cite path="|13A|12|05|.02" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective December 25, 1989 (16:25 Md. R. 2714); January 6, 1992 (18:26 Md. R. 2831)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-12-25"><cite path="|13A|12|05|.08|A." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .08A</cite> amended effective December 25, 1989 (16:25 Md. R. 2714)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-11-07" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|13A|12|05|.01" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">.01</cite>—<cite path="|13A|12|05|.08" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">.08</cite> repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|13A|12|05|.01" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">.01</cite>—<cite path="|13A|12|05|.08" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">.08</cite> adopted effective November 7, 1994 (21:22 Md. R. 1879)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-03-05"><cite path="|13A|12|05|.02|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective July 23, 2001 (28:14 Md. R. 1323); March 5, 2012 (39:4 Md. R. 337)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-01-20"><cite path="|13A|12|05|.02|C." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .02C</cite>, D amended effective September 23, 1996 (23:19 Md. R. 1376); January 20, 2003 (30:1 Md. R. 26)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-03-05"><cite path="|13A|12|05|.03|A." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .03A</cite> amended effective March 5, 2012 (39:4 Md. R. 337)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-08-27"><cite path="|13A|12|05|.08" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .08</cite> amended effective August 27, 2007 (34:17 Md. R. 1509)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-01-01" discontinuity="true">For a history of certification requirements before January 1, 1989, see the Administrative History for COMAR 13A.07.01.</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-04-01" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|13A|12|05|.01" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">.01</cite>—<cite path="|13A|12|05|.08" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">.08</cite> repealed under Subtitle 12 Certification Chapter 05 Suspensions and Revocations and new Regulations <cite path="|13A|12|05|.01" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">.01</cite>—<cite path="|13A|12|05|.15" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">.15</cite> adopted under Subtitle 12 Educator Licensure Chapter 05 Administrators and Supervisors effective April 1, 2024 (51:5 Md R. 231)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-15"><cite path="|13A|12|05|.05" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .05</cite> repealed and new Regulation .05 adopted effective September 15, 2025 (52:18 Md. R. 924)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-03-03"><cite path="|13A|12|05|.06|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .06B</cite> amended effective March 3, 2025 (52:4 Md. R. 220)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-03-03"><cite path="|13A|12|05|.07" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective March 3, 2025 (52:4 Md. R. 220)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-03-03"><cite path="|13A|12|05|.08|A." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .08A</cite> amended effective March 3, 2025 (52:4 Md. R. 220)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-03-03"><cite path="|13A|12|05|.10|A." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .10A</cite> amended effective March 3, 2025 (52:4 Md. R. 220)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-03-03"><cite path="|13A|12|05|.15|C." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .15C</cite> amended effective March 3, 2025 (52:4 Md. R. 220)</annotation>
          </annotations>
        </codify:replace>
      </container>
      <container>
        <num>25-009-F-I</num>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="26|12|01|.01" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="26|12|01|.01">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.01</num>
            <heading>Incorporation by Reference.</heading>
            <text>All provisions of the Regulations for the Control of Ionizing Radiation (1994) as amended by Supplement 1 through Supplement 35 are incorporated by reference.</text>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="26|12|01|annos" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="26|12|01|annos">
          <annotations>
            <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Environment Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|8-106">8-106</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|8-301">8-301</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|8-304">8-304</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1976-02-04">Effective date: February 4, 1976 (3:3 Md. R. 150)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1977-05-25"><cite path="|26|12|01|.01" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective May 25, 1977 (4:11 Md. R. 866)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1982-12-06"><cite path="|26|12|01|.01" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .01</cite> repealed and new Regulation .01 adopted effective December 6, 1982 (9:24 Md. R. 2390)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-10-09"><cite path="|26|12|01|.01" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective September 21, 1986 (13:19 Md. R. 2121); October 9, 1995 (22:20 Md. R. 1546)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" discontinuity="true"><cite path="10.14.02.01" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">COMAR 10.14.02.01</cite> recodified to <cite path="26.12.01.01" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">COMAR 26.12.01.01</cite></annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-15"><cite path="|26|12|01|.01" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective December 16, 1996 (23:25 Md. R. 1787); November 3, 1997 (24:22 Md. R. 1552); June 29, 1998 (25:13 Md. R. 997); December 28, 1998 (25:26 Md. R. 1926); June 14, 1999 (26:12 Md. R. 926); February 7, 2000 (27:2 Md. R. 149); April 1, 2002 (29:6 Md. R. 570); October 13, 2003 (30:20 Md. R. 1448); October 27, 2003 (30:21 Md. R. 1530); March 29, 2004 (31:6 Md. R. 510); June 7, 2004 (31:11 Md. R. 858); June 20, 2005 (32:12 Md. R. 1048); December 8, 2005 (32:24 Md. R. 1906); October 9, 2006 (33:20 Md. R. 1617); December 17, 2007 (34:25 Md. R. 2216); June 15, 2009 (36:12 Md. R. 839); November 15, 2010 (37:23 Md. R. 1612); November 15, 2010 (37:23 Md. R. 1612); September 19, 2011 (38:19 Md. R. 1148); August 6, 2012 (39:15 Md. R. 965); October 29, 2012 (39:21 Md., R. 1380); January 6, 2014 (40:26 Md. R. 2165); September 15, 2014 (41:18 Md. R. 1011); January 19, 2015 (42:1 Md. R. 19); June 22, 2015 (42:12 Md. R. 764); September 14, 2015 (42:18 Md. R. 1180); October 26, 2015 (42:21 Md. R. 1303); November 24, 2016 (43:23 Md. R. 1281); May 21, 2018 (45:10 Md. R. 504); February 22, 2021 (48:4 Md. R. 178); December 27, 2021 (48:26 Md. R. 1113); December 12, 2022 (49:12 Md. R. 1052)​; August 7, 2023 (50:15 Md. R. 683); August 19, 2024 (51:16 Md. R. 744); September 15, 2025 (52:18 Md. R. 924)</annotation>
          </annotations>
        </codify:replace>
      </container>
    </container>
  </container>
</document>
