<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Maryland Register, Volume 52, Issue 19" codify:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">
  <num>52-19</num>
  <meta>
    <stub/>
    <effective>2025-09-29</effective>
    <citations>
      <citation type="register" url="./52-19.pdf">52:19</citation>
    </citations>
    <history>
      <published>2025-09-19</published>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <container name="regulations">
    <container name="final">
      <container>
        <num>25-016-F</num>
        <codify:insert history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="09|14" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="09|14|18|.01|annos">
          <container>
            <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
            <num>18</num>
            <heading>Muay Thai Regulations — Professional</heading>
            <section>
              <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
              <num>.01</num>
              <heading>Applicable Boxing Regulations.</heading>
              <text>Unless otherwise indicated, the regulations in this subtitle pertaining to the sport of boxing shall apply to the sport of Professional Muay Thai.</text>
            </section>
            <section>
              <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
              <num>.02</num>
              <heading>Definitions.</heading>
              <para>
                <num>A.</num>
                <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated and, unless otherwise indicated, the regulations in this subtitle pertaining to the sport of boxing shall apply to the sport of Professional Muay Thai.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>B.</num>
                <text>Terms Defined.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>"Commission" means the State Athletic Commission of Maryland.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>“Contest” means any Muay Thai:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <text>Competition;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <text>Match;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <text>Performance; or</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(d)</num>
                    <text>Show.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <text>“Contestant” means a Muay Thai fighter who participates against an opponent in a contest.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <text>Manager.</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <text>“Manager” means a person who, under contract, agreement, or other arrangement, undertakes to control or administer, directly or indirectly, a Muay Thai contest-related matter on behalf of a contestant.</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <text>“Manager” includes, but is not limited to:</text>
                    <para>
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <text>A booking agent; and</text>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <text>An advisor.</text>
                    </para>
                  </para>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <text>“Muay Thai” means a competition in which contestants use interdisciplinary forms of fighting, including striking with the hands, feet, knees, or elbows.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(6)</num>
                  <text>“Official record” means the cumulative results of Muay Thai contests, sanctioned by a regulatory agency, in which a contestant has participated.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(7)</num>
                  <text>“Promoter” means an individual, partnership, corporation, club, association or other organization that gives, holds, or otherwise conducts a Muay Thai contest within the State.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(8)</num>
                  <text>“Regulatory agency” means a commission, board, or other entity of a state, commonwealth, territory, or country, created by law or executive order, which regulates Muay Thai contests.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(9)</num>
                  <text>“Second” means an individual who assists a Muay Thai contestant during a contest.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
            </section>
            <section>
              <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
              <num>.03</num>
              <heading>Weights and Classes.</heading>
              <para>
                <num>A.</num>
                <text>The Commission recognizes the following weights and classes in Professional Muay Thai:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>Mini-Flyweight up to and including 105 pounds</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>Light-Flyweight over 105 to 108 pounds;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <text>Flyweight over 108 to 112 pounds;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <text>Super-Flyweight over 112 to 115 pounds;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <text>Bantamweight over 115 to 118 pounds;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(6)</num>
                  <text>Super-Bantamweight over 118 to 122 pounds;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(7)</num>
                  <text>Featherweight over 122 to 126 pounds;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(8)</num>
                  <text>Super-Featherweight over 126 to 130 pounds;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(9)</num>
                  <text>Lightweight over 130 to 135 pounds;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(10)</num>
                  <text>Super Lightweight over 135 to 140 pounds ;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(11)</num>
                  <text>Welterweight over 140 to 147 pounds;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(12)</num>
                  <text>Super-Welterweight over 147 to 154 pounds;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(13)</num>
                  <text>Middleweight over 154 to 160 pounds;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(14)</num>
                  <text>Super Middleweight over 160 to 168 pounds;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(15)</num>
                  <text>Light Heavyweight over 168 to 175 pounds;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(16)</num>
                  <text>Cruiserweight over 175 to 200 pounds;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(17)</num>
                  <text>Heavyweight over 200 to 225 pounds; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(18)</num>
                  <text>Super Heavyweight over 225 pounds</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>B.</num>
                <text>If a Muay Thai contestant’s weight is greater than the specified weight in the promoter-contestant contract, the contest may not take place without special permission of the Commission.</text>
              </para>
            </section>
            <section>
              <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
              <num>.04</num>
              <heading>Muay Thai Contestants Equipment.</heading>
              <para>
                <num>A.</num>
                <text>General. Each Muay Thai contestant shall use the equipment, and in the manner, specified in this regulation.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>B.</num>
                <text>Bandage. For all weight classes, bandages shall be:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>A maximum of one roll (no more than 2 inches wide and 20 yards in length) of white, soft, cloth gauze is permitted per hand;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>A maximum of one roll (no more than 2 inches wide and 10 feet in length) of white athletic tape is permitted per hand, which shall:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <text>Be placed directly on each hand for protection near the wrist;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <text>Cross the back of the hand twice but may not extend within three-fourths of an inch of the knuckles when the hand is clenched to make a fist;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <text>Placed between the fingers; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(d)</num>
                    <text>Not be allowed to cover the knuckles.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <text>Placed on a Muay Thai contestant’s hands in the dressing room in the presence of the chief second of the Muay Thai contestant’s opponent; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <text>Be inspected and approved by the Commission prior to the gloves being placed on the hands of the Muay Thai contestant.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>C.</num>
                <text>Gloves. Gloves worn by each Muay Thai contestant during the contest shall:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>Be open-fingered;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>Conform to specifications as determined by the Commission;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <text>Weigh 8 ounces from weight classes Mini-Flyweight to Super-Welterweight; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <text>Weigh 10 ounces from weight classes Middleweight to Super-Heavyweight.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>D.</num>
                <text>A mouth guard shall be approved by the Commission.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>E.</num>
                <text>Groin protection shall be approved by the Commission.</text>
              </para>
            </section>
            <section>
              <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
              <num>.05</num>
              <heading>Proper Attire and Appearance.</heading>
              <para>
                <num>A.</num>
                <text>Rules for Shorts/trunks Worn in Competition.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>Fighters shall wear shorts approved by the Commission;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>Rules for male and female fighters are the same.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <text>The hem of trunks shall not extend below the mid-thigh;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <text>Long pants or leggings are prohibited.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <text>Compression shorts may be worn under the approved fight trunks, but they may not extend down the leg below the bottom of the trunks.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>B.</num>
                <text>Male fighters shall not wear any form of clothing on their upper body.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>C.</num>
                <text>Clothing Rules for Female Fighters.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>Female fighters shall wear short sleeved (above the elbow) or sleeveless form fitting rash guard and or sports bra.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>No loose-fitting tops shall be allowed.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <text>The use of breast protectors is optional for female fighters as determined by the Commission.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <text>Female fighters shall follow the same requirements for bottom coverings as male fighters, minus the requirement for groin protection.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>D.</num>
                <text>No clothing worn in the ring shall have exposed Velcro, clasps, pockets, zippers, or other items that may be harmful to the fighter or their opponent.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>E.</num>
                <text>Fighters shall not wear shoes in the cage or ring.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>F.</num>
                <text>When deemed necessary by the referee, or Commission, all fighters shall have their hair secured in a manner that does not interfere with the vision and safety of either fighter.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>G.</num>
                <text>No object can be worn to secure the fighter’s hair which may cause injury to their opponent.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>H.</num>
                <text>The wearing of jewelry will be strictly prohibited during all contests.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>I.</num>
                <text>Fighters may wear an inscribed cloth, an amulet, or an inscribed charm around the upper arm or strung around the waist, but neatly wrapped and covered with cloth.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>J.</num>
                <text>Wrapping the ankles or legs with pieces of cloth is prohibited.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>K.</num>
                <text>If during the contest, the Pra Jiad (arm band) loosens or moves in a way that may be harmful, or a distraction, it may be removed at the discretion of the referee.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>L.</num>
                <text>Cosmetics</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>Body cosmetics are any product applied to the body for cleansing, beautifying, or altering appearance and shall be prohibited during all contests.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>Facial cosmetics are products used improve the appearance of the face, and. the use of such products shall be at the discretion of the Commission and/or referee.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>M.</num>
                <text>Protective Garments.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>Other than the fighter’s hands, as previously listed, there will be no taping, covering, or protective gear of any kind on the upper body, which includes but is not limited to:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <text>Joint sleeves;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <text>Padding; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <text>Any form of brace or body gauze/tape.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>Ankle joint sleeves:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <text>A fighter may use one soft neoprene type sleeves to cover each ankle joint; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <text>Approved sleeves may not have padding, Velcro, plastic, metal, ties, or any other material considered to be unsafe or that may create an unfair advantage.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>N.</num>
                <text>Tape and gauze, or any materials other than the approved sleeves, are not permitted on the lower body.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>O.</num>
                <text>The allowable length and color of sleeves shall be determined by the Commission.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>P.</num>
                <text>A Muay Thai contestant shall have properly trimmed fingernails and toenails.</text>
              </para>
            </section>
            <section>
              <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
              <num>.06</num>
              <heading>Fighting Area.</heading>
              <para>
                <num>A.</num>
                <text>A Muay Thai contest shall be held in a ring or in a fenced area.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>B.</num>
                <text>A ring used for a Muay Thai contest shall meet the following requirements.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>The ring may not be smaller than 20 feet square and may not be larger than 32 feet square within the ropes.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>The ring floor shall:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <text>Extend at least 18 inches beyond the ropes;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <text>Be padded with Ensolite or another similar closed-cell foam, with at least a 1-inch layer of foam padding, which shall extend beyond the ring ropes and over the edge of the platform;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <text>Have a top covering of canvas, duck, or similar material that:</text>
                    <para>
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <text>Does not tend to gather in lumps or ridges; and</text>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <text>Is tightly stretched and laced to the ring platform; and</text>
                    </para>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(d)</num>
                    <text>Be free of any obstruction or object, including a triangular border;</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <text>The ring platform:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <text>May not be more than 4 feet above the floor of the building; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <text>Shall have suitable steps for the use of the Muay Thai contestant;</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <text>The ring posts:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <text>Shall be made of metal;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <text>May not be more than 3 inches in diameter, extending from the floor of the building to a minimum height of 58 inches above the ring floor;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <text>Shall be at least 18 inches away from the ring ropes; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(d)</num>
                    <text>Shall be properly padded in a manner approved by the Commission.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <text>The ring ropes:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <text>Shall be five in number;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <text>May not be less than 1 inch in diameter;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <text>Shall be wrapped in soft material; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(d)</num>
                    <text>Shall be at least 12 inches above the ring floor.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>C.</num>
                <text>A fenced area used for a contest of mixed martial arts shall meet the following requirements:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>The fenced area shall be circular or have at least four equal sides.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>The fenced area may not be smaller than 20 feet wide and may not be larger than 32 feet wide in diameter.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <text>The floor of the fenced area shall:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <text>Be padded with Ensolite or another similar closed-cell foam, with at least a 1-inch layer of foam padding; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <text>Have a top covering of canvas, duck, or similar material that:</text>
                    <para>
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <text>. Does not tend to gather in lumps or ridges; and</text>
                      <text>(ii.) Is tightly stretched and laced to the platform of the fenced area.</text>
                    </para>
                  </para>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <text>The platform of the fenced area:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <text>May not be more than 4 feet above the floor of the building; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <text>Shall have suitable steps for the use of the Muay Thai contestants.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <text>The fence posts of the fenced area shall be:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <text>Made of metal, not more than 6 inches in diameter, extending from the floor of the building to between 5 and 7 feet above the floor of the fenced area; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <text>Properly padded in a manner approved by the Commission.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(6)</num>
                  <text>The fencing used to enclose the fenced area shall be made of a material that will prevent a Muay Thai contestant from falling out of, or breaking through, the fenced area onto the floor of the building or onto the spectators.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(7)</num>
                  <text>Any metal portion of the fenced area shall be covered and padded in a manner approved by the Commission and may not be abrasive to the Muay Thai contestant.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(8)</num>
                  <text>The fenced area shall have two entrances.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(9)</num>
                  <text>There may not be any obstruction on any part of the fence surrounding the area where Muay Thai Contestant are to be competing.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
            </section>
            <section>
              <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
              <num>.07</num>
              <heading>Rounds.</heading>
              <para>
                <num>A.</num>
                <text>Each round shall be 3 minutes in duration, with a 1 minute rest period between rounds.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>B.</num>
                <text>Bouts shall ordinarily be scheduled for either three or five rounds.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>C.</num>
                <text>When a tournament and/or another format is approved, the total number of rounds allowed to be contested in a day shall be determined by the Commission.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>D.</num>
                <text>At the discretion of the Commission, bouts will begin after the completion of any pre-fight rituals, in accordance with Thai traditions.</text>
              </para>
            </section>
            <section>
              <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
              <num>.08</num>
              <heading>Referee.</heading>
              <para>
                <num>A.</num>
                <text>The referee is the sole arbiter of a bout.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>B.</num>
                <text>The referee and/or the ringside physician are the only individuals authorized to stop the contest, as determined by the Commission.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>C.</num>
                <text>The referee shall confirm with the fighter that the mouthpiece is inserted and shall confirm with male fighters that a groin protector is inserted before the start of the contest.</text>
              </para>
            </section>
            <section>
              <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
              <num>.09</num>
              <heading>Knockdown.</heading>
              <para>
                <num>A.</num>
                <text>In the event of a knockdown the referee shall send the standing fighter to a neutral corner and administer a mandatory eight count to the downed fighter.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>B.</num>
                <text>When a fighter is knocked through the ropes and off the platform of the ring and onto a table or the floor by a legal blow or blows, the fighter will receive a mandatory 18 count and must be standing before the count of 20.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>C.</num>
                <text>There is no standing eight count.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>D.</num>
                <text>A fighter who has been knocked down cannot be saved by the bell in any round, including the final round.</text>
              </para>
            </section>
            <section cache:ref-path="09|14|18|.10">
              <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
              <num>.10</num>
              <heading>Method of Judging.</heading>
              <para>
                <num>A.</num>
                <text>Judges shall consider damage, domination, and duration when evaluating the relative merits of each fighter’s performance in each round. Towards that end they shall use the following prioritized criteria to establish their score.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>A fighter who has an advantage in the number or quality of knockdowns in a round shall never lose that round.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>If there is no advantage in knockdowns, the fighter with a clear advantage in cumulative damage shall win the round.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <text>If there is not a clear advantage in cumulative damage, the fighter with the greater number and/or variety of clean scoring Muay Thai techniques shall win the round.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>B.</num>
                <text>If the criteria in <cite path="09|14|18|.10|A." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">§A of this regulation</cite> fails to distinguish either fighter, the round may be awarded to the fighter who was more successful in applying either aggressiveness, control or effective defense in their efforts to win the round.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>C.</num>
                <text>All bouts will be evaluated and scored by a minimum of three judges.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>D.</num>
                <text>The 10 Point Must System will be the standard system for scoring a bout.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>Under the 10 Point Must Scoring System, ten points must be awarded to the winner of the round.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>The fighter who has lost the round may be awarded nine or less points depending on the margin of advantage.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <text>In the very rare case that neither fighter has shown even a marginal advantage, a 10-10 round may be awarded.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <text>Partial or incomplete rounds shall be scored. If no significant action has occurred, the round shall be scored as 10-10. This is at the discretion of the judges.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <text>Any time the referee penalizes either fighter, then the appropriate points shall be deducted when the scorekeeper calculates the final score including partial rounds.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>E.</num>
                <text>The following objective scoring criteria shall be utilized by the judges when scoring a round:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>An extremely rare 10-10 round is not a score to be used as an excuse by a judge that cannot assess the differences in the action of a round. It should only be used to score an incomplete round where nothing occurred in the round.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>A round is to be scored as a 10-9 round when there is a slight or clear advantage in overall action favoring one fighter, but not an overwhelming advantage.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <text>A round is to be scored as a 10-8 round when there is an overwhelming advantage without a knockdown, or a fighter won the round and scored a knockdown.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <text>A round is to be scored as a 10-7 round when a fighter won the round and scored two knockdowns.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <text>A round is to be scored as a 10-6 round when a fighter won the round and scored three knockdowns.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
            </section>
            <section>
              <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
              <num>.11</num>
              <heading>Permissible Strikes.</heading>
              <text>The following strikes are permitted during a contest:</text>
              <para>
                <num>A.</num>
                <text>Punches;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>B.</num>
                <text>Kicks;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>C.</num>
                <text>Knees; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>D.</num>
                <text>Elbows.</text>
              </para>
            </section>
            <section>
              <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
              <num>.12</num>
              <heading>Fouls.</heading>
              <para>
                <num>A.</num>
                <text>The following acts are prohibited:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>Head butts;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>Groin strikes;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <text>Thumbing or eye gouging;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <text>Biting;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <text>Spiting at the opponent;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(6)</num>
                  <text>Hair pulling;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(7)</num>
                  <text>Attacks to the throat;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(8)</num>
                  <text>Striking your opponent while grounded;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(9)</num>
                  <text>Strikes directed to the back of the head or the spine;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(10)</num>
                  <text>Tripping or sweeping an opponent;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(11)</num>
                  <text>Hip, shoulder, or leg throws;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(12)</num>
                  <text>Grasping the opponent’s lower back while also forcing an opponent's spine to hyperextend;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(13)</num>
                  <text>Intentionally falling on a downed opponent, pressing elbow or knee upon the opponent;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(14)</num>
                  <text>Wrestling, back or arm locks or any similar judo or wrestling hold;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(15)</num>
                  <text>Attempting to pile-drive an opponent's head into the canvas;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(16)</num>
                  <text>Catching an opponent's kick and pushing an opponent for more than one step in any direction without attempting to deliver an attacking technique;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(17)</num>
                  <text>If a fighter’s leg is caught while kicking, the opponent may not intentionally ground themselves;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(18)</num>
                  <text>Striking a downed fighter or fighter entangled in the ropes;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(19)</num>
                  <text>Failure to obey the referee’s commands;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(20)</num>
                  <text>Striking on a break;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(21)</num>
                  <text>Striking after a bell;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(22)</num>
                  <text>Holding the ropes/cage or using the ropes/cage while striking or clinching;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(23)</num>
                  <text>Holding the opponent’s shorts;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(24)</num>
                  <text>Timidity or causing intentional delays in the action;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(25)</num>
                  <text>Unsportsmanlike behavior including use of abusive language and/or gestures; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(26)</num>
                  <text>Attacking an opponent who is under the care of the referee.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>B.</num>
                <text>Time Considerations for Fouls.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>Low Blow.</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <text>A fighter who has been struck with a low blow as called by the referee, is allowed up to 5 minutes to recover from the foul, as long as, in the ringside physician’s opinion, the fighter may possibly continue on in the contest.</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <text>If the fighter states that they can continue before the 5 minutes of time have expired, the referee shall restart the fight as soon as practical.</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <text>If the fighter goes over the 5 minutes time allotment, the fight cannot be restarted and the contest must come to an end with the outcome determined by how the low blow occurred the round, and time in which the fight was stopped.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>Eye Poke.</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <text>A fighter, who has received an eye poke as called by the referee, is allowed up to 5 minutes to recover from the foul as long as the ringside physician confirms the fighter may possibly continue in the contest once recovered.</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <text>If the fighter states that they can see and wishes to continue before the 5 minutes of time have expired, and confirmed by the ringside physician, the referee shall restart the fight as soon as practical.</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <text>If the fighter goes over the 5 minutes time allotment, the fight cannot be restarted and the contest must come to an end with the outcome determined by how the eye poke occurred, the round, and time in which the fight was stopped.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>C.</num>
                <text>Intentional Fouls.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>If an intentional foul causes an injury, and the injury is severe enough to terminate the bout immediately, the fighter causing the injury shall lose by disqualification.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>If an intentional foul causes an injury and the bout is allowed to continue, the referee shall notify the authorities and deduct two points from the fighter who caused the foul. Point deductions for intentional fouls will be mandatory.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <text>If an injury caused by an intentional foul results in the contest being stopped in any round after half of the scheduled rounds have been completed, by either another legal or illegal strike, the judges will score the incomplete round and:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <text>If the injured fighter is ahead on the scorecards, he shall be declared the winner by a Technical Decision; or</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <text>If the injured fighter is behind or even on the scorecards, the contest shall be declared a Technical Draw.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <text>If a fighter injures themselves while attempting to intentionally foul their opponent, but is able to continue fighting, the referee shall take no action and treat the injury as if produced by a fair blow. If the referee determined the fighter who injured themselves is unable to continue, that fighter will lose by Technical Knockout/Knockout.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>D.</num>
                <text>Accidental Fouls.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>If an accidental foul causes an injury severe enough for the referee to terminate the bout immediately, the bout will result in either a No Contest or Disqualification if stopped before:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <text>A completed 2 rounds of a scheduled 3 round bout; or</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <text>A completed 3 rounds of a scheduled 5 round bout.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>If an accidental foul causes an injury severe enough for the referee to terminate the bout, the bout will result in a Technical Decision awarded to the fighter who is ahead on the score cards at the time the bout is stopped immediately, after:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <text>A completed 2 rounds of a scheduled 3 round bout; or</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <text>A completed 3 rounds of a scheduled 5 round bout.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <text>If a fighter, during the course of a round, visibly loses control of bodily function (vomit, urine, feces), the fight shall be stopped by the referee and the fighter shall lose the contest by a Technical Knockout (TKO) due to Medical Stoppage.</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <text>In the event a loss of bodily function occurs in the rest period between rounds, the ringside physician shall be called in to evaluate if the fighter can continue. If the fighter is not cleared by the ringside physician to continue, that fighter shall lose by a Technical Knockout (TKO) due to Medical Stoppage</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <text>If fecal matter becomes apparent at any time, the contest shall be halted by the referee, and the offending fighter shall lose by a Technical Knockout (TKO) due to Medical Stoppage.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
              </para>
            </section>
            <section>
              <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
              <num>.13</num>
              <heading>Result of the Contest.</heading>
              <para>
                <num>A.</num>
                <text>The winner of the match may be decided in the following ways:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>Points Decision.</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <text>Unanimous Decision—when all three judges score the bout for the same fighter;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <text>Split Decision—when two judges score the bout for one fighter and one judge scores the bout for the opponent;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <text>Majority Decision—when two judges score the bout for one fighter and one judge scores the bout a draw;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(d)</num>
                    <text>Technical Decision—when a bout is prematurely stopped due to injury from an accidental foul and a fighter is leading on the score cards.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>Draws occur when:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <text>Unanimous Draw—when all three judges score the bout a draw;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <text>Majority Draw—when two judges score the bout a draw;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <text>Split Draw—when one judge scores the bout for one fighter, one judge scores the bout for the opponent, and one judge scores the bout a draw;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(d)</num>
                    <text>Technical Draw—when an injury is sustained during competition as a result of an intentional foul and the bout is allowed to continue, then later the injury requires stoppage from either a legal or illegal strike to the affected area; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(e)</num>
                    <text>Draw—when both fighters go down at the same time, and neither can resume the fight within the referee’s ten count.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <text>Knockouts occur when a fighter is incapable of resuming the fight within the referee’s ten-count due to legal strikes or the referee stops the contest because a fighter cannot effectively defend themselves.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <text>Technical Knockouts occur when:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <text>Referee Stoppage occurs when a referee terminates a contest if:</text>
                    <para>
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <text>The referee determines a fighter shows no will to or is incapable of resuming the fight due to a legal technique;</text>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <text>The referee determines the fighter is not effectively defending themselves;</text>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <text>The fighter does not leave their corner to take part in the fight following the sounding of the bell; or</text>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <num>(iv)</num>
                      <text>The referee is of the opinion that one fighter is outmatched by the opponent and continuing the match would jeopardize the fighter’s health and safety;</text>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <num>(v)</num>
                      <text>A fighter or their corner indicates to the referee or regulatory representative they no longer wish to continue the contest.</text>
                    </para>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <text>Medical Stoppage occurs when a ringside physician terminates a contest if:</text>
                    <para>
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <text>The bout is terminated for medical reasons due to injury resulting from a legal technique.</text>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <text>The bout is terminated on the advice of the ringside physician.</text>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <text>There is a loss of control of bodily function.</text>
                    </para>
                  </para>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <text>Disqualification occurs when an injury sustained during the bout as a result of an intentional foul is severe enough to terminate the bout, multiple fouls have been assessed, interference from a fighter’s corner, and/or there is a flagrant disregard for the rules and/or referee’s commands.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>B.</num>
                <text>No Decision/No Contest occurs when:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>When a bout is prematurely stopped due to an accidental injury and a sufficient number of rounds have not been completed to render a decision via the scorecards.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>If the referee decides both fighters must be disqualified.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
            </section>
            <annotations>
              <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Business Regulations Article, §§4-205, 4-301, and 4-303, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
              <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-29">Effective date: September 29, 2025 (52:19 Md. R. 956)</annotation>
            </annotations>
          </container>
        </codify:insert>
      </container>
      <container>
        <num>25-123-F</num>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|32|06|.02" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|32|06|.02">
          <section cache:ref-path="10|32|06|.02">
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.02</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>Terms Defined.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>“Board” means the State Board of Physicians.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>“Board eligible” means a physician’s status that starts upon completion of all the requirements to take a sleep medicine certifying examination and lasts for a limited period of time, as determined by the American Board of Medical Specialties or the American Osteopathic Association.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>“Capnography” means measurement of the amount of CO<sub>2</sub> being eliminated from the lungs.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>“Committee” means the Polysomnography Professional Standards Committee established under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|14-5">Health Occupations Article, §14-5</cite>C-05, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(5)</num>
                <text>“Direct supervision” means supervision by a licensed physician who is physically present on the premises while services are provided.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(6)</num>
                <text>“Electroencephalography” means a test that measures the electrical activity of the brain as recorded by electrodes placed on the scalp.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(7)</num>
                <text>“Electromyography” means a test that measures the electrical activity of the muscles.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(8)</num>
                <text>“Electrooculography” means a test that measures the movements of the eye.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(9)</num>
                <text>“Enrolled in a sleep technologist educational program” means that a student has started the Accredited Sleep Technology Program self-study online modules developed by the American Academy of Sleep Medicine but has not completed the final self-study module.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(10)</num>
                <text>“General supervision” means supervision by a licensed physician who is available to give immediately available direction, either in person, by telephone, or by electronic means.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(11)</num>
                <text>“License” means a license issued by the Board.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(12)</num>
                <text>“Licensed polysomnographic technologist” means an individual licensed by the Board to practice polysomnography under the supervision of a licensed physician.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(13)</num>
                <text>“Licensed physician” means an individual who is licensed by the Board to practice medicine.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(14)</num>
                <text>“Oximetry” means a test that measures the concentration of oxygen in the blood.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(15)</num>
                <text>“PH probe” means a device to measure the acidity of the esophagus.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(16)</num>
                <text>“Plethysmography” means a test to measure changes in blood flow or air volume in different parts of the body.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(17)</num>
                <text>“Practice polysomnography” means:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Monitoring and recording physiologic data during sleep, including sleep-related respiratory disturbances, under the supervision of a licensed physician; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Using the data collected under <cite path="10|32|06|.02|B.|(17)|(a)" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">§B(17)(a) of this regulation</cite> for the purposes of assisting a licensed physician in the diagnosis and treatment of sleep and wake disorders.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(18)</num>
                <text>“Registered polysomnographic technologist” means a polysomnographic technologist who is registered by the Board of Registered Polysomnographic Technologists.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(19)</num>
                <text>“Student” means an individual who is:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Enrolled in an accredited educational program in order to qualify for a license as a polysomnographic technologist; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Performing polysomnography services within the accredited program under the supervision of a licensed physician and without compensation.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(20)</num>
                <text>“Supervision” means general supervision or direct supervision of a licensed polysomnographic technologist by a licensed physician.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|32|06|.04" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|32|06|.04">
          <section cache:ref-path="10|32|06|.04">
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.04</num>
            <heading>Application for Initial Licensure as a Polysomnographic Technologist.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>An applicant shall:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Complete an application on a form supplied by the Board;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Pay the required application fee set by the Board in <cite path="|10|32|06|.09" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .09 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>Be 18 years old or older;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>Be of good moral character;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(5)</num>
                <text>Demonstrate spoken and written competency in English by any of the following:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Documentation of graduation from a recognized English-speaking high school or undergraduate school after at least 3 years of enrollment;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Documentation of graduation from a recognized English-speaking professional school; or</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>Documentation of receiving a grade of at least:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <text>26 on the "Speaking Section" of the Internet-based Test of English as a Foreign Language; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <text>79 on the Internet-based Test of English as a Foreign Language;</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(6)</num>
                <text>Provide documentation of current certification as a registered polysomnographic technologist by the Board of Registered Polysomnographic Technologists or by another national certification agency approved by the Board;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(7)</num>
                <text>Provide documentation of licensure, certification, or registration from all states where the applicant has ever held a license, certificate, or registration in any health profession; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(8)</num>
                <text>Meet the requirements of <cite path="10|32|06|.04|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>An applicant shall meet the requirements of one of the following pathways to licensure:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Graduation from a polysomnographic educational program that is accredited by the Commission on Accreditation of Allied Health Education Programs;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>In regard to a respiratory care educational program:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Graduation from a respiratory care educational program that is accredited by the Commission on Accreditation of Allied Health Education Programs; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Completion of the Committee on Accreditation for Respiratory Care’s curriculum for a polysomnography certificate that is accredited by the Commission on Accreditation of Allied Health Education Programs;</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>In regard to an electroneurodiagnostic technology educational program:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Graduation from an electroneurodiagnostic technology educational program that is accredited by the Commission on Accreditation of Allied Health Education Programs; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Completion of an add-on track in polysomnography for electroneurodiagnostic technologists that is accredited by the Commission on Accreditation of Allied Health Education Programs; or</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>In regard to a sleep technologist educational program, completion of the requirements of <cite path="10|32|06|.04|C." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">§C of this regulation</cite>.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>C.</num>
              <text>An applicant who has graduated from a sleep technologist education program accredited by the American Academy of Sleep Medicine shall:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Provide proof of meeting core competencies in the 3 years preceding the date of the submission of the licensure application as assessed by a sleep technologist credentialed as a Registered Polysomnographic Technologist, a sleep technologist with national certification approved by the Board, or a physician who is either board-eligible or board-certified in sleep medicine by the American Board of Sleep Medicine, American Board of Medical Specialties, or American Osteopathic Association;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Provide a letter of attestation for completion of clinical hours and competencies from a physician who is either board-eligible or board-certified in sleep medicine by the American Board of Sleep Medicine, American Board of Medical Specialties, or American Osteopathic Association where the applicant practiced; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>Provide proof of completion of a minimum of 546 hours of clinical experience in the 3 years preceding the date of the submission of the licensure application as either:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>A student enrolled in a sleep technologist educational program supervised at a sleep laboratory accredited by the American Academy of Sleep Medicine or The Joint Commission by:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <text>A sleep technologist credentialed as a Registered Polysomnographic Technologist;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <text>A sleep technologist with national certification approved by the Board; or</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <text>A licensed physician who is either board-eligible or board-certified in sleep medicine by the American Board of Sleep Medicine, American Board of Medical Specialties, or American Osteopathic Association; or</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>A sleep technologist with a current, active, unrestricted license in another state or is otherwise recognized and has practiced as a sleep technologist in another state who has:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <text>Full-time practice experience as a sleep technologist in another state at a sleep laboratory accredited by the American Academy of Sleep Medicine or The Joint Commission for a minimum of 6 months in the 3 years preceding the date of the submission of the licensure application; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <text>Completed at least 30 hours of approved continuing education in the 3 years preceding the date of the submission of the licensure application.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
              </para>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|32|06|.06" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|32|06|.06">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.06</num>
            <heading>Identification as Polysomnographic Technologist; Notice of Name or Address Change.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>A licensed polysomnographic technologist shall wear an identification tag or a badge displaying in readily visible type that the individual is a licensed polysomnographic technologist.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>An individual may not identify himself or herself as a polysomnographic technologist unless the individual is licensed by the Board.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>C.</num>
              <text>Change of Name or Address.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>A licensed polysomnographic technologist shall advise the Board in writing of any change in name or mailing address within 60 days.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>The Board may impose a fine of $100 for failure to notify the Board of a change in name or mailing address.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|32|06|.07" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|32|06|.07">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.07</num>
            <heading>Renewal and Reinstatement.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>Renewal.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>The Board may not renew a license until the Comptroller of Maryland has verified that the individual has paid all undisputed taxes and unemployment insurance contributions, or arranged for repayment.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>An individual who has been licensed by the Board as a polysomnographic technologist may renew the license on or before the date specified by the Board by:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Submitting a renewal application on a form supplied by the Board;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Paying the required renewal fee set by the Board in <cite path="|10|32|06|.09" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .09 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>Attesting to the completion of at least 20 hours of approved continuing education, earned during the 2-year period preceding the expiration of the license, as specified in <cite path="|10|32|06|.08" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .08 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <text>Meeting any other requirement set by the Board.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>Reinstatement. The Board shall reinstate the license of a polysomnographic technologist if the polysomnographic technologist:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Completes a reinstatement application on a form supplied by the Board;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Pays the required reinstatement fee and any other fees specified in <cite path="|10|32|06|.09" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .09 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>Documents evidence of completion of at least 20 hours of approved continuing education in the 2-year period preceding the date of the submission of the application for reinstatement, as specified in <cite path="|10|32|06|.08" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .08 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>Meets any additional requirements set by the Board for reinstatement of a license.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|32|06|.09" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|32|06|.09">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.09</num>
            <heading>Fees.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>The following fees are applicable to polysomnographic technologists:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Initial licensure application fee — $200;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>License renewal fees:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>License renewal fee — $150; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Maryland Health Care Commission (MHCC) fee — As determined by MHCC in accordance with <cite path="|10.25.02" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">COMAR 10.25.02</cite>;</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>Reinstatement fee — $200; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>Written verification of licensure fee — $25.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>Fees paid to the Board are non-refundable.</text>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|32|06|.10" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|32|06|.10">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.10</num>
            <heading>Prohibited Conduct.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>Subject to the hearing provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|14-405">Health Occupations Article, §14-405, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and in accordance with <cite path="|10.32.02" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">COMAR 10.32.02</cite>, a disciplinary panel may deny a license to any applicant, reprimand any licensee, place any licensee on probation, or suspend or revoke a license if the applicant or licensee:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Fraudulently, or deceptively obtains or attempts to obtain a license for the applicant or licensee, or for another;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Fraudulently or deceptively uses a license;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>Is guilty of unprofessional or immoral conduct in the practice of polysomnography;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>Is professionally, physically, or mentally incompetent;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(5)</num>
                <text>Abandons a patient;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(6)</num>
                <text>Is habitually intoxicated;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(7)</num>
                <text>Is addicted to or habitually abuses any narcotic or controlled dangerous substance as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|5-101">Criminal Law Article, §5-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(8)</num>
                <text>Provides professional services while:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Under the influence of alcohol; or</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Using any narcotic or controlled dangerous substance as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|5-101">Criminal Law Article, §5-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or any other drug that is in excess of therapeutic amounts or without valid medical indication;</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(9)</num>
                <text>Promotes the sale of services, drugs, devices, appliances, or goods to a patient so as to exploit the patient for financial gain;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(10)</num>
                <text>Willfully makes or files a false report or record in the practice of polysomnography;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(11)</num>
                <text>Willfully fails to file or record any report as required under law, willfully impedes or obstructs the filing or recording of a report, or induces another to fail to file or record a report;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(12)</num>
                <text>Breaches patient confidentiality;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(13)</num>
                <text>Pays or agrees to pay any sum or provide any form of remuneration or material benefit to any individual for bringing or referring a patient, or accepts or agrees to accept any sum or any form of remuneration or material benefit from an individual for bringing or referring a patient;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(14)</num>
                <text>Knowingly makes a misrepresentation while practicing polysomnography;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(15)</num>
                <text>Knowingly practices polysomnography with an unauthorized individual, or aids an unauthorized individual in the practice of polysomnography;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(16)</num>
                <text>Knowingly delegates a polysomnographic duty to an unlicensed individual;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(17)</num>
                <text>Offers, undertakes, or agrees to cure or treat disease by a secret method, treatment, or medicine;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(18)</num>
                <text>Is disciplined by a licensing or disciplinary authority, is convicted or disciplined by a court of any state or country, or is disciplined by any branch of the United States uniformed services or the U.S. Department of Veterans Affairs for an act that would be grounds for disciplinary action under the Board's disciplinary statutes;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(19)</num>
                <text>Fails to meet appropriate standards for the delivery of polysomnographic services performed in a hospital sleep laboratory or a stand-alone sleep center;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(20)</num>
                <text>Knowingly submits false statements to collect fees for which services are not provided;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(21)</num>
                <text>Has been subject to investigation or disciplinary action by a licensing or disciplinary authority or by a court of any state or country for an act that would be grounds for disciplinary action under the Board's disciplinary statutes and has:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Surrendered the license, if any, issued by the state or country; or</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Allowed the license, if any, issued by the state or country to expire or lapse;</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(22)</num>
                <text>Knowingly fails to report suspected child abuse in violation of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|5-704">Family Law Article, §5-704, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(23)</num>
                <text>Sells, prescribes, gives away, or administers drugs for illegal or illegitimate medical purposes;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(24)</num>
                <text>Practices or attempts to practice beyond the authorized scope of practice;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(25)</num>
                <text>Is convicted of, or pleads guilty or nolo contendere to, a felony or to a crime involving moral turpitude, whether or not any appeal or other proceeding is pending to have the conviction or plea set aside;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(26)</num>
                <text>Refuses, withholds from, denies, or discriminates against an individual with regard to the provision of professional services for which the licensee is licensed and qualified to render because the individual is HIV positive;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(27)</num>
                <text>Practices or attempts to practice a polysomnography procedure or uses or attempts to use polysomnography equipment if the applicant or licensee has not received education and training in the performance of the procedure or the use of the equipment; or</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(28)</num>
                <text>Fails to cooperate with a lawful investigation conducted by the Board.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>Crimes of Moral Turpitude.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Proceedings for crimes of moral turpitude under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|14-5">Health Occupations Article, §14-5</cite>C-17(c), Annotated Code of Maryland, shall be held in accordance with <cite path="10.32.02.07" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">COMAR 10.32.02.07</cite>.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>On the filing of certified docket entries with the Board by the Office of the Attorney General, a disciplinary panel shall order the suspension of a license if the licensee is convicted of, or pleads guilty or nolo contendere with respect to, a crime involving moral turpitude, whether or not any appeal or other proceeding is pending to have the conviction or plea set aside.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>After completion of the appellate process, if the conviction has not been reversed or the plea has not been set aside with respect to a crime involving moral turpitude, the disciplinary panel shall order the revocation of a license on the certification by the Office of the Attorney General.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|32|06|.11" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|32|06|.11">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.11</num>
            <heading>Required Reports.</heading>
            <text>A reporting entity, as defined in <cite path="10.32.22.02" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">COMAR 10.32.22.02</cite>, shall file all required reports in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|14-5">Health Occupations Article, §14-5</cite>C-18, Annotated Code of Maryland, and <cite path="|10.32.22" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">COMAR 10.32.22</cite>.</text>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|32|06|.12" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|32|06|.12">
          <section cache:ref-path="10|32|06|.12">
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.12</num>
            <heading>Penalties, Fines, and Sanctions.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>An individual who violates any provision of Heath Occupations Article, Title 14, Subtitle 5C, Annotated Code of Maryland, is guilty of a misdemeanor and on conviction is subject to a fine not exceeding $1,000 or imprisonment not exceeding 1 year, or both.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>An individual who violates any provision of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 14, Subtitle 5C, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or any regulation in this chapter, is subject to a civil fine of not more than $5,000 to be levied by the Board or a disciplinary panel.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>C.</num>
              <text>The Board shall pay any penalty collected under §A or B of this regulation into the Board of Physicians Fund.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>D.</num>
              <text>Employment of Unlicensed Polysomnography Practitioner.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>A person who violates <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|14-5">Health Occupations Article, §14-5</cite>C-22.1, Annotated Code of Maryland, is subject to a civil fine of not more than $5,000 to be levied by the Board.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>The Board shall pay any fine collected under <cite path="10|32|06|.12|D." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">§D of this regulation</cite> into the State’s General Fund.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>E.</num>
              <text>The Board may impose a fine up to $1,000 for a reporting entity, as defined in <cite path="10.32.22.02" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">COMAR 10.32.22.02</cite>, that fails to make a report to the Board required by <cite path="|10.32.22" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">COMAR 10.32.22</cite>.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>F.</num>
              <text>General Application of Sanctioning Guidelines.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Sections F and G of this regulation and <cite path="|10|32|06|.13" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .13 of this chapter</cite> do not apply to offenses for which a mandatory sanction is set by statute or regulation.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Except as provided in <cite path="10|32|06|.12|G." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">§G of this regulation</cite>, for violations of the sections of the Maryland Polysomnography Act listed in the sanctioning guidelines, a disciplinary panel shall impose a sanction not less severe than the minimum listed in the sanctioning guidelines nor more severe than the maximum listed in the sanctioning guidelines for each offense.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>Ranking of Sanctions.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>For the purposes of this regulation, the severity of sanctions is ranked as follows, from the least severe to the most severe:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <text>Reprimand;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <text>Probation;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <text>Suspension; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <text>Revocation.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>A stayed suspension in which the stay is conditioned on the completion of certain requirements is ranked as probation.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>A stayed suspension not meeting the criteria for <cite path="10|32|06|.12|F.|(3)|(b)" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">§F(3)(b) of this regulation</cite> is ranked as a reprimand.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>The disciplinary panel may impose more than one sanction, provided that the most severe sanction neither exceeds the maximum nor is less than the minimum sanction permitted in the chart.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(5)</num>
                <text>Any sanction may be accompanied by conditions reasonably related to the offense or to the rehabilitation of the offender. The inclusion of conditions does not change the ranking of the sanction.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(6)</num>
                <text>If a licensee has violated more than one ground for discipline as set out in the sanctioning guidelines:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>The sanction with the highest severity ranking shall be used to determine which ground will be used in developing a sanction; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>The disciplinary panel may impose concurrent sanctions based on other grounds violated.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(7)</num>
                <text>Notwithstanding the sanctioning guidelines set forth in <cite path="|10|32|06|.13" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .13 of this chapter</cite>, in order to resolve a pending disciplinary action, the disciplinary panel and the licensee may agree to a surrender of license or a consent order with terms and sanction agreed to by the disciplinary panel, the administrative prosecutor, and the licensee.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(8)</num>
                <text>Depending on the facts and circumstances of each case, and to the extent that the facts and circumstances apply, the disciplinary panel may consider the aggravating and mitigating factors set out in §G(4) and (5) of this regulation and may in its discretion determine, based on those factors, that an exception should be made and that the sanction in a particular case should fall outside the range of sanctions listed in the sanctioning guidelines.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(9)</num>
                <text>If the disciplinary panel imposes a sanction that departs from the sanctioning guidelines as set forth in <cite path="|10|32|06|.13" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .13 of this chapter</cite>, the disciplinary panel shall state its reasons for doing so in its final decision and order.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>G.</num>
              <text>Aggravating and Mitigating Factors.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Depending on the facts and circumstances of each case, and to the extent that the facts and circumstances apply, the disciplinary panel may consider the aggravating and mitigating factors set out in §G(4)—(5) of this regulation and may in its discretion determine, based on those factors, that an exception should be made and that the sanction in a particular case should fall outside the range of sanctions listed in the sanctioning guidelines.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Nothing in this regulation requires the disciplinary panel or an Administrative Law Judge to make findings of fact with respect to any of these factors.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>The existence of one or more of these factors does not impose on the disciplinary panel or an Administrative Law Judge any requirement to articulate its reasoning for not exercising its discretion to impose a sanction outside of the range of sanctions set out in the sanctioning guidelines.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>Mitigating factors may include, but are not limited to, the following:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>The absence of a prior disciplinary record;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>The offender self-reported the incident;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>The offender voluntarily admitted the misconduct, made full disclosure to the Board, and was cooperative during the Board proceedings;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <text>The offender implemented remedial measures to correct or mitigate the harm arising from the misconduct;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <text>The offender made good faith efforts to make restitution or to rectify the consequences of the misconduct;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <text>The offender has been rehabilitated or exhibits rehabilitative potential;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <text>The misconduct was not premeditated;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <text>There was no potential harm to patients or the public or other adverse impact; or</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <text>The incident was isolated and is not likely to recur.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(5)</num>
                <text>Aggravating factors may include, but are not limited to, the following:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>The offender has a previous criminal or administrative disciplinary history;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>The offense was committed deliberately or with gross negligence or recklessness;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>The offense had the potential for or actually did cause patient harm;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <text>The offense was part of a pattern of detrimental conduct;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <text>The offender committed a combination of factually discrete offenses adjudicated in a single action;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <text>The offender pursued his or her financial gain over the patient’s welfare;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <text>The patient was especially vulnerable;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <text>The offender attempted to hide the error or misconduct from patients or others;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <text>The offender concealed, falsified, or destroyed evidence or presented false testimony or evidence;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <text>The offender did not cooperate with the investigation; or</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <text>Previous attempts to rehabilitate the offender were unsuccessful.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(6)</num>
                <text>A departure from the sanctioning guidelines set forth in <cite path="|10|32|06|.13" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .13 of this chapter</cite> is not a ground for any hearing or appeal of a disciplinary panel action.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>H.</num>
              <text>Offenses Related to Continuing Education Requirements.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>If a licensee has submitted an application claiming the completion of continuing education credits and the licensee fails to document the completion of such continuing education credits when audited by the Board, the licensee may be charged under one or more of the following, as appropriate:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|14-5">Health Occupations Article, §14-5</cite>C-17(a)(3), Annotated Code of Maryland;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|14-5">Health Occupations Article, §14-5</cite>C-17(a)(10), Annotated Code of Maryland; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|14-5">Health Occupations Article, §14-5</cite>C-17(a)(11), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Upon a finding of a violation, the disciplinary panel may impose any discipline authorized under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|14-5">Health Occupations Article, §14-5</cite>C-17, Annotated Code of Maryland, and the sanctioning guidelines.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>I.</num>
              <text>Payment of Fines Imposed by the Board or a Disciplinary Panel.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>An individual shall pay to the Board any fine imposed pursuant to this regulation within 15 calendar days of the date of the order, unless the order specifies otherwise.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Filing an appeal under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-222">State Government Article, §10-222, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, does not stay payment of a fine imposed pursuant to this regulation.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>If an individual fails to pay, in whole or in part, a fine imposed pursuant to this regulation, the Board may not restore, reinstate, or renew a license until the fine has been paid in full.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>In its discretion, the Board may refer all cases of delinquent payment to the Central Collection Unit of the State Department of Budget and Management to institute and maintain proceedings to ensure an individual’s prompt payment.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|32|06|.13" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|32|06|.13">
          <section cache:ref-path="10|32|06|.13">
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.13</num>
            <heading>Sanctioning Guidelines for Polysomnographic Technologists.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>A. Subject to provisions of Regulation .12F and G of this chapter, a disciplinary panel may impose sanctions as outlined in <cite path="10|32|06|.13|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">§B of this regulation</cite> on polysomnographic technologists for violations of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|14-5">Health Occupations Article, §14-5</cite>C-17(a), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>Range of Sanctions.</text>
              <text>
                <table>
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th>Ground</th>
                      <th>Maximum <br/>Sanction</th>
                      <th>Minimum <br/>Sanction</th>
                      <th>Maximum <br/>Fine</th>
                      <th>Minimum <br/>Fine</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Fraudulently or deceptively obtains or attempts to obtain a license for the applicant, licensee, or for another</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Revocation</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Reprimand with probation for 2 years</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$5,000</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$1,000</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td data-vertical-align="middle">(2) Fraudulently or deceptively uses a license</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Revocation</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Probation</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$5,000</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$1,000</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td data-vertical-align="middle">(3) Is guilty of unprofessional or immoral conduct in the practice of polysomnography</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Revocation</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Reprimand with probation for 2 years</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$5,000</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$1,000</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>(4) Incompetence.</p>
                        <p class="text-indent-1">(a) Is physically or mentally incompetent;</p>
                      </td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Revocation</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Suspension until professional incompetence is addressed to Board’s satisfaction</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$5,000</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$1,000</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td class="text-indent-1">(b) Is professionally incompetent</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Revocation</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Suspension until physical or mental incompetence is addressed to Board’s satisfaction</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$5,000</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$0</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td data-vertical-align="middle">(5) Abandons a patient</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Revocation</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Reprimand</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$5,000</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$1,000</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>(6) Is habitually intoxicated</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Revocation</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Suspension until licensee is in treatment and has been abstinent for 6 months</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$5,000</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$0</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td data-vertical-align="middle">(7) Is addicted to or habitually abuses any narcotic or controlled dangerous substance as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|5-101">Criminal Law Article, §5-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite></td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Revocation</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Suspension until licensee is in treatment and has been abstinent for 6 months</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$5,000</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$0</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td data-vertical-align="middle">
                        <p>(8) Provides professional services while:</p>
                        <p class="text-indent-1">(a) Under the influence of alcohol; or</p>
                        <p class="text-indent-1">(b) Using any narcotic or controlled dangerous substance as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|5-101">Criminal Law Article, §5-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or any other drug that is in excess of therapeutic amounts or without valid medical indication</p>
                      </td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Revocation</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Suspension until licensee is in treatment and has been abstinent for 6 months</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$5,000</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$500</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td data-vertical-align="middle">(9) Promotes the sale of services, drugs, devices, appliances, or goods to a patient so as to exploit the patient for financial gain</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Suspension for 5 years</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Reprimand</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$5,000</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$1,000</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td data-vertical-align="middle">(10) Willfully makes or files a false report or record in the practice of polysomnography</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Revocation</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Reprimand</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$5,000</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$1,000</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td data-vertical-align="middle">(11) Willfully fails to file or record any report as required under law, willfully impedes or obstructs the filing or recording of a report, or induces another to fail to file or record a report</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Revocation</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Reprimand</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$5,000</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$1,000</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td data-vertical-align="middle">(12) Breaches patient confidentiality</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Revocation</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Reprimand</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$5,000</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$1,000</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td data-vertical-align="middle">(13) Pays or agrees to pay any sum or provide any form of remuneration or material benefit to any person for bringing or referring a patient or accepts or agrees to accept any sum or any form of remuneration or material benefit from an individual for bringing or referring a patient</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Revocation</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Reprimand</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$5,000</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$500</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td data-vertical-align="middle">(14) Knowingly makes a misrepresentation while practicing polysomnography</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Revocation</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Reprimand</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$5,000</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$1,000</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td data-vertical-align="middle">(15) Knowingly practices polysomnography with an unauthorized individual or aids an unauthorized individual in the practice of polysomnography</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Revocation</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Reprimand</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$5,000</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$1,000</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td data-vertical-align="middle">(16) Knowingly delegates a polysomnographic duty to an unlicensed individual</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Revocation</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Reprimand</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$5,000</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$1,000</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td data-vertical-align="middle">(17) Offers, undertakes, or agrees to cure or treat disease by a secret method, treatment, or medicine</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Revocation</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Reprimand</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$5,000</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$1,000</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>(18) Is disciplined by a licensing or disciplinary authority or is convicted or disciplined by a court of any state or country or is disciplined by any branch of the United States uniformed services or the U.S. Department of  Veterans Affairs  for an act that would be grounds for disciplinary action under the Board’s disciplinary statutes</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Penalty comparable to what the Board  imposes under equivalent Maryland  ground for discipline</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Penalty equivalent to that imposed by original licensing authority if this is less than the Board  sanction would be</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Fine comparable to what the Board imposes under equivalent Maryland ground for discipline</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Fine equivalent to that imposed by the original licensing authority if this is lesser than the Board sanction would be</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td data-vertical-align="middle">(19) Fails to meet appropriate standards for the delivery of polysomnographic services performed in a hospital sleep laboratory or stand-alone sleep center</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Revocation</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Reprimand</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$5,000</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$500</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td data-vertical-align="middle">(20) Knowingly submits false statements to collect fees for which services are not provided</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Revocation</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Reprimand</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$5,000</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$1,000</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td data-vertical-align="middle">
                        <p>(21) Has been subject to investigation or disciplinary action by a licensing or disciplinary authority or by a court of any state or country for an act that would be grounds for disciplinary action under the Board’s disciplinary statutes and has:</p>
                        <p class="text-indent-1">(a) Surrendered the license, if any, issued by the state or country; or</p>
                        <p class="text-indent-1">(b) Allowed the license, if any,  issued by the state or country to expire or lapse</p>
                      </td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Penalty comparable to what the Board imposes under equivalent Maryland  ground for discipline</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Penalty equivalent to that imposed by original licensing authority if this is less than the sanction would be from the Board</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Fine comparable to what the Board imposes under equivalent Maryland ground for discipline</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Fine equivalent to that imposed by the original licensing authority if this is less than  the Board sanction would be</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td data-vertical-align="middle">(22) Knowingly fails to report suspected child abuse in violation of  <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|5-704">Family Law Article, §5-704, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite></td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Revocation</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Reprimand</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$5,000</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$500</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>(23) Sells, prescribes, gives away, or administers drugs for illegal or illegitimate medical purposes</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Revocation</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Reprimand, probation for 3 years with practice oversight</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$5,000</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$500</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td data-vertical-align="middle">(24) Practices or attempts to practice beyond the authorized scope of practice</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Revocation</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Suspension for 3  months</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$5,000</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$2,500</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td data-vertical-align="middle">(25) Is convicted of or pleads guilty or nolo contender to a felony or to a crime involving moral turpitude, whether or not any appeal or other proceeding is pending to have the conviction or plea set aside</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Revocation</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Suspension</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$5,000</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$500</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td data-vertical-align="middle">(26) Refuses, withholds from, denies, or discriminates against an individual with regard to the provision of professional services for which the licensee is licensed and qualified to render because the individual is HIV positive</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Suspension for 1 year</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Reprimand</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$5,000</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$500</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td data-vertical-align="middle">(27) Practices or attempts to practice a polysomnography procedure or uses or attempts to use polysomnography equipment if the applicant or licensee has not received education and training in the performance of the procedure or the use of the equipment</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Revocation</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Suspension for 3  months</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$5,000</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$2,500</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td data-vertical-align="middle">(28) Fails to cooperate with a lawful investigation conducted by the Board</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Revocation</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">Reprimand</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$5,000</td>
                      <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">$1,000</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
              </text>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|32|06|annos" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|32|06|annos">
          <annotations>
            <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|1-213">1-213</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|1-221">1-221</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|1-606">1-606</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|14-205">14-205</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|14-5">14-5</cite>C-01—14-5C-23, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-12-01">Effective date: December 1, 2008 (35:24 Md. R. 2078)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-10-05"><cite path="|10|32|06|.01|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .01B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective October 1, 2009 (36:17 Md. R. 1311); amended permanently effective October 5, 2009 (36:20 Md. R. 1528)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-03-05"><cite path="|10|32|06|.01|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective March 5, 2012 (39:4 Md. R. 337)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-05-11"><cite path="|10|32|06|.01|E." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .01E</cite>, F adopted effective May 11, 2015 (42:9 Md. R. 647)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-29"><cite path="|10|32|06|.02|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective August 15, 2016 (43:16 Md. R. 900); September 29, 2025 (52:19 Md. R. 956)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-29"><cite path="|10|32|06|.04" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective December 22, 2014 (41:25 Md. R. 1485); September 29, 2025 (52:19 Md. R. 956)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-06-20"><cite path="|10|32|06|.04|A." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .04A</cite> amended effective June 20, 2016 (43:12 Md. R. 667)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-08-15"><cite path="|10|32|06|.04|C." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .04C</cite> repealed effective August 15, 2016 (43:16 Md. R. 900)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-10-05"><cite path="|10|32|06|.04|G." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .04G</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective October 1, 2009 (36:17 Md. R. 1311); amended permanently effective October 5, 2009 (36:20 Md. R. 1528)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-03-05"><cite path="|10|32|06|.04|G." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .04G</cite> amended effective March 5, 2012 (39:4 Md. R. 337)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-29"><cite path="|10|32|06|.06" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective September 29, 2025 (52:19 Md. R. 956)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-01-02"><cite path="|10|32|06|.07" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective January 2, 2017 (43:26 Md. R. 1446)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-29"><cite path="|10|32|06|.07|A." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .07A</cite> amended effective September 29, 2025 (52:19 Md. R. 956)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-12-22"><cite path="|10|32|06|.07|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .07B</cite>, C amended effective December 22, 2014 (41:25 Md. R. 1485)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-01-02"><cite path="|10|32|06|.08|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .08B</cite> amended effective August 15, 2016 (43:16 Md. R. 900); January 2, 2017 (43:26 Md. R. 1446)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-29"><cite path="|10|32|06|.09" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .09</cite> amended effective May 11, 2015 (42:9 Md. R. 647); September 29, 2025 (52:19 Md. R. 956)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-29"><cite path="|10|32|06|.10" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .10</cite> amended effective September 29, 2025 (52:19 Md. R. 956)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-05-11"><cite path="|10|32|06|.10|A." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .10A</cite> amended effective May 11, 2015 (42:9 Md. R. 647)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-29"><cite path="|10|32|06|.11" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .11</cite> amended effective September 29, 2025 (52:19 Md. R. 956)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-29"><cite path="|10|32|06|.12" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .12</cite> amended effective May 11, 2015 (42:9 Md. R. 647); September 29, 2025 (52:19 Md. R. 956)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-07-22"><cite path="|10|32|06|.12|D." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .12D</cite>—H adopted effective July 22, 2013 (40:14 Md. R. 1175)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-07-22"><cite path="|10|32|06|.13" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .13</cite> adopted effective July 22, 2013 (40:14 Md. R. 1175)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-05-11"><cite path="|10|32|06|.13" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .13</cite> amended effective May 11, 2015 (42:9 Md. R. 647)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-29"><cite path="|10|32|06|.13|A." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .13A</cite> amended effective September 29, 2025 (52:19 Md. R. 956)</annotation>
          </annotations>
        </codify:replace>
      </container>
      <container>
        <num>25-117-F</num>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|34|04|.01" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|34|04|.01">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.01</num>
            <heading>Scope.</heading>
            <text>This chapter governs the:</text>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>Transfer of prescriptions for non-controlled dangerous substances between pharmacies;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>Filling of prescriptions at one pharmacy pursuant to the request of staff of a second pharmacy; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>C.</num>
              <text>Preparation of medication for stock and investigational use.</text>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|34|04|.03" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|34|04|.03">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.03</num>
            <heading>Permanent Transfer of a Prescription Between Pharmacies.</heading>
            <text>A pharmacist from a primary pharmacy may permanently transfer a prescription order to a secondary pharmacy to be dispensed to a specific patient if the pharmacist transferring the prescription from the primary pharmacy indicates on the prescription, within the prescription computer database and within any appropriate other records used for dispensing:</text>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>That the prescription has been permanently transferred;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>The name of the secondary pharmacy;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>C.</num>
              <text>The name of the pharmacist who transferred the prescription to the secondary pharmacy;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>D.</num>
              <text>The name of the pharmacist at the secondary pharmacy to whom the prescription was transferred if the transfer occurred in an oral manner; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>E.</num>
              <text>The date on which the prescription was transferred to the secondary pharmacy.</text>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|34|04|.06" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|34|04|.06">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.06</num>
            <heading>Transfers of Prescription for Controlled Dangerous Substances.</heading>
            <text>A pharmacist may transfer a prescription for a controlled dangerous substance in accordance with federal law.</text>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|34|04|.07" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|34|04|.07">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.07</num>
            <heading>Outsourcing of a Prescription Order.</heading>
            <text>A pharmacist from a primary pharmacy may transmit a prescription order to a secondary pharmacy for preparation and final dispensing to a specific patient or for return to the primary pharmacy for final dispensing to a specific patient if:</text>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>The label contains the name, address, and phone number of the primary pharmacy;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>The patient is informed in writing of the name and address of the secondary pharmacy;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>C.</num>
              <text>The patient is informed in writing that the prescription order was prepared at a secondary pharmacy;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>D.</num>
              <text>The original prescription order is filed as a prescription order at the primary pharmacy;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>E.</num>
              <text>The pharmacist from the primary pharmacy documents in a readily retrievable and identifiable manner:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>That the prescription order was prepared by a secondary pharmacy;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>The name of the secondary pharmacy;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>The name of the pharmacist who transmitted the prescription order to the secondary pharmacy;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>The name of the pharmacist at the secondary pharmacy to whom the prescription order was transmitted if the transmission occurred in an oral manner;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(5)</num>
                <text>The date on which the prescription was transmitted to the secondary pharmacy; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(6)</num>
                <text>The date on which the medication was sent to the primary pharmacy;</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>F.</num>
              <text>Both the primary and secondary pharmacies are licensed in this State, or operated by the federal government; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>G.</num>
              <text>The primary pharmacy maintains, in a readily retrievable and identifiable manner, a record of preparations received from the secondary pharmacy.</text>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|34|04|.08" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|34|04|.08">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.08</num>
            <heading>Documentation by the Secondary Pharmacy when a Prescription Order is Outsourced.</heading>
            <text>The permit holder at the secondary pharmacy is responsible for maintaining documentation in a readily retrievable and identifiable manner, which includes:</text>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>That the prescription order was transmitted from another pharmacy;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>The name and information identifying the specific location of the primary pharmacy;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>C.</num>
              <text>The name of the pharmacist who transmitted the prescription to the secondary pharmacy if the transmission occurred in an oral manner;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>D.</num>
              <text>The name of the pharmacist at the secondary pharmacy who accepted the transmitted prescription order;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>E.</num>
              <text>The name of the pharmacist at the secondary pharmacy who prepared the prescription order;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>F.</num>
              <text>The date on which the prescription order was received at the secondary pharmacy; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>G.</num>
              <text>The date on which the prepared product was sent to the primary pharmacy if it was sent back to the primary pharmacy.</text>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|34|04|.09" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|34|04|.09">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.09</num>
            <heading>Preparation of Stock and Investigational Medications.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>A pharmacist may provide medication for use as stock medication for a licensed health care facility in accordance with applicable laws, if the pharmacy providing the medication also serves as the primary provider of patient specific medication for the facility.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>A pharmacist may provide medication for use as stock medication for final dispensing or administration by an authorized prescriber who is permitted by law to administer or dispense medication if the pharmacist receives a written stock medication order from the authorized prescriber for each delivery of medication to the authorized prescriber.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>C.</num>
              <text>A pharmacist may prepare, package, and label investigational drugs not destined for a specific individual at the time of preparation, packaging, and labeling if:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>The study for which medications are prepared, packaged, and labeled is approved by an institutional review board as defined in federal law; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>The pharmacy permit holder ensures that records disclosing the identity of the subject who eventually receives the medication are:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Received by a pharmacist on duty at the pharmacy within 30 days after being provided to a patient; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Maintained in the pharmacy.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:insert history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|34|04" before="annos" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|34|04|.10">
          <section cache:ref-path="10|34|04|.10">
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.10</num>
            <heading>Permit and Quality Assurance.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>The permit holder of a pharmacy which prepares patient specific prescriptions as a secondary pharmacy such that these prescriptions account for 5 percent or more of the pharmacy's total number of prescriptions filled shall submit to the Board of Pharmacy, for approval by the Board or a designee of the Board, a plan detailing the steps it has taken to ensure the safety and quality of prescriptions filled as a secondary pharmacy.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>The plan under <cite path="10|34|04|.10|A." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">§A of this regulation</cite> shall include:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Measures to be taken to comply with State and federal laws;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>The method by which each pharmacist responsible for each prescription is identified in the records;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>Measures taken to maintain the security, integrity, and confidentiality of patient records; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>The establishment and maintenance of a quality assurance program.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>C.</num>
              <text>Except as provided in <cite path="|10|34|04|.06" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>, a permit holder of a pharmacy shall obtain manufacturing and distribution permits in order to compound or package medication that is not prepared as a prescription destined for a specific patient, but is forwarded to another pharmacy, authorized prescriber, licensed distributor, or other person or entity.</text>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:insert>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|34|04|annos" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|34|04|annos">
          <annotations>
            <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">
              <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|12-205">Health Occupations Article, §12-205(a)(3)(ii), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>
            </annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1979-05-04">Effective date: May 4, 1979 (6:9 Md. R. 728)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-02-19"><cite path="|10|34|04|.01" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective February 19, 1990 (17:3 Md. R. 298)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-02-19"><cite path="|10|34|04|.02" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective February 19, 1990 (17:3 Md. R. 298)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-02-19"><cite path="|10|34|04|.03|A." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .03A</cite> amended effective February 19, 1990 (17:3 Md. R. 298)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-06-25">Regulations <cite path="|10|34|04|.01" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">.01</cite> — <cite path="|10|34|04|.04" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">.04</cite>, Transfer of Prescriptions Between Pharmacies repealed effective June 25, 2001 (28:12 Md. R. 1110)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-06-25" discontinuity="true"><cite path="|10|34|04|.01" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .01</cite> — .09 Transfer and Outsourcing of Prescriptions and Prescription Orders adopted effective June 25, 2001 (28:12 Md. R. 1110)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-29" discontinuity="true"><cite path="|10|34|04|.01|A." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .01A</cite> amended effective September 29, 2025 (Md. R. 956)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-29"><cite path="|10|34|04|.03" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective September 29, 2025 (Md. R. 956)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-29"><cite path="|10|34|04|.06" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .06</cite> recodified to Regulation .07 effective September 29, 2025 (Md. R. 956)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-29"><cite path="|10|34|04|.06" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .06</cite> adopted effective September 29, 2025 (Md. R. 956)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-29"><cite path="|10|34|04|.07" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .07</cite> recodified to Regulation .08 effective September 29, 2025 (Md. R. 956)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-29"><cite path="|10|34|04|.08" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .08</cite> recodified to Regulation .09 effective September 29, 2025 (Md. R. 956)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-29"><cite path="|10|34|04|.09" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .09</cite> recodified to Regulation .10 effective September 29, 2025 (Md. R. 956)</annotation>
          </annotations>
        </codify:replace>
      </container>
      <container>
        <num>25-126-F</num>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|34|07|.01-1" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|34|07|.01-1">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.01-1</num>
            <heading>Equipment.</heading>
            <text>A pharmacy shall have the following equipment to carry out the practice of pharmacy in Maryland:</text>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>If applicable, a Class A prescription balance and weights, or a prescription balance with equivalent or superior sensitivity to a Class A prescription balance; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>A refrigerator and freezer, if applicable, solely for the storage of drugs requiring refrigeration, with a thermometer or a temperature monitoring device.</text>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="10|34|07|annos" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="10|34|07|annos">
          <annotations>
            <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|12-205">12-205</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|12-403">12-403</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1980-03-21">Effective date: March 21, 1980 (7:6 Md. R. 608)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1984-09-10"><cite path="|10|34|07|.03" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .03</cite> adopted effective September 10, 1984 (11:18 Md. R. 1585)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-02-19" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective February 19, 1990 (17:3 Md. R. 298)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-11-07"><cite path="|10|34|07|.03" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective November 7, 1994 (21:22 Md. R. 1877)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-08-30"><cite path="|10|34|07|.01|A." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .01A</cite> amended effective August 30, 2004 (31:17 Md. R. 1312)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-07-01" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective July 1, 2010 (37:10 Md. R. 722)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-29" discontinuity="true"><cite path="|10|34|07|.01-1" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .01-1</cite> amended effective September 29, 2025 (52:19 Md. R. 956)</annotation>
          </annotations>
        </codify:replace>
      </container>
      <container>
        <num>25-088-F</num>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="11|05|03|.02" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="11|05|03|.02">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.02</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>Terms Defined.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>“Access control point” means a location where credentials are produced and verified to ensure authorized access to the facilities.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>“Berth permit” means a permit issued by the MPA Office of Security or designee that permits parking upon a berth.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>“Cargo gate pass” means the document issued at the access control point by security personnel for a vehicle delivering or receiving cargo or designated as cargo.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>“Citation” has the meaning stated in <cite path="11.05.02.02|B.|(2)" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">COMAR 11.05.02.02B(2)</cite>.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(5)</num>
                <text>“Conviction” means a plea of guilty, a finding of guilty, a plea of nolo contendere, or acceptance of probation before judgment.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(6)</num>
                <text>“Decal” means the individually numbered and adhesive backed decal that is issued and applied to the motor vehicle windshield by the MPA Office of Security or designee.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(7)</num>
                <text>“Electronic Pass” (E-Pass) means an electronic pass generated by the MPA and verified at the access control point by security personnel.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(8)</num>
                <text>“Law Enforcement Agency” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|3-201">Public Safety Article, §3-201(d), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(9)</num>
                <text>“Law Enforcement Permit” means a hang tag issued by the MPA Office of Security or designee to law enforcement and MPA Office of Security personnel.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(10)</num>
                <text>“MdTA Police” means Maryland Transportation Authority personnel designated as members of the Police Force under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|4-208">Transportation Article, §4-208, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or any other police officers as defined by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|3-201">Public Safety Article, §3-201(e), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and who are authorized to perform law enforcement duties on MPA property.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(11)</num>
                <text>MdTA Police Cadet means an employee of the Maryland Transportation Authority Police or any other law enforcement agency that is authorized to enforce parking regulations on MPA property.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(12)</num>
                <text>MdTA Police Port Detachment means personnel of the Maryland Transportation Authority Police or any other law enforcement agency that are specifically assigned to MPA property or Port facilities and that are authorized to enforce criminal laws and the regulations in this title.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(13)</num>
                <text>Motor Vehicle.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>“Motor vehicle”, except as otherwise used in these regulations, means a vehicle that is self-propelled, including all automobiles, whether or not privately owned.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>“Motor vehicle” also includes multipurpose passenger vehicles, van pool vehicles, trucks, truck tractors, trailers, semitrailers, pole trailers, motorcycles, export or import cargo, and special mobile equipment.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>“Motor vehicle” includes any vehicle qualifying as a motor vehicle which is subject to all the requirements of this chapter while being pulled or towed by another motor vehicle.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <text>“Motor vehicle” does not include vehicles designed to operate only on rails or tracks.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(14)</num>
                <text>“MPA” means the Maryland Port Administration.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(15)</num>
                <text>“MPA property” means all property owned, leased, or operated by or under the control of the Maryland Port Administration.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(16)</num>
                <text>“Permit” means:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>The decal that is affixed to the vehicle windshield by the MPA Office of Security or designee;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>The visitor or vendor vehicle pass, cargo gate pass or E-Pass generated by the MPA and verified by security personnel at the facility access control point; or</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>The 14-day pass issued by the MPA Office of Security or designee.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(17)</num>
                <text>“Port facilities” means any one or more or combination of facilities and structures owned, leased, operated by, or under the control of the MPA, including:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Lands, piers, docks, wharves, warehouses, sheds, transit sheds, elevators, compressors, refrigeration storage plants, buildings, structures, and other facilities, appurtenances, or equipment useful or designed for use in connection with the operation of a port;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Every kind of terminal or storage structure or facility useful or designed for use in handling, storing, loading, or unloading freight or passengers at marine terminals;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>Every kind of transportation facility useful or designed for use in connection with any of these.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(18)</num>
                <text>Special Mobile Equipment.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>“Special mobile equipment” means vehicles that are not used primarily for highway transportation of people or property, but which are operated or moved on a highway only as an incident to their non-highway use.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>“Special mobile equipment” includes road construction or maintenance machines, mobile cranes, ditch diggers, well drillers, portable concrete mixers, job site vehicles, portable power generators, fork lift trucks, yard hustlers, straddle carriers, crew haulers, rubber tired gantries, and other vehicles used to move personnel around the terminals in connection with the movement of cargo in maritime commerce.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(19)</num>
                <text>“Tenant” means a person who has been given authorization to use a facility for cargo handling purposes under a lease or other contract with MPA.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(20)</num>
                <text>“Vehicle operator” means the person in actual physical control of a motor vehicle.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(21)</num>
                <text>“Visitor or Vendor vehicle pass” means the document issued at the access control point by security personnel for single day access to a facility for a motor vehicle.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="11|05|03|.03" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="11|05|03|.03">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.03</num>
            <heading>Motor Vehicle Port Admission Permit.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>Permit Requirements.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>A person may not operate or bring a motor vehicle on MPA property unless the motor vehicle has been issued a Decal or a Visitor, Vendor, 14-Day, Cargo Gate Pass or E-Pass in accordance with this chapter.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Failure to display the decal or pass properly may result in the denial of access to MPA property.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>Access to MPA property is subject to limitations and time frames specified by the MPA.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>A motor vehicle specifically exempted by these regulations is not subject to permit requirements.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>Types of Permits.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Decal. Motor vehicles regularly operated on MPA property or requiring regular visits to the property, shall display evidence of having obtained a Decal. The decal shall be applied to the outside lower portion of the driver side of the vehicle’s front windshield with the expiration date clearly displayed.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>14-Day Pass. Non-decaled motor vehicles operated by authorized persons on MPA property on a daily basis for 7 days or longer, shall display evidence of having obtained a 14-Day Pass. Issuance of a 14-Day Pass requires prior notification of the MPA Office of Security or designee. The pass shall be placed on the dashboard in the driver’s front left windshield area of the vehicle so as to be visible from the outside.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>Visitor or Vendor Vehicle Pass. Motor vehicles, owned or operated by persons on MPA property on a daily basis for a length of time less than 7 days, shall display evidence of having obtained a printed Visitor or Vendor Pass, or shall display an E-Pass on their mobile device. Issuance of a Visitor or Vendor Pass or E-Pass requires prior notification to the MPA via its electronic database. The printed pass shall be placed on the dashboard in the driver’s front left windshield area of the vehicle so as to be visible from the outside. The E-Pass shall be displayed via the user’s mobile device when requested by security personnel or MdTA Police.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>Cargo Gate Pass. A Motor vehicle which is designed to carry cargo or is designated as cargo is required to obtain a Cargo Gate Pass at one of the truck access control points before reporting directly to the marine terminal operator or cargo processor within MPA property that is handling the cargo. The vehicle operator shall be registered via MPA’s electronic database, eModal, before entering the facility.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(5)</num>
                <text>Exemptions. Special mobile equipment and emergency vehicles, as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|11-118">Transportation Article, §11-118, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite> are exempt from the permit requirements of this chapter when they are being used:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>In the performance of official duties; or</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>For conducting business on any MPA facility.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>C.</num>
              <text>Application Procedures.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Requirements for a Decal. A person desiring a decal under this regulation shall:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Establish to the satisfaction of the MPA Office of Security a legitimate purpose for being on a facility;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Submit a completed permit application to the MPA Office of Security or designee on the form provided;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>Exhibit a valid State registration card or proof of ownership for the vehicle for which application is made; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <text>Exhibit a valid State driver's license, of the class authorized for that particular type of vehicle, covering the person operating the vehicle at the time of application, and exhibit proof of insurance for the vehicle for which application is made.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Requirements for a Visitor or Vendor Vehicle Pass. A Visitor or Vendor Vehicle Pass shall be obtained at the access control point of the facility to which access is desired. All visitors and vendors shall have received prior authorization to enter the facility from the MPA, the MdTA Police, or a tenant or other user of the facility. The person who authorized the visitor or vendor’s entry to the facility shall provide all required identification information to the MPA in advance through MPA’s electronic database.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>Requirements for a 14-Day Pass. A person desiring a 14-Day Pass under this regulation shall:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Provide to the MPA Office of Security or designee evidence of hardship or exigent circumstances justifying the person’s failure to obtain a decal; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Receive prior authorization from the MPA, the MdTA Police, or a tenant or other user of the Port facility to be on the facility for the requested period.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>Requirements for a Cargo Gate Pass. A motor vehicle entering MPA port facilities to deliver or pick up cargo shall be issued a Cargo Gate Pass or E-Pass after its driver produces valid identification and establishes a legitimate business purpose for entry to the facility. The Cargo Gate Pass or E-Pass shall be validated by the tenant while the vehicle is on the facility and verified by the security guard on exit.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>D.</num>
              <text>Decision on Application for Decals.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>A Decal may be issued only to those persons who have employment-related or business-related purposes for gaining admission to MPA property.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>If an application is denied, the applicant may confer with the MPA Director of Security as to the reason for the denial.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>If the MPA Director of Security concurs in the denial, the applicant may appeal this decision to the MPA Deputy Executive Director.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>An applicant has the rights granted in the Maryland Administrative Procedure Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 10, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>E.</num>
              <text>Display of Decals and Passes.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Decals. Upon approval of an application for a Decal, the MPA Office of Security or designee shall issue an identifying decal. This decal signifies to the MdTA Police and the MPA that an application is on file for the vehicle which has met all the requirements of this chapter. The decal, upon issue, shall immediately be applied to the vehicle windshield by the MPA Office of Security or designee and is the only evidence of application approval and is valid until termination.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>14-Day Passes. Upon approval of an application for a 14-Day Pass, the MPA Office of Security or designee shall issue a 14-Day Pass to the applicant. This pass, upon issue, shall be prominently displayed within the front left windshield area of the vehicle and in full view from the exterior while the motor vehicle is on MPA property.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>Visitor or Vendor Vehicle Pass. Upon approval of a visitor or vendor's entrance into a facility, a designated security officer shall issue a Visitor or Vendor Vehicle Pass or E-Pass to the driver.  The printed Visitor or Vendor Vehicle Pass shall be prominently displayed within the windshield area of the vehicle and in full view from the exterior with the date clearly visible while the motor vehicle is on MPA property. The E-Pass shall be displayed via the user’s mobile device when requested by security personnel or MdTA Police.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(4)</num>
                <text>An operator or owner of a motor vehicle is in violation of this regulation if the owner or operator is required to display a decal or pass for the motor vehicle but:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Does not display a decal or pass; or</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Displays an expired decal or pass.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>F.</num>
              <text>Non-Transferability of Decals and Passes. A Decal or Visitor or Vendor Vehicle, 14-Day, or Cargo Gate Pass may not be transferred to or displayed on any vehicle other than the vehicle to which the decal or pass has been issued. A pass may not be transferred to or displayed by any person other than the person to whom issued.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>G.</num>
              <text>Termination of Decals and Passes.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Decals.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Upon termination of a Decal, the decal shall be removed by the vehicle owner, by another person on the owner's behalf, or by a designated MPA or MdTA police employee.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Decal termination occurs on the earliest of:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <text>The date the need for facility access stated in support of the original application no longer exists (for example, termination of employment on the terminal);</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <text>The date the owner or operator voluntarily surrenders the permit;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <text>The date the MPA Office of Security or designee revokes or suspends the permit.</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <text>The date ownership of the vehicle is transferred by the person who obtained the decal; or</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(v)</num>
                    <text>Upon expiration of the Decal.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Visitor or Vendor Vehicles Passes.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>The Visitor or Vendor Vehicle Pass shall be returned to a designated security officer or electronically closed upon departure of the motor vehicle from the facility.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>The Visitor or Vendor Vehicle Pass automatically expires at the end of the calendar date indicated, upon its voluntary surrender, upon departure of the motor vehicle from the MPA facility at which the permit was issued, or upon revocation by the MPA Office of Security or designee in accordance with the provisions in this chapter.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>14-Day Passes.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>The 14-Day Pass shall be returned to the MPA Office of Security or designee upon expiration of the pass.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>The 14-Day Pass automatically expires at the end of the calendar date indicated, upon its voluntary surrender, when the need for which the permit was issued no longer exists, or upon revocation by the MPA Office of Security or designee in accordance with the provisions in this chapter.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>H.</num>
              <text>Notice of Changes in Conditions.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Changes in the information given in the original application for the decal shall be reported by the applicant to the MPA Office of Security or designee immediately after the change.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>The following changes shall be reported:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>New motor vehicle registration plate number;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Sale or other disposition of the motor vehicle;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>Loss of or damage to the decal;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <text>Change of regularly assigned place of employment;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <text>Change of applicant's employer; or</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <text>Change in the home address of the owner of the motor vehicle.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>I.</num>
              <text>Limitations. The issuance of any decal or pass under this chapter or permission for any person to enter MPA property does not permit the motor vehicle or persons unrestricted access throughout a facility or unrestricted movement or parking in the facility for which the decal or pass is issued. Motor vehicles with decals or passes, and persons allowed to enter are permitted access to the property only when the need for access, as given in support of the application, exists. Every person in the facility shall obey these regulations regarding the operation and parking of motor vehicles together with all directives and signs issued by the MPA and all oral or written directions given by MdTA Police to implement this chapter.</text>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="11|05|03|annos" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="11|05|03|annos">
          <annotations>
            <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|6-201">6-201</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|6-211">6-211</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1975-09-03">Effective date: September 3, 1975 (2:20 Md. R. 1300)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1980-06-01">Chapter revised effective June 1, 1980 (7:11 Md. R. 1038)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-10-15"><cite path="|11|05|03|.02|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective October 15, 1990 (17:20 Md. R. 2429)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-10-15"><cite path="|11|05|03|.03" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective October 15, 1990 (17:20 Md. R. 2429)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-02-24"><cite path="|11|05|03|.03|E." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .03E</cite> amended effective February 24, 1986 (13:4 Md. R. 396)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-10-15"><cite path="|11|05|03|.05|A." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .05A</cite> amended effective October 15, 1990 (17:20 Md. R. 2429)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-10-15"><cite path="|11|05|03|.14|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .14B</cite> amended effective October 15, 1990 (17:20 Md. R. 2429)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-05-08" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective May 8, 1995 (22:9 Md. R. 646)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-10-05" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective October 5, 1998 (25:20 Md. R. 1532)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-29"><cite path="|11|05|03|.02|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective February 18, 2002 (29:3 Md. R. 222); April 6, 2009 (36:7 Md. R. 525); January 5, 2015 (41:26 Md. R. 1570); September 29, 2025 (52:19 Md. R. 957)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-29"><cite path="|11|05|03|.03" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective February 18, 2002 (29:3 Md. R. 222); April 6, 2009 (36:7 Md. R. 525); January 5, 2015 (41:26 Md. R. 1570); September 29, 2025 (52:19 Md. R. 957)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-01-05"><cite path="|11|05|03|.04|A." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .04A</cite>, E amended effective January 5, 2015 (41:26 Md. R. 1570)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-04-06"><cite path="|11|05|03|.04|E." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .04E</cite>, F amended effective April 6, 2009 (36:7 Md. R. 525)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-01-05"><cite path="|11|05|03|.04|H." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .04H</cite> adopted effective January 5, 2015 (41:26 Md. R. 1570)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-01-05"><cite path="|11|05|03|.05|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .05B</cite>, C amended effective January 5, 2015 (41:26 Md. R. 1570)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-04-06"><cite path="|11|05|03|.05|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .05B</cite> amended effective April 6, 2009 (36:7 Md. R. 525)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-01-05"><cite path="|11|05|03|.07" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective January 5, 2015 (41:26 Md. R. 1570)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-01-05"><cite path="|11|05|03|.08" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .08</cite> amended effective January 5, 2015 (41:26 Md. R. 1570)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-04-06"><cite path="|11|05|03|.09" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .09</cite> amended effective April 6, 2009 (36:7 Md. R. 525)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-01-05"><cite path="|11|05|03|.09|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .09B</cite> amended effective January 5, 2015 (41:26 Md. R. 1570)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-01-05"><cite path="|11|05|03|.12" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .12</cite> amended effective January 5, 2015 (41:26 Md. R. 1570)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-04-06"><cite path="|11|05|03|.13" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .13</cite> amended effective April 6, 2009 (36:7 Md. R. 525)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-04-06"><cite path="|11|05|03|.14|A." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .14A</cite> amended effective April 6, 2009 (36:7 Md. R. 525)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-02-18"><cite path="|11|05|03|.14|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .14B</cite> amended effective February 18, 2002 (29:3 Md. R. 222)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-01-05"><cite path="|11|05|03|.14|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .14B</cite>, D amended effective January 5, 2015 (41:26 Md. R. 1570)</annotation>
          </annotations>
        </codify:replace>
      </container>
      <container>
        <num>25-144-F</num>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="15|03|08|.05" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="15|03|08|.05">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.05</num>
            <heading>Fees for Classes of Weights and Measures.</heading>
            <text>The Department's fees for registering each class of weight and measure used for commercial purposes under this subtitle are as follows:</text>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>Scale with a capacity of up to 100 pounds—$25 for each scale, plus $75 for each business location;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>Scale with a capacity of more than 100 pounds, up to 2,000 pounds—$100;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>C.</num>
              <text>Scale with a capacity of more than 2,000 pounds—$125;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>D.</num>
              <text>Belt conveyor scale—$350;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>E.</num>
              <text>Railroad track scale—$350;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>F.</num>
              <text>Vehicle scale—$350;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>G.</num>
              <text>Grain moisture meter—$150;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>H.</num>
              <text>Retail motor fuel dispenser meter of under 20 gallons per minute—$20 each for each meter, plus $75 per business location;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>I.</num>
              <text>Retail motor fuel dispenser meter of 20 gallons per minute or more—$65;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>J.</num>
              <text>Retail DEF dispensers—$20 per meter;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>K.</num>
              <text>Bulk petroleum fuel vehicle mounted meter of 20 gallons per minute or more—$100;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>L.</num>
              <text>Bulk petroleum fuel meter stationary—$100;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>M.</num>
              <text>Liquefied petroleum meter of 3/4 inch diameter or less—$100;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>N.</num>
              <text>Liquefied petroleum gas meter 3/4 inch—2 inch diameter—$125;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>O.</num>
              <text>Liquefied petroleum gas meters greater than 2 inch diameter—$150;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>P.</num>
              <text>Point of sale system, as defined by the National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST) Handbook 44, connected to a weighing or measuring device (per business location)—$125;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>Q.</num>
              <text>Electrical Vehicle Service Equipment—$150 per port;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>R.</num>
              <text>Mass Flow Meters—$330 per meter; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>S.</num>
              <text>Device registration fee 30 days or more delinquent—$125 per account.</text>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="15|03|08|annos" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="15|03|08|annos">
          <annotations>
            <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Agriculture Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|11-204">11-204</cite>.1—11-204.7, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-10-12">Effective date: October 12, 1992 (19:20 Md. R. 1818)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-29"><cite path="|15|03|08|.05" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective October 2, 2000 (27:19 Md. R. 1728); September 29, 2025 (52:19 Md. R. 957)</annotation>
          </annotations>
        </codify:replace>
      </container>
      <container>
        <num>25-111-F</num>
        <codify:insert history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="33|05|01" before="annos" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="33|05|01|.04">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.04</num>
            <heading>Voter Registration Security — Background Check Required.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>All employees or contractors who electronically access the Statewide voter registration list must undergo a criminal background check.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>The local board may accept a criminal background check performed within 6 months prior to hire if conducted by the State Board or another local board, if the provider verifies and documents its authenticity.</text>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:insert>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="33|05|01|annos" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="33|05|01|annos">
          <annotations>
            <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Election Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|2-102">2-102</cite>(b)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|4">4</cite>), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|2-202">2-202</cite>(b), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|3-101">3-101</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|3-202">3-202</cite>.1, and 3-204.1, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-04-17">Regulations <cite path="|33|05|01|.01" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">.01</cite>—<cite path="|33|05|01|.03" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">.03</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective February 1, 2000 (27:6 Md. R. 635); adopted permanently effective April 17, 2000 (27:7 Md. R. 708)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-10-14"><cite path="|33|05|01|.02|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .02B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 3, 2002 (29:18 Md. R. 1440); amended permanently effective October 14, 2002 (29:20 Md. R. 1595)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-12-13"><cite path="|33|05|01|.02|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective November 24, 2003 (30:23 Md. R. 1654); May 31, 2010 (37:11 Md. R. 767); September 16, 2013 (40:18 Md. R. 1480); December 13, 2021 (48:25 Md. R. 1081)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-29"><cite path="|33|05|01|.04" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .04</cite> adopted effective September 29, 2025 (52:19 Md. R. 957)</annotation>
          </annotations>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="33|07|11|.01" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="33|07|11|.01">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.01</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>Terms Defined.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>“Previously served” means an election judge who:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Was previously appointed in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|10-203">Election Law Article, §10-203, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Completed a term of office; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>Served in the capacity of an election judge during the term of office in the immediately preceding Statewide primary, general, or special election.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>“Term of office” means the time from appointment to the office of election judge through the Tuesday that is 13 weeks before the next Statewide primary election.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="33|07|11|annos" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="33|07|11|annos">
          <annotations>
            <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Election Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|2-102">2-102</cite>(b)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|4">4</cite>), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|2-202">2-202</cite>(b), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|10-202">10-202</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|10">10</cite>–<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|203">203</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|10">10</cite>–<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|205">205</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-11-27">Effective date: November 27, 2023 (50:23 Md. R. 1005)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-29"><cite path="|33|07|11|.01|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective September 29, 2025 (52:19 Md. R. 957)</annotation>
          </annotations>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:insert history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="33|10|01" before="annos" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="33|10|01|.30">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.30</num>
            <heading>System Security—Background Check Required.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>All employees or contractors who perform maintenance, testing, or programming functions, in an administrative capacity, other than normal polling place activities, on the voting system or its components must undergo a criminal background check.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>The local board may accept a criminal background check performed within 6 months prior to hire if conducted by the State Board or another local board, if the provider verifies and documents its authenticity.</text>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:insert>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="33|10|01|annos" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="33|10|01|annos">
          <annotations>
            <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Election Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|2-102">2-102</cite>(b)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|4">4</cite>), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|2-202">2-202</cite>(b), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|9-102">9-102</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|9-105">9-105</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|11-201">11-201</cite>, and Title 9, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-04-11">Regulations <cite path="|33|10|01|.01" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">.01</cite>—<cite path="|33|10|01|.07" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">.07</cite> and Regulations <cite path="|33|10|01|.09" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">.09</cite>—<cite path="|33|10|01|.29" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">.29</cite> adopted effective April 11, 2016 (43:7 Md. R. 452)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-02-10"><cite path="|33|10|01|.17|F." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .17F</cite> amended effective February 10, 2020 (47:3 Md. R. 173)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-07-10"><cite path="|33|10|01|.18" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .18</cite> amended effective July 10, 2023 (50:13 Md. R. 514)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-29"><cite path="|33|10|01|.30" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .30</cite> adopted effective September 29, 2025 (52:19 Md. R. 957)</annotation>
          </annotations>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:insert history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="33|11|01" before="annos" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="33|11|01|.05">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.05</num>
            <heading>Absent Uniformed Services Voters and Overseas Voters in Special Elections.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>The State Board shall provide notice to absent uniformed services voters and overseas voters concerning a special election as follows:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>In a vote by mail special election under COMAR §33.21.01—.08, by sending an absentee ballot to all absent uniformed service voters and overseas voters; or</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>In a special election that is not conducted as a vote by mail election, by providing notice to a major news outlet and social media.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>Absent uniform service voters and overseas voters may request an absentee ballot as provided in COMAR §<cite path="33.11.02.01" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">33.11.02.01</cite>—.04.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>C.</num>
              <text>Absent uniform service voters and overseas voters may request delivery of an absentee ballot for a special election using any of the following methods to ensure timely return:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>By mail, including a postage paid return envelope;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>By email; or</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>By fax.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:insert>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="33|11|01|annos" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="33|11|01|annos">
          <annotations>
            <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Election Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|2-102">2-102</cite>(b)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|4">4</cite>), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|2-202">2-202</cite>(b), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|2-304">2-304</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|2-305">2-305</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|3-202">3-202</cite>.1, 9-303, 9-305, 9-306, 11-301, 11-302, and 11-30, and 11-304, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-04-17">Regulations .01, .02 adopted as an emergency provision effective February 1, 2000 (27:6 Md. R. 637); adopted permanently effective April 17, 2000 (27:7 Md. R. 709)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-12-13"><cite path="|33|11|01|.01|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective May 31, 2010 (37:11 Md. R. 768); August 19, 2013 (40:16 Md. R. 1346); September 16, 2013 (40:18 Md. R. 1480); January 13, 2020 (47:1 Md. R. 19); December 13, 2021 (48:25 Md. R. 1081)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-05-31"><cite path="|33|11|01|.03" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .03</cite> adopted effective May 31, 2010 (37:11 Md. R. 768)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-04-04"><cite path="|33|11|01|.04" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .04</cite> adopted effective April 4, 2022 (49:7 Md. R. 469)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-04-15"><cite path="|33|11|01|.04|D." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .04D</cite>— F adopted effective April 15, 2024 (51:7 Md. R. 335)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-29"><cite path="|33|11|01|.05" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .05</cite> adopted effective September 29, 2025 (52:19 Md. R. 957)</annotation>
          </annotations>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="33|11|03|.06" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="33|11|03|.06">
          <section cache:ref-path="33|11|03|.06">
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.06</num>
            <heading>Return of Ballot.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>Date Stamp Return Envelope.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Except as provided in <cite path="33|11|03|.06|A.|(2)" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">§A(2) of this regulation</cite>, whenever an absentee ballot is received by a local board office, the election director shall stamp the return envelope with the date received.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>The election director shall:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Stamp the return envelope with the date received if the local board received the return envelope on the day before the election or any day thereafter; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Store the return envelopes in a container labeled with the date the ballots were received.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>Ballots Returned Without Return Envelope. If an absentee ballot is returned in an envelope other than the envelope provided by the local board and the envelope was opened during the normal process of opening mail, the election director shall immediately:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Tape the envelope closed;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Initial the tape and write "Absentee" on the envelope; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>Stamp the envelope with the date received.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>C.</num>
              <text>Ballots Returned Without a Signed Oath.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Except as provided in <cite path="33|11|03|.06|C.|(3)" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">§C(3) of this regulation</cite>, if an absentee ballot is timely received but the voter did not sign the required oath, the election director shall:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>As soon as practicable, but not later than 3 business days after the election director determines that the voter failed to sign the oath, notify the voter that the voter did not sign the oath; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Explain how the voter can provide a signed oath and when the signed oath must be received for the voter's ballot to be accepted.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Method of Notification.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>The election director shall notify the voter using the voter's preferred method of communication, as indicated on the voter's form, to request the ballot.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>If the notice is not delivered using the voter's preferred method of communication, the election director shall use another means to notify the voter.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>If an absentee ballot is timely received on or after the second Wednesday after an election (and the ballot was otherwise completed and mailed on or before election day, as established by <cite path="|33|11|03|.08|B.|(4)|(b)" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .08B(4)(b) of this chapter</cite>, the election director shall make reasonable efforts to comply with §C(1) and (2) of this regulation.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>Method of Communication with Local Board.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>A voter may choose to communicate with the local board to correct the failure to sign the oath by text, email, portal, mailed form, and in-person visit to the local board.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>A voter may sign the oath by email, SBE-approved text application, mail, in-person visit to the local board, or other means offered by the State Board.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>D.</num>
              <text>Ballots Returned to Wrong Election Office.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>If an absentee ballot is received by the wrong election office, that office shall immediately:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Stamp the envelope with the date received; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Send the ballot to the appropriate local board office, with the ballot envelope unopened and, except for the date stamp, unmarked and unchanged in any way.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>The date stamped on the envelope under <cite path="33|11|03|.06|C.|(1)|(a)" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">§C(1)(a) of this regulation</cite> is the official date of receipt of that ballot.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>E.</num>
              <text>Ballot Return Envelope Returned Without an Absentee Ballot.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>If upon receipt of a ballot return envelope it is determined by the local board that there is no ballot contained in the envelope, the election director shall:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>If the identity of the voter can be determined:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <text>As soon as practicable, but not later than 3 business days after the election director determines that the voter failed to return a ballot, notify the voter that the voter did not return a ballot; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <text>Explain how the voter can provide their voted ballot, and explain when the ballot must be received for the voter's ballot to be counted; or</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>If the voter identity cannot be determined, document that on the return envelope.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Method of Notification.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>The election director shall notify the voter using the voter's preferred method of communication, as indicated on the voter's form, to request the ballot.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>If the notice is not delivered or cannot be delivered timely using the voter's preferred method of communication, the election director shall use another means to notify the voter.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>If an absentee ballot envelope is not received on or before election day, as established by <cite path="|33|11|03|.08|B.|(4)|(b)" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .08B(4)(b) of this chapter</cite>, the election director need not comply with §E(1) and (2) of this regulation.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>F.</num>
              <text>Ballots in Return Envelope with Request for Personal Identification Information. A return envelope marked with a request for personal identification information shall be considered a provisional ballot and canvassed under <cite path="|33.16.05" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">COMAR 33.16.05</cite>.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>G.</num>
              <text>Ballots Returned at an Early Voting Center or Polling Place. Whenever an absentee ballot is received at an early voting center or polling place, a chief judge or designee shall:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>Instruct the voter to put the voted absentee ballot into the absentee ballot bag;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Ensure the security of the absentee ballot bag; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>Return the absentee ballot bag to the local board of elections at the end of voting hours each day of early voting and on election day.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>H.</num>
              <text>Ballots Returned at a Designated Ballot-Return Location.</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>A voter can return a voted ballot at a ballot drop box designated by the local board to serve as ballot-return locations.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>The ballot drop box shall:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>Be designed to prevent an individual from accessing voted ballots once deposited;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>Include a statement that tampering with ballots is a crime; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>Include the State Board's phone number.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(3)</num>
                <text>The local board shall retrieve ballots and any other election materials according to chain of custody procedures issued by the State Administrator.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="33|11|03|annos" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="33|11|03|annos">
          <annotations>
            <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Election Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|2-102">2-102</cite>(b)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|4">4</cite>), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|2-202">2-202</cite>(b), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|2-305">2-305</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|9-303">9-303</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|9-305">9-305</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|9-306">9-306</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|9-310">9-310</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|11-301">11-301</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|11-302">11-302</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|11-304">11-304</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-04-17">Regulations <cite path="|33|11|03|.01" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">.01</cite>—<cite path="|33|11|03|.08" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">.08</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective February 1, 2000 (27:6 Md. R. 637); adopted permanently effective April 17, 2000 (27:7 Md. R. 709)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-11-24"><cite path="|33|11|03|.01|A." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .01A</cite> amended effective November 24, 2003 (30:23 Md. R. 1655)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-05-31"><cite path="|33|11|03|.02" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective May 31, 2010 (37:11 Md. R. 768)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-04-15"><cite path="|33|11|03|.02|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective November 24, 2003 (30:23 Md. R. 1655); April 15, 2024 (51:7 Md. R. 334)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-05-31"><cite path="|33|11|03|.03|C." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .03C</cite> adopted effective May 31, 2010 (37:11 Md. R. 768)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-09-16"><cite path="|33|11|03|.04" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective September 16, 2013 (40:18 Md. R. 1480)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-01-16"><cite path="|33|11|03|.04|A." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .04A</cite> amended effective January 16, 2006 (33:1 Md. R. 42)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-05-31"><cite path="|33|11|03|.04|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .04B</cite>, C amended effective May 31, 2010 (37:11 Md. R. 768)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-05-31"><cite path="|33|11|03|.05" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective May 31, 2010 (37:11 Md. R. 768)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-29"><cite path="|33|11|03|.06" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective May 31, 2010 (37:11 Md. R. 768); December 13, 2021 (48:25 Md. R. 1081); September 29, 2025 (52:19 Md. R. 957)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-09-04"><cite path="|33|11|03|.06|A." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .06A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective September 4, 2020 (47:20 Md. R. 873)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-04-18"><cite path="|33|11|03|.06|A." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .06A</cite> amended effective April 18, 2022 (49:8 Md. R. 501)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-10-14"><cite path="|33|11|03|.06|C." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .06C</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 3, 2002 (29:18 Md. R. 1440); amended permanently effective October 14, 2002 (29:20 Md. R. 1595)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-07-18"><cite path="|33|11|03|.06|C." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .06C</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 18, 2022 (49:17 Md. R. 788); emergency provision expired</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-04-15"><cite path="|33|11|03|.06|C." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .06C</cite> amended effective December 12, 2022 (49:25 Md. R. 1052); April 15, 2024 (51:7 Md. R. 335)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-01-13"><cite path="|33|11|03|.06|E." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .06E</cite> adopted effective January 13, 2020 (47:1 Md. R. 19)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-06-01"><cite path="|33|11|03|.06|E." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .06E</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective June 1, 2020 (47:13 Md. R. 640); emergency provision expired July 31, 2020</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-09-04"><cite path="|33|11|03|.06|F." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .06F</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective September 4, 2020 (47:20 Md. R. 873); emergency provision expired December 31, 2020</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-04-18"><cite path="|33|11|03|.06|G." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .06G</cite> adopted effective April 18, 2022 (49:8 Md. R. 501)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-08-14"><cite path="|33|11|03|.07|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .07B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective June 2, 2006 (33:13 Md. R. 1062); amended permanently effective August 14, 2006 (33:16 Md. R. 1366)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-02-29"><cite path="|33|11|03|.07|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .07B</cite> amended effective February 29, 2016 (43:4 Md. R. 335)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-10-14"><cite path="|33|11|03|.08|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .08B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 3, 2002 (29:18 Md. R. 1440); amended permanently effective October 14, 2002 (29:20 Md. R. 1595)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-11-24"><cite path="|33|11|03|.08|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .08B</cite> amended effective November 24, 2003 (30:23 Md. R. 1655)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-03-01"><cite path="|33|11|03|.08|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .08B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective January 2, 2004 (30:24 Md. R. 1738); amended permanently effective March 1, 2004 (31:4 Md. R. 319)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-01-06"><cite path="|33|11|03|.08|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .08B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective October 4, 2004 (31:20 Md. R. 1483); amended permanently effective January 6, 2005 (31:26 Md. R. 1868)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-09-25"><cite path="|33|11|03|.08|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .08B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective June 21, 2006 (33:15 Md. R. 1277); amended permanently effective September 25, 2006 (33:19 Md. R. 1562)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-07-27"><cite path="|33|11|03|.08|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .08B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 27, 2007 (34:18 Md. R. 1578)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-01-13"><cite path="|33|11|03|.08|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .08B</cite> amended effective September 24, 2007 (34:19 Md. R. 1650); March 19, 2012 (39:5 Md. R. 385); August 19, 2013 (40:16 Md. R. 1346); January 13, 2020 (47:1 Md. R. 19)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-06-01"><cite path="|33|11|03|.08|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .08B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective June 1, 2020 (47:13 Md. R. 640); emergency provision expired July 31, 2020</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-09-04"><cite path="|33|11|03|.08|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .08B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective September 4, 2020 (47:20 Md. R. 873); emergency provision expired December 31, 2020</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-04-15"><cite path="|33|11|03|.08|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .08B</cite> amended effective January 13, 2022 (49:1 Md. R. 16) ​​; April 15, 2024 (51:7 Md. R. 334)</annotation>
          </annotations>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:insert history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="33|12|04" before="annos" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="33|12|04|.07">
          <section>
            <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
            <num>.07</num>
            <heading>Effect of Ending a Recount Prior to Completion.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>A.</num>
              <text>In General. If a recount is not completed, the local board shall not make any changes to:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(1)</num>
                <text>The official returns; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(2)</num>
                <text>Any certificates that were issued on the basis of those returns.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>B.</num>
              <text>Notice to State Board of Elections. The local board shall immediately notify the State Board that the recount was terminated.</text>
            </para>
          </section>
        </codify:insert>
        <codify:replace history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="33|12|04|annos" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="33|12|04|annos">
          <annotations>
            <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Election Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|2-102">2-102</cite>(b)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|4">4</cite>), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|2-202">2-202</cite>(b), and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|12-106">12-106</cite>(a), Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-04-17">Regulations <cite path="|33|12|04|.01" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">.01</cite>—<cite path="|33|12|04|.06" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">.06</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective February 1, 2000 (27:6 Md. R. 637); adopted permanently effective April 17, 2000 (27:7 Md. R. 709)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-02-14"><cite path="|33|12|04|.02|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .02B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective October 22, 2004 (31:23 Md. R. 1650); amended permanently effective February 14, 2005 (32:3 Md. R. 290)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-08-14"><cite path="|33|12|04|.02|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .02B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective June 2, 2006 (33:13 Md. R. 1062); amended permanently effective August 14, 2006 (33:16 Md. R. 1366)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-03-09"><cite path="|33|12|04|.02|B." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .02B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective October 31, 2008 (35:24 Md. R. 2074); emergency status expired January 20, 2009; amended permanently effective March 9, 2009 (36:5 Md. R. 424)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-08-14"><cite path="|33|12|04|.03" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .03</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective June 2, 2006 (33:13 Md. R. 1062); amended permanently effective August 14, 2006 (33:16 Md. R. 1366)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-02-29"><cite path="|33|12|04|.06|A." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .06A</cite> amended effective February 29, 2016 (43:4 Md. R. 335)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-03-09"><cite path="|33|12|04|.06|C." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .06C</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective October 31, 2008 (35:24 Md. R. 2074); emergency status expired January 20, 2009; amended permanently effective March 9, 2009 (36:5 Md. R. 424)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-02-29"><cite path="|33|12|04|.06|A." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .06A</cite>, C amended effective February 29, 2016 (43:4 Md. R. 335)</annotation>
            <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-29"><cite path="|33|12|04|.07" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .07</cite> adopted effective September 29, 2025 (52:19 Md. R. 957)</annotation>
          </annotations>
        </codify:replace>
        <codify:insert history="false" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" path="33|17" codified:doc="Code of Maryland Regulations" codified:path="33|17|08|.01|annos">
          <container>
            <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
            <num>08</num>
            <heading>Appeals Process for Public Buildings</heading>
            <section>
              <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
              <num>.01</num>
              <heading>Purpose.</heading>
              <text>The purpose of this chapter is to provide a uniform procedure for a public building to appeal its selection as an early voting center by a local board of election, pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|10-301">Election Law Article, §10-301</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
            </section>
            <section>
              <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
              <num>.02</num>
              <heading>Public Building Defined.</heading>
              <text>“Public building” means a building, structure, or improved area that is:</text>
              <para>
                <num>A.</num>
                <text>Owned by the State or any political subdivision of the State; or</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>B.</num>
                <text>Leased by the State or a political subdivision of the State.</text>
              </para>
            </section>
            <section>
              <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
              <num>.03</num>
              <heading>Who May File.</heading>
              <text>A public official responsible for the public building that has been selected to be used as an early voting center by a local board may file an appeal under this chapter.</text>
            </section>
            <section cache:ref-path="33|17|08|.04">
              <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
              <num>.04</num>
              <heading>Form of Appeal.</heading>
              <para>
                <num>A.</num>
                <text>Writing and Notarization. An appeal shall be in writing, signed and sworn by the public official responsible for the public building, and notarized.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>The appeal shall provide the following information:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <text>Reason use of the public building is a hardship;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <text>Who the hardship affects;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <text>Any violations of law that would arise by using the public building as an early voting center; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(d)</num>
                    <text>Any other information pertinent to the designation of the public building as an early voting center or the hardship.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>The appeal must be in writing and bear the original signature of the public official.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>B.</num>
                <text>Prescribed or Other Form. The public official may use:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>The form prescribed by the State Board, which is available from the State or from any local board, or which may be downloaded from the State Board website; or</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>Any other form satisfying the requirements of <cite path="33|17|08|.04|A." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
            </section>
            <section>
              <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
              <num>.05</num>
              <heading>Place and Time for Filing; Copy for State Board.</heading>
              <para>
                <num>A.</num>
                <text>Place for Filing. An appeal shall be filed with the local board that selected the public building or use as an early voting center.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>B.</num>
                <text>Time for Filing. An appeal shall be filed within 15 days after the local board gives written notice of intent indicating that the public building will be used as an early voting center.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>C.</num>
                <text>Copy for State Board. The public official shall mail or deliver a copy of the appeal to the State Board, to the attention of the State Administrator.</text>
              </para>
            </section>
            <section>
              <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
              <num>.06</num>
              <heading>Opportunity to Be Heard by Local Board of Elections.</heading>
              <para>
                <num>A.</num>
                <text>General Requirements.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>If a local board issues a written notice of intent to the public building indicating that the public building will be used as an early voting center, the local board  shall offer the public official the opportunity to appear before the local board   to show cause why the public building should not be used for early voting.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>The opportunity to be heard shall be afforded the public official no more than 15 days after the request is made under <cite path="|33|17|08|.04" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>B.</num>
                <text>Notice Requirements. The notice requirements for the opportunity to be heard are as follows:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>The local board shall provide at least 72 hours notice of the board meeting where the public official will be given the opportunity to be heard.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>The public official shall confirm attendance at the board meeting 24 hours in advance of the meeting.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>C.</num>
                <text>Format of the Meeting.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>The members of the local board may be recognized by the presiding member to ask questions of either party appearing before the local board.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>The public official may:</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <text>Present witnesses;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <text>Submit evidence; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <text>Respond to questions from members and the presiding member of the local board.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <text>The local board shall determine the amount of time the public official has to be heard, and present evidence and witnesses.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <text>The opportunity to be heard shall be offered in person or virtually.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
            </section>
            <section cache:ref-path="33|17|08|.07">
              <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
              <num>.07</num>
              <heading>Decision by Local Board of Elections.</heading>
              <para>
                <num>A.</num>
                <text>Final Determination.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>If there has been no information provided under <cite path="|33|17|08|.06" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>, the local board shall review the record and determine whether the decision to use the public building as an early voting center should be upheld.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>After an opportunity to be heard is provided under <cite path="|33|17|08|.06" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>, the local board shall determine whether use of the public building would constitute an undue burden on the public building.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>B.</num>
                <text>Form of Determination.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>The local board shall provide written notice of its decision under <cite path="33|17|08|.07|A." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">§A of this regulation</cite> within 3 days of the opportunity to be heard.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>The local board shall explain in the written decision the reasons for the determination.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <text>The local board shall include information about the public official’s ability to appeal to the State Board.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>C.</num>
                <text>Notice of Determination. The final determination of the local board shall be:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>Mailed to the public official, the State Board, and any other interested person who has asked in writing to be advised of the final determination;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>Published on the State Board website; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <text>Made available on request to any interested person.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
            </section>
            <section cache:ref-path="33|17|08|.08">
              <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
              <num>.08</num>
              <heading>Appeal to the State Board of Elections.</heading>
              <para>
                <num>A.</num>
                <text>Place for Filing.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>If a local board denies an appeal by a public official under <cite path="|33|17|08|.07" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite>, the public official may appeal the decision to the State Board.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>A complaint shall be filed with the State Board to the attention of the State Administrator.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>B.</num>
                <text>Contents of Filing: The appeal shall provide the following information:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>Reason use of the public building is a hardship;</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <text>Who the hardship affects;</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <text>Any violations of law that would arise by using the public building as an early voting center; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <text>Any other information pertinent to the designation of the public building as an early voting center or the hardship.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>How the local board abused its discretion in selecting the public building for use as an early voting center.</text>
                  <para>
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <text>Request an absentee ballot for a special election; and</text>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <text>Return an absentee ballot by mail in a timely manner.</text>
                  </para>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>C.</num>
                <text>Prescribed or Other Form. The public official may use:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>The form prescribed by the State Board, which is available from the State or from any local board, or which may be downloaded from the State Board website; or</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>Any other form satisfying the requirements of <cite path="33|17|08|.08|A." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <text>The appeal must be in writing, signed and sworn by the public official responsible for the public building, and notarized.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>D.</num>
                <text>Time for Filing. A complaint shall be filed within 5 days after the local board gives notice that appeal has been denied.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>E.</num>
                <text>Copy for Local Board. The public official shall mail or deliver a copy of the complaint to the local board, to the attention of the election director.</text>
              </para>
            </section>
            <section>
              <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
              <num>.09</num>
              <heading>Opportunity to be Heard by the State Board of Elections.</heading>
              <para>
                <num>A.</num>
                <text>If the public official appeals an adverse decision by the local board, the State Board shall offer the public official the opportunity to appear before the Board to show cause why the public building should not be used for early voting.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>B.</num>
                <text>Notice Requirements. The notice requirements for the opportunity to be heard are as follows:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>The State Board shall provide the local board and public official at least 72 hours notice of the board meeting where the public official will be given the opportunity to be heard.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>The public official and local board shall confirm attendance at the board meeting 24 hours in advance of the meeting.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>C.</num>
                <text>The members of the State Board may be recognized by the presiding member to ask questions of either party appearing before the State Board.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>D.</num>
                <text>If a public official or local board chooses not to attend in person, the opportunity to submit a written response shall be provided by the State Board.</text>
              </para>
            </section>
            <section cache:ref-path="33|17|08|.10">
              <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
              <num>.10</num>
              <heading>Decision by State Board of Elections.</heading>
              <para>
                <num>A.</num>
                <text>Final Determination.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>If there has been no information provided under <cite path="|33|17|08|.09" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .09 of this chapter</cite>, the State Board shall review the record and determine whether the decision to use the public building as an early voting center should be upheld.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>After an opportunity to be heard is provided under <cite path="|33|17|08|.09" doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">Regulation .09 of this chapter</cite>, the State Board shall determine whether the local board abused its discretion in determining that the use of the public building would not constitute an undue burden.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>B.</num>
                <text>Form of Determination.</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>The State Board shall provide written notice of its decision under <cite path="33|17|08|.10|A." doc="Code of Maryland Regulations">§A of this regulation</cite> within 3 days of the opportunity to be heard.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>The State Board shall explain in a written decision the reasons for the determination.</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <text>The State Board shall include that the decision is final.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>C.</num>
                <text>Notice of Determination. The final determination of the State Board shall be:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>Mailed to the public official, the local board, and any other interested person who has asked in writing to be advised of the final determination;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>Published on the State Board website; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <text>Made available on request to any interested person.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
            </section>
            <annotations>
              <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Election Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|2-102">2-102</cite>(b)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|4">4</cite>), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|2-202">2-202</cite>(b), and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|10-301">10-301</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
              <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-29">Effective date: September 29, 2025 (52:19 Md. R. 957)</annotation>
            </annotations>
          </container>
        </codify:insert>
      </container>
    </container>
  </container>
</document>
