<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>14</num>
  <heading>Driver Knowledge and Skills Tests</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>The purpose of these regulations is to establish uniform procedures for the:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Administration of driver's license skills and knowledge tests; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Establishment of waiver criteria for commercial driver's license skills tests.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Administration" means the Motor Vehicle Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Air brakes" means any braking system operating fully or partially on the air brake principle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Alternative test” means a knowledge test that is given orally either by an individual or in which an electronic oral test is presented to the applicant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Class A combination" means a combination of vehicles with a GVWR of 26,001 or more pounds provided the GCWR of the vehicle or vehicles being towed is in excess of 10,000 pounds.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Class F (tractor)" means a truck tractor or farm truck tractor used for propelling, supporting, or drawing a trailer or semitrailer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Class G (trailer)" means a freight or nonfreight trailer or semitrailer over 10,000 pounds GVWR designed to be pulled by a Class F (tractor).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Combination vehicle knowledge test" means the test which the Administration has established as a means of testing the knowledge of an applicant for a license which authorizes driving Class A combinations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Commercial driver's license (CDL)" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|11-109">Transportation Article, §11-109, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Commercial motor vehicle (CMV)" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-803">Transportation Article, §16-803, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Conviction" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-803">Transportation Article, §16-803, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Double/triple trailer endorsement" means a State-issued endorsement which authorizes the licensee to drive combinations of two or more trailers or semitrailers.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>"Gross vehicle weight rating (GVWR)" and "gross combination weight rating (GCWR)" have the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-803">Transportation Article, §16-803, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>"HAZMAT endorsement" and "hazardous materials endorsement" means a State-issued endorsement which authorizes the licensee to drive vehicles which are required to be placarded under Federal Hazardous Materials Regulations, 49 CFR Part 172, Subpart F.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>“Knowledge test” means a written, electronic, or oral test which is administered to any driver’s license applicant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>"Passenger transport endorsement" means a State-issued endorsement which authorizes the licensee to drive vehicles which are intended to transport 16 or more passengers, including the driver.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>"Passenger transport vehicle" means a vehicle which is designed to transport 16 or more passengers, including the driver.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>"Physical qualifications" means the physical qualifications specified by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>49 CFR §391.11, which is incorporated by reference, for interstate operations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text><cite path="|11.21.01">COMAR 11.21.01</cite>, for intrastate operations; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text><cite path="|11.19.05">COMAR 11.19.05</cite>, for school vehicle operations.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>"Regularly employed" means currently employed, or having been employed, during the preceding 2 years in a job requiring operation of a commercial motor vehicle of the equivalent class.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>"School vehicle" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|11-154">Transportation Article, §11-154, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>"School vehicle endorsement" means a State-issued endorsement for a license to operate a school vehicle issued under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-815">Transportation Article, §16-815, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and in accordance with 49 CFR §383.123.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>"School vehicle knowledge test" means a test that meets the knowledge test requirements of 49 CFR §383.123 for a school vehicle endorsement administered by the Administration to an applicant for a commercial driver's license school vehicle endorsement.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>"Skills log" means a formal document with a certification page issued by the Administration to certify that a minimum of 40 hours of practice driving beyond the required driver's education course was accomplished by a noncommercial Type I Learner's Instructional Permit holder.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>"Skills test" means a driving test given to assess an applicant's ability to drive motor vehicles of a specific class.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(24)</num>
        <text>“State” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|11-161">Transportation Article, §11-161, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(25)</num>
        <text>"Tank vehicle" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-803">Transportation Article, §16-803, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(26)</num>
        <text>"Tanker endorsement" means a State-issued endorsement which authorizes the licensee to drive or tow tank vehicles.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(27)</num>
        <text>"Tillerman" means the second (rear) driver for the pivotable rear wheels of an articulated vehicle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Application — Repealed.</heading>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Maryland Knowledge Test.</heading>
    <text>A driver’s license applicant is required to pass the Maryland knowledge test, except a holder of a valid Maryland driver’s license, a holder of Maryland driver’s license that has not been expired for more than 1 year, or a valid out-of-State driver’s license.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Commercial Driver's License Knowledge Tests.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant for a commercial driver's license is required to pass the commercial driver's license general knowledge test except:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A Maryland commercial driver's license renewal applicant;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A holder of a valid Maryland commercial driver's license who is applying for another class of commercial driver's license; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An applicant who is transferring a valid commercial driver's license, issued by another state, to a Maryland commercial driver's license.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A Class A commercial driver's license applicant is required to pass the commercial driver's license combination vehicle knowledge test, except:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A Maryland Class A commercial driver's license renewal applicant; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An applicant who is transferring a valid Class A commercial driver's license, issued by another state, to a Maryland commercial driver's license.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An applicant for a double/triple endorsement is required to pass the commercial driver's license double/triple knowledge test, except:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A Maryland Class A commercial driver's license renewal applicant with an existing double/triple endorsement; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An applicant who is transferring a valid Class A commercial driver's license with a double/triple endorsement, issued by another state, to a Maryland commercial driver's license.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An applicant for a tanker endorsement is required to pass the commercial driver's license tanker knowledge test, except:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A Maryland commercial driver's license renewal applicant with an existing tanker endorsement; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An applicant who is transferring a commercial driver's license with a tanker endorsement issued by another state to a Maryland commercial driver's license.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Hazardous Materials Endorsement.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An applicant for a hazardous materials endorsement is required to pass the hazardous materials knowledge test, except for existing commercial driver's license holders who are applying for a corrected or duplicate commercial driver's license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An applicant for the renewal or transfer of a commercial driver's license with a hazardous materials endorsement is required to pass the hazardous materials knowledge test regardless of the length of time the applicant has had a hazardous materials endorsement.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>An applicant for a passenger transport endorsement is required to pass the commercial driver's license passenger transport knowledge test, except:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A Maryland commercial driver's license renewal applicant with an existing passenger transport endorsement; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An applicant who is transferring a valid commercial driver's license with a passenger transport endorsement, issued by another state, to a Maryland commercial driver's license.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>An applicant who wishes to drive a commercial motor vehicle equipped with air brakes is required to pass the commercial driver's license air brakes knowledge test, except:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A Maryland commercial driver's license renewal applicant who has previously passed the test in this section; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An applicant who is transferring a valid commercial driver's license without an air brake restriction, issued by another state, to a Maryland commercial driver's license.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>School Vehicle Endorsement.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An applicant for a commercial driver's license with a school vehicle endorsement is required to pass the school vehicle knowledge test.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An applicant for the renewal, upgrade, or transfer of a commercial driver's license with a school vehicle endorsement is required to pass the school vehicle knowledge test regardless of the length of time the applicant has had a school vehicle endorsement, except:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An applicant for the renewal or upgrade of a commercial driver's license with a school vehicle endorsement who has previously passed the school vehicle knowledge test; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An applicant renewing a commercial driver's license with a school vehicle endorsement issued before September 30, 2006, provided the applicant passes the school vehicle knowledge test before September 30, 2006.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A school vehicle endorsement held by a commercial driver's licensee who has not passed the school vehicle knowledge test shall be cancelled without further action by the Administration at 12:01 a.m. on September 30, 2006.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Cancellation of the school vehicle endorsement does not affect the validity of the commercial driver's license or any other endorsement.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>All applicants for a commercial driver's license with a school vehicle endorsement shall also meet the requirements for a passenger transport endorsement before the issuance of a school vehicle endorsement.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Administration of Commercial Driver's License Knowledge Tests.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Administration may offer Maryland commercial driver’s license knowledge tests in written, electronic, or alternative formats.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An applicant also shall be required to demonstrate the ability to read and understand highway signs regulating, warning, and directing traffic in English.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The passing score on all commercial driver's license knowledge tests is 80 percent.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall offer the commercial driver’s license hazardous material knowledge test in a written or electronic format only.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An applicant for a school vehicle endorsement, and an applicant surrendering a valid commercial driver's license with a school vehicle endorsement issued by another state, for a Maryland commercial driver's license, shall pass the commercial driver's license knowledge tests for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Passenger transport; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>School vehicles.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>In addition to taking and passing the commercial driver's knowledge tests, an individual shall take and pass specialized tests to qualify for an endorsement to operate the following types of vehicles:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Double or triple trailers;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Passenger vehicles;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Tank vehicles;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Vehicles transporting hazardous materials as defined in 49 CFR §383.5; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>School vehicles.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|17|14|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Commercial Driver's License Skills Tests.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The commercial driver's license skills test is a three-part test established by the Administration to certify the driving skills necessary for operation of a commercial motor vehicle. The test consists of a:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Pretrip inspection;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Basic skills test; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Road test.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A commercial driver's license applicant is required to pass the commercial driver's license skills test in the order specified in <cite path="11|17|14|.07|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, except:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An out-of-State applicant with a valid commercial driver's license who is transferring to a Maryland commercial driver's license of the same class;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A Maryland commercial driver's license renewal applicant; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An applicant who qualifies for a waiver of skills test as defined in <cite path="|11|17|14|.08">Regulation .08 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A skills test applicant shall provide an appropriate vehicle for the skills test purposes.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A skills test applicant shall pay the skills test fee as set forth in <cite path="|11.11.05">COMAR 11.11.05</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Failure of the pretrip inspection is considered a failure of a skills test for purposes of the skills retest fee set forth in <cite path="|11.11.05">COMAR 11.11.05</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>An appointment is required for the CDL skills test.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>An applicant who fails to arrive ready for testing with 15 minutes of the scheduled appointment shall be denied testing and must pay the retest fee set forth in <cite path="|11.11.05">COMAR 11.11.05</cite> before scheduling the next appointment.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Waiver of Commercial Driver's License Skills Test.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Administration may waive the commercial driver's license skills test for an applicant who is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Renewing a Maryland commercial driver’s license not expired over 1 year;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Transferring a valid out-of-State commercial driver's license to a Maryland commercial driver's license; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Converting a noncommercial Class C license or out-of-State equivalent license to a Maryland Class C commercial driver's license without a passenger endorsement.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An individual converting a commercial Class C license or an individual with an out-of-State equivalent license may obtain a commercial Class C driver's license with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>No endorsement;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A hazardous materials endorsement;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A tanker endorsement; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Any combination of §B(1)—(3) of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The commercial driver's license skills test may be waived if the applicant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Submits a commercial driver's license skills test waiver supplied by the Administration, certifying that during a 2-year period immediately before applying for a commercial driver's license, the applicant has not had;</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>More than one license;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A driving privilege or license suspended, revoked, canceled, or disqualified;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A conviction for any type of motor vehicle violation of a disqualifying offense contained in Table 1 under 49 CFR §383.51(b);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>More than one conviction for any type of motor vehicle serious traffic violation contained in Table 2 under 49 CFR §383.51(c);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>A conviction for a violation of State or local law relating to motor vehicle traffic control, other than parking, arising in connection with any traffic accident; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>A record of an accident in which the applicant was at fault; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provides evidence and certifies that the applicant is regularly employed in a job requiring operation of a commercial motor vehicle, and that either the applicant has:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Previously taken and passed a skills test given by a state with a classified licensing and testing system, and that the test was behind the wheel in a representative vehicle for that applicant's driver's license classification, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Operated, for at least 2 years immediately preceding application for a commercial driver's license, a vehicle representative of the commercial motor vehicle the driver applicant operates or expects to operate.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08-1</num>
    <heading>Physical Qualifications for New Commercial Driver License Applicants.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant for a Class A or B learner's instructional permit is required to show evidence that the applicant meets the physical qualifications specified for interstate or intrastate operation, as appropriate.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An applicant applying to add a hazardous materials endorsement to an existing commercial driver's license is required to show evidence that the applicant meets the physical qualifications specified for interstate or intrastate operation, as appropriate.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An applicant applying to add a passenger endorsement to an existing commercial driver's license is required to show evidence that the applicant meets the physical qualifications specified for interstate, intrastate, or school vehicle operation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Appropriate Motor Vehicle Commercial Driver's License Skills Tests.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each applicant for a commercial driver's license shall provide a motor vehicle of a type appropriate to test the applicant's ability to drive vehicles of the license class for which applied.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Class A Commercial Driver's License Skills Test.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For a Class A commercial driver's license skills test, the applicant shall provide a Class A combination of vehicles that include a Class F (tractor) and a Class G (trailer).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the applicant provides a combination of vehicles other than a Class F (tractor) and a Class G (trailer), the Administration shall restrict the applicant to combinations of vehicles other than tractor-trailers.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the combination of vehicles is not equipped with air brakes, the Administration shall restrict the applicant to vehicles without air brakes.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the motor vehicle is not a passenger transport vehicle (bus) designed to transport 16 or more passengers, the Administration may not endorse the applicant's license for a passenger transport vehicle in that class of vehicle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If the vehicle is equipped with a rear driving position and pivoting rear wheels, the tillerman shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be required to hold the wheels which the tillerman controls in a centered position during the skills test; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Have a valid driver's license in the tillerman's possession.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>If the motor vehicle is not a school vehicle designed to transport 16 or more passengers, the Administration may not endorse the applicant's license for a school vehicle in that class of vehicle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Class B Commercial Driver's License Skills Test. The applicant shall provide a single motor vehicle with a GVWR of 26,001 or more pounds. If the vehicle is not:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Equipped with air brakes, the Administration shall restrict the applicant to vehicles without air brakes;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A passenger transport vehicle (bus) designed to transport 16 or more passengers, the Administration may not endorse the applicant's license for a passenger transport vehicle in that class of vehicle; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A school vehicle designed to transport 16 or more passengers, the Administration may not endorse the applicant's license for a school vehicle in that class of vehicle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Class C Commercial Driver's License Skills Test.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a Class C commercial driver's license skills test is required, the applicant shall provide a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Single motor vehicle with a GVWR more than 10,000 pounds and less than 26,001 pounds;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Passenger transport vehicle with a GVWR less than 26,001 pounds;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>School vehicle with a GVWR less than 26,001 pounds; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Combination of vehicles with a GCW in excess of 26,001 pounds with the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Towed unit not in excess of 10,000 pounds, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Power unit less than 26,001 pounds.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the vehicle or combination of vehicles is not equipped with air brakes, the Administration shall restrict the applicant to vehicles without air brakes.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the motor vehicle is not a passenger transport vehicle (bus) designed to transport 16 or more passengers, the Administration may not endorse the applicant's license for a passenger transport vehicle in that class of vehicle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Passenger Transport (Bus) Endorsements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For a Class B passenger transport vehicle endorsement, the applicant shall provide a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Passenger transport vehicle with a GVWR of 26,001 or more pounds that is designed to transport 16 or more passengers, including the driver; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Full size Type I school vehicle that is designed to transport 49 or more passengers, including the driver.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For a Class C passenger transport vehicle endorsement, the applicant shall provide a passenger transport vehicle with a GVWR not in excess of 26,000 pounds that is designed to transport 16 or more passengers, including the driver.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Noncommercial Driver's License Knowledge Tests.</heading>
    <text>An applicant for a Maryland noncommercial driver's license shall be administered a noncommercial knowledge test and may be administered additional tests specific to the license class for which applied, except an applicant who is:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Renewing a Maryland noncommercial driver's license; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Transferring a valid driver's license of equal or higher class, issued by another state, to a Maryland noncommercial license.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Administration of Noncommercial Driver’s License Knowledge Tests.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Maryland noncommercial driver’s license knowledge tests may be offered in written, electronic, or alternative formats.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall set a time limit for an applicant to complete the Maryland noncommercial driver’s license knowledge test.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The passing score on the Maryland knowledge test is 85 percent.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Noncommercial Driver's License Skills Tests.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The noncommercial driver's license skills test shall be established by the Administration to certify the driving skills necessary for operation of a noncommercial motor vehicle.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The noncommercial driver's license skills test shall consist of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Maneuvers performed on a test course;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In-traffic driving;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any examination designed to determine driving skills in a simulated or computer-assisted environment; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Any combination of tests described in §B(1), (2), or (3) of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Before a skills test, a Type I (Initial License Issuance) learner’s permit holder shall submit, to the Administration, in a format determined by the Administration, a completed and signed skills log containing a certification page as described in <cite path="|11|17|14|.13">Regulation .13 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Administration may require appointment scheduling for skills tests.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Skills Log Certification.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A skills log shall include a certification page providing the learner permit holder's:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Name;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Permit or soundex number; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Parent, guardian, or mentor's signature as required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-105">Transportation Article, §16-105, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The individual signing the skills log certification shall attest that the permit holder completed a minimum of 60 hours behind-the-wheel practice driving, 10 hours of which shall occur during the period beginning 30 minutes before sunset and ending 30 minutes after sunrise, under the supervision of a licensed driver who is 21 years old or older with at least 3 years driving experience.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>After the permit holder meets all requirements and successfully completes the skills test, the Administration shall retain, in the records of the Administration, the skills log certification page as part of the permit holder's license application.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|17|14|.14">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Appropriate Motor Vehicle for Noncommercial Skills Tests.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each applicant for a noncommercial driver's license shall provide a motor vehicle of a type appropriate to test the applicant's ability to drive vehicles of the license class for which applied.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Class A Noncommercial Driver's License Skills Tests.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For a Class A noncommercial driver's license skills test, the applicant shall provide a Class A combination of vehicles as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A Class F (tractor) and a Class G (trailer); or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Other than a Class F (tractor) and a Class G (trailer), the vehicles shall have a GCWR of 26,001 or more pounds, with the towed vehicle and trailer having a GVWR of 10,001 or more pounds.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Administration shall restrict an applicant to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Combinations of vehicles other than tractors and trailers if the combination of vehicles described in <cite path="11|17|14|.14|B.|(1)|(b)">§B(1)(b) of this regulation</cite> is provided; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Vehicles without air brakes if the combination of vehicles provided is not equipped with air brakes.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the vehicle is equipped with a rear driving position and pivoting rear wheels, the tillerman shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be required to hold the wheels which the tillerman controls in a centered position during the skills test; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Have a valid driver's license in the tillerman's possession.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Class B Noncommercial Driver's License Skills Tests.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For a Class B noncommercial driver's license skills test, the applicant shall provide a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Single, noncommercial motor vehicle with a GVWR of 26,001 or more pounds; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Combination of motor vehicles with a GCWR of 26,001 or more pounds with the towed vehicle not to exceed a GVWR of 10,000 pounds.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the vehicle is not equipped with air brakes, the Administration shall restrict the applicant to vehicles without air brakes.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Class C Noncommercial Driver's License Skills Tests. For a Class C noncommercial driver's license skills test, the applicant shall provide an automobile, station wagon, light truck, or any motor vehicle, other than a motorcycle, with a GVWR less than 26,001 pounds.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Class M Noncommercial Driver's License Skills Tests.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For a Class M noncommercial driver's license skills test, the applicant shall provide a motorcycle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Administration shall restrict the applicant to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A motorcycle with a sidecar if provided by the applicant; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A three-wheeled motorcycle if provided by the applicant.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|11-109">11-109</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-104">12-104</cite>(b), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-105">16-105</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-110">16-110</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-807">16-807</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland;<br/>49 CFR §§383.123 and 383.77</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-12-25">Effective date: December 25, 1989 (16:25 Md. R. 2713)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-06-12"><cite path="|11|17|14|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective August 1, 1994 (21:15 Md. R. 1307); August 28, 1995 (22:17 Md. R. 1320); June 12, 2000 (27:11 Md. R. 1079)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-09-30"><cite path="|11|17|14|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 26, 2005 (32:17 Md. R. 1437); emergency status expired effective September 30, 2005</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-03-13"><cite path="|11|17|14|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective September 30, 2005 (32:23 Md. R. 1824); adopted permanently effective March 13, 2006 (33:5 Md. R. 521)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-07-30"><cite path="|11|17|14|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective July 30, 2018 (45:15 Md. R. 726)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-07-30"><cite path="|11|17|14|.03">Regulation .03</cite> repealed effective July 30, 2018 (45:15 Md. R. 726)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-07-30"><cite path="|11|17|14|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective June 12, 2000 (27:11 Md. R. 1079); July 30, 2018 (45:15 Md. R. 726)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-06-12"><cite path="|11|17|14|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective June 12, 2000 (27:11 Md. R. 1079)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-08-01"><cite path="|11|17|14|.05|E.">Regulation .05E</cite> amended effective August 1, 1994 (21:15 Md. R. 1307)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-03-13"><cite path="|11|17|14|.05|H.">Regulation .05H</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective September 30, 2005 (32:23 Md. R. 1824); adopted permanently effective March 13, 2006 (33:5 Md. R. 521)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-07-30"><cite path="|11|17|14|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective June 12, 2000 (27:11 Md. R. 1079); July 30, 2018 (45:15 Md. R. 726)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-01-20"><cite path="|11|17|14|.06|D.">Regulation .06D</cite> amended effective July 8, 1991 (18:13 Md. R. 1483); January 20, 2025 (52:1 Md. R. 18)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-09-30"><cite path="|11|17|14|.06|F.">Regulation .06F</cite>, G, H adopted as an emergency provision effective July 26, 2005 (32:17 Md. R. 1437); emergency status expired effective September 30, 2005</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-03-13"><cite path="|11|17|14|.06|F.">Regulation .06F</cite>, G adopted as an emergency provision effective September 30, 2005 (32:23 Md. R. 1824); adopted permanently effective March 13, 2006 (33:5 Md. R. 521)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-01-01"><cite path="|11|17|14|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective January 1, 1992 (18:25 Md. R. 2756)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-11-16"><cite path="|11|17|14|.07|E.">Regulation .07E</cite> amended effective November 16, 1998 (25:23 Md. R. 1697)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-06-12"><cite path="|11|17|14|.07|G.">Regulation .07G</cite> amended effective June 12, 2000 (27:11 Md. R. 1079)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-08-01"><cite path="|11|17|14|.08">Regulation .08</cite> repealed and new Regulations .08 and .08-1 adopted effective August 1, 1994 (21:15 Md. R. 1307)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-07-30"><cite path="|11|17|14|.08|A.">Regulation .08A</cite> amended effective July 8, 1991 (18:13 Md. R. 1483); July 30, 2018 (45:15 Md. R. 726)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-06-12"><cite path="|11|17|14|.08|C.">Regulation .08C</cite> amended effective June 12, 2000 (27:11 Md. R. 1079)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-09-30"><cite path="|11|17|14|.08|C.">Regulation .08C</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 26, 2005 (32:17 Md. R. 1437); emergency status expired effective September 30, 2005</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-03-13"><cite path="|11|17|14|.08|C.">Regulation .08C</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective September 30, 2005 (32:23 Md. R. 1824); adopted permanently effective March 13, 2006 (33:5 Md. R. 521)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-06-12"><cite path="|11|17|14|.09">Regulation .09</cite> amended effective June 12, 2000 (27:11 Md. R. 1079)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-09-30"><cite path="|11|17|14|.09">Regulation .09</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 26, 2005 (32:17 Md. R. 1437); emergency status expired effective September 30, 2005</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-03-13"><cite path="|11|17|14|.09">Regulation .09</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective September 30, 2005 (32:23 Md. R. 1824); adopted permanently effective March 13, 2006 (33:5 Md. R. 521)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-11-16"><cite path="|11|17|14|.09|B.">Regulation .09B</cite> amended effective November 16, 1998 (25:23 Md. R. 1697)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-06-12">Regulations <cite path="|11|17|14|.10">.10</cite>—<cite path="|11|17|14|.14">.14</cite> adopted effective June 12, 2000 (27:11 Md. R. 1079)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-07-30"><cite path="|11|17|14|.11|A.">Regulation .11A</cite>, B amended effective July 30, 2018 (45:15 Md. R. 726)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-11-24"><cite path="|11|17|14|.11|B.">Regulation .11B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective August 12, 2014 (41:18 Md. R. 1008); amended permanently effective November 24, 2014 (41:23 Md. R.1374)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-10-01"><cite path="|11|17|14|.13|B.">Regulation .13B</cite> amended effective October 1, 2005 (32:18 Md. R. 1520)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-07-30"><cite path="|11|17|14|.12">Regulation .12</cite> amended effective July 30, 2018 (45:15 Md. R. 726)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-09-30"><cite path="|11|17|14|.14">Regulation .14</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 26, 2005 (32:17 Md. R. 1437); emergency status expired effective September 30, 2005</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-03-13"><cite path="|11|17|14|.14">Regulation .14</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective September 30, 2005 (32:23 Md. R. 1824); adopted permanently effective March 13, 2006 (33:5 Md. R. 521)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
