<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>19</num>
  <heading>Issuance of Temporary Driver Licenses Valid in Maryland Only</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>This chapter establishes procedures for the issuance of a 90-day temporary driver's license, valid in Maryland only, as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-113">Transportation Article, §16-113(e), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Administration" means the Motor Vehicle Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Initial violation" means the originating action or charge that led to the suspension or revocation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Jurisdiction" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-401">Transportation Article, §12-401, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Revoked" means to terminate, by formal action, an individual's license or privilege to drive a motor vehicle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Suspended" means to withdraw temporarily, by formal action, an individual's license or privilege to drive a motor vehicle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Temporary driver's license" means a temporary license issued to an eligible individual for a period not to exceed 90 days that allows the individual to operate a motor vehicle in Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Application.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Administration may issue a temporary driver's license, which is valid only in Maryland, for a period not to exceed 90 days if the individual:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is suspended or revoked in another jurisdiction;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Previously held a valid Maryland driver's license;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Has made application:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>To renew the valid Maryland driver's license,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For a duplicate or corrected driver's license,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>For a driver's license after approval for reinstatement of a revoked Maryland driver's license, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>For a replacement driver's license after withdrawal of a suspension against the Maryland driver's license;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Is revoked or suspended in another jurisdiction as a result of failing to comply with its licensing requirements, but would not have been suspended or revoked in this State for a comparable violation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Did not receive the initial violation that led to the suspension or revocation within the preceding 5 years;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Is otherwise qualified to be licensed in Maryland; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Has the opportunity to satisfy all requirements of the initial violation and receive clearance from the jurisdiction in question within the 90-day temporary license period.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration may not issue a temporary driver's license which is valid in Maryland if the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Individual is suspended or revoked in more than one jurisdiction;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Individual holds a commercial driver's license, unless the license is downgraded to a noncommercial license;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Initial violation that led to the suspension or revocation occurred less than 5 years before the date of application for the temporary driver's license;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Initial violation that led to the revocation or suspension resulted from any offense that involved a fatality;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Initial violation that led to the revocation or suspension resulted from an offense or charges involving the use of alcohol or drugs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Clearance requirement of the other jurisdiction cannot be met within the 90-day temporary license period;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Applicant's privilege to drive is cancelled, refused, or disqualified in another jurisdiction;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Individual is suspended, revoked, cancelled, refused, or disqualified in Maryland; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Applicant is not otherwise qualified to be licensed in Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-104">12-104</cite>(b) and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|16-113">16-113</cite>(e), Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-04-16">Effective date: April 16, 2001 (28:7 Md. R. 692)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
