<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Procedure for Application, Evaluation, and Issuance of Certificates</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Application Procedure.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Before submission of an application, a potential applicant may be requested to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Attend a preliminary conference with the Secretary to obtain information concerning the Board's procedures, guidelines, policies, and scheduling regarding submission of applications; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Have first applied for any regulatory permits required and to have progressed at least through evaluation of preliminary design concepts in pursuit of these permits.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Dates When Applications Are to Be Accepted.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board shall specify dates when applications will be accepted.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Board may declare closed periods in which applications may not be accepted when:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Studies are underway which have been directed by the Board, or which are being conducted by another source and which promise to materially improve the Board's capability to conduct an adequate review;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Board has directed the Service to submit an application;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Board is in the process of obtaining the resources necessary to conduct an adequate review.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All dates governing submission of applications will be established by action of the Board in open session and published in the Maryland Register.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Schedule of Fees.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The fee for processing an application for a certificate of public necessity shall consist of two parts, an initial application fee and a processing fee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The initial application fee for all applications shall be $10,000, to be paid by certified check. This fee shall cover the cost of initial review of an application. The initial application fee is not refundable.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>As part of the determination of completeness of an application, the Board will determine, in its sole discretion, the costs of evaluation and processing of the application. The estimated cost shall include the cost of additional staff, if any, consultants, hearing officer, reporter and transcripts, transportation, witnesses called by the Board, meeting places and associated expenses, and other costs which are attributable directly to the evaluation and processing of the application. The sum of these estimated costs shall constitute the processing fee to be paid by the applicant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Once determined and paid by the applicant, the processing fee is not subject to increase or decrease, except that if processing of an application is terminated before the start of any services which formed part of the fee calculation, that portion of the fee shall be refunded to the applicant. For any processing partially or fully undertaken, there shall be no refund of the fee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Submission and Evaluation of Application.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The applicant shall submit 50 copies of the application to the Secretary.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The initial application fee shall accompany the application. An initial application will not be reviewed until the full initial fee has been received.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Secretary will promptly acknowledge, by certified mail, the receipt of any application. Notice of receipt, however, does not signify any decision regarding the completeness of the application.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Secretary shall transmit five copies of the application to the Department as an application for a facility permit. Transmittal by the Board does not signify completeness of the application or relieve the applicant of any additional or subsequent requirements by the Department or any other regulatory agency.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Board may conduct working sessions with an applicant, in either open or closed session (depending on whether confidential information will be discussed, or otherwise as law permits) to further its review of the completeness of the application.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The Board shall determine in its sole discretion the completeness of any application.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The Board, upon a determination of completeness, shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Advise the applicant of the amount of the processing fee. The determination of completeness will not be submitted for publication in the Maryland Register in accordance with§D(7)(b) until the Board has received from the applicant the full processing fee.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Announce the determination by publication in the Maryland Register. The date of publication commences the 6-month processing time for consideration of applications required by the Act.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Secretary shall mail copies of the application to recipients designated by law and as directed by the Board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Board may discontinue consideration of a completed application at any time if it determines that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The application contains materially false information;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A State or federal regulatory agency has denied a required permit or the Board has reason to believe that a required permit cannot be obtained;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Board amends its adopted policy as to the need for any type of facility; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>There exists any changed circumstance regarding representations made in the application concerning ownership of the facility, financial responsibility, site design, or any other material fact.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Applications for changes in certified sites and facilities shall be processed by the Board under the same requirements, procedures, and restrictions as for an initial application.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Content of Application.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Applicant's Burden of Production. An applicant shall have the burden of setting forth in the application the information described in this regulation and all other factual, technical, or expert information which the applicant wishes the Board to consider in acting on the application. In addition, an applicant shall have the burden of setting forth in the application each inference or conclusion which the applicant is asking the Board to make in determining to issue a certificate of public necessity in accordance with the Natural Resources Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|3-702">3-702</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|3-705">3-705</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland, and shall have the burden of relating in the application the informational basis for each inference or conclusion. The Board will not determine an application to be complete unless and until the applicant has met these burdens.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Format.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each application shall contain a letter of intent signed by a person with the authority to obligate the firm or other entity submitting the application. The letter shall state the purpose of the application and shall reference supporting information. The applicant shall submit the application to the Board in care of the Secretary.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The letter of intent shall be supported and accompanied by any forms required by the Board and supplemental reports or other materials which shall contain information of the type, quality, and detail that will permit adequate consideration of the application by the Board. The supporting reports and any supplemental information submitted shall be considered an integral part of the application.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Each application shall contain a summary of the proposed site and facility. The summary shall include a factual description of the site, the facility and the treatment, disposal, or recovery process proposed and shall highlight any major risks to the environment and public health or safety associated with the proposal and describe the methods proposed to eliminate or reduce those risks. The applicant shall highlight in the summary the conclusions and inferences the applicant is asking the Board to make in accordance with §A.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Supporting Reports and Other Information.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each application shall include an ownership report which contains the following information:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Legal description of applicant, including identification of all principal participants, such as major shareholders, corporate officers, affiliated firms;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A current audited financial statement or statements of the applicant based upon an audit or audits by a certified public accountant including the accountant's opinions;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A description of all liability insurance or other type of liability coverage the applicant has or plans to obtain for the proposed site and facility and a description of the financial and managerial arrangements for closure and post-closure care of the facility and site;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A description of any other hazardous waste facilities operated or owned currently or in the past by the applicant with details of their compliance record.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Each application shall include a site-assessment report which contains a 7-1/2 minute series United States Geological Survey topographic map of the site vicinity and detailed information about the existing environmental, health, and community conditions surrounding the proposed site and facility. It shall describe any possible environmental, health, or community impacts which the proposed site and facility may cause, including descriptions of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The geology and hydrology surrounding the site;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The surface and groundwater resources surrounding the site and facility and any positive or negative impacts the site and facility may have on these resources along with a list of all local, State, or federal water or soil permits or approvals the facility will be required to have and the applicant's plans for compliance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The ambient air quality surrounding the facility and site vicinity and any positive or negative impacts the site and facility may have on the surrounding air quality along with a list of any local, State, or federal air or noise permits or approvals the facility will be required to have and the applicant's plans for compliance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Any other existing environmental features of the site vicinity and any impacts which the site or facility may have on those features and any other State, local, or federal health or environmental permits or approvals the facility will be required to have before construction or operation and the applicant's plans for compliance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The surrounding land uses and affected communities and the existing local planning and zoning provisions;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The transportation routes and methods the customers of the facility will generally use and the existing and proposed State, local, and federal plans for repair, maintenance, and control of those routes and methods;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>The volume of traffic the facility will generate and the traffic volume and accident records for the routes the customers will use;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Any community or environmental mitigation or compensation plans the applicant has;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Any known objections or endorsements by State and local governments and citizens in the site vicinity of the proposed facility.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The application shall include a facility and operation report which contains a detailed description and discussion of the mechanical, operational, and financial aspects of the facility and treatment, disposal, or recovery process including a discussion of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The designed capability and capacity of the facility;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The types and amounts of wastes which will be accepted and their geographic origin;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The relationship of the applicant to the customers including a sample customer contract form;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The process or processes to be employed including its basic characteristics and principal limitations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Any emission controls, liquid or gaseous discharges, and solid residues the facility will emit or discharge which were not discussed in the site-assessment report;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Normal operating procedures including waste acceptance requirements, compliance with the manifest system and other pertinent hazardous substances transportation laws and regulations, employee training, testing procedures and any company regulatory compliance monitoring;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>The emergency prevention and control plans including a description of on-site equipment and trained personnel and existing or proposed nearby state or local equipment or personnel such as fire equipment or rescue squads;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Planned operational safeguards and monitoring of the facility following cessation of operation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Cost effectiveness of the process.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Form of the Application.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The application should be contained in one or more three-ring loose leaf binders on preferably 8-1/2 x 11 inch paper.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All maps required by this regulation shall be detachable, but may be fold-outs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The summary shall be capable of separate reproduction and distribution.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Procedure for Issuing Certificate.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The notice required by Regulation .01D(7) announcing that a completed application has been received shall contain a brief description of the applicant, site, and facility. It shall also indicate the date, time, and place of the information meeting between the applicant and interested members of the general public. It shall also indicate the possibility of a pre-hearing conference or further procedures as outlined in Regulation .04, below, if an adjudicatory hearing is to be convened. The notice shall advise that the completed application (including the applicant's summary) is available for inspection and copying at the office of the Secretary.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This notice shall appear in the Maryland Register and in one or more newspapers of general circulation in the affected county or counties. The cost of all legal notices shall be paid for by the applicant.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Any person (other than the applicant or person requesting an adjudicatory hearing pursuant to Regulation .04 below) desiring to make known to the Board other relevant facts concerning an application shall do so within 50 days of the public notice of the completed application. Failure to provide the Board with this information within the 50 day period will preclude its consideration by the Board, unless the Board determines that the information could not have been submitted during the 50-day period. The applicant shall have the opportunity to contest any such information.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Information Meeting with Applicant.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A meeting with interested members of the public shall be held in the county in which the proposed site is located at which the applicant will present and discuss its application. The information meeting is the first phase of the public participation process.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the proposed site is located in two or more counties, the meeting will be held at a location reasonably convenient and accessible to citizens in all these counties.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Notice of the meeting shall be published in the Maryland Register and in one or more newspapers of general circulation in the affected county or counties and sent by ordinary mail to any person who has requested to receive notice of Board meetings. The costs of this notice shall be borne by the applicant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The meeting will be conducted by the Secretary. The applicant will present its proposal and entertain questions.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An adjudicatory hearing may be held after the informational meeting, at times and dates specified by the Board. An adjudicatory hearing is to resolve disputed issues of adjudicative fact raised by the application in accordance with Regulation .04 below, and the Administrative Procedure Act.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Upon completion of the factual record on an application, including completion of any adjudicatory hearing, the Board shall schedule a public hearing for the purpose of receiving advice and comment on the application. The hearing shall be conducted in accordance with the procedures set out in Regulation .05 below.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Procedure for Adjudicatory Hearing on an Application.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definitions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Adjudicative fact" means facts which involve a particular party or facility and have no general applicability--for example, the types and quantities of pollutant emissions which one facility will have.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Adjudicatory hearing" means a contested case hearing conducted pursuant to the relevant provisions of the Act and the Administrative Procedure Act.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Requester" means the person requesting an adjudicatory hearing who seeks to or has become a party to the proceedings, and whose legal rights, duties, statutory entitlements, or privileges are adversely affected by the decision of the Board on an application.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Requests for Adjudicatory Hearings.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within 50 calendar days from the date of publication in the Maryland Register of the notice of the completed application, persons requesting an adjudicatory hearing shall submit to the Secretary, in writing, specific grounds for their grievances.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Requesters for adjudicatory hearings shall do all of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>State the name, address, and telephone number of the person making the request;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Identify the specific rights, duties, statutory entitlements, or privileges of the requester which are adversely affected by the application for which the adjudicatory hearing is requested, and upon which the requester asserts his or her grievance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Identify any other person whom the requester represents;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>State separately and specifically the issues of adjudicative fact proposed to be considered at the hearing; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Describe the data and information which, if established through relevant and competent evidence at the hearing, would be adequate to justify resolution of the factual issue(s) in the way sought by the person.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Board's Consideration of Requests.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board shall consider any requests for an adjudicatory hearing promptly and give notice of its decision to requesters by certified mail. Before an adjudicatory hearing is granted, the Board may request briefs from all requesters on the issue of standing or other threshold issues. The Board or its hearing officer will determine which parties will have standing as to each issue. Any requester may be admitted as a party for limited purposes.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Requests for an adjudicatory hearing will be granted if the requester has shown all of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>There is a genuine issue of material adjudicative fact for resolution at a hearing. An adjudicatory hearing will not be granted on issues of policy or law or on issues of fact which are of no consequence to the determination of whether or not a certificate should issue.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The factual issue is capable of being resolved by available and specifically identified evidence. A hearing will not be granted on the basis of mere allegations or denial or general descriptions of positions and contentions.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The data and information identified in the request for hearing, if established through relevant and competent evidence at a hearing, would be adequate to justify resolution of the factual issue in the way sought by the person. A hearing will be denied if the Board concludes that, even assuming the truth and accuracy of all of the data and information submitted in support of the objection and request for hearings, they are insufficient to justify the factual determination urged.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Pre-hearing Conference.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The hearing officer may hold a pre-hearing conference to determine standing or any other preliminary matters.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>At the discretion of the hearing officer, persons other than parties may attend pre-hearing conferences.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>At a pre-hearing conference or within some reasonable time set by the hearing officer, each party shall make available to the other parties the names of experts and other witnesses the party expects to call, together with a brief written summary of their anticipated testimony.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>At a pre-hearing conference, or within some reasonable time set by the hearing officer, the following matters shall be considered:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The documents within the Board's file shall be identified.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Stipulations and admissions of facts and the genuineness of documents and other matters upon which there is agreement shall be identified.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Matters of which official notice may be taken shall be identified.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Disputed issues of a purely legal nature shall be identified and submitted by the hearing officer to the Attorney General.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Disputed issues of policy shall be identified and deferred for consideration until the public hearing held on the application.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Disputed issues of fact which concern technical matters (plans, specifications, construction drawings, process controls, operation procedures, etc.) subject to determination by the Department in connection with issuance of a facility or discharge permit may be deferred, at the hearing officer's sole discretion, to the Department with the Department's concurrence. Until the resolution of the disputed factual issue by the Department or issuance of necessary permits, the Board shall presume resolution of the disputed fact in a manner consistent with issuance of the certificate. Post-permit review by the Board shall be as set forth in Regulation .07E.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>When possible, consideration shall be given to and decisions made upon objections to the introduction into evidence at the hearing of any written documents, papers, exhibits, testimony, or materials proposed to be introduced at the hearing by a party. The hearing officer may determine to receive evidence on an issue by issue basis. To the extent possible, parties of like interest in the application shall consolidate the presentation of their cases.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>A schedule of presentation order for the following shall be established:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Submissions of written statements;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Presentation of oral and written statements;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Presentation of oral, direct, and cross-examinations;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Presentation of oral arguments.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The hearing officer shall prepare a written pre-hearing order reciting the actions taken at the pre-hearing conference.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>General Procedure for Hearing. Adjudicatory hearings shall be conducted generally in the following order, unless modified by the hearing officer during the pre-hearing conference:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Call of the case by the hearing officer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Opening statements by the parties;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Presentation of the case by the applicant and intervenors in favor of the application:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Direct evidence,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Cross-examination in an order to be determined by the hearing officer;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Presentation of the case by opponent or opponents in an order to be determined by hearing officer:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Direct evidence by the opposition,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Cross-examination by the applicant or intervenors in favor of the application, or both;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Written rebuttals to be filed within 3 days of the close of oral testimony:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Concluding arguments by the applicant and other proponents,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Concluding arguments by the opponents;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Concluding arguments shall be heard by a majority of the Board. The Board may also examine witnesses.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The party who raises material issues of fact has the burden to present an affirmative case upon the issues. The burden of production on any specific issue may vary between the parties at the discretion of the hearing officer. The hearing officer may issue a summary dismissal of any issue of fact after presentation of a party's case when, even assuming the truth and accuracy of all evidence submitted by that party, it is insufficient to justify the factual determination urged. The applicant has the ultimate burden of persuasion on all factual issues adjudicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Authority and Duty of Hearing Officer.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The hearing officer shall have the authority and duty to conduct a fair and impartial hearing, to take action to avoid unnecessary delay in the disposition of the proceedings, and to maintain order.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The hearing officer shall have all powers necessary to these ends, including the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>To administer oaths and affirmations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>To issue summonses for witnesses and subpoenas requiring the production of documents;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>To rule upon offers of proof and receive relevant and material evidence;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>To consider and rule upon all procedural motions and other motions appropriate to the proceedings;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>To examine witnesses;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>To maintain order, limit unduly repetitious testimony, and limit the time for presentations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>To identify and submit issues of law to the Attorney General;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>To identify and determine appropriate issues of fact to be deferred to the Department;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>To grant a continuance for good cause shown;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>To require parties to submit proposed findings of fact.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Parties may cross-examine a witness who appears at an adjudicatory hearing to the extent that cross-examination is necessary for full and true disclosure of the facts. The provisions of the Administrative Procedure Act shall apply to the adjudicatory hearing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>In multi-party proceedings, the hearing officer may limit cross-examination to one party on each side if he or she is satisfied that the cross-examination by that party will adequately protect the other parties. Other parties may engage in cross-examination relevant to matters not adequately covered by previous cross-examination.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Rulings of the hearing officer on the admissibility of evidence, the propriety of cross-examination, and other procedural matters shall be final and shall appear in the record. Parties shall be presumed to have taken exception to an adverse ruling.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Record of Adjudicatory Hearing.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All orders issued by the hearing officer, stenographic notes or tapes, or transcripts of oral hearings or arguments, written statements of position, written direct and rebuttal testimony, and any other data, studies, reports, documentation, information, and other written matter submitted in the adjudicatory hearing, shall be available to the public in the office of the Secretary upon compilation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Adjudicatory hearings shall be either stenographically reported verbatim or tape recorded, and then may be transcribed. Stenographic notes or tapes, or originals of the transcript, shall be filed with the record along with all exhibits.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The hearing officer shall certify that the stenographic notes or tapes, or transcripts and exhibits are received, and each of the parties shall be so notified by certified mail. Any party who desires a copy of a transcript of the hearing may request a copy from the hearing office and pay the costs. If the transcript is prepared by a private stenographer, the hearing officer may direct interested persons to make arrangements for copies by dealing directly with the reporter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Within 10 calendar days after mailing to the parties notice of certification of the stenographic notes, tapes, or transcript, any party may file with the hearing officer proposed findings of fact and conclusions and a brief in support thereof, each containing appropriate references to the record. A copy of the findings, conclusions, and brief shall be mailed to every other party at the same time. The time for filing may be shortened or extended by the hearing officer only for good cause shown.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Procedure for Public Hearing on an Application.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>After completion of the factual record for each application being considered, the Board shall schedule a public hearing. The hearing shall be held in the county in which the proposed site is located. If the proposed site is located in two or more counties, the hearing will be held at a location reasonably convenient and accessible to the citizens of all these counties.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Notice.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notice will be given by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Publication at least 15 calendar days in advance in the Maryland Register and one or more newspapers of general circulation in the county or counties in which the proposed site is located;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Ordinary mail to the governing body of any county in which the proposed site is located and the governing body of every adjoining county and every incorporated municipality within 10 miles of the site; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Ordinary mail to any person who has requested to receive notice of Board meetings.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Arrangements for all legal notices shall be made by the Board at the expense of the applicant.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>At least a majority of the members of the Board shall be present at the public hearing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Chairman may be the hearing officer or the chairman may designate another Board member or person as hearing officer.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>At the public hearing the Board shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Announce any findings of facts which may have been determined in any adjudicatory hearing or by the Department or otherwise in respect to a particular application.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Receive advice and comments from interested persons as to the suitability of the site in question.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Receive advice and comment from interested persons on any issues of policy identified by the Board as being presented by the application. Any issues so identified by the Board shall be stated in the public notice announcing the public hearing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Board may permit the parties to any adjudicatory hearing to present their final arguments at the public hearing or may schedule the arguments at another meeting before the public hearing as time and circumstances permit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The record shall remain open for written public advice and comment for a period to be specified by the Board, but not less than 15 days.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The Board may establish procedural rules governing the conduct of hearings, consolidation of hearings, ceding of time, time limits, and other such matters as the Board deems appropriate.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Decision to Issue or Deny a Certificate.</heading>
    <text>After consideration of information submitted as part of the application, findings of fact determined at any adjudicatory hearing or otherwise, the advice and comments of interested persons, and other relevant information, the Board shall announce its decision to grant or deny a certificate. The Board shall promptly notify by certified mail, the applicant, other parties to any adjudicatory hearings, and the chief executive officer of any municipality within 10 miles of the proposed site and of any affected county of its decision. The Board shall include in the notice its reasons for granting or denying a certificate and shall state the terms and conditions of the certificate.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Form, Terms, and Conditions of Certificate.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The certificate shall state the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A statement in large print that it is a Certificate of Public Necessity;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A citation to the statutory authority for issuance;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The signatures of the Chairman and the Secretary;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The effective date and, when appropriate, a renewal date;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The purpose for which the certificate is issued;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A description of the site and proposed facility;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>All terms and conditions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Any referenced exhibits to be attached or incorporated by reference into the certificate.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A complete copy of the certificate including all conditions, shall be prominently displayed by the applicant at the facility, or, before construction, at a location reasonably accessible for inspection.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A certificate may be assigned or transferred only with the prior permission of the Board. The Board may require additional information and appearance before the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Board shall impose terms and conditions necessary to assure that a facility and site are consistent with the purpose of the certificate and with the purposes of the Act. These terms and conditions may include but are not limited to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The specific geographic area for which the certificate applies;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A general description of the facility including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Facility type,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Technology to be applied in treating, storing, recycling, or disposing of hazardous waste at the facility,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Required buffer areas or buffer mechanisms,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Description of types and quantities of wastes, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Transportation routes.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>During the process of obtaining any other necessary permits, the design and operation of the site or facility may be altered in such a way that it results in significantly different impacts on the site or surrounding community than were considered by the Board in its decision to issue a certificate. If this occurs, the Board shall review the changes and consider their effects. The Board may decide to revoke the certificate or change or impose new terms and conditions on the certificate as specified in§D after such hearings as may be required by law. The decision shall be within the sole discretion of the Board and shall be final. The certificate holder shall be notified as to the effectiveness of the certificate within 3 weeks after the issuance of these permits.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|3-704">Natural Resources Article,§3-704</cite>; Article 41,§248; Article 76A, §2(a), Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1981-05-29">Effective date: May 29, 1981 (8:11 Md. R. 976)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1981-12-07"><cite path="|14|14|03|.01|C.">Regulation .01C</cite> and D amended effective December 7, 1981 (8:24 Md. R. 1937)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1983-09-26"><cite path="|14|14|03|.01|C.">Regulation .01C</cite> amended effective September 26, 1983 (10:19 Md. R. 1691)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1982-11-08"><cite path="|14|14|03|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective November 8, 1982 (9:22 Md. R. 2198)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
