<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>General Regulations</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Mission.</heading>
    <text>The mission of Patuxent Institution is to reduce the rate of reincarceration by providing appropriate clinical assessment and treatment services within a secure environment to both mentally disordered or physically impaired inmates of the Division of Correction. Comprehensive and systemic habilitative opportunities shall be provided to assist inmates to become economically competitive, socially productive, and law-abiding citizens. In meeting this mandate, due regard to the safety of the public, correctional staff, and the inmate population shall be of paramount importance.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Purpose and Philosophy.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The purpose of the Institution is to provide efficient and adequate programs and services for treatment with the goal of rehabilitation of eligible persons. This shall include a range of program alternatives indicated by the current state of knowledge to be appropriate and effective for the population being served. As an integral part of its program an effective research and development effort will be established and maintained to evaluate and recommend improvements on an ongoing basis.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Programs, Services, and Goals.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In keeping with the purpose and philosophy, the Institution will provide a range of programs and services including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Inmate evaluation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Treatment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Community supervision;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Research;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Program evaluation; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Professional training.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Institution's operations will be guided by the following policy-relevant goals:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Respond to the identified needs of eligible persons, employ the best affordable methods of mental health care, and provide the highest possible quality of care that will enable eligible persons to return to the community as productive, law-abiding citizens;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Provide a full range of mental health services responsive to the needs of eligible persons, and provide continuity of care by moving these persons among programs as their needs change;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Provide full protection of the rights of eligible persons within legal mandates and Departmental policies;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Provide for long-term service needs in the environment which provides the most appropriate level of security necessary to meet the eligible person's needs while protecting the public safety.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="12|12|01|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this subtitle, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Board of Review" means the Patuxent Institution Board of Review, created by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|4-205">Correctional Services Article, §4-205, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Chronically mentally disordered" means exhibiting a recurrent pattern of major psychiatric illness.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Chronic youthful offender" means an individual who has been tried in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcj|3-804">Courts and Judicial Proceedings Article, §3-804(e), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and who exhibits a persistent pattern of conduct, typically manifested before the age of 18, in which the basic rights of others and other age-appropriate societal norms or rules are violated. The behavior pattern typically is present in the home, at school, with peers, and in the community.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Commissioner" means the Commissioner of Correction or a designee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Conditional release" means any leave, work release, school release, or parole status granted to an eligible person by the Board of Review.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Department" means the Department of Public Safety and Correctional Services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Director" means the Director of Patuxent Institution or a designee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Division" means the Division of Correction, which may include the Patuxent Institution D.C. Building, or any other housing units as designated by the Secretary during an emergency.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Eligible person" means a Division inmate who has met the criteria for eligibility specified in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|4-101">Correctional Services Article, §4-101(e), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and <cite path="12.12.03.05">COMAR 12.12.03.05</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Emotional imbalance" means a diagnosable and treatable mental disorder, which includes but is not limited to the disorders defined in §B(2) and (3) of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Evaluation team" means the team of Patuxent staff that evaluates Division inmates to determine whether they are eligible persons, and includes at a minimum a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Social worker or behavioral scientist;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Psychologist; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Psychiatrist.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>"Institution" means Patuxent Institution.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>"Intellectual deficiency" means impaired intellectual functioning for which treatment may be ameliorative, and includes but is not limited to mental retardation, as defined in <cite path="12|12|01|.03|B.|(14)">§B(14) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>"Mentally retarded" means exhibiting significantly subaverage general intellectual functioning, accompanied by significant deficits or impairments in adaptive functioning, with onset before the age of 18.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>"Noneligible person" means a Division inmate who does not meet the criteria for eligibility as specified in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|4-101">Correctional Services Article, §4-101(e), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and <cite path="12.12.03.05">COMAR 12.12.03.05</cite>, or an eligible person who no longer meets these criteria.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>"Prerelease status" means leaves, work release, school release, or any other type of out-of-institution status granted to an eligible person, except parole, as authorized by law.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>"Prescreening" means the preliminary assessment conducted by the Division to determine whether a Division inmate is eligible to be referred to the Institution for evaluation, as specified in <cite path="12.12.02.01">COMAR 12.12.02.01</cite> or .02.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>"Secretary" means the Secretary of Public Safety and Correctional Services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>"Treatment team" means a unit of treatment personnel, which includes a psychiatrist, psychologists, and social workers. There are four treatment teams (or treatment units) at the Institution. Each inmate is assigned to a specific treatment unit, and the inmate will usually remain with the same unit throughout the inmate's stay at the Institution. The treatment unit is responsible for the inmates assigned to their unit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>"Victim" means a person who suffers personal physical injury or death, or, if the victim is deceased, a designated family member, as set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|4-101">Correctional Services Article, §4-101(i), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>"Warden" means the Warden of Patuxent Institution or a designee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|4-208">Correctional Services Article, §4-208, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-02-03">Effective date: February 3, 1992 (19:2 Md. R. 155)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1984-09-24" discontinuity="true">Annotation: Former <cite path="|12.12.01">COMAR 12.12.01</cite> "Public Information Requests" under  Subtitle 12 "Emergency Management and Civil Defense Agency" adopted   effective January 7, 1982 (8:26 Md. R. 2106) was repealed  September 24, 1984  (11:19 Md. R. 1667)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
