<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Evaluation Process</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>General.</heading>
    <text>The Institution, in accordance with the availability of current program vacancies, shall assign an evaluation team to determine the eligibility of Division inmates referred by the Commissioner. The Institution shall maintain a list of Division inmates who have been evaluated and found to be eligible for Institution programs when vacancies occur.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Evaluation Team.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A minimum of three members of the evaluation team shall examine the referred inmate at either a Division of Correction facility or at the Institution. The members of the evaluation team who examine the inmate shall include a social worker or a behavioral scientist, a psychologist, and a psychiatrist. The selection of the location for the examination shall be at the discretion of the Director.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The evaluation team shall meet at the Institution to determine whether the Division inmate is an eligible person, according to the criteria specified in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|4-101">Correctional Services Article, §4-101(e), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and <cite path="|12|12|03|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="12|12|03|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Records Review.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If the examination is to be conducted at a Division of Correction facility, the records needed by the evaluation team shall be assembled by the Division as specified below:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The following documents from the base file:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Copy of commitment order,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Admission summary,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Copy of sentencing guidelines,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Presentence investigation, parole, probation, and other reports that have been prepared concerning the inmate, or documentation that none exist,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Police reports and other relevant information concerning the crime for which the inmate was most recently convicted and the sentence imposed upon that conviction,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>State's version of the crime,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Prior criminal and juvenile history and all relevant records concerning it,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Disciplinary record, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Correspondence from judges and State's Attorneys relating to their referral and recommendation of inmates to the Institution;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>School records;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The inmate's prior medical history, including any relevant medical and hospital records and reports and the inmate's medical file;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The inmate's prior mental health history, including the inmate's psychological file, previous psychological or psychiatric evaluations, record of psychiatric medications, progress notes, and records of any previous psychiatric, drug abuse, or alcohol abuse treatment; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>All other relevant information, records, and reports concerning the inmate's social, physical, or mental condition and history.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the examination is to be conducted at the Institution, the Division shall ensure that all of the records specified in <cite path="12|12|03|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> accompany the Division inmate to the Institution.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Resources.</heading>
    <text>The evaluation team shall be provided the workspace and resources necessary to carry out the examination.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="12|12|03|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Eligibility Criteria.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A Division inmate shall be considered an eligible person if the evaluation team reaches all of the following conclusions:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The inmate meets all of the referral criteria specified in <cite path="12.12.02.01">COMAR 12.12.02.01</cite> or .02;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The inmate has an emotional imbalance or intellectual deficiency;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The inmate can be expected to benefit from current programs and services provided at the Institution; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The inmate can be better habilitated through the Institution's programs and services than by other incarceration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In making the determination required by <cite path="12|12|03|.05|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, the evaluation team may consider the following information concerning the Division inmate:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Age;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The nature of the offense;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Current sentence;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Prior criminal history;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Disciplinary record; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Clinical criteria, as approved by the Director and the Secretary, to be used by the evaluation team in selecting candidates for vacancies in the roster of a specific program.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Findings.</heading>
    <text>After its review, the evaluation team shall develop a list of inmates in the following categories:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Eligible persons, who may be admitted to the Institution when program vacancies occur; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Noneligible persons, who may not be admitted to the Institution.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Written Reports.</heading>
    <text>The evaluation team shall deliver a report to the Director recommending whether the inmate is an eligible person or a noneligible person. The report shall support the team's findings with respect to each of the criteria set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|2-113">Correctional Services Article, §2-113, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and <cite path="|12|12|03|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|4-208">Correctional Services Article, §4-208, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-02-03">Effective date: February 3, 1992 (19:2 Md. R. 155)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
