<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>06</num>
  <heading>Board of Review</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Composition and Qualifications.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board of Review shall have nine members including four institutional members and five public members. Of the five public members, one shall be a member of a victim's rights organization.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The four institutional members of the Board of Review shall include the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Director;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Associate Director, Warden;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Associate Director, Treatment; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Associate Director, Behavioral Science, who shall serve as Executive Secretary.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The five public members of the Board of Review shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be members of the general public;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Be appointed by the Governor with the advice and consent of the Senate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Serve a term of 4 years; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Be paid as provided in the State budget.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Chairman of the Board of Review shall be appointed by the Governor.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Powers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>During its annual review of each eligible person, the Board of Review shall consider the eligible person's response to treatment and decide whether the eligible person may continue in treatment or be returned to the Division of Correction.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In addition, the Board of Review may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Grant, revoke, extend, or change the conditions governing the status of an eligible person, including eligible persons on leave, work release, and school release status;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Revoke, extend, or modify the conditions governing the status of a paroled eligible person;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Recommend to the original sentencing court that a paroled eligible person be released from supervision, and the remaining sentence be suspended or vacated, after the paroled eligible person has successfully completed 3 years on parole without violation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Recommend to the Secretary parole for eligible persons serving nonlife sentences for crimes committed after March 20, 1989;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Recommend to the Governor parole for eligible persons serving life sentences for crimes committed after July 1, 1982 and on or before March 20, 1989;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Recommend to the Secretary and the Governor parole for eligible persons serving life sentences for crimes committed after March 20, 1989;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Grant parole to eligible persons serving nonlife sentences for crimes committed on or before March 20, 1989, and to eligible persons serving life sentences for crimes committed on or before July 1, 1982;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Ratify the issuance of retake warrants for eligible persons on prerelease status and parole;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Order the return to the Institution of an eligible person on prerelease status or parole, for the purposes of a special appearance before the Board;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Decide grievances of an eligible person on prerelease status or parole;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Decide matters without a hearing concerning:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Compassionate leaves for eligible persons on prerelease or parole status,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Leave schedules and dates for eligible persons on prerelease or parole status, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Requests from eligible persons on prerelease status or parole;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Recommend interstate compact agreements for paroled eligible persons with other jurisdictions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Conduct annual reviews of the status of each eligible person;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>Recommend policies to the Director; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>Consider only those matters approved by the Director.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The unit treatment teams shall make recommendations for changes in an eligible person's status to the Director, and upon the approval of the Director these recommendations shall be forwarded to the Board of Review.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Hearings.</heading>
    <text>The Board of Review shall conduct hearings as required by law or these regulations.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Meetings and Procedures.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board of Review shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Meet not less than once per month and may meet more often as needed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Conduct executive sessions during its regular meetings to discuss issues relating to eligible persons and policy matters;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Conduct an administrative session not less than once per year to discuss broader policy issues; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Hold informal hearings in all matters, except as provided elsewhere in this subtitle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Board of Review meetings are closed to the public, unless the Board of Review has approved the attendance of a member of the public.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="12|12|06|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Quorum.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A quorum of the Board of Review consists of seven members, three of whom shall be public members.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An eligible person may only be released into the community on prerelease status, or recommended to the Secretary or the Governor for parole status, if the decision has been approved by a quorum of the Board of Review, as defined in <cite path="12|12|06|.05|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>All other decisions of the Board of Review require a simple majority of the members present.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Secretary's Authority.</heading>
    <text>Under the provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|2-113">Correctional Services Article, §2-113, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the Secretary may exercise discretion or perform any power, duty, responsibility, or function of the Institution.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Correctional Services Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|4-205">4-205</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|4-208">4-208</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-02-03">Effective date: February 3, 1992 (19:2 Md. R. 155)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
