<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>07</num>
  <heading>Leave, Work Release, and School Release</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>Eligible persons may be granted the privilege of leaving confinement during necessary and reasonable hours for the purposes of leave, working at gainful private or public employment, or attending school as part of a school release program. These programs may also include, under appropriate conditions, release for the purpose of seeking employment or schooling. Leave, work release, and school release are considered prerelease programs intended to prepare eligible persons for parole, mandatory supervision, or expiration of sentence. An eligible person does not have any right to be granted leave, work release, or school release. Leave, work release, and school release are privileges to be granted or revoked at the discretion of the Board of Review.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Inmate" means an eligible person, as defined in <cite path="12.12.01.03|B.|(9)">COMAR 12.12.01.03B(9)</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Leave.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Accompanied day leave" means a leave in which the prerelease inmate is accompanied into the community by an Institution staff member, usually a member of the treatment team, for the purpose of becoming familiar with the community resources, or to find employment, or to accomplish a basic task of community reentry.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Compassionate leave" means a leave for a prerelease inmate authorized only for the purpose of visiting a member of the immediate family who is seriously ill or attending the funeral of a member of the family.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>"Holiday leave" means a special leave which follows a holiday schedule approved by the Board of Review and consists of 5 days and 4 nights at an approved place in the community. The usual holiday periods are: Washington's Birthday, Easter, Memorial Day, Independence Day, Labor Day, Thanksgiving, and Christmas. Prerelease inmates who have monthly leave status are eligible for holiday leave, which may be granted instead of, but not in addition to, any other leave.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>"Monthly leave" means a leave in which the prerelease inmate may be granted up to 3 days and 2 nights of leave to an approved place in the community once a month. The usual hours of the leave are from 7:30 a.m. on the first day to 9 p.m. on the last day.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>"Unaccompanied day leave" means a leave in which the prerelease inmate may depart the Institution at 7:30 a.m. and return by 9 p.m. The prerelease inmate shall have a specific destination which has been approved by the unit. A prerelease inmate on day leave status may have two leaves a month, which must be separated by at least 5 days unless authorized by the Director. The hours of the leave may be changed if necessary and if approved by the Director.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Level" means the system of treatment tiers through which an inmate may progress while confined to the Institution for treatment. There are four treatment tier levels, with level 1 having the most restrictions and the least inmate privileges, and level four having the least restrictions and the most inmate privileges and responsibilities. Inmates are promoted through the treatment tiers on the basis of their behavior within the Institution and their progress in treatment. Inmates are only eligible to be considered for the prerelease program if they are on level 4.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Parole" means a conditional release from the Institution, after a portion of the sentence has been served in confinement, to serve the balance of the sentence under supervision in the community. Parole is a privilege and not a right.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"School release" means conditional leave from the Institution for participation in an education program offered in the community and deemed beneficial to the treatment of the prerelease inmate, and not detrimental to the public. School release is a part of the Institution's treatment program to prepare the prerelease inmate for survival in the community upon parole, mandatory supervision, or expiration of sentence.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Work release" means a conditional leave from the Institution for participation in an employment program offered in the community and deemed beneficial to the treatment of the prerelease inmate, and not detrimental to the public. Work release is a part of the Institution's treatment program to prepare the prerelease inmate for survival in the community upon parole, mandatory supervision, or expiration of sentence.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>General.</heading>
    <text>The Board of Review has the power to grant, revoke, or modify an inmate's prerelease status.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="12|12|07|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Public Safety Criteria.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In considering an inmate for any form of prerelease status, the Board of Review shall consider the following public safety criteria:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The compatibility of the release of the inmate on leave, work release, or school release with the safety and welfare of society;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The length of the inmate's sentence and the amount of time served on the current term of imprisonment to date;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The nature of the crime for which the inmate is currently incarcerated;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The circumstances surrounding the crime for which the inmate is currently incarcerated;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The determination that leave, work release, or school release would not depreciate the seriousness of the inmate's crime, promote disrespect for the law, or have an adverse effect on Institution discipline;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The existence of any unresolved out-of-State or federal detainers;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Any reports or recommendations made by the inmate's victim or victims, or a representative designated by the victim;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Any reports or recommendations made by the sentencing judge, State's Attorney, or a professional medical consultant;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Any other factors or information which the Board of Review may find relevant in assessing the risk to public safety which may be posed by placing the inmate on prerelease status.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In making the determination required by <cite path="12|12|07|.04|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite>, the Board shall consider:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The inmate's prior criminal and juvenile record, and prior incarceration, parole, and probation records;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The inmate's past use of narcotics, other controlled dangerous substances, or alcohol;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The inmate's family status and family stability;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A recent assessment of the inmate's propensity toward violence conducted by a mental health practitioner;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Any reports or recommendations made by the Institution treatment or custody staff concerning the likelihood that the inmate will remain at liberty without violating local, State, or federal laws or the terms and conditions governing the inmate's prerelease status; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The adequacy of the inmate's leave, school, or work release plan, which shall include information concerning employment plans, occupational skills, and job potential.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="12|12|07|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Progress-in-Treatment Criteria.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In considering an inmate for prerelease status, the Board of Review shall consider the following progress-in-treatment criteria:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The inmate's overall progress in treatment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The inmate's overall behavior and adjustment while incarcerated;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Whether prerelease status would assist in the inmate's treatment by enhancing the inmate's ability to lead a law-abiding life;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Whether the inmate has successfully functioned in any previous prerelease status; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Any other factors or information which the Board of Review considers relevant in assessing the inmate's progress in treatment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In making the determination required by <cite path="12|12|07|.05|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite>, the Board of Review shall consider:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The reports or recommendations of the Institution treatment and custody staff;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The inmate's adjustment on level 4;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Whether the inmate's treatment level history demonstrates progressive responsibility in moving from level 1 to level 4;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The inmate's participation in Institution treatment programs and self-help programs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Whether the inmate has demonstrated emotional maturity and insight into his or her problems, as assessed through the reports or recommendations of the Institution treatment and custody staff;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The inmate's ability and readiness to assume obligations and undertake responsibilities; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The inmate's educational, vocational, and other training.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In making the determination required by <cite path="12|12|07|.05|A.|(2)">§A(2) of this regulation</cite>, the Board of Review shall consider:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The inmate's Institution disciplinary record; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The inmate's current attitude towards discipline and other authority, as assessed through the reports or recommendations of Institution treatment and custody staff.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Hearings.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board of Review shall conduct a hearing to determine the appropriateness of granting or revoking leave, work release, or school release. Hearings shall consider the recommendations of the inmate's unit treatment team.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A record shall be maintained of the hearing noting the date, the vote of the Board of Review, and the outcome of the proceedings.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Board of Review shall conduct hearings at the Institution in accordance with a preestablished schedule.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Procedure for Hearings.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A leave, work release, or school release hearing is an interview of the inmate by the Board of Review. Attendance shall be restricted to authorized Institution staff, except that other interested persons, including victims, may attend with the approval of the Board of Review. The hearing is private and shall be held in an informal manner, allowing the opportunity to give free expression to an inmate's views and feelings relating to the case. Formal presentations by an attorney, relatives, victims, and other interested persons are not permitted at the hearing. Attorneys, relatives, victims, and other interested persons may submit information in writing for the Board of Review's consideration before the hearing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Detailed reports shall be furnished by those familiar with the inmate to assist the Board of Review in its deliberations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The unit treatment team or work release supervisor from the treatment unit assigned to the inmate shall attend all hearings concerning that inmate. The inmate's work release supervisor or other unit member having knowledge of relevant facts shall be available to provide new information which may have developed since the date of the reports furnished to the Board of Review and to assist in answering questions which may arise concerning the inmate or Institution policy.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Granting Leave, Work Release, and School Release.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Leave, work release, or school release may not be granted unless approved by the affirmative vote of a quorum of the Board of Review, as defined in <cite path="12.12.06.05|A.">COMAR 12.12.06.05A</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Victim Comment, Victim Notification, and Police Notification.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board of Review shall give the inmate's victim a reasonable opportunity to comment in writing before the Board of Review decides whether to grant leave, work release, or school release to the inmate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The victim may designate, in writing to the Board of Review, the name and address of a representative, who is a resident of the State, to receive notice for the victim that the inmate will be considered for leave, work release, or school release.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Board of Review shall delete the victim's address and telephone number before examination of any document by the inmate or the inmate's representative.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the victim cannot be located, the judge holding jurisdiction over the inmate's sentence may be contacted for comment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Board of Review shall notify the victim of its decision regarding leave, work release, or school release.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The Board of Review shall notify the police department possessing jurisdiction over the locality in which an inmate's crime was originally committed whenever an inmate has been approved for leave, work release, or school release status.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Board of Review shall notify the inmate of its decision regarding placement on leave, work release, or school release.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Director shall ensure that a waiver of extradition form is completed by an inmate before authorizing an inmate for leave, work release, or school release.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A member of the inmate's unit treatment team shall ensure that the waiver of extradition form is filed in the inmate's base file.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Governing Rules.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Before starting a leave, work release, or school release program, the inmate shall sign an agreement that affirms the inmate's understanding of the regulations governing the leave, work release, or school release programs. These regulations are as found in this section.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The inmate on leave, work release, or school release may not go outside the limits of the State without the written permission of the Institution Board of Review.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The inmate on leave, work release, or school release may not commit any act which would be a violation of any federal law, State law, or municipal ordinance, and shall conform to all rules of conduct imposed by the Institution or an authorized representative of the Institution.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The inmate on leave, work release, or school release shall report back to the Institution at the time specified on the pass, or wherever and whenever an authorized representative of the Institution may direct.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The inmate on leave, work release, or school release may not own, possess, use, buy, sell, or have under his or her control any firearm or weapon of any description.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The inmate on leave, work release, or school release may not enter into any contract to engage in business, borrow money, enter into any installment contract, incur any debt, or acquire ownership of any motor vehicle without first having obtained written permission from the Board of Review.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The inmate on leave, work release, or school release may not unlawfully possess, use, buy, sell, or have under his or her control any narcotic drug, controlled dangerous substance, or related paraphernalia.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The inmate on leave, work release, or school release shall submit to any test or search that is prescribed by the Institution or its authorized representative to detect the usage of alcohol or controlled dangerous substances, or the possession of contraband.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>If work release has been granted by the Board of Review, and the court has ordered restitution as part of the sentence or as a condition of probation, the Board of Review shall require the inmate to make restitution payments.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>The inmate on leave, work release, or school release may not engage in conduct that would pose a threat to public safety.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>The inmate on leave, work release, or school release may not drink any intoxicating beverage.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>The inmate on leave, work release, or school release shall have a pass in his or her possession at all times while outside the confines of the Institution and shall notify the Institution in case of emergency or to resolve questions of identity.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>The inmate on leave shall request approval from the Board of Review to withdraw additional funds from his or her financial accounts for his or her personal needs and to defray the cost of transportation to and from the Institution.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>The inmate on leave, work release, or school release shall deposit all wages in the Institution's business office on a weekly basis, unless otherwise specified, together with an attached voucher indicating the number of hours worked, hourly wages, deductions, and number of days worked.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>The inmate on leave shall strictly adhere to the times and geographical locations specified on the inmate's leave itinerary.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>Work release or school release inmates shall use their time outside the Institution for purposes of work or attending school. Work or school attendance is regularly supervised by the Institution. Employers or school supervisors are requested to call the Institution if the inmate does not report as scheduled. In appropriate cases, inmates on work release or school release may be granted leaves for purposes other than work or school attendance.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>Inmates on leave status are not permitted to use their leaves for the purposes of engaging in employment. This does not prohibit the authorized search for employment in preparation for work release.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>Unless otherwise indicated, a work release or school release inmate shall report to the community supervision clinic for supervision as scheduled.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Housing of Inmates Granted Work Release or School Release Privileges.</heading>
    <text>The Institution shall designate facilities for the housing of inmates granted work release or school release privileges.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="12|12|07|.08">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Monitoring and Supervision of Leave, Work Release, and School Release Participants.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Every participant in the prerelease program shall be monitored and supervised in the community to assure the continued safety of the public.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Associate Director for Treatment and the administrator of the reentry facility shall develop and implement a plan for community supervision of participants in the work release and school release programs. The plan shall be approved by the Director, and shall include procedures for work or school site visits, home visits, and documentation and reporting of any prerelease violations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The following shall be responsible for managing the community monitoring program and shall see that the personnel performing the monitoring tasks meet the requirements of the plan developed pursuant to <cite path="12|12|07|.08|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For the leave program, the unit treatment team chairman shall be the responsible manager;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For the work release and school release program, the administrator of the reentry facility shall be the responsible party.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A disapproval decision for leave of an inmate by the unit treatment team is subject to appeal to the Board of Review by the inmate.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An inmate who is successfully participating in the work release or school release program may be eligible for a 1-day leave. To be eligible, the inmate shall have the recommendation of the inmate's direct supervisor in the work release or school release program, meet all the leave regulations specified in <cite path="|12|12|07|.06|F.">Regulation .06F of this chapter</cite>, and have the approval of the Board of Review.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>An inmate released from confinement on leave or a work release or school release program who commits a major violation as delineated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|4-306">Correctional Services Article, §4-306(c), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and <cite path="12.12.09.03|A.">COMAR 12.12.09.03A</cite>, shall be subject to the penalties provided.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Disposition of Earnings.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General. Inmates employed in the community under a work release or school release program shall surrender to the Institution their total earnings less payroll deductions required by law.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Institution shall deduct from these earnings, in the following order of priority, an amount determined to be the cost to the State of providing the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Food, lodging, and clothing for the inmate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The actual and necessary food, travel, and other expenses of the inmate when released from actual confinement under the program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The amount which the inmate may be legally obligated to pay for the support of the inmate's dependents; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The amount ordered to be paid by the court as restitution.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>School release inmates receiving a stipend or other monies not subject to payroll deductions are not subject to room, board, clothing, and travel fees.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Any balance remaining of the inmate's earnings after these deductions and payments shall be credited to the inmate's account and shall be paid to the inmate upon obtaining parole.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An inmate shall use, on a weekly basis, adequate funds from a work release or school release account to defray the cost of transportation, meals, and sundries on a schedule approved by the Board of Review.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Request for Additional Funds.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An inmate may request approval from the Board of Review to withdraw additional funds for personal needs from the inmate's work release or school release account.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An inmate shall be provided adequate funds from the inmate's work release or school release account to meet the inmate's needs, and to assure that the inmate will have the financial means to return to the Institution. The Board of Review shall indicate the specific amount to be provided.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Correctional Services Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|4-208">4-208</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|4-303">4-303</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-02-03">Effective date: February 3, 1992 (19:2 Md. R. 155)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
