<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>08</num>
  <heading>Parole</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Adjudicated Federal Detainer.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Adjudicated federal detainer" means a detainer based on an offense for which the inmate has been tried, convicted, sentenced, and committed to the custody of the U.S. Attorney General.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Adjudicated federal detainer" does not mean a detainer based on an untried indictment, information, or complaint, or a detainer of federal parole or federal probation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Inmate" means an eligible person, as defined in <cite path="12.12.01.03|B.|(9)">COMAR 12.12.01.03B(9)</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Medical parole" means a parole granted to an inmate because of a diagnosed serious medical condition.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Parole" means a conditional release from the Institution, after a portion of the sentence has been served in confinement, to serve the balance of the sentence under supervision in the community. Parole is a privilege and not a right. Parole may be revoked in accordance with the procedures described in <cite path="12.12.12.03">COMAR 12.12.12.03</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>General.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Parole may not be recommended unless approved by the affirmative vote of a quorum of the Board of Review, as defined in <cite path="12.12.06.05|A.">COMAR 12.12.06.05A</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board of Review has the exclusive power to recommend an inmate for parole to the Secretary or the Governor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Date Crime Committed.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The required approval for parole status depends on the date that the crime for which an inmate is incarcerated was committed, and whether an inmate is serving a life or nonlife sentence.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Inmates Serving Life Sentences.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If an inmate's crime was committed on or before July 1, 1982, the inmate may be paroled by the approval of the Board of Review.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If an inmate's crime was committed after July 1, 1982 and on or before March 20, 1989, the inmate may be paroled by the recommendation of the Board of Review and the approval of the Governor.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If an inmate's crime was committed after March 20, 1989, the inmate may be paroled by the recommendation of the Board of Review and the approval of the Secretary and the Governor.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Inmates Serving Nonlife Sentences.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If the inmate's crime was committed on or before March 20, 1989, the inmate may be paroled by the approval of the Board of Review.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If an inmate's crime was committed after March 20, 1989, the inmate may be paroled by the recommendation of the Board of Review and the approval of the Secretary.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Victim Comment, Victim Notification, and Police Notification.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board of Review shall give the inmate's victim a reasonable opportunity to comment in writing before the Board of Review decides whether to grant parole to the inmate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The victim may designate, in writing to the Board of Review, the name and address of a representative, who is a resident of the State, to receive notice for the victim that the inmate will be considered for parole.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the victim cannot be located, the judge holding jurisdiction over the inmate's sentence may be contacted for comment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Board of Review shall delete the victim's address and telephone number before examination of any document by the inmate or the inmate's representative.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Board of Review shall notify the victim of its decision regarding parole.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The Board of Review shall notify the police department possessing jurisdiction over the locality in which an inmate's crime was originally committed whenever an inmate has been released on parole.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Board of Review shall notify the inmate of its decision regarding placement on parole.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Board of Review has the power to revoke, extend, or modify an inmate's parole.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The Board of Review has the authority to return the paroled inmate to the Institution if the paroled inmate's progress in the community is considered to pose a risk to public safety or pose a risk to the paroled inmate.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The Board of Review may impose special conditions on paroled inmates.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Length of Sentence and Time Served Criteria.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In considering an inmate for parole, if the inmate has been incarcerated for a crime committed after March 20, 1989, the Board of Review shall consider the length of the inmate's sentence and the amount of time served on the current term of imprisonment to date.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An inmate incarcerated for a crime committed after March 20, 1989, who has been sentenced to life imprisonment for rape in the first degree, a sexual offense in the first degree, or murder in the first degree is not eligible for parole until the inmate has served 15 years of the sentence, or the equivalent of 15 years when considering allowances for diminution of the period of confinement provided for by law.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An inmate incarcerated for a crime committed after March 20, 1989, who has been sentenced to life imprisonment under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|2-304">Criminal Law Article, §2-304, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, is not eligible for parole until the inmate has served 25 years of the sentence, or the equivalent of 25 years when considering allowances for diminution of the period of confinement provided for by law.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An inmate incarcerated for a crime committed on or before March 20, 1989, is eligible for parole at any time. The Board of Review may consider the length of the inmate's sentence and the amount of time served on the sentence to date in considering whether to grant or recommend parole.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Progress on Work Release or School Release.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In considering an inmate for parole, the Board of Review shall determine whether the inmate has performed successfully on work release or school release. Letters from employers, friends, family members, and others, which describe the inmate's adjustment on work release or school release, shall be permitted to go to the Board of Review for the purpose of parole consideration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In determining successful performance on work release or school release, the Board of Review shall consider an inmate's progress based upon the public safety criteria and progress-in-treatment criteria specified in <cite path="12.12.07.04">COMAR 12.12.07.04</cite> and .05.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>To make these determinations concerning parole, the Board of Review shall also consider:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Whether the inmate has successfully participated in a substance abuse program while on work release or school release, if appropriate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Whether the inmate has continued to demonstrate emotional maturity and insight, as assessed through the reports and recommendations of Institution treatment and custody staff;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The inmate's ability and readiness to assume obligations and to undertake responsibilities to live in the community;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The inmate's community resources, and the stability of the family that will assist the inmate to return to the community;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The inmate's physical health; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Any other factors or information which the Board of Review may find relevant to the inmate's consideration for parole.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Medical Parole.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The criteria for medical parole consideration are that the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Inmate is imminently terminal, or has a condition which would indicate that continued imprisonment would serve no useful purpose, for example, an irreversible coma; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Inmate's release would not unduly jeopardize public safety.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Contents of Medical Parole Request.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Director shall ensure that all documents forming the basis for a medical parole request are submitted to the Board of Review. If a quorum of the Board of Review recommends the inmate for a medical parole, the recommendation shall be submitted to the Secretary for consideration when the inmate is serving a nonlife sentence, and to the Secretary and the Governor when the inmate is serving a life sentence.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>To initiate consideration for a medical parole, the inmate's unit treatment team shall send a summary of the inmate's incarceration record since admission to the Director. The summary shall include the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>History of program participation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Special housing requirements;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Reasons for the recommendation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>An aftercare treatment plan for the inmate; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>A statement by the attending physician which includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Diagnosis,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Prognosis,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Inpatient or outpatient status, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Criteria justification.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Board of Review may reject a recommendation for medical parole that has been submitted by the Director. The Board of Review's decision to deny a medical parole is final.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Parole to Adjudicated Federal Detainer.</heading>
    <text>An inmate with an adjudicated federal detainer shall be subject to the same procedures and criteria in being considered for parole to meet the detainer as an inmate who does not have an adjudicated federal detainer.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Granting of Parole.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Before starting a parole program, the inmate shall sign an agreement that affirms the inmate's understanding of the regulations governing parole, as set forth in this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The regulations outlined in <cite path="12.12.07.06|F.|(1)">COMAR 12.12.07.06F(1)</cite>--(10) shall also apply to parolees.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The parolee shall make a reasonable effort to remain gainfully employed or otherwise occupied, as directed by the Board of Review.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The parolee may not change his or her place of residence or employment without first having obtained the permission of the Board of Review.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The inmate may not be released on parole until the order of parole is presented and acknowledged by the inmate's signature. An inmate shall be released on parole as soon as practical after a favorable decision, unless:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board of Review has specified a deferred release date;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The investigation of the community resources of the inmate to be paroled indicates that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The parolee is likely to be unemployed upon release, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The parolee is without a satisfactory home plan; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The parole plan has not been approved by the Board of Review as specified in <cite path="|12|12|08|.08">Regulation .08 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The order of parole shall bear the signature or facsimile of the signature of a member of the Board of Review and the official seal of the Board of Review. Another member of the Board of Review shall attest the signature.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The Board of Review may, for the safety and welfare of the inmate on parole and for the safety of the public, impose reasonable special conditions to be complied with before release on parole.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Parole Release Plan.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A parole release plan shall be completed and submitted before the parole hearing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Elements in a release plan include, but are not limited to, the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The name of the parolee's employer or evidence of other legitimate means of financial support;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The location at which the parolee will reside; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The nature of any community services necessary to meet the special needs of the parolee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Modification of Release Plan.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An inmate's parole release plan previously approved by the Board of Review may only be altered or changed by the Board of Review.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Board of Review may, from time to time, and upon good cause, change or modify the conditions of an inmate's parole.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>In case of modification, the parolee shall be given the opportunity to show cause why a condition should not be changed, added, or modified.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The parolee may request a hearing before the Board of Review to discuss the modification.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Monitoring and Supervision of Parolees.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each parolee shall be seen by an assigned parole supervisor or designee for parole supervision in accordance with the terms of parole established by the Board of Review. Every contact with a parolee shall be documented by the supervisor or the designee. Contact shall include both scheduled and unscheduled meetings, and meetings may take place in the field, home, place of employment, and any other place assigned.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Schedule of Meetings.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board of Review shall establish a schedule of required supervisory meetings between parolees and their parole supervisors and shall make adherence to that schedule a written condition of parole.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>First-year parolees shall meet with their parole supervisor a minimum of once each week.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Second-year parolees shall meet with their parole supervisor a minimum of once every 2 weeks.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Third-year parolees shall meet with their parole supervisor a minimum of once each month.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Recommendations for a change in a parolee's supervision schedule shall be presented to the Board of Review for final approval.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The parolee shall be seen at a Board-approved designated location in the State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The supervisor or designee shall prepare a written report of every scheduled or unscheduled contact with a parolee, including unkept appointments, and shall make that report a part of the parolee's official record.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A parolee, when seen, shall present proof that the parolee is maintaining steady employment, attending substance abuse group meetings if appropriate, and living at a specified address. This information will be verified and documented.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A parolee shall give a random urine specimen as required by the parolee's supervisor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>A parolee shall discuss the problems or the progress that the parolee is having in the community and the types of relationships that the parolee may be establishing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>A parolee may be subject to a search for contraband during the parolee's visit by the parole supervisor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Periodic job checks and home checks shall be made by the parole supervisor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>A parolee functioning on Interstate Compact or paroled to meet a detainer shall be monitored at least yearly by a designated employee of the Institution.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>A parolee shall be employed or enrolled in school, and have a legitimate means of financial support. If unemployed or unemployable, the parolee shall have a legitimate means of financial support while on parole.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>When paroled, an inmate shall receive all current funds in the inmate's active and reserve accounts, which have been maintained at the Institution. If paroled from work release, the inmate shall receive 100 percent of their work release account upon being paroled, less the deductions specified in <cite path="12.12.07.09|B.">COMAR 12.12.07.09B</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>A parolee shall be counseled concerning the benefits of establishing savings accounts at financial institutions in the community.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>A parolee who needs financial assistance shall be referred to appropriate community agencies and assisted in the application processes of the community agencies by a parole supervisor.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Correctional Services Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|4-208">4-208</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|4-305">4-305</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-02-03">Effective date: February 3, 1992 (19:2 Md. R. 155)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
