<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>09</num>
  <heading>Major Violations and Penalties for Eligible Persons on Conditional Release</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>For the purpose of maintaining order, discipline, and security, the Institution establishes rules of behavior which it expects eligible persons to obey and sanctions that may be imposed for violation of these rules. The purpose of any sanction shall be to aid in the maintenance of order, discipline, and security within the Institution or within the community, to punish the offender, and to deter future misbehavior.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Conditional release" means any of the forms of release status, as defined in <cite path="12.12.01.03|B.|(5)">COMAR 12.12.01.03B(5)</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Disciplinary Committee" means the panel of three Institution staff members whose purpose is to conduct hearings and impose penalties for eligible persons who violate the Institution's rules. The panel is composed of one custody supervisor, one treatment staff member, and one member of the education department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Escape" means when an eligible person leaves the confines of the Institution by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Breaching the Institution's security perimeter;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Failing to return from an authorized prerelease status, that is, work release, school release, or day or overnight leave;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Escaping from escort officers while outside the confines of the Institution; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Absconding from parole supervision.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Incident report" means a less severe disciplinary action that is disposed of informally. Incident reports are not appealable.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Notice of infraction" means the official document that charges an eligible person with violating an Institution rule.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Parole violator" means a paroled eligible person who has failed to comply with any of the conditions of his or her parole agreement, or who has committed a new offense while paroled.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Specification of Major Violations.</heading>
    <text>Major violations of Institution rules shall include:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Escape from parole, work release, school release, or leave;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Failure to return from parole, work release, school release, or leave within 1 hour of the time due, unless the failure to return was due to causes beyond the control of the eligible person;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Commission of a new offense, other than a minor traffic violation, while on parole, work release, school release, or leave;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Commission of a major violation of the Institution's disciplinary rules, which shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Altering, destroying, or damaging any item valued at $50 or over,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Arson,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Attempting to commit any major violation,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Creating a disturbance,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Hoarding authorized medication,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Interfering with or obstructing a staff member from performing the staff member's duties,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Possession of a weapon,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Possession of implements reasonably expected to be used in an escape,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Refusing a direct order when the refusal jeopardizes the security or order of the Institution,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Rioting or inciting a riot,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Any sexual acts involving others, or directed towards others, within the Institution or the reentry facility,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Soliciting, conspiring, being an accessory to, or aiding and abetting the commission of a major violation,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Soliciting or attempting to influence an employee to jeopardize the security of the Institution,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>Tampering with or misusing any communication system in such a way as to jeopardize the security of the Institution,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>Throwing excrement,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>Unauthorized possession, sale, use, passing, or receiving of drugs, controlled dangerous substances, alcohol, or drug paraphernalia,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>Assault or battery, or both, on an inmate, staff member, correctional officer, visitor, or any other person,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>Threatening another inmate, staff member, correctional officer, visitor, or any other person, or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>Unauthorized physical contact with another inmate, staff member, correctional officer, or visitor;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Violation of any parole, work release, school release, or leave rule not categorized as a minor violation under the regulations of the Institution; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Use of any controlled dangerous substance if the eligible person is not entitled to use the controlled dangerous substance under the laws of this State.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="12|12|09|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Disciplinary Procedures Pertaining to Major Violations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Director shall ensure that major violations are disposed of formally, in accordance with established procedures concerning:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The status of the alleged violator pending formal disposition, that is, the determination of the need for temporary segregation from the general population;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The timely serving of the notice of infraction to the alleged violator;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Notice to the alleged violator that he or she has the right to representation by a staff member, or an eligible person, who volunteers to represent the alleged violator; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Notice to the alleged violator that he or she has the right to call witnesses on his or her behalf.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Within 24 hours of the alleged major violation, the Warden shall review the circumstances of the alleged violation and approve or disapprove the decision to place the alleged violator on temporary segregation, and:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Forward the notice of infraction to the Disciplinary Committee for a hearing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Reduce the notice of infraction to an incident report, notify the eligible person and reporting staff member in writing of the action taken, and if the eligible person does not consent to have the notice of infraction reduced to an incident report, the matter shall proceed to a hearing pursuant to <cite path="12|12|09|.04|B.|(3)">§B(3) of this regulation</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Return the notice of infraction to the reporting staff member for correction of inaccuracies or inadequacies, clarification of statements, or substantiation of charges, if these deficiencies are noted, and forward the revised notice of infraction to the Disciplinary Committee for a hearing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Director shall ensure that all Disciplinary Committee hearings are conducted in accordance with established procedures concerning:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The timeliness of the hearing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The alleged violator's right to appear before the Disciplinary Committee for a hearing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The alleged violator's right to waive the right to appear at the hearing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Disciplinary Committee's right to conduct a hearing in absentia and render a decision, upon receipt of the alleged violator's waiver of the right to appear or documented refusal to appear;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The right of the alleged violator to be advised of the charge or charges against him or her;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The right of the alleged violator to enter a plea;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The right of the alleged violator to cross-examine each witness;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The right of the alleged violator to testify on his or her own behalf;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>The right of the alleged violator not to testify on his or her own behalf, without inference of guilt;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>The right to be represented by a staff member or an eligible person who volunteers to represent the alleged violator;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>The right of the alleged violator to present the testimony of his or her witnesses, provided that the chairman of the Disciplinary Committee determines that the witnesses' testimony may be relevant;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>The right of the alleged violator or his or her representative to examine any real evidence, at the discretion of the chairman, provided it would not endanger the security of the Institution;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>The right of the alleged violator to request a postponement of the proceedings;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>The right of the alleged violator to be informed of the Disciplinary Committee's factual findings, the disposition, and the reasons for the decision, and to receive a copy of the findings and disposition; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>The right of the violator to appeal the decision of the Disciplinary Committee to the Director within 48 hours.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>All proceedings before the Disciplinary Committee shall be recorded on audio recording tape and stored by the Institution for a period of 1 year from the date of the disciplinary hearing, unless the Institution has received notice of an appeal of the disciplinary result to the Inmate Grievance Commission or notice of a pending action in a court of law. If notice has been received, the tape shall be preserved pending a final decision in the forum or forums in which action is pending.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Authority of the Disciplinary Committee.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An eligible person is entitled to a hearing by the Disciplinary Committee if the eligible person has been charged with an Institution violation and fails to consent to the notice of infraction being reduced to an incident report.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If a Disciplinary Committee hearing results in a finding of guilt, the Committee may impose penalties on the eligible person as it deems appropriate under the circumstances, with the exception of the removal of the eligible person from the Institution.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="12|12|09|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Removal from the Institution.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board of Review will review all eligible persons with conditional release status who have been found guilty of charges heard by the Disciplinary Committee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="12|12|09|.06|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, an eligible person incarcerated for a crime committed:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>On or before March 20, 1989, who commits a major violation while on parole, work release, school release, or leave shall be confined to the Institution and shall be ineligible for work release, school release, or leave for a period of 6 months;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>After March 20, 1989, who commits a major violation while on parole, work release, school release, or leave shall be confined to the Institution and shall be ineligible for parole, work release, school release, or leave for a period of 6 months.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the Board of Review or the Secretary determines that a major violation was severe enough to warrant removing an eligible person from the Institution, the eligible person may be removed from the Institution and returned to the Division to serve the remainder of his or her original sentence.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If an eligible person commits a second major violation while on parole, work release, school release, or leave, the person shall be removed from the Institution and returned to the Division to serve the remainder of his or her original sentence.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Corrective Services Article, §4-208, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-02-03">Effective date: February 3, 1992 (19:2 Md. R. 155)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
