<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>13</num>
  <heading>Mandatory Supervision and Release Upon Expiration of Sentence</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Inmate" means an eligible person, as defined in <cite path="12.12.01.03|B.|(9)">COMAR 12.12.01.03B(9)</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Mandatory supervision" means the release of an inmate from the Institution to the supervision of the Division of Parole and Probation, on the date that the inmate has served the equivalent of his or her full sentence minus allowances for diminution of the period of confinement or sentence provided for by law.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Maximum Expiration Date.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Maximum expiration date" means the date computed by adding an inmate's total sentence length to the beginning date of the first sentence with the earliest start date which is part of the inmate's then current term of confinement.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Maximum expiration date" includes adjustments for time out of custody without credit.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Release by expiration of sentence" means the release of an inmate:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Whose only sentences are for offenses committed before July 1, 1970, and who has served the term or terms of confinement to which the inmate was sentenced less the diminution of confinement deductions provided for in Correctional Services Article, Title 3, Subtitle 7, and Title 11, Subtitle 5, Annotated Code of Maryland; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Who has actually served the day for day maximum term or terms of confinement to which the inmate was sentenced.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Total sentence length" means the period covered by the inmate's then current term of confinement excluding time out of custody without credit. If the inmate is serving a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Single sentence, it is the period of confinement under that sentence;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Combination of concurrent sentences, it is the period of confinement between the earliest starting date of those sentences and the latest expiration date of those sentences;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Combination of consecutive sentences, it is the period of confinement between the starting date of the first consecutive sentence and the expiration date of the last consecutive sentence; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Combination of concurrent and consecutive sentences, it is the period of confinement between the earliest starting date of the sentences and the last expiration date of the sentences.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>General.</heading>
    <text>An inmate shall be released and transferred from the Institution in accordance with normal procedures established by law.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="12|12|13|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Diminution of Confinement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each inmate admitted to the Institution is entitled to a diminution of the period of commitment or total sentence length, up to a maximum allowable deduction of 15 days per calendar month, in accordance with the provisions of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An inmate shall be allowed an initial deduction from the period of commitment or sentence, subject to the inmate's future good conduct. This deduction shall be calculated at the rate of 5 days for each calendar month, and on a prorated basis for any portion of a calendar month, within the period between the first day of commitment to the custody of the Commissioner and the inmate's maximum expiration date.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>For each calendar month during which an inmate has manifested exceptional industry, application, and skill in the performance of industrial, agricultural, or administrative tasks assigned to the inmate, the inmate may be allowed an additional deduction of 5 days from the period of the commitment or sentence. These deductions shall commence on the first day that the task is performed and shall be made on a prorated basis for any portion of a calendar month during which the inmate performed the task.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>For each calendar month during which an inmate has manifested satisfactory industry, application, and progress in vocational or other educational and training courses, the inmate may be allowed an additional deduction of 5 days from the period of the commitment or sentence. These deductions shall commence on the first day that the inmate participates in these courses and shall be made on a prorated basis for any portion of a calendar month during which the inmate participated in the course.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Projects and Programs.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For each calendar month, or any portion of a calendar month, commencing on the first day of assignment, during which the inmate has manifested satisfactory industry, application, and progress in special selected work projects, or other special programs, the inmate may be allowed an additional deduction of days, not exceeding 5 in number, from the period of the commitment or sentence.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Director, with the approval of the Secretary and based on the Institution's current policy and procedure, may establish a list of projects and programs that qualify for special projects credit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Diminution credits may be awarded for projects or programs under <cite path="12|12|13|.03|E.|(2)">§E(2) of this regulation</cite> which include, but need not be limited to the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Prison industry assignments;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Education programs;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Work details;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Work release employment; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Rehabilitation programs including, but not limited to, programs addressing:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Substance abuse; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Criminal behavior.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The maximum allowable deduction under the combined operation of §§C and D in any calendar month is 5 days.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>For any major violation of the Institution's rules a portion or all of the deductions allowed under §§B and E may be revoked. The Institution may restore any portion of the deductions revoked.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>If an inmate is released under mandatory supervision on sentences for offenses occurring on or after July 1, 1989, and the mandatory supervision is later revoked, the inmate may not earn any new diminution of confinement credits as otherwise provided for under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs">Correctional Services Article, Title 3, Subtitle 7, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="12|12|13|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Restoration of Revoked Diminution Credit.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Good conduct credit, as described in <cite path="|12|12|13|.03|B.">Regulation .03B of this chapter</cite>, and special projects credit, as described in <cite path="|12|12|13|.03|E.">Regulation .03E of this chapter</cite>, may be restored by the Director if it has been revoked. The Director may consider restoring revoked diminution credit upon receiving the recommendation for restoration, and supporting documentation described in <cite path="12|12|13|.04|J.">§J of this regulation</cite>, from the inmate's unit treatment team chairman.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A unit treatment team chairman may recommend restoration of revoked diminution credit for an inmate who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Has been infraction free for the preceding 6 months;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is not serving a disciplinary segregation sentence; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Has not been released from disciplinary segregation within the preceding 6 months.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A unit treatment team chairman has complete discretion to recommend restoration of revoked diminution credit, and an inmate who meets the criteria in <cite path="12|12|13|.04|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> has no expectation of approval for restoration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Director shall ensure that the amount of diminution credit restored does not exceed 50 percent of the total amount that has been revoked, if the inmate has been convicted of an infraction within the past 12 months.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Director shall ensure that a decision to restore revoked diminution credit is based upon all aspects of the inmate's behavior and Institution adjustment after revocation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Director's responsibility under this regulation may not be delegated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The Director shall ensure that by the tenth day of each month, the records supervisor forwards to each unit treatment team chairman a list of inmates from their unit who, if the maximum possible amount of the revoked diminution credit for which the inmate is eligible were restored, would reach mandatory supervision or maximum expiration dates within 90 days. The records supervisor shall ensure that the list includes the inmate's name, Institution number, and total number of diminution credits revoked.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The records supervisor shall forward a copy of each list to the Director and the Warden.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Eligibility for Restoration.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within 5 working days of the receipt of the information specified in <cite path="12|12|13|.04|G.">§G of this regulation</cite>, the unit treatment team chairman shall determine an inmate's eligibility for restoration of revoked diminution credits.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If an inmate is ineligible for restoration, the unit treatment team chairman shall document the reason or reasons on the progress sheet in the inmate's base file.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the inmate is eligible for restoration, the unit treatment team chairman shall prepare the supporting documentation described in <cite path="12|12|13|.04|J.">§J of this regulation</cite> for submission to the Director.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>A unit treatment team chairman considering an inmate for restoration of revoked diminution credits shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Affirmatively establish whether the inmate meets the eligibility requirements of this regulation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Recommend that restoration of revoked diminution credits be approved or disapproved;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Specify the number of days to be restored in any recommendation for restoration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Notify the inmate of the recommendation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Document the rationale for the recommendation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>The Director's decision to disapprove a unit treatment team chairman's recommendation for restoration is final.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>If the Director approves the restoration of credit, the unit treatment team chairman shall forward a copy of the Director's approval to the records supervisor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>The records supervisor shall deduct the restored credit from the mandatory supervision release date on the inmate's diminution of confinement record.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Notification for Mandatory Supervision.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Inmate Records Supervisor shall notify the Division of Parole and Probation of any inmates to be placed on mandatory supervision at least 1 week before the scheduled release date. Notification shall also be sent to the inmate, the Parole Commission, the Parole and Probation reporting office, the victim if the victim has filed a written request to be informed, the inmate's base file, and the inmate's commitment jacket.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The inmate placed on mandatory supervision shall be subject to all laws, rules, regulations, and conditions applicable to parolees and shall remain under the supervision of the Division of Parole and Probation until the expiration of the maximum term or terms for which the inmate was sentenced.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>This regulation does not prevent delivery of inmates to any state or federal authority otherwise entitled to their custody by detainer.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Notification for Inmates Released Upon Expiration of Sentence.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Director shall ensure that the inmate records supervisor provides notification of an inmate released by expiration of sentence to the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Inmate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Victim, if the victim has filed a written request to be informed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Inmate base file; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Inmate commitment jacket.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This regulation does not prevent delivery of an inmate to another state or federal authority otherwise entitled to the authority's custody by detainer.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An inmate released as a result of expiration of sentence is not within the supervision of the Maryland Parole Commission and is not required to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Sign a mandatory supervision release certificate; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Report to a parole and probation intake unit for processing and supervision.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If an inmate is to be released through expiration of sentence, the Director shall notify the Commissioner 30 days before the inmate's release.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Correctional Services Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|4-208">4-208</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|4-304">4-304</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-02-03">Effective date: February 3, 1992 (19:2 Md. R. 155)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-02-12"><cite path="|12|12|13|.03|E.">Regulation .03E</cite> amended effective February 12, 2007 (34:3 Md. R. 300)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
