<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>15</num>
  <heading>Annual Report</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose and Content.</heading>
    <text>The purpose of the annual report is to transmit the following information to the Secretary and to the Governor:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The information described in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|4-203">Correctional Services Article, §4-203, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, which includes expenses, receipts, disbursements, condition and progress of the Institution, number of prisoners, their age, sex, color, place of birth, place of conviction, offense, term of confinement, escapes, pardons, and discharges, accompanied by such remarks and suggestions as may be necessary to the advancement of the interests of the Institution;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The information described in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|4-203">Correctional Services Article, §4-203, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, which includes:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The total number of eligible and noneligible persons evaluated at the Institution,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The decisions of the Board of Review to grant leave to eligible persons,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The total number of rearrests, reconvictions, reincarcerations, and parole violations of persons formerly incarcerated at the Institution,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The total number of eligible persons incarcerated at the Institution who are returned to the Division for major violations of the Institution's disciplinary rules, and the type of major violation, and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Information on education programs and community reentry activities.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Submission.</heading>
    <text>The Director is responsible for completing the annual report. The Director shall submit the annual report to the Secretary and to the Governor by the end of October of each year.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Correctional Services Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|4-203">4-203</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|4-208">4-208</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-02-03">Effective date: February 3, 1992 (19:2 Md. R. 155)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
