<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>17</num>
  <heading>Special Activities</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Citizen participant" means a person who provides a service on an irregular and infrequent basis, not exceeding 6 visits per year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Coordinator" means a volunteer services coordinator.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Employee volunteer" means a person who is employed by the Institution and who provides a service on personal time to the Institution.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"FBI Criminal History Record Information" means the primary method by which criminal history information is reported.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Inmate" means an eligible person, as defined in <cite path="12.12.01.03|B.|(9)">COMAR 12.12.01.03B(9)</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Lay Volunteer.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Lay volunteer" means a person who volunteers on that person's personal time to provide services on a regular or frequent basis. The volunteer may be associated with a group, such as a civic, fraternal or services organization, or church.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Lay volunteer" does not mean a student intern, volunteer professional, or citizen participant.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Maryland CCH IDENT/INDEX and Criminal History Record Information" means the computerized Criminal History Identification Index.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Material/monetary donor" means a person or group that provides material or monetary donations to the Institution.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Reasonable suspicion" means the apparent state of facts or circumstances which would lead a reasonably prudent person to believe that a violation has been committed, is in the process of being committed, or may be committed by a specific individual.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Registered volunteer" means a volunteer who has completed the screening and orientation procedures, and has obtained the authorized approval necessary to make regular visits to the Institution.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Student intern" means a student from a post-high school educational institution who, for credit and under the supervision of that person's school, performs services on a regular or frequent basis.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>"Volunteer" means a citizen who provides a service or donation to the Institution or its inmates without receiving direct compensation from the Institution and who has been identified as a volunteer through the procedures described in <cite path="|12|12|17|.03|G.">Regulation .03G of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Volunteer Professional.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Volunteer professional" means a person who represents another agency in providing a service on a regular or frequent basis and is paid by that agency.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Volunteer professional" does not mean personnel from the Department of Education, or contractual personnel who provide substance abuse treatment.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>"Volunteer services" means planned activities which aid staff in promoting inmate adjustment and which utilize citizens as the major resource.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Recreational, Cultural, and Community Activities.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Director shall develop, implement, and maintain a recreational program for the inmate population.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Director shall ensure that an inmate is given the opportunity to participate in as many recreational activities as possible, considering Institution security and control needs.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A volunteer may be used at the Institution for the recreation program, under the supervision of the recreation staff, and in conjunction with the volunteer services program requirements and security regulations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Director may develop procedures for inmate participation in a community league when consistent with established Institution policy and security requirements.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The unit treatment teams shall also be responsible for reviewing community activities and securing permission for inmates with appropriate leave status to attend community functions.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Staff members involved with inmate recreation programs may consult with community-based interest groups to provide liaison services for programs, and to ensure community and Institution interaction.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Volunteer Services.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The members of the public are encouraged to participate in inmate volunteer activities.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Coordinator, serving under the supervision of the Warden, shall be responsible for the coordination of all volunteer activities, volunteer groups, and religious education classes within the Institution.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Institution encourages the activities of self-help and self-improvement groups consistent with the rules, regulations, and operational capabilities of the Institution.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A Volunteer Advisory Committee shall assist the Coordinator. A Volunteer Advisory Committee shall include one representative and alternate of each of the volunteer activities scheduled at the Institution quarterly or more frequently. Committee members shall be approved by and serve at the pleasure of the Director. The Director may appoint a volunteer representative at the recommendation of the Coordinator, the Chaplain, or the Warden.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Volunteer activities shall be scheduled at least 1 week in advance for regularly scheduled weekly activities and 60 days in advance for special events or programs. Notification shall include identification of all volunteers scheduled to enter the Institution and all equipment or materials necessary for the function. Cancellation of any program shall be made at the earliest possible time by notifying the shift commander and all departments involved in the scheduled function.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Volunteer Services Program Management.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Warden and the Coordinator shall develop annual goal statements based on needs assessment results and direction from the Director.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Each registered volunteer shall have a written assignment description prepared by the Coordinator.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Warden and the Coordinator shall recruit volunteers from all cultural and socioeconomic segments of the community.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Warden shall ensure that gifts, contributions, and donations to the Institution are accepted and processed per Department of Budget and Fiscal Planning Procurement Regulation <cite path="|02.01.08">02.01.08</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Selection.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Coordinator shall ensure that each volunteer applicant is screened using the following methods:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Personal interview;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Completion of application for volunteer service;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Investigation of credentials, if credentials are germane to volunteer services; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Criminal history investigation using, at a minimum, the following screens:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Maryland CCH IDENT/INDEX and Criminal History Record Information,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>FBI check using transaction codes CCH and CCF,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>OBSCIS II,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Motor vehicle records, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Fingerprinting followed by submission of prints to the FBI for identification, at the Warden's discretion.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A citizen participant, an employee volunteer, or a material or monetary donor may receive a less stringent screening at the discretion of the Director.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person with a criminal record or a former inmate, whether previously incarcerated, or on supervised parole or supervised probation, may be accepted as a registered volunteer with the approval of the Director, with the following stipulations:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The person may not be selected for service other than as a citizen participant until 1 year has elapsed after termination of supervision by closure or abatement through any criminal justice agency;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The person may not have been arrested since termination from supervision;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A person who has had a condition of supervision requiring drug abuse treatment shall also provide as a reference the name of his or her most recent parole or probation agent, or his or her substance abuse treatment counselor.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>An employee volunteer shall sign an agreement to volunteer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The application of any volunteer applicant who is rejected by the Warden, along with the rationale for rejection, shall be forwarded to the Director for a final determination.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Volunteer Orientation.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A registered volunteer shall receive standardized orientation and shall sign required documents stating that orientation has been received.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Orientation shall be conducted by the Coordinator and shall include, at a minimum:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Basic rules and regulations which affect a volunteer; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A description of Institution programs and operations.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A citizen participant may receive a more cursory orientation at the discretion of the Director.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>A volunteer will begin providing services only after receiving orientation and shall be assigned a staff supervisor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>The Coordinator shall provide special skills training as needed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>A supervisor of a volunteer shall work cooperatively with the Coordinator to ensure adequate supervision of volunteer efforts.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Volunteer Access to the Institution.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A volunteer shall sign a volunteer log as provided by the Institution upon entering and leaving the Institution.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Search Procedures.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A volunteer is subject to routine search procedures.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A volunteer shall sign authorization for a clothed body search. Refusal to consent to a clothed body search shall result in denial of access to the Institution.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A volunteer shall sign an authorization for a strip search if the Warden has determined that reasonable suspicion exists. Refusal to consent to a strip search shall result in denial of access to the Institution.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Suspension and Discharge of Volunteers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Coordinator shall implement appropriate action if a volunteer is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Arrested;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Violates Institution rules; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Has not performed responsibilities in accordance with the assignment description or the expectations of the supervisor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The action may include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Suspension; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Discharge.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In the event of discharge, the Coordinator shall advise the volunteer of the reason or reasons for the discharge and conduct an exit interview.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The name of a volunteer who is discharged for unsatisfactory behavior, with the specific rationale for discharge, shall be forwarded to the Warden.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The volunteer may appeal the decision in writing, to the Director, within 30 days from receiving notice.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Coordinator's Responsibilities.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The coordinator shall ensure that a volunteer receives formal and informal recognition for that person's contributions.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Coordinator shall ensure that each inmate receives information about volunteer services at Institution orientation sessions and that bulletins describing volunteer services are posted throughout the Institution.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Coordinator shall be responsible for assessing the promotion of productive relationships among staff and volunteers.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Coordinator shall maintain a file for each volunteer, to contain at least the following documents:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Volunteer application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Volunteer assignment description;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Acknowledgement of orientation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Volunteer exit notice; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Program notes.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Coordinator shall ensure that the Director has approved major modifications to existing Institution volunteer programs and new program initiatives before implementation by the Coordinator.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Chaplaincy Services.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Policy.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>It is the policy of the Institution that an inmate shall have absolute freedom of religious belief.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Within security and program limitations, the Director shall ensure that each inmate has reasonable opportunity to exercise his or her religious beliefs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Director shall ensure that each religion receives equal status and protection.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A chaplaincy service, in conjunction with other Institution programs and activities, presents the opportunity for an inmate to make incarceration a productive period of personal change and growth.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Inmate participation in religious programming is voluntary.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Director shall ensure that religious services are conducted by chaplains or approved volunteer clergy and are available to the general inmate population.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Religious activities are subject to supervision by Institution security staff.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Abstention from Offered Food Items.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An inmate shall be permitted to abstain from regularly offered food items that the inmate believes to be prohibited by the inmate's religion.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A 7-day menu shall be posted on each side of the food serving line in a menu box with a glass front. Pork items shall be marked by an asterisk. Foods which are a nutritionally equivalent substitute shall be provided on the food line for inmates who require a pork-free diet.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Ceremonial Food Packages. When consistent with the operational capabilities of the Institution, food packages of a ceremonial nature shall be admitted during religious holidays. These packages shall be provided free of charge to the Institution in a factory-sealed container, and shall be subject to inspection and approval by the Director.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Inmate Request to Marry.</heading>
    <text>Patuxent Institution shall comply with provisions under <cite path="|12.02.21">COMAR 12.02.21</cite> if an inmate at Patuxent Institution requests to marry.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|4-208">Correctional Services Article, §4-208, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-02-03">Effective date: February 3, 1992 (19:2 Md. R. 155)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-04-11"><cite path="|12|12|17|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective April 11, 2016 (43:7 Md. R. 451)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
