<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>19</num>
  <heading>Inmate Telephone Privileges</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Emergency situation" means those situations in which the unit chairman or designee determines that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An immediate family member of the inmate is hospitalized for serious health reasons, or is in imminent danger of death; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A legal proceeding in which the inmate is a party is scheduled for a hearing, or has a court imposed deadline for filing legal papers within 1 week.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Immediate family" means a grandparent, parent, substitute parent, brother, sister, wife, son, daughter, grandson, or granddaughter. If a relationship other than those specified is involved, a determination of eligibility for telephone use may be made on a therapeutic evaluation of the relationship between the inmate and the relative.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Inmate" means an eligible person, as defined in <cite path="12.12.01.03|B.|(9)">COMAR 12.12.01.03B(9)</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>General.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>There are telephones available at the main Jessup facility for the use of inmates on a collect call basis, as scheduled in accordance with the rules, regulations, and operational capabilities of the Institution.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Institution allows inmates housed at the main Jessup facility to use the telephone in certain emergency situations. The inmate shall provide justification that can be reasonably assessed by Institution staff.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Pay telephones are available at the reentry facility for the use of conditionally released inmates, in emergency and nonemergency situations. Conditionally released inmates shall be allowed access to the telephone consistent with the rules, regulations, and operational capabilities of the reentry facility.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Procedures for the Emergency Use of Telephones.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A telephone shall be made available for use in an emergency situation by an inmate who has the required authorization. All long distance telephone calls shall be made collect.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The procedures for securing a telephone call in an emergency situation require an inmate to submit in writing a request to the inmate's unit chairman, who shall approve or disapprove the call within 24 hours. An approval shall be directed to the appropriate shift commander or designee, who shall arrange for the call. If the unit chairman is not accessible, an inmate may make the request of another unit treatment team staff member. In the event of a verifiable dire emergency, the shift commander or designee may approve the telephone call if appropriate unit treatment team staff are not accessible.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the shift commander or designee approves an incoming or outgoing telephone call in an emergency situation, the shift commander or designee shall document and justify this approval in writing to the Warden and the Associate Director for Treatment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If a legal proceeding in which the inmate is a party is scheduled for a hearing, or has a court imposed deadline for filing legal papers within 1 week, then the inmate shall be permitted a telephone call to the inmate's attorney, the Legal Aid Bureau, or the Public Defender's Office.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The provisions of this regulation shall be contingent upon the availability of sufficient staff to escort an inmate to make the telephone call as permitted by this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|4-208">Correctional Services Article, §4-208, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-02-03">Effective date: February 3, 1992 (19:2 Md. R. 155)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
