<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>21</num>
  <heading>Death, Serious Illness, or Injury of an Inmate</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Death of an Inmate.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Family member" means a person who is immediately related to an inmate by blood or law, including a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Spouse;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Child who is at least 18 years old;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Parent;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Sibling;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Grandparent; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Grandchild who is at least 18 years old.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Indigent inmate" means an inmate who, at the time of death, is under the control of the Institution and who has:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Insufficient funds to pay for funeral and burial expenses;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>No person legally responsible for his or her support who is able to pay funeral and burial expenses; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>No resources available, including family funds, death benefits, estate, or inmate account, which may be used to pay funeral and burial expenses.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Inmate" means an eligible person, as defined in <cite path="12.12.01.03|B.|(9)">COMAR 12.12.01.03B(9)</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Medical examiner" means the Baltimore City Medical Examiner for the reentry facility located in Baltimore City and the Howard County Medical Examiner for the main Jessup facility.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Police" means the Baltimore City Police for the reentry facility located in Baltimore City and the State Police for the main Jessup facility.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Upon discovery of the death of an inmate, medical services staff or the senior shift supervisor shall immediately notify the following authorities:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Secretary;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Director;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Warden;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Associate Director of Treatment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Police; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Medical Examiner.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>After receiving clearance to do so by the appropriate investigating agency, Institution staff shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Immediately inventory and secure the deceased inmate's property;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Take the fingerprints of the deceased for the purpose of positive identification; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Prepare a notice of death for the Federal Bureau of Investigation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Upon official pronouncement of death, the Director shall contact the decedent's next of kin. The identity of a deceased inmate may not be released to the media until the next of kin have been notified.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Institution shall obtain two copies of the autopsy report when appropriate. One copy shall be placed in the inmate's base file and one copy shall be forwarded to the Director for inclusion in the serious incident report.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>If an inmate is known to have died of natural causes while in the Institution's infirmary, or while in an outside hospital, the following action shall be taken after a medical doctor on the scene has pronounced the inmate dead:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The responsible officer on duty at the infirmary or the hospital at the time of the inmate's death shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Immediately notify the Institution shift commander or the officer in charge,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Obtain a receipt for the body before leaving the infirmary or the hospital, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Inventory the inmate's personal possessions at the infirmary or the hospital and return the property to the Institution property officer;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Associate Director of Treatment shall be notified by the shift commander or the officer in charge.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>After the required immediate actions have been taken and the initial notifications have been made, the Warden shall secure three copies of the death certificate from the Maryland Department of Health, Division of Vital Records, to be distributed as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>One copy shall be placed in the inmate's base file;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>One copy shall be given or mailed to the next of kin for use in settling the estate of the deceased; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>One copy shall be included in the serious incident report.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>The Warden shall ensure that the provisions of <cite path="|12|12|21|.02">Regulation .02 of this chapter</cite> are followed in cases when the next of kin intends to claim the body of the deceased inmate, if both the next of kin and the inmate are indigent.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>The Warden shall advise the next of kin to seek the assistance of legal counsel to obtain authority to receive the personal property of the deceased inmate, and shall follow the procedures described in <cite path="12.12.26.03|B.">COMAR 12.12.26.03B</cite> in disposing of the deceased inmate's inventoried possessions.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Funeral and Burial Expenses of Indigent Inmates.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The warden shall refer a family member of the deceased indigent inmate to the Department of Human Services for the determination of his or her eligibility for funeral and burial funds.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The unit chairman from the deceased inmate's treatment unit shall ensure that a family member who assumes responsibility for burial is known to the Department of Human Services, by current eligibility for one of the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Cash benefit support;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Food stamps; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Medical assistance.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The unit chairman shall ensure that the current eligibility of the family member is confirmed by a local agency of the Department of Human Services.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A family member assuming responsibility for burial shall visit the local Department of Human Services agency to complete the appropriate application for Institution funeral and burial expenses.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Upon eligibility confirmation and receipt of the vendor's billing statement, the funds shall be paid by the Institution directly to the funeral director of the family's choice.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The amount of the entitlement will supplement available funds, including the inmate's account, as specified in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="88A|62A">Article 88A, §62A, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>If the body of the deceased indigent inmate is not claimed within 48 hours, the Warden shall coordinate disposition of the body with the State Anatomy Board.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Serious Illness or Injury of Inmate.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Institution shift commander or designee shall immediately notify the following officials when an inmate is seriously ill or injured:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Director;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Warden; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Assistant Warden.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Upon notification of serious illness or injury to an inmate, the Director shall contact the inmate's next of kin and inform them of the inmate's condition.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|4-208">Correctional Services Article, §4-208, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-02-03">Effective date: February 3, 1992 (19:2 Md. R. 155)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
