<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>22</num>
  <heading>Medical Services</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Abortion" means spontaneous or induced termination of pregnancy.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Inmate" means an eligible person, as defined in <cite path="12.12.01.03|B.|(9)">COMAR 12.12.01.03B(9)</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Involuntary admission" means admission of an inmate to a psychiatric hospital, as defined under Health-General Article, §§10-613—10-617, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Postnatal care" means the necessary intervention affording health care and support that is provided to the infant immediately after birth.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Postpartum care" means the necessary intervention affording health care and support to a woman who has recently given birth.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Pregnancy" means the gestational process of growth and development within the woman of a new individual, from conception through the embryonic and fetal periods to birth.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Prenatal care" means the necessary intervention affording health care to both the woman and to the fetus during pregnancy and before birth.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Terminal" means ending in death.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Inmate Pregnancy.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Assessment and Treatment.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The health services provider shall provide a complete history, physical examination, and definitive laboratory test to determine pregnancy when requested by the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Inmate;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Medical staff; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Warden.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All prenatal and postpartum care shall be provided in accordance with acceptable health services standards to include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Regular appointments with an accredited obstetrical clinic;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Medications as necessary; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Patient education.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Director shall ensure that standards are developed to address:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Prenatal care;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Postnatal care;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Postpartum care;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Abortion;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Hospital admission;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Disposition of the child in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|9-601">Correctional Services Article, §9-601, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Executive clemency.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Involuntary Admission of an Inmate to a Psychiatric Hospital.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Warden shall ensure that an admission to a mental hospital is limited to a Maryland Department of Health psychiatric hospital and shall comply with the requirements for an involuntary admission under Health-General Article, §§10-613—10-619, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Institution, when transferring an inmate, shall provide the Maryland Department of Health psychiatric hospital with the following information:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The inmate's current condition;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The inmate's medical and psychiatric history and condition;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Circumstances threatening the life or safety of the inmate or others; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Current medication and other treatment being provided to the inmate.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>When the Institution transfers an inmate to a Maryland Department of Health psychiatric hospital, the Institution shall pick up and return the inmate to the Institution following notification by the Maryland Department of Health psychiatric hospital that the inmate is ready for discharge from the hospital.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Medical Treatment of Inmates while on Prerelease Status or Escape.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Institution is financially responsible for treatment of injury or illness sustained by an inmate while on leave, work release, school release, or in an escape status.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Emergency medical treatment shall be provided to Institution inmates by a community hospital.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>All invoices for services provided shall be submitted to the Institution health services contractor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Nonemergency treatment shall be rendered by the Institution health services provider.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Exposure of Correctional Officer to Contagious Disease or Virus.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If, while treating or transporting an ill or injured inmate to a medical care facility, or while acting in the performance of duty, a correctional officer comes into contact with an inmate who is subsequently diagnosed, as a result of information obtained in conjunction with the services provided during the visit to the facility, as having a contagious disease or virus, the correctional officer and the Institution are entitled to receive the notification specified in Health-General Article, §18-213(d) and (e), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>As part of a correctional officer's training, the education specified in Health-General Article, §18-213(j), Annotated Code of Maryland, concerning the human immunodeficiency virus and the hepatitis B virus, shall be provided by the Institution.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A correctional officer shall receive the equipment specified in Health-General Article, §18-213(k), Annotated Code of Maryland, that is recommended to protect the officer from exposure to the human immunodeficiency virus and the hepatitis B virus while rendering emergency medical care.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>As specified in Health-General Article, §18-213(m), a correctional officer may not refuse to treat or transport an inmate because the inmate is human immunodeficiency virus positive.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Institution shall develop written procedures for the implementation of these regulations and shall make copies of these procedures available, upon request, to the individuals specified in Health-General Article, §18-213(l), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|4-208">Correctional Services Article, §4-208, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-02-03">Effective date: February 3, 1992 (19:2 Md. R. 155)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
