<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>23</num>
  <heading>Public and Media Relations</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following term has the meaning indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Term Defined. "Inmate" means an eligible person, as defined in <cite path="12.12.01.03|B.|(9)">COMAR 12.12.01.03B(9)</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Public Relations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Director shall ensure that the Institution:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Responds to citizens' inquiries and complaints transmitted either in writing, by telephone, or through personal visits;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Designates a person to handle inquiries or complaints; the public relations representative may refer a matter to a more appropriate individual or agency for a response;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Ensures that switchboard operators, receptionists, mail room personnel, and other staff refer citizen telephone calls, mail, and visitors to the Institution's designated public relations representative.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Director shall ensure that a person who answers telephone calls from the public is trained in the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Mechanics of the telephone system;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Proper telephone courtesy;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Prompt attention to calls; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Use of directories to forward a caller to the appropriate person.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Director shall ensure that written communication:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is stamped with the name of the Institution and the date immediately upon receipt;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is responded to within 10 business days of receipt, if a response is required;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Is addressed by an interim response to the citizen when the communication cannot be properly responded to within the 10 business days' requirement; the Director shall ensure that the interim response addresses the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The name of the individual responsible for the reply,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The reason for the delay, if it can be stated,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The telephone number of the individual responsible for reply, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>An estimate as to when a reply will be made.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Personal Visit.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Institution staff shall encourage a citizen to make an appointment when a citizen wishes to speak in person with an Institution staff member about an inmate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Director shall ensure that a clear and current notice is posted within the visitor area to notify a visitor as to where information may be obtained.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Director shall ensure that an employee having contact with a visitor to the Institution is adequately prepared and has available appropriate information which may be of use to the visitor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Director shall designate a person to handle visitors' requests during posted business hours. A citizen may call to confirm the business hours of the Institution.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The process for referring a visitor inquiry is as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each inquiry, complaint, or request shall be accepted;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If an inquiry, complaint, or request is not resolved immediately, it shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Referred to an appropriate person for further handling, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Recorded for future processing;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The inquirer shall be advised of information required to direct the request to a more appropriate agency to obtain the information requested;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Director shall ensure that a citizen making an inquiry is advised when an inquiry is referred to another agency, by sending the citizen a copy of the referral letter which will include the reason for referral to another agency for response.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Director shall ensure that appropriate staff receive a copy of the citizen response plan and receive orientation in those procedures.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="12|12|23|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Media Relations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Cooperation with Media Representatives.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Director shall encourage and develop mutual cooperation with media representatives, and permit the greatest possible access to public information within the limitations of applicable statutes and within operational limitations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An employee of the Institution shall refer all media inquiries to the Director.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Director shall determine whether media inquiries will be forwarded to the Public Information Office of the Office of the Secretary.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Institution employees who provide information to media representatives shall ensure that the information is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The best available;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Truthful, objective, and accurate; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Limited to the information authorized for release under Access to Public Records, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-611">State Government Article, §10-611 </cite>et seq., and <cite path="12|12|23|.03|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Visits by a Media Representative.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A representative of the media may visit the Institution and an inmate confined in the Institution for the purpose of conducting a recorded interview only with prior approval of the Director.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Director shall ensure that the Public Information Office of the Office of the Secretary is notified of a media visit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A media representative shall be required to produce evidence of media employment or authorization which shall be subject to verification before admission to the Institution.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A representative of the media shall conduct an interview with an inmate within a normal visiting area unless otherwise approved by the Director, consistent with security needs and routine activities of the Institution.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>An inmate has the right to refuse to be interviewed and a right to refuse to be photographed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>An inmate may have his or her photograph taken, be filmed, or otherwise be interviewed only if he or she agrees in writing and has the prior approval of the Director.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The Director shall ensure that a signed authorization indicating inmate approval is placed in the inmate's base file.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Release of Information on Inmates.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Information regarding inmates confined in the Institution or subject to its jurisdiction may not be released except pursuant to statutory authorization under either <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|4-209">Correctional Services Article, §4-209, </cite>or State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-611">10-611</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-628">10-628</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland, or other appropriate statutes. Release of information regarding the identity of inmates confined to the Institution is limited to the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Name of the inmate;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Criminal offense for which incarcerated;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Length of sentence;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Jurisdiction where convicted;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Institution status, that is, either confined for evaluation or committed as an eligible person;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Date received, and date of escape if an escapee; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>If the inmate is an active escapee, a physical description may be released as well as a photograph if available.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In any situation when there is a question as to the legality of the release of information, the Director shall consult Department counsel for advice before releasing the information.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Request for Information After Hours.</heading>
    <text>Any request for information received after normal business hours will be referred to the Director.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Emergencies.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>When an emergency or nonroutine incident occurs, the Public Information Office of the Office of the Secretary shall be notified immediately and, in most cases, shall be responsible for the release of information about the event. At the discretion of the Director and in consideration of the public safety, basic information about the event may be released by the Director.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In an unusual or emergency situation such as a riot, fire, job action, strike, escape, or another unusual occurrence as designated by the Director, media representatives are not allowed on the grounds of the Institution without express permission of the Director. The Director may prohibit the use of television or photographic equipment on the grounds of the Institution, if use of the equipment would exacerbate the situation and further jeopardize the safety of the Institution.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Public Information Officer, with the advice and consent of the Director, shall establish media staging and parking areas. A representative of the media will remain within the designated area and will be briefed by the Public Information Officer.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Briefings by Public Information Officer.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The public information officer shall prepare and present a preliminary briefing to the news media within 1 hour after arrival.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>During this briefing, the news media shall be informed of security procedures and safety requirements that will affect them, the nature of the emergency, and background information on the institution.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>At this time, a briefing timetable shall be established which will permit news media representatives to meet their deadlines.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>It shall be clearly explained to the news media that an inmate within the institution can monitor radio and television reports, and this prevents the release of certain information which could jeopardize security or response tactics.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If, during the course of negotiations, an inmate requests that a member of the media be present and if that request is granted by the Director, then the media representative shall be advised that the media representative is expected to brief all other members of the media on site within 1 hour after negotiations have ended.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Representatives of the news media may not be permitted into areas of the institution other than the news media briefing area for any purpose without the approval of the Director. A request for pool photography or news media tours, or both, may be considered by the Director after the emergency is under control. Representatives of the media shall be advised that efforts to enter, or to have another person enter, the prohibited area for the purposes of filming the event or interviewing inmates may not be tolerated. If the Public Information Officer has reason to believe that a restriction of aircraft overflights is necessary, the Public Information Officer shall notify the Federal Aviation Administration to seek a restriction.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Tours by Citizens.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A citizen interested in requesting a tour of the Institution may apply to the Director by letter. The letter requesting the tour shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The requested date and time for the tour;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A telephone number and address of the tour applicant;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The reason or reasons for the tour; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The number of citizens who are requesting to participate in the tour.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The letter requesting the tour shall be mailed a minimum of 4 weeks before the requested tour date, to allow for administrative review of the request and associated planning.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Community Relations Officer.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Director shall appoint a Community Relations Officer to assist the Director in contacts with the community and to respond to citizen inquiries and complaints.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Community Relations Officer shall establish a speakers bureau to address business and community-based organizations on Institution operations.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Application to the Reentry Facility.</heading>
    <text>The provisions of this chapter shall apply to the reentry facility.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|4-208">Correctional Services Article, §4-208, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-02-03">Effective date: February 3, 1992 (19:2 Md. R. 155)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
