<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>28</num>
  <heading>Patuxent Institution Youth Program—Leave, Work Release, and School Release</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Accompanied day leave" means a leave during which the prerelease inmate is accompanied into the community by an Institution staff member, usually a member of the treatment unit to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Become familiar with community resources;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Find employment; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Accomplish a basic task of community reentry.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Compassionate leave" means a leave granted for a prerelease inmate to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Visit a member of the immediate family who is seriously ill; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Attend the funeral of a family member.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Holiday leave" means a special leave which follows a holiday schedule approved by the Board of Review and consists of not more than 5 days and 4 nights at an approved place in the community. The usual holiday periods are Washington's Birthday, Easter, Memorial Day, Independence Day, Labor Day, Thanksgiving, and Christmas.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Inmate" means a Patuxent youth as defined in <cite path="12.12.27.02|B.">COMAR 12.12.27.02B</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Level" means the system of four treatment tiers through which an inmate may progress based upon the inmate's behavior within the Institution and progress in treatment. An inmate is eligible to be considered for the prerelease program if the inmate is on the fourth level.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Monthly leave" means a leave which may be granted to a prerelease inmate for up to 3 days and 2 nights at an approved place in the community.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Parole" means a conditional release from the Institution, after a portion of the sentence has been served in confinement, to serve the balance of the sentence under supervision in the community.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"School release" means conditional leave from the Institution for participation in an education program offered in the community and deemed beneficial to the treatment of the prerelease inmate and not detrimental to the public.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Work release" means a conditional leave from the Institution for participation in an employment program offered in the community and deemed beneficial to the treatment of the prerelease inmate and not detrimental to the public.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Prerelease Status.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board of Review has the power to grant, revoke, or modify an inmate's prerelease status.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Patuxent youth may be granted the privilege of leaving confinement during necessary and reasonable hours for leave, working at gainful private or public employment, or attending school as part of a school release program. These programs may also include, under appropriate conditions, release to seek employment or schooling. Leave, work release, and school release are considered prerelease programs intended to prepare Patuxent youth for parole, mandatory supervision, or expiration of sentence. A Patuxent youth does not have a right to be granted leave, work release, or school release. Leave, work release, and school release are privileges to be granted or revoked at the discretion of the Board of Review.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="12|12|28|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Prerelease Status—Public Safety Criteria.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In considering an inmate for prerelease status, the Board of Review shall consider the following public safety criteria:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The compatibility of the release of the inmate on leave, work release, or school release with the safety and welfare of society;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The length of the inmate's sentence and the amount of time served on the current term of imprisonment to date;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The nature of the crime for which the inmate is currently incarcerated;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The circumstances surrounding the crime for which the inmate is currently incarcerated;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The determination that leave, work release, or school release would not:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Depreciate the seriousness of the inmate's crime,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Promote disrespect for the law, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Have an adverse effect on Institution discipline;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The existence of unresolved out-of-State or federal detainers;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>A report or recommendation made by the inmate's victim or victims, or a representative designated by the victim;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>A report or recommendation made by the sentencing judge, the State's attorney, or a professional medical consultant; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Other factors or information which the Board of Review may find relevant in assessing the risk to public safety which may be posed by placing the inmate on prerelease status.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In making the determination required by <cite path="12|12|28|.03|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite>, the Board of Review shall consider:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The inmate's prior criminal and juvenile record, and prior incarceration, parole, and probation records;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The inmate's past use of narcotics, other controlled dangerous substances, or alcohol;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The inmate's family status and family stability;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A recent assessment conducted by a mental health practitioner of the inmate's propensity toward violence;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A report or recommendation made by the Institution treatment or custody staff concerning the likelihood that the inmate will remain at liberty without violating local, State, or federal laws or the terms and conditions governing the inmate's prerelease status; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The adequacy of the inmate's leave, school, or work release plan, which shall include information concerning employment plans, occupational skills, and job potential.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="12|12|28|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Progress-in-Treatment Criteria.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In considering an inmate for prerelease status, the Board of Review shall consider the following progress-in-treatment criteria:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The inmate's overall progress in treatment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The inmate's overall behavior and adjustment while incarcerated;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Whether prerelease status would assist in the inmate's remediation by enhancing the inmate's ability to lead a law-abiding life;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Whether the inmate has successfully functioned in a previous prerelease status; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Other factors or information which the Board of Review considers relevant in assessing the inmate's progress in treatment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In making the determination required by <cite path="12|12|28|.04|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite>, the Board of Review shall consider:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The reports or recommendations of the Institution treatment and custody staff;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The inmate's adjustment on level four;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Whether the inmate's treatment level history demonstrates progressive responsibility in moving from level one to level four;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The inmate's participation in Institution remediation and self-help programs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Whether the inmate has demonstrated emotional maturity and insight into the inmate's problems, as assessed through the reports or recommendations of the Institution treatment and custody staff;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The inmate's ability and readiness to assume obligations and undertake responsibilities; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The inmate's educational, vocational, and other training.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In making the determination required by <cite path="12|12|28|.04|A.|(2)">§A(2) of this regulation</cite>, the Board of Review shall consider the inmate's:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Institution disciplinary record; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Current attitude towards discipline and other authority, as assessed through the reports or recommendations of Institution treatment and custody staff.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Hearings.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board of Review shall conduct a hearing to determine the appropriateness of granting or revoking leave, work release, or school release. Hearings shall consider the recommendations of the inmate's treatment unit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A record shall be maintained of the hearing that notes the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Date;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Vote of the Board of Review; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Outcome of the proceedings.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Board of Review shall conduct hearings at the Institution according to a preestablished schedule.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Procedure for Hearings.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A leave, work release, or school release hearing is an interview of the inmate by the Board of Review. Attendance is restricted to authorized Institution staff, except that other interested individuals, including victims, may attend with the approval of the Board of Review. The hearing is private and is held in an informal manner, allowing the opportunity to give free expression to an inmate's views and feelings relating to the case. Formal presentations by an attorney, relatives, victims, and other interested individuals are not permitted at the hearing. Attorneys, relatives, victims, and other interested individuals may submit information in writing for the Board of Review's consideration before the hearing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Detailed reports shall be furnished by the inmate's treatment unit to assist the Board of Review in its deliberations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The treatment unit assigned to the inmate shall attend all hearings concerning that inmate. The inmate's treatment unit shall be available to provide new information which may have developed since the date of the reports furnished to the Board of Review and to assist in answering questions concerning the inmate or Institution policy.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Granting Leave, Work Release, and School Release.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Leave, work release, or school release may not be granted unless approved by the affirmative vote of a quorum of the Board of Review, as defined in <cite path="12.12.08.05|A.">COMAR 12.12.08.05A</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Victim Comment, Victim Notification, and Police Notification.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board of Review shall give the inmate's victim a reasonable opportunity to comment in writing before the Board of Review decides whether to grant leave, work release, or school release to the inmate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The victim may designate in writing to the Board of Review the name and address of a representative, who is a resident of the State, to receive notice for the victim that the inmate will be considered for leave, work release, or school release.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Board of Review shall delete the victim's address and telephone number before examination of a document by the inmate or the inmate's representative.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the victim cannot be located, the judge holding jurisdiction over the inmate's sentence may be contacted for comment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Board of Review shall notify the victim of its decision regarding leave, work release, or school release.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The Board of Review shall notify the police department possessing jurisdiction over the locality in which an inmate's crime was originally committed when an inmate has been approved for leave, work release, or school release status.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Board of Review shall notify the inmate of its decision regarding placement on leave, work release, or school release.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Director shall ensure that a waiver of extradition form is completed by an inmate before authorizing an inmate for leave, work release, or school release.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A member of the inmate's treatment unit shall ensure that the waiver of extradition form is filed in the inmate's base file.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Leave and Release Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Before starting a leave, work release, or school release program, the inmate shall sign an agreement that affirms the inmate's understanding of the regulations governing it.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The inmate on leave, work release, or school release:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>May not go outside the limits of the State without the written permission of the Board of Review;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>May not commit an act which would be a violation of a federal law, State law, or municipal ordinance, and shall conform to all rules of conduct imposed by the Institution or an authorized representative of the Institution;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Shall report back to the Institution at the time specified on the pass, or wherever and whenever an authorized representative of the Institution directs;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>May not own, possess, use, buy, sell, or have under the inmate's control a firearm or weapon of any description;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>May not enter into a contract to engage in business, borrow money, enter into an installment contract, incur debt, or acquire ownership of a motor vehicle without first having obtained written permission from the Board of Review;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>May not unlawfully possess, use, buy, sell, or have under the inmate's control a narcotic drug, controlled dangerous substance, or related paraphernalia;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Shall submit to any test or search that is prescribed by the Institution or its authorized representative to detect the usage of alcohol or controlled dangerous substances, or the possession of contraband;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>May not engage in conduct that would pose a threat to public safety;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>May not drink an intoxicating beverage;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Shall have a pass in the inmate's possession at all times while outside the confines of the Institution and notify the Institution in case of an emergency or to resolve questions of identity;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Shall request approval from the Board of Review to withdraw additional funds from the inmate's financial accounts for personal needs and to defray the cost of transportation to and from the Institution;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>Shall deposit all wages in the Institution's business office on a weekly basis, unless otherwise specified, together with an attached voucher indicating the number of hours worked, hourly wages, deductions, and number of days worked; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>Shall strictly adhere to the times and geographical locations specified on the inmate's leave itinerary.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Work release or school release inmates shall use their time outside the Institution to work or attend school, both of which are regularly supervised by the Institution. An employer or school supervisor is requested to call the Institution if the inmate does not report as scheduled. In appropriate cases, inmates on work release or school release may be granted leave for other than work or school attendance.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>An inmate on leave status may not use leave to engage in employment. This restriction does not prohibit the authorized search for employment in preparation for work release.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Unless otherwise indicated, a work release or school release inmate shall report to the community supervision clinic for supervision as scheduled.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Housing of Inmates Granted Work Release or School Release Privileges.</heading>
    <text>The Institution shall designate facilities for the housing of inmates granted work release or school release privileges.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="12|12|28|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Monitoring and Supervision of Leave, Work Release, and School Release Participants.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A participant in the prerelease program shall be monitored and supervised in the community to assure the continued safety of the public.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Associate Director responsible for treatment services and the administrator of the reentry facility shall develop and implement a plan for community supervision of participants in the work release and school release programs. The plan shall be approved by the Director and include procedures for work or school site visits, home visits, and documentation and reporting of prerelease violations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The following are responsible for managing the community monitoring program and ensuring that the personnel performing the monitoring tasks meet the requirements of the plan developed in <cite path="12|12|28|.07|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For the leave program, the treatment unit chairman is the responsible manager; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For the work release and school release programs, the administrator of the reentry facility is the responsible party.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An inmate may appeal to the Board of Review a treatment unit's decision to deny a leave.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An inmate who is successfully participating in the work release or school release program may be eligible for a leave of 1 day if the following conditions are met:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The inmate has the recommendation of the inmate's direct supervisor in the work release or school release program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Leave regulations are met; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The leave is approved by the Board of Review.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>An inmate released from confinement on leave, or for a work release or school release program, who commits a major violation under orrectional Services Article, §4-306(c), Annotated Code of Maryland, and <cite path="12.12.11.03">COMAR 12.12.11.03</cite> is subject to the penalties provided.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Disposition of Earnings.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An inmate employed in the community under a work release or school release program shall surrender to the Institution the inmate's total earnings less payroll deductions required by law.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Institution shall deduct from the inmate's earnings, in the following order of priority, an amount determined to be the cost to the State of providing the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Food, lodging, and clothing for the inmate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The actual and necessary cost of food, travel, and other expenses of the inmate when released from actual confinement under the program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The amount which the inmate may be legally obligated to pay for the support of the inmate's dependents; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The amount ordered to be paid by the court as restitution.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A school release inmate receiving a stipend or other monies not subject to payroll deductions is not subject to room, board, clothing, and travel fees.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Any balance remaining of an inmate's earnings after the deductions and payments set forth in this regulation shall be credited to the inmate's account and paid to the inmate when paroled.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An inmate shall use, on a weekly basis, adequate funds from a work release or school release account to defray the cost of transportation, meals, and sundries according to a schedule approved by the Board of Review.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Request for Additional Funds.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An inmate may request approval from the Board of Review to withdraw additional funds for personal needs from the inmate's work release or school release account.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An inmate shall be provided adequate funds from the inmate's work release or school release account to meet the inmate's needs, and to ensure that the inmate will have the financial means to return to the Institution. The Board of Review shall indicate the specific amount to be provided.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Correctional Services Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|4-208">4-208</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|4-401">4-401</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1996-12-02">Effective date: December 2, 1996 (23:24 Md. R. 1683)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
