<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>29</num>
  <heading>Patuxent Institution Youth Program—Parole</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Adjudicated Federal Detainer.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Adjudicated federal detainer" means a detainer based on an offense for which the inmate has been tried, convicted, sentenced, and committed to the custody of the United States Attorney General.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Adjudicated federal detainer" does not mean a detainer based on an untried indictment, information, or complaint, or a detainer of federal parole or federal probation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Director" means the Director of Patuxent Institution or a designee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Inmate" means a Patuxent youth defined in <cite path="12.12.27.02|B.">COMAR 12.12.27.02B</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Medical parole" means a parole granted to an inmate because of a diagnosed, serious medical condition.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Parole" has the meaning stated in <cite path="12.12.27.02|B.">COMAR 12.12.27.02B</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Secretary" means the Secretary of Public Safety and Correctional Services.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>General.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Parole, as defined in <cite path="12.12.08.05|A.">COMAR 12.12.08.05A</cite>, may not be recommended unless approved by the affirmative vote of a quorum of the Board of Review.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board of Review has the exclusive power to recommend an inmate for parole to the Secretary or to the Governor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Date Crime was Committed.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The required approval for parole status depends on:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The date that the crime for which an inmate is incarcerated was committed; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Whether an inmate is serving a life or nonlife sentence.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Inmates Serving Life Sentences. An inmate serving a life sentence may be paroled by the recommendation of the Board of Review and the approval of the Governor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Inmates Serving Nonlife Sentences. An inmate serving a nonlife sentence may be paroled by the recommendation of the Board of Review and the approval of the Secretary.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Victim Comment, Victim Notification, and Police Notification.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board of Review:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Shall give the inmate's victim a reasonable opportunity to comment in writing before the Board of Review decides whether to grant parole to the inmate;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Shall delete the victim's address and telephone number before examination of a document by the inmate or the inmate's representative;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Shall notify the victim of its decision regarding parole;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Shall notify the police department possessing jurisdiction over the locality in which an inmate's crime was originally committed when an inmate is released on parole;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Shall notify the inmate of its decision regarding placement on parole;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Has the power to revoke, extend, or otherwise modify an inmate's parole;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Has the authority to return the paroled inmate to the Institution if the paroled inmate's progress in the community is considered to pose a risk to public safety or pose a risk to the paroled inmate; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>May impose special conditions on paroled inmates.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The victim may designate, in writing to the Board of Review, the name and address of a representative, who is a resident of the State, to receive notice for the victim that the inmate will be considered for parole.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the victim cannot be located, the judge holding jurisdiction over the inmate's sentence may be contacted for comment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Length of Sentence and Time Served Criteria.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An inmate sentenced to life imprisonment is ineligible for parole consideration until the inmate has served 15 years or the equal of 15 years after considering allowances for diminution of the period of confinement provided by law when diminution of sentence credits are otherwise applicable to establish a mandatory supervision release date.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An inmate sentenced to life imprisonment as a result of a proceeding under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcr|2-303">Criminal Law Article, §2-303, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, is not eligible for parole consideration until the inmate has served 25 years or the equal of 25 years after considering the allowances for diminution of the period of confinement provided by law when diminution of sentence credits are otherwise applicable to establish a mandatory supervision release date.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Progress on Work Release or School Release.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>When considering an inmate for parole, the Board of Review shall determine whether the inmate has performed successfully on work release or school release. Letters from employers, friends, family members, and others which describe the inmate's adjustment on work release or school release are forwarded to the Board of Review for parole consideration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In determining successful performance on work release or school release, the Board of Review shall consider an inmate's progress based upon the public safety criteria and progress-in-treatment criteria specified in <cite path="12.12.10.04">COMAR 12.12.10.04</cite> and .05.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>When making a determination concerning parole, the Board of Review shall also consider:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Whether the inmate has successfully participated in a substance abuse program while on work release or school release, if appropriate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Whether the inmate has continued to demonstrate emotional maturity and insight as assessed through the reports and recommendations of Institution treatment and custody staff;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The inmate's ability and readiness to assume obligations and to undertake responsibilities to live in the community;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The inmate's community resources and the stability of the family that will assist the inmate to return to the community;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The inmate's physical health; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Other factors or information which the Board of Review may find relevant to parole consideration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Medical Parole.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The following criteria are used when considering an inmate for medical parole:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The inmate is imminently terminal or has a condition which indicates that continued imprisonment would serve no useful purpose, for example, an irreversible coma; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The inmate's release would not unduly jeopardize public safety.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Contents of Medical Parole Request.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Director shall ensure that all documents forming the basis for a medical parole request are submitted to the Board of Review.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When a quorum of the Board of Review recommends the inmate for a medical parole, the recommendation is submitted to the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Secretary for consideration, if the inmate is serving a nonlife sentence; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Secretary and the Governor, if the inmate is serving a life sentence.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>To initiate consideration for a medical parole, the inmate's treatment unit shall send to the Director a summary of the inmate's incarceration record since admission that includes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A history of program participation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Special housing requirements;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The reasons for the recommendation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>An aftercare treatment plan for the inmate; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>A statement by the attending physician which includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Diagnosis,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Prognosis,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Inpatient or outpatient status, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Criteria justification.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Board of Review may reject a recommendation for medical parole that has been submitted by the Director.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Board of Review's decision to deny a medical parole is final.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Parole to Adjudicated Federal Detainer.</heading>
    <text>An inmate with an adjudicated federal detainer is subject to the same procedures and criteria to meet the detainer when being considered for parole as an inmate who does not have an adjudicated federal detainer.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Granting of Parole.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Agreement.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Before starting a parole program, the inmate shall sign an agreement that affirms the inmate's understanding of the regulations governing parole set forth in this regulation. This agreement includes the conditions in §A(2) and (3) of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>General Conditions.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The parolee may not go outside the limits of the State without the written permission of the Board of Review.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The parolee shall promptly report to the Patuxent Institution, or wherever and whenever an authorized representative may direct.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The parolee may not commit an act which would be a violation of federal or State law, or local ordinance, and shall conform to rules of conduct imposed by the Patuxent Institution or an authorized representative.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The parolee shall make reasonable effort to be gainfully employed or otherwise occupied as directed by the Board of Review.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The parolee may not change place of residence or employment without first obtaining the permission of the Patuxent Institution or an authorized representative.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The parolee may not own, possess, use, sell, or have under control a firearm or weapon of any description, including a device which resembles and is used as a weapon.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>The parolee may not enter into a contract to engage in business, borrow money, enter into an installment contract, incur a debt, or acquire ownership of a motor vehicle without first obtaining permission from the Board of Review.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>The parolee may not unlawfully possess, use, buy, sell, or have under control a narcotic drug, controlled dangerous substance, or related paraphernalia.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>A parolee, when seen, shall present proof, which shall be verified and documented, that the parolee is maintaining steady employment, attending substance abuse group meetings if appropriate, and living at a specified address.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>A parolee shall give a random urine specimen as required by the parolee's supervisor.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>A parolee shall discuss the problems or the progress that the parolee is having in the community and the types of relationships that the parolee may be establishing.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>A parolee may be subject to a search for contraband by the parole supervisor during the parolee's visit.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>A parolee shall cooperate with job checks and home visits conducted by the parole supervisor.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(n)</num>
          <text>A parolee on an Interstate Corrections Compact Agreement or paroled to meet a detainer shall be monitored at least yearly by a designated employee of the Institution.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(o)</num>
          <text>A parolee shall be employed or enrolled in school and have a legitimate means of financial support.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(p)</num>
          <text>If unemployed or unemployable, the parolee shall have a legitimate means of financial support while on parole.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(q)</num>
          <text>When paroled, an inmate shall receive all current funds in the inmate's active and reserve accounts which have been maintained at Patuxent Institution.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(r)</num>
          <text>If paroled from work release, an inmate shall receive 100 percent of the inmate's work release account upon being paroled, less the deductions specified in <cite path="12.12.10.09|B.">COMAR 12.12.10.09B</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(s)</num>
          <text>A parolee shall be counseled concerning the benefits of establishing savings accounts at financial institutions in the community.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(t)</num>
          <text>A parolee who needs financial assistance shall be referred to appropriate community agencies and assisted in the application processes of the community agencies by a parole supervisor.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Special Conditions. Special conditions may be imposed by the Institutional Board of Review as appropriate.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text><cite path="12.12.10.06|F.|(1)">COMAR 12.12.10.06F(1)</cite>—(11) also applies to parolees.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An inmate may not be released on parole until the order of parole is presented and acknowledged by the inmate's signature. An inmate shall be released on parole as soon as practical after a favorable decision, unless:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board of Review has specified a deferred release date;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The investigation of the community resources of the inmate to be paroled indicates that the parolee is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Likely to be unemployed upon release, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Without a satisfactory home plan; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The parole plan has not been approved by the Board of Review as specified in <cite path="|12|12|29|.08">Regulation .08 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An inmate may not be released under the order for parole when the Director is made aware of a fact or circumstance after Board consideration of which the Board was unaware. Under this circumstance, the Board shall reconsider the decision to parole as soon as possible.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The order of parole shall bear the signature of a member of the Board of Review, attested to by another Board member, and the official seal of the Board of Review.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Board of Review may, for the safety and welfare of the inmate on parole and for the safety of the public, impose reasonable special conditions to be complied with before release on parole.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Parole is a privilege and not a right, and may be revoked under <cite path="12.12.08.05|A.">COMAR 12.12.08.05A</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Parole Release Plan.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A parole release plan shall be completed and submitted before the parole hearing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Elements in a parole release plan include, but are not limited to, the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The name of the parolee's employer or evidence of other legitimate means of financial support;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The location at which the parolee will reside; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The nature of community services necessary to meet the special needs of the parolee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Modification of Parole Release Plan.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An inmate's parole release plan previously approved by the Board of Review may only be changed by the Board of Review.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Board of Review may, with good cause, modify the conditions of an inmate's parole.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>In case of modification, the parolee shall be given the opportunity to show cause why a condition should not be modified.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The parolee may request a hearing before the Board of Review to discuss the modification.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Monitoring and Supervision of Parolees.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A parolee shall be seen by an assigned parole supervisor or designee for parole supervision in accordance with the terms of parole established by the Board of Review. Each contact with a parolee shall be documented by the supervisor or the designee. Contact includes both scheduled and unscheduled meetings and may take place in the field, home, place of employment, or other location.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Schedule of Meetings.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board of Review shall establish a schedule of required supervisory meetings between a parolee and the parolee's supervisor and make adherence to that schedule a written condition of parole.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A first-year parolee shall meet with the parole supervisor a minimum of once a week.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A second-year parolee shall meet with the parole supervisor a minimum of once every 2 weeks.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A third-year parolee shall meet with the parole supervisor a minimum of once a month.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A recommendation by a treatment unit for a change in a parolee's supervision shall be presented to the Board of Review for final approval.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The parolee shall be seen at a Board-approved designated location in the State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The supervisor or designee shall prepare a written report of each scheduled or unscheduled contact with a parolee, including unkept appointments, and make that report a part of the parolee's official record.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Correctional Services Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|4-208">4-208</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcs|4-401">4-401</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1996-12-02">Effective date: December 2, 1996 (23:24 Md. R. 1683)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
