<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>12</num>
  <heading>Exemption for Coal Extraction Incidental to Government-Financed Highway or Other Construction</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>General.</heading>
    <text>Coal extraction which is an incidental part of government-financed construction is exempt from all requirements of the Regulatory Program except the requirements of this chapter.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Government-Financed Construction.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Government-financed construction" means construction funded 50 percent or more by funds appropriated from a government financing agency's budget or obtained from general revenue bonds. Funding at less than 50 percent may qualify if the construction is undertaken as an approved reclamation project under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen">Environment Article, Title 15, Subtitle 11, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and 30 CFR Subchapter R.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Government-financed construction" does not mean government financing agency guarantees, insurance, loans, funds obtained through industrial revenue bonds or their equivalent, or in-kind payments.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Extraction of coal incidental to government-financed construction" means the extraction of coal which is necessary to enable the construction to be accomplished. Only that coal extracted from within the right-of-way, in the case of a road, railroad, utility line, or other similar constructions, or within the boundaries of the area directly affected by other types of government-financed construction, may be considered incidental to that construction. Extraction of coal outside the right-of-way or boundary of the area directly affected by the construction is subject to the requirements of the Regulatory Program.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Documentation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Any person extracting coal incidental to government-financed highway or other construction shall maintain, on the site of the extraction operation and available for inspection, documents which show:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A description of the construction project;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The exact location of the construction, right-of-way, or the boundaries of the area which will be directly affected by the construction; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The government agency which is providing the financing and the kind and amount of public financing, including the percentage of the entire construction costs represented by the government financing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The government financing agency may be a federal, State, county, municipal, or local unit of government, or a department, bureau, agency, or office of the unit which, directly or through another unit of government, finances construction.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="26|20|12|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Government-Funded Reclamation Projects.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>When the Bureau is considering an abandoned mine land reclamation project as government-financed construction and the level of funding will be less than 50 percent of the total cost because of planned coal extraction, the Bureau shall determine the likelihood:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>That nearby or adjacent mining activities may create new environmental problems or adversely affect existing environmental problems at the site;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>That reclamation activities at the site may adversely affect nearby or adjacent mining activities; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Of the coal being mined under a permit issued in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen">Environment Article, Title 15, Subtitle 5, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The determination under <cite path="26|20|12|.04|A.|(3)">§A(3) of this regulation</cite> shall take into account available information, such as:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Coal reserves from existing mine maps or other sources;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Existing environmental conditions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All prior mining activity on or adjacent to the site;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Current and historic coal production in the area; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Any known or anticipated interest in the mining site.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the Bureau decides to proceed with the reclamation project after making the determinations under <cite path="26|20|12|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, the Bureau shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Determine the limits on any coal refuse, coal waste, or other coal products which may be extracted under this regulation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Delineate the boundaries of the abandoned mine land reclamation project.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Bureau shall include documentation in the abandoned mine land project file for the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Determinations made under §§A and C of this regulation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Information taken into account in making the determinations; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Names of the persons making the determinations.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>For each abandoned mine land reclamation project to be approved under this regulation, the Bureau shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Characterize the site in terms of mine drainage, active slides and slide prone areas, erosion and sedimentation, vegetation, toxic materials, and hydrologic balance;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Ensure that the reclamation project is conducted in accordance with the provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen">Environment Article, Title 15, Subtitle 11, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and 30 CFR Subchapter R;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Develop specific-site reclamation requirements, including performance bonds, when appropriate, in accordance with State procedures; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Require the contractor conducting the reclamation to provide, before the time the reclamation project begins, documents that clearly authorize the extraction of coal and payment of royalties.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Bureau shall require a reclamation contractor who extracts coal beyond the limits of the incidental coal specified in <cite path="26|20|12|.04|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> to obtain a permit for the coal in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen">Environment Article, Title 15, Subtitle 5, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|15-503">Environment Article, §15-503, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Regulations .01, .02, and .03 were previously codified as <cite path="08.13.09.12|A.">COMAR 08.13.09.12A</cite>, A(1) and (2), and B, respectively. Recodification occurred in April, 1993. For a history of these regulations before April, 1993, see "Administrative History of <cite path="|08.13.09">COMAR 08.13.09</cite> before April, 1993" which follows <cite path="|26.20.01">COMAR 26.20.01</cite>.</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" discontinuity="true">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|08.20.12">COMAR 08.20.12</cite> to <cite path="|26.20.12">COMAR 26.20.12</cite>, June 1996</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-05-14"><cite path="|26|20|12|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective May 14, 2001 (28:9 Md. R. 890)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-05-14"><cite path="|26|20|12|.04">Regulation .04</cite> adopted effective May 14, 2001 (28:9 Md. R. 890)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
