<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>18</num>
  <heading>Signs and Markers</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Specifications.</heading>
    <text>All signs and markers shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Be posted and maintained by the permittee;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Be easily seen and read, and of a uniform design throughout the operation;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Be made of durable material;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Conform to local ordinances and codes; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Be maintained during the conduct of all activities to which they pertain.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Permit Identification.</heading>
    <text>Permit identification signs shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Be displayed at each point of access to the permit area from public roads;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Contain information identifying the name, business address, and telephone number of the operator, the Bureau of Mines permit number, the Water Resources Administration discharge permit number, and NPDES discharge permit number;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Be constructed of metal or wood and be a minimum of 2 feet by 2 feet, affixed to a suitably located tree, or a 2 inch diameter metal or wood post driven into the earth at least 3 feet with a minimum of 4 feet exposed;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Be retained and maintained until after the release of all bonds for the permit area.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Perimeter Markers.</heading>
    <text>All perimeter markers shall clearly mark the perimeter of the permit area before and during surface mining activities. The markers shall be, at a minimum, 2 inch diameter pipes or wood posts or metal posts driven into the earth with a minimum of 3 feet exposed to mark the beginning and ending points of the permit area and any other point necessary to clearly identify the permit area. They shall be identified by painting the exposed portion red or other color as indicated in the permit application. Other marker specifications may be used if approved by the Bureau.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Blasting Signs.</heading>
    <text>If blasting is conducted incident to surface mining activities, the permittee shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Conspicuously display signs reading "Blasting Area" along the edge of any blasting area that comes within 50 feet of any road within the permit area, and within 100 feet of any public road right of way.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Conspicuously flag or post within the blasting area, the immediate vicinity of charged holes.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Place at all entrances to the permit area from public roads or highways conspicuous signs which state: "Blasting Area", and which clearly explain the blast warning and all-clear signals that are in use, and the marking of blast areas and charged holes within the permit area. These signs shall be a minimum size of 2 feet by 4 feet.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Topsoil Markers.</heading>
    <text>If topsoil or other vegetation-supporting material is segregated and stockpiled, the stockpiled material shall be clearly marked by a method described in the permit application.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|15-503">Environment Article, §15-503, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-10-20">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Regulations <cite path="|26|20|18|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|26|20|18|.05">.05</cite> were previously codified as <cite path="08.13.09.21|A.">COMAR 08.13.09.21A</cite>—E, respectively. Recodification occurred in April, 1993. For a history of these regulations before April, 1993, see "Administrative History of <cite path="|08.13.09">COMAR 08.13.09</cite> before April, 1993" which follows <cite path="|26.20.01">COMAR 26.20.01</cite>.</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" discontinuity="true">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|08.20.18">COMAR 08.20.18</cite> to <cite path="|26.20.18">COMAR 26.20.18</cite>, June 1996</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
