<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>26</num>
  <heading>Excess Spoil Disposal</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>General Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="|26|20|26|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>, excess spoil shall be placed in designated disposal areas within the permit area in a controlled manner to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Minimize the adverse effects of leachate and surface water runoff from the fill on surface and ground waters;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Ensure mass stability and prevent mass movement during and after construction; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Ensure that the final fill is suitable for reclamation and revegetation compatible with the natural surroundings and the approved postmining land use.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The fill and appurtenant structures shall be designed using current, prudent engineering practices and shall meet any design criteria established by the Bureau. A qualified registered professional engineer experienced in the design of earth and rock fills shall certify the design of the fill and appurtenant structures.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>All vegetative and organic materials shall be removed from the disposal area and disposed of in an approved manner and location. All topsoil shall be removed and handled in accordance with <cite path="26.20.25.02">COMAR 26.20.25.02</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Slope protection shall be provided to minimize surface erosion at the site. All disturbed areas, including diversion ditches that are not riprapped, shall be vegetated upon completion of construction.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The disposal areas shall be located on the most moderately sloping and naturally stable areas available as approved by the Bureau. If the placement provides additional stability and prevents mass movement, fill materials suitable for disposal shall be placed upon or above a natural terrace, bench, or berm.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The spoil shall be hauled or conveyed and placed in horizontal lifts not exceeding 4 feet in thickness in a controlled manner, concurrently compacted as necessary to ensure mass stability and prevent mass movement during and after construction, covered with topsoil or substitute material, and graded to allow surface and subsurface drainage to be compatible with the natural surroundings and ensure a long-term static safety factor of 1.5. The Bureau may approve a design which incorporates placement of excess spoil in horizontal lifts other than 4 feet in thickness when it is demonstrated by the operator and certified by a qualified registered professional engineer that the design will ensure the stability of the fill and will meet all other applicable requirements.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The final configuration of the fill shall be suitable for postmining land uses approved in accordance with the permit, except that no depressions or impoundments shall be allowed on the completed fill.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Terraces may be constructed on the outslope of the fill if required for stability, control of erosion, to conserve soil moisture, or to facilitate the approved postmining land use. The grade of the outslope between terrace benches may not be steeper than 2:1 (50 percent).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>If the slope in the disposal area exceeds 2.8:1 keyway cuts (excavations to stable bedrock) or rock toe buttress shall be constructed to stabilize the fill. If the toe of the spoil rests on a downslope, stability analyses shall be performed to determine the size of rock toe buttresses and keyway cuts.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Excess spoil that is acid-forming or toxic-forming or combustible shall be adequately covered with nonacid, nontoxic and noncombustible material, or treated to control the impact on surface and ground water in accordance with <cite path="|26.20.20">COMAR 26.20.20</cite>, to prevent sustained combustion, and to minimize adverse effects on plant growth and the approved postmining land use.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>A qualified registered professional engineer, or other qualified professional specialist under the direction of the professional engineer, shall periodically inspect the fill during construction. The professional engineer or specialist shall be experienced in the construction of earth and rock fills.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>The inspections shall be made at least quarterly throughout construction and during critical construction periods. Critical construction periods shall include at a minimum:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Foundation preparation, including the removal of all organic material and topsoil;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Placement of underdrains and protective filter systems;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Installation of final surface drainage systems; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The final graded and revegetated fill.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>Regular inspections by the engineer or specialist shall also be conducted during placement and compaction of fill materials.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>The qualified registered professional engineer shall provide a certified report to the Bureau promptly after each inspection stating that the fill has been constructed and maintained as designed and in accordance with the approved plan and this chapter. The report shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Appearances of instability;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Structural weakness; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Other hazardous conditions.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>The certified report on the drainage system and protective filters shall include color photographs taken during and after construction, but before underdrains are covered with excess spoil. If the underdrain system is constructed in phases, each phase shall be certified separately.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>P.</num>
      <text>The photographs accompanying each certified report shall be taken in adequate size and number with enough terrain or other physical features of the site shown to provide a relative scale to the photographs and to specifically and clearly identify the site.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>Q.</num>
      <text>A copy of each inspection report shall be retained at or near the mine site.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>R.</num>
      <text>Coal processing wastes may not be disposed of in head-of-hollow or valley fills, and may only be disposed of in other excess spoil fills if the waste is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Placed in accordance with the construction specifications;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Demonstrated to be nontoxic and non-acid-forming; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Demonstrated to be consistent with the design stability of the fill.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>S.</num>
      <text>If the disposal area contains springs, natural or man-made water courses, or wet weather seeps, an underdrain system consisting of durable rock shall be constructed from the wet areas in a manner that prevents infiltration of the water into the spoil material. The underdrain system shall be protected by an adequate filter and shall be designed and constructed using standard geotechnical engineering methods.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>T.</num>
      <text>The foundation and abutments of the fill shall be stable under all conditions of construction and operation. Sufficient foundation investigation and laboratory testing of foundation materials shall be performed in order to determine the design requirements for stability of the foundation. Analyses of foundation conditions shall include the effect of underground mine workings, if any, upon the stability of the structure.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>U.</num>
      <text>Excess spoil may be returned to underground mine workings, but only in accordance with a disposal program approved by the Bureau and MSHA.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Valley Fills.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Valley fills shall meet all of the general requirements for disposal of excess spoil and the additional requirements of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The fill shall be designed to attain a long-term static safety factor of 1.5 based upon data obtained from subsurface exploration, geotechnical testing, foundation design, and accepted engineering analyses.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A subdrainage system for the fill shall be constructed in accordance with the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A system of underdrains constructed of durable rock shall meet the following requirements:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be installed along the natural drainage system;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Extend from the toe to the head of the fill; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Contain lateral drains to each area of potential drainage or seepage.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A filter system to insure the proper functioning of the rock underdrain system shall be designed and constructed using standard geotechnical engineering methods.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>In constructing the underdrains, not more than 10 percent of the rock may be less than 12 inches in size and no single rock may be larger than 25 percent of the width of the drain. The minimum size of the main underdrain shall be:</text>
        <text>
          <table class="layout-table">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th>Total amount of fill material</th>
                <th>Predominant<br/>type of fill material</th>
                <th colspan="2">Minimum size<br/>of drain, in feet</th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <th/>
                <th/>
                <th>Width</th>
                <th>Height</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Less than 1,000,000 yards</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Sandstone</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">10</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Shale</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">16</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">More than 1,000,000 yards</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Sandstone</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">16</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Shale</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">16</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">16</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Underdrains shall consist of nondegradable, non-acid-forming or non-toxic-forming rock such as natural sand and gravel, sandstone, limestone, or other durable rock that will not slake in water and will be free of coal, clay, or shale.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Spoil shall be hauled or conveyed and placed in a controlled manner and concurrently compacted as specified by the Bureau, in lifts not greater than 4 feet or less if required by the Bureau to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Achieve the densities designed to ensure mass stability;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Prevent mass movement;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Avoid contamination of the rock underdrain or rock core; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Prevent formation of voids.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Surface water runoff from the area above the fill shall be diverted away from the fill and into stabilized diversion channels designed to pass safely the runoff from a 100-year, 24-hour precipitation event. Surface runoff from the fill surface shall be diverted to stabilized channels off the fill which will safely pass the runoff from a 100-year, 24-hour precipitation event.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The tops of the fill and any terrace constructed to stabilize the face shall be graded no steeper than 20:1. The vertical distance between terraces may not exceed 50 feet.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Drainage may not be directed over the outslope of the fill.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The outslope of the fill may not exceed 2:1.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Head-of-Hollow Fills.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Disposal of spoil in a head-of-hollow fill shall meet all standards set forth in Regulations .01 and .02 of this chapter, and the additional requirements of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The fill shall be designed to completely fill the disposal site to the approximate elevation of the ridgeline. A rock-core chimney drain may be used instead of the subdrain and surface diversion system required for valley fills. If the crest of the fill is not approximately at the same elevation as the low point of the adjacent ridgeline, the fill shall be designed as specified in valley fills, with diversion of runoff around the fill. A fill associated with contour mining and placed at or near the coal seam, and which does not exceed 250,000 cubic yards may use the rock-core chimney drain.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The alternative rock-core chimney drain system shall be designed and incorporated into the construction of head-of-hollow fills as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The fill shall have, along the vertical projection of the main stream channel or rill, a vertical core of durable rock at least 16 feet thick which shall extend from the toe of the fill to the head of the fill, and from the base of the fill to the surface of the fill. A system of lateral rock underdrains shall connect this rock core to each area of potential drainage or seepage in the disposal area. Rocks used in the rock core and underdrains shall meet the requirements of valley fills.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A filter system to ensure the proper functioning of the rock core shall be designed and constructed using standard geotechnical engineering methods.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The grading may drain surface water away from the outslope of the fill and toward the rock core. The maximum slope of the top of the fill shall be 33:1. A drainage pocket may be obtained at the head of the fill during and after construction, to intercept surface runoff and discharge the runoff through or over the rock drain, if stability of the fill is not impaired. This pocket or sump may not have a potential for impounding more than 10,000 cubic feet of water. Terraces on the fill shall be graded with a 3 to 5 percent grade toward the fill and 1 percent slope toward the rock core.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The drainage control system shall be capable of passing safely the runoff from a 100-year, 24-hour precipitation event.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Durable Rock Fills.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Bureau may approve alternative methods of disposal of hard rock spoil, including fill placement by dumping in a single lift, on a site specific basis, provided the services of a registered professional engineer experienced in the design and construction of earth and rockfill embankments are used and provided the requirements of this regulation and the general requirements for disposal of excess spoil are met.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>"Hard rock spoil" means rock fill consisting of at least 80 percent by volume of sandstone, limestone, or other rocks that do not slake in water. Resistance of the hard rock spoil to slaking shall be determined by using the slake index and slake durability tests in accordance with guidelines and criteria established by the Bureau.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Special Placement.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Spoil is to be transported and placed in a specified and controlled manner which will ensure stability of the fill.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The method of spoil placement shall be designed to ensure mass stability and prevent mass movement.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Loads of noncemented clay shale, clay spoil, or both, in the fill shall be mixed with hard rock spoil in a controlled manner to limit on a unit basis concentrations of noncemented clay shale and clay in the fill. These materials shall comprise not more than 20 percent of the fill volume as determined by tests performed by a registered professional engineer and approved by the Bureau.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Stability Analyses.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Stability analyses shall be made by a registered professional engineer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Parameters used in the stability analyses shall be based on adequate field reconnaissance, subsurface investigations, including borings, and laboratory tests.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The embankment which constitutes the valley fill or head-of-hollow fill shall be designed with the following factors of safety:</text>
        <text>
          <table class="layout-table">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th>Case</th>
                <th>Design Condition</th>
                <th>Minimum factor of safety</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">I</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">End of construction</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">1.5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">II</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Earthquake</td>
                <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">1.3</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Internal Drainage System.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The design of a head-of-hollow fill shall include an internal drainage system which will ensure continued free drainage of anticipated seepage from precipitation and from springs or wet weather seeps.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Anticipated discharge from springs and seeps and due to precipitation shall be based on records, field investigations, or both, to determine seasonal variation. The design of the internal drainage system shall be based on the maximum anticipated discharge.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All granular material used for the drainage system shall be free of clay and consist of durable particles such as natural sands and gravels, sandstone, limestone, or other durable rock which will not slake in water.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The internal drain shall be protected by a properly designed filter system.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Surface water runoff from the areas adjacent to and above the fill may not be allowed to flow onto the fill and shall be diverted into stabilized channels which are designed to pass safely the runoff from a 100-year, 24-hour precipitation event.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The top surface of the completed fill shall be graded so that the final slope after settlement will be no steeper than 20:1 toward properly designed drainage channels in natural ground and the periphery of the fill. Surface runoff from the top surface of fill may not be allowed to flow over the outslope of the fill.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Surface runoff from the outslope of the fill shall be diverted off the fill to properly designed channels which will pass safely a 100-year, 24-hour precipitation event.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Terraces shall be constructed on the outslope if required for control of erosion or for roads included in the approved postmining land use plan. Terraces shall meet the following requirements:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The slope of the outslope between terrace benches may not exceed 2:1.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>To control surface runoff, each terrace bench shall be graded to a slope of 20:1 toward the embankment. Runoff shall be collected by a ditch along the intersection of each terrace bench and the outslope.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Terrace ditches shall have a 5 percent slope toward the channels specified in <cite path="|26|20|26|.04|H.">Regulation .04H of this chapter</cite> unless steeper slopes are necessary in conjunction with approved roads.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Placement of Excess Spoil on Abandoned Mine Land.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Excess spoil from a permitted coal mining operation may be placed on abandoned mine land outside of the permit area if the Department determines that the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Abandoned mine land is eligible for funding under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen">Environment Article, Title 15, Subtitle 11, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Abandoned mine land is referenced in the permit application and identified on the permit map;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Plan for the placement of the excess spoil on the abandoned mine land meets all applicable design requirements of Maryland's approved program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Legal right to enter upon the abandoned mine land to place excess spoil on the area has been obtained from the surface owner; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Excess spoil will be placed in accordance with the provisions of a contract executed between the Department and the permittee for reclamation of the abandoned mine land.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Reclamation Standards.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Excess spoil beyond the amount needed to restore the abandoned mine land to its approximate original contour may not be placed on the abandoned mine land.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The final configuration of the excess spoil that is placed on the abandoned mine land area outside of the permit area shall be compatible with the natural surroundings and suitable for the intended land use.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Valley, head of hollow, or durable rock fills may not be constructed on abandoned mine land.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Placement of excess spoil on abandoned mine land shall be planned and implemented in accordance with the requirements of Maryland's approved program.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The placement of excess spoil from a permit area on abandoned mine land outside of a permit area may not be approved unless the Department finds, in writing, on the basis of information set forth in the plan or otherwise available, that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Placement of the excess spoil and reclamation of the abandoned mine land can be accomplished in accordance with the plan submitted by the operator;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Excess spoil placement operation has been designed to prevent damage to the hydrologic balance outside of the abandoned mine land;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Excess spoil placement operation will not adversely affect any publicly owned parks or places included in the National Register of Historic Places, unless approved by the appropriate jurisdictional agency;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Applicant has submitted documentation establishing a legal right to enter and conduct the proposed reclamation on the abandoned mine land; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Proposed activities will not affect the continued existence of endangered or threatened species or result in the destruction or adverse modification of their critical habitats, as determined under the Endangered Species Act.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The placement of excess spoil from a permitted coal mining operation on abandoned mine land outside of the permit area shall be accomplished in accordance with a contract between the Department and the permittee that contains conditions which:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Document the method of placement of the excess spoil and reclamation on the area;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Require the operator to permit and bond the abandoned mine land area if the operator defaults on the contract; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Authorize the Department to issue a cessation order to cease all mining operations on the adjacent permit area until the operator submits:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An application for a permit, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The required amount of bond for the abandoned mine land area in the event the operator defaults on the contract.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Department shall monitor the placement of excess spoil and the reclamation of the abandoned mine land area to ensure that the work is performed in accordance with the contract. If the operator fails to meet the terms of the contract, the Department shall issue a cessation order to stop work on the area until the failure has been corrected.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|15-503">Environment Article, §15-503, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Regulations <cite path="|26|20|26|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|26|20|26|.04">.04</cite> were previously codified as <cite path="08.13.09.32|A.">COMAR 08.13.09.32A</cite>—D, respectively. Recodification occurred in April, 1993. For a history of these regulations before April, 1993, see "Administrative History of <cite path="|08.13.09">COMAR 08.13.09</cite> before April, 1993" which follows <cite path="|26.20.01">COMAR 26.20.01</cite>.</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" discontinuity="true">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|08.20.26">COMAR 08.20.26</cite> to <cite path="|26.20.26">COMAR 26.20.26</cite>, June 1996</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-01-14"><cite path="|26|20|26|.01|A.">Regulation .01A</cite> amended effective January 14, 1999 (26:1 Md. R. 25)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-01-14"><cite path="|26|20|26|.05">Regulation .05</cite> adopted effective January 14, 1999 (26:1 Md. R. 25)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
