<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>33</num>
  <heading>Permit Suspension, Revocation, and Bond Forfeiture</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>General.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Any permit issued under the Regulatory Program may be revoked upon a determination by the Bureau that a permittee has persistently or repeatedly failed to comply with the requirements of the Regulatory Program, or has failed to produce coal or remove overburden on the permit site for a period in excess of 6 months.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the Director determines that a permittee has persistently or repeatedly failed to comply with any requirements of the Regulatory Program, or that the permittee has not produced coal or removed overburden on the permit site for more than 6 months, the Director shall issue an order which requires the permittee to show cause why the permit should not be revoked and the bonds forfeited, and shall give the permittee 30 days in which to request an adjudicatory hearing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Violations by a person conducting surface coal mining and reclamation operations on behalf of the permittee shall be attributed to the permittee unless the permittee proves that they were acts of deliberate sabotage.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="26|20|33|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Persistent Failure to Comply.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Director may determine that a permittee has persistently failed to comply with the requirements of the Regulatory Program if, on two or more occasions within a 12-month period, a permittee has failed to meet the requirements of a:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notice of violation within the time limit set forth in the NOVO;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Cessation order within the time limit set forth in the order.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In making a determination under <cite path="26|20|33|.02|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, the Director may consider mitigating circumstances, including the severity of departure of a violation from the requirements of the Regulatory Program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Director shall determine that a permittee has persistently failed to comply with the requirements of the Regulatory Program if, within a 12-month period, a permittee has failed to meet the requirements of a cessation order issued under <cite path="26.20.31.07|B.">COMAR 26.20.31.07B</cite> within 30 days from the date the cessation order was issued.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Repeated Failure to Comply.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Director may review the history of violations of a permittee who, within a 12-month period, has been issued on:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Two or more occasions violation of the same or related requirements of the Regulatory Program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Three or more occasions for violations of different requirements of the Regulatory Program.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Director shall review the history of violations of a permittee who, within a 12-month period, has been issued on three or more occasions:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Violations for the same or related requirements of the Regulatory Program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Cessation orders under <cite path="26.20.31.07|B.">COMAR 26.20.31.07B</cite>, regardless of whether the permittee abated the violation within 30 days.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>After the review in §§A and B of this regulation, the Director shall determine whether a permittee has repeatedly failed to comply with the requirements of the Regulatory Program.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Show Cause Order and Hearing.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If, after a review of the history of any permit, the Director determines that a persistent or repeated failure to comply under Regulation .02 or .03 of this chapter exists or has existed, or that the permittee has not produced coal or removed overburden on the permit site for more than 6 months, the Director shall issue a show cause order as required by <cite path="|26|20|33|.01|B.">Regulation .01B of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Director may decline to issue a show cause order if he finds that, taking into account exceptional factors present in the particular case, it would be demonstrably unjust to issue the order. The basis for this finding shall be documented, in writing, and may include a determination that the violations were not the result of willful or unwarranted failure to comply on the part of the permittee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A show cause order issued by the Director shall be in writing and sent by certified mail to the permittee. The order shall contain a:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Detailed description of the basis for the Bureau's determination that the permittee has persistently or repeatedly failed to comply with the requirements of the Regulatory Program, or has failed to produce coal or remove overburden on the permit site for a period in excess of 6 months;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Statement that the permittee has 30 days from receipt of the order to request an adjudicatory hearing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Statement that unless the permittee requests an adjudicatory hearing to show cause why the permit should not be revoked and the bonds forfeited, the Bureau will immediately, upon expiration of the 30-day period, revoke the permit and forfeit the bonds covering the permit area;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Statement that the permittee may be represented by an attorney;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Statement that permit revocation and bond forfeiture will result in denial of future Maryland operator licenses to anyone involved in the failure to comply with the Regulatory Program.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the permittee requests a hearing, the Bureau shall give 30 days written notice of the date, time, and place of the hearing to the permittee and all interested parties. If practicable, the Bureau shall publish notice of the hearing in a newspaper of general circulation in the area of the permit and shall post the notice at the Bureau's office.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Show cause hearings to revoke a permit and forfeit the bonds shall be held in accordance with <cite path="|26.20.34">COMAR 26.20.34</cite>. The Bureau shall have the burden of going forward to establish a prima facie case for revocation of a permit and forfeiture of the bonds. The ultimate burden of persuasion that a permit should not be revoked and the bonds should not be forfeited shall rest with the permittee. The show cause order shall be made part of the hearing record, provided that the Bureau makes available a witness, subject to cross-examination on the reasons contained in the order for initiating revocation and bond forfeiture proceedings.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The existence of a show cause proceeding does not relieve the permittee from the permittee's responsibilities under the permit and the Regulatory Program. Failure to abate any continuing violation, or to manage the site properly, may subject the permittee to civil penalties and will be a significant factor in any decision to seek further prosecution.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Suspension.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If, at any time before a final decision in a permit revocation and bond forfeiture proceeding, the permittee demonstrates that the permittee is making good faith efforts to bring the operation into compliance and submits a schedule acceptable to the Bureau for bringing the operation into complete compliance, the parties may request the hearing officer to order the temporary suspension of the permit, instead of revocation and forfeiture.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Suspension of a permit shall be accepted by the permittee in a written agreement in which the permittee stipulates to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The facts and circumstances which led to the show cause order;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The present conditions at the permit site;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A specific reclamation or compliance schedule;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The submission of periodic reports, or other conditions required by the Bureau, to ensure the operation is brought into compliance;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The payment of any civil penalties assessed against the permittee within 30 days of the execution of the agreement; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The immediate revocation of the permit and forfeiture of the bonds by the Director, without further adjudication, if the permittee fails to comply with the schedule.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Suspensions may be lifted by the Director, in writing, based upon a finding that the operation has been returned to compliance with all requirements of the Regulatory Program. Lifting of suspension will result in reactivation of the permit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the permittee fails to comply with any reclamation or compliance schedule set forth in a stipulation agreement, the Director shall immediately notify the permittee, in writing, and by certified mail, that the permit is revoked and the bonds or other collateral covering the permit are forfeited.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Revocation and Forfeiture.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If the right of appeal is not exercised within the appeal deadline, or if the final decision upon appeal is to revoke the permit and forfeit the bond, the Director shall, in writing, and by certified mail, notify the former permittee and the surety, if applicable, that all bonds are forfeited and shall make claim for payment. The notice and claim shall advise that payment may be avoided if the former permittee or another person with a financial interest in the permit begins reclamation activities and continuously reclaims the site in accordance with a compliance schedule which meets the conditions of the Regulatory Program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Completion of reclamation work by a third party, instead of forfeiture, does not entitle that party to receipt of any collateral held by the Bureau. In all instances, the Bureau shall return collateral to the former permit holder in the same manner as if the permit had not been revoked, and may not become involved in private arrangements between the former permit holder and a third party.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In all cases, the total bond amount or other collateral held on a permit shall be forfeited, regardless of the actual amount of reclamation work required at the site. The Director shall pay all forfeited bond funds into the Bituminous Coal Open-Pit Mining Reclamation Fund.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Service of Show Cause Orders and Notices.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Show cause orders and any notices required by this chapter shall be served on the permittee at the address shown on the permit, or on the operator's license.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Service shall be made by sending a copy of the order or notice by certified mail. Service shall be complete upon mailing and may not be deemed incomplete because of refusal to accept.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|15-503">Environment Article, §15-503, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-10-20">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Regulations <cite path="|26|20|33|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|26|20|33|.07">.07</cite> were previously codified as <cite path="08.13.09.42|A.">COMAR 08.13.09.42A</cite>—G, respectively. Recodification occurred in April, 1993. For a history of these regulations before April, 1993, see "Administrative History of <cite path="|08.13.09">COMAR 08.13.09</cite> before April, 1993" which follows <cite path="|26.20.01">COMAR 26.20.01</cite>.</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" discontinuity="true">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|08.20.33">COMAR 08.20.33</cite> to <cite path="|26.20.33">COMAR 26.20.33</cite>, June 1996</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
