<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Designation of Neighborhood Conservation Areas</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>The purpose of this chapter is to prescribe the procedure for designating Neighborhood Conservation Areas by the Department upon request of a local government under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtp|9-255">Tax-Property Article, §9-255, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Act" means <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ghs">Housing and Community Development Article, Title 6, Subtitle 3, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Application" means an application to the Department as described in <cite path="|05|17|03|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Department" means the Department of Housing and Community Development, a principal department of the State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Local government" has the meaning stated in <cite path="05.17.01.02">COMAR 05.17.01.02</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Priority funding area" has the meaning stated in <cite path="05.17.01.02">COMAR 05.17.01.02</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Secretary" means the Secretary of Housing and Community Development.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Sustainable community" means the part of a priority funding area that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Has been designated as a sustainable community in accordance with Title 6, Subtitle 02 of the Act;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has been designated as a BRAC Revitalization and Incentive Zone under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gec">Economic Development Article, Title 5, Subtitle 13, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Has been designated as a transit-oriented development under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|7-101">Transportation Article, §7-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Application Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An application for Neighborhood Conservation Area designation shall be submitted by a local government to the Department in accordance with the schedule that the Department establishes.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An application shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be on standard forms prescribed by the Department;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide a detailed map of the proposed neighborhood conservation area including electronic geographic information system (GIS) shape files;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Provide a description of the proposed neighborhood conservation area including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The concentration of foreclosure activity;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The concentration of blighted or vacant properties; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Housing market trends over time;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Describe whether the proposed neighborhood conservation area includes a sustainable community or is located near a sustainable community; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Describe the process used to seek and receive public input on the proposed neighborhood conservation area, including the nature and extent of public support or opposition.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An application for a designation of a neighborhood conservation area shall demonstrate that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The neighborhood conservation area:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is located within a priority funding area;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has a concentration of foreclosure activity; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Has a concentration of blighted or vacant properties;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The local government either;</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Included an area in the proposed area located in or near a sustainable community; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Evaluated areas in or near sustainable communities and determined that the proposed area was more desirable as a neighborhood conservation area; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The proposed neighborhood conservation area has housing market trends that are weaker than average for the jurisdiction.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Application Processing.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Application Evaluation.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each application shall be submitted to the Department to determine whether all of the information required under <cite path="|05|17|03|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite> is contained in the application.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Upon receipt of all required information, the Department shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Convene a review team to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Review the applications;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Provide assistance and guidance to applicants; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Make recommendations to the Secretary;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Refer the application to other State agencies for comment, as the Department considers appropriate;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Consider any recommendation from a State agency; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Analyze each application as to determine whether the proposed neighborhood conservation area merits designation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Department, in its discretion, may request additional information from the local government concerning an application, including oral presentations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Upon completion of the requirements in §A(1)—(3) of this regulation, the Department shall make a recommendation on the application to the Secretary.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Recommendation by the Department. Upon receipt of the Department’s recommendation, the Secretary:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>May request additional information from the local government concerning the application, including oral presentations; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shall make a determination to approve, disapprove, or approve with modifications the designation of the area as a community conservation area.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="05|17|03|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Designation of a Neighborhood Conservation Area.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Secretary may designate an area as a Neighborhood Conservation Area.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Denial of Applications. If the Secretary, acting under <cite path="05|17|03|.05|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, determines not to designate all or part of an area as a neighborhood conservation area, the Secretary shall issue a written notice of denial with an evaluation and explanation of the denial.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Reconsiderations.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An applicant may request initial reconsideration of a denial by submitting a written request to the Secretary.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The request for reconsideration must be received within 30 days following the date of the denial notice.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The request for reconsideration shall address each reason for the denial and provide documentation supporting reasons for reconsideration of the application.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Department, as applicable, shall respond in writing to the applicant’s request for reconsideration within 90 days of receipt of the request for reconsideration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>An initial decision or reconsideration of a decision is not a contested case within the meaning of the Administrative Procedure Act or <cite path="05.01.01.02">COMAR 05.01.01.02</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Modification of a Neighborhood Conservation Area Designation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A local government or local governments may submit modifications to a neighborhood conservation area designation to the Department in accordance with the schedule that the Department establishes.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Secretary may approve modifications to a Neighborhood Conservation Area designation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Regulations <cite path="|05|17|03|.03">.03</cite>—<cite path="|05|17|03|.05">.05</cite> of this chapter shall apply to the procedures and approval process for modifying a neighborhood conservation area designation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Department may establish an abbreviated application for modifying a neighborhood conservation area designation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Tax Property Article, §9-255(a)(2), Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-04-15">Effective date: April 15, 2013 (40:7 Md. R. 609)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
