<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>Certification of Nursing Assistants</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Board” means the Maryland Board of Nursing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Central Repository” means the Maryland Criminal Justice Information System Central Repository of the Department of Public Safety and Correctional Services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Certificate” means a certificate issued by the Board to practice as a certified nursing assistant in this State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Certified Nursing Assistant (CNA).</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Certified nursing assistant (CNA)” means an individual, regardless of title, who routinely performs nursing tasks delegated by a registered nurse (RN) or licensed practical nurse (LPN) for compensation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Certified nursing assistant (CNA)” does not include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A medication technician; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>An individual who merely provides assistance with activities of daily living unless the client's needs are such that adverse health consequences are predictable.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“CFR” means the Code of Federal Regulations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Criminal history records check” means the performance of both a State criminal history check by the Central Repository and a national criminal history check performed by the Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Criminal history records information” means information provided by the criminal history records check regarding an applicant's criminal arrests, charges, and convictions and other dispositions of criminal charges.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Geriatric nursing assistant (GNA)” means a CNA who has successfully completed the requirements for a GNA set forth in 42 CFR §§483.151—483.156 and <cite path="10.07.02.39">COMAR 10.07.02.39</cite>—.42.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“Geriatric nursing assistant competency examination (GNA-CE)” means an examination approved by the Board that meets the requirements of 42 CFR §§483.151—483.156 to determine entry-level competence for a GNA.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>“Home health aide (HHA)” means a CNA who has successfully completed the requirements for certification as an HHA set forth in:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>42 CFR §484.36;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text><cite path="10.07.02.43">COMAR 10.07.02.43</cite> and .44; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text><cite path="10.39.01.09">COMAR 10.39.01.09</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>“Licensed practical nurse (LPN)” means an individual who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is licensed by the Board to practice licensed practical nursing; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has a multistate licensure privilege to practice licensed practical nursing.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>“Maryland Geriatric Nursing Assistant Registry (MGNAR)” means the registry maintained by the State in compliance with 42 CFR §483.156.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>“Medication technician (MT)” means an individual who has completed the 20-hour medication administration course approved by the Board.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>“Multistate licensure privilege” has the meaning set forth in <cite path="10.27.01.01|B.">COMAR 10.27.01.01B</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>“Registered nurse (RN)” means an individual who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is licensed by the Board to practice registered nursing; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has a multistate licensure privilege to practice registered nursing.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Fees.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Fees are as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Initial certification fee — $20;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Endorsement fee — $20;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Renewal fee — $40;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Verification of certification to another jurisdiction — $25;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Returned check fee — $25;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Duplicate certificate fee — $10.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Fees are not refundable.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|39|01|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>General Provisions for Applications.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant shall submit:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A completed application to the Board on the form that the Board requires;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>To a criminal history records check (CHRC) in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8">Health Occupations Article, §8</cite>–303, Annotated Code of Maryland;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Written evidence satisfactory to the Board that the applicant has submitted to a CHRC as required by <cite path="10|39|01|.03|A.|(2)">§A(2) of this regulation</cite> by submitting:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Two sets of fingerprints, as required by the Central Repository and the FBI; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>All fees required by the Central Repository and the FBI;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Any documentation requested from the applicant by the Board including, but not limited to, official certified or true test court documents and a signed, dated explanation written by the applicant, regarding the facts and circumstances, outcome, and current status of any criminal history record information received by the Board:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Under <cite path="10|39|01|.03|A.|(2)">§A(2) of this regulation</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>In an answer to a question on the Board’s application form; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>From any other source; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Any additional documentation requested by the Board if the documentation received from the applicant under <cite path="10|39|01|.03|A.|(4)">§A(4) of this regulation</cite> is incomplete or insufficient.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If an application is not complete when initially submitted to the Board by the applicant, the applicant shall have no longer than 12 months from the date the application is received by the Board to complete the application and provide all information and documents required in <cite path="10|39|01|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If an applicant fails to provide to the Board a complete application and any additional documentation requested by the Board under <cite path="10|39|01|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> within 12 months from the date the application is received by the Board, then the application shall be considered abandoned and may be destroyed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Once an application is deemed abandoned under <cite path="10|39|01|.03|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, an individual seeking CNA certification shall submit a new application on the form required by the Board and meet all of the requirements for CNA certification and pay the required fees that are in effect at the time of re-application.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Qualifications of Applicants for Certification.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant for nursing assistant certification shall provide satisfactory evidence of completing a CNA program that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is approved by the Board; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In another state or territory meets the standards for an approved CNA training program established by the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An applicant for nursing assistant certification shall be 16 years old or older.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An applicant for nursing assistant certification may not have:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Committed any act or omission that would be grounds for discipline or denial of certification under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-6">Health Occupations Article, §8-6</cite>A-10, Annotated Code of Maryland; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A record of abuse, negligence, or misappropriation of a client's property or any disciplinary action taken or pending in any other state or territory of the United States against the certification of the CNA.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Application for Certification.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Comply with all of the requirements under <cite path="|10|39|01|.03|A.">Regulation .03A of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Pay the required fee to the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Each application for certification shall be signed by the administrator or faculty of the nursing assistant training program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Applications may be signed before graduation. The person signing the application is responsible for submitting written verification of program completion to the Board within 5 business days of program completion.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Certification by Endorsement. An applicant certified as a nursing assistant in another state or territory is eligible for certification if the applicant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Complies with all of the requirements under <cite path="|10|39|01|.03|A.">Regulation .03A of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Pays the required fee; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Submits the following verifications directly to the Board from the appropriate authority:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A certificate in good standing from another state or territory with requirements that are essentially similar to the requirements in this State;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A certificate from an approved nursing assistant training program in that state or territory;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A statement that the applicant has not committed any act or omission that would be grounds for discipline or denial of certification; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A statement that the applicant has no record of abuse, negligence, or misappropriation of a client's property or any disciplinary action taken or pending in any state or territory of the United States against the certification of the CNA.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A certificate may not be issued until the Board has:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Received and reviewed the criminal history records information; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Approved the application.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Board may issue a temporary practice certificate in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-6">Health Occupations Article, §8-6</cite>A-07(g), Annotated Code of Maryland, to an applicant who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Has met the appropriate certification requirements to the satisfaction of the Board;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Does not have a criminal record; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Has not been the subject of a health professional disciplinary action in this State or another jurisdiction.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Unless the Board suspends or revokes a temporary practice certificate, the temporary practice certificate expires 90 days after issuance.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>A temporary practice certificate may be extended up to an additional 90 days if the applicant is awaiting the completion of the criminal history record information.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Issuance of Certification.</heading>
    <text>The Board shall issue a certificate to each applicant qualifying for certification if the applicant meets all the requirements of this chapter. The initial certificate may not be issued for less than 90 days.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|39|01|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Renewal.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board shall renew the certificate of each certificate holder who meets the requirements of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-6">Health Occupations Article, §8-6</cite>A-08, Annotated Code of Maryland and of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The certificate holder shall renew the certificate every 2 years by birth month according to the following schedule:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A certificate holder with an odd-numbered birth year shall always renew in an odd-numbered year not later than the 28th day of the certificate holder’s birth month; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A certificate holder with an even-numbered birth year shall always renew in an even-numbered year not later that the 28th day of the certificate holder’s birth month.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>At least 3 months before a certificate expires, the Board shall send the certificate holder a renewal notice by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>First-class mail to the last known address of the certificate holder; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Electronic means to the last known electronic address of the certificate holder.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The certificate holder shall notify the Board if a renewal notice is not received.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Board cannot guarantee that renewal applications received later than 30 days before the expiration date will be processed before the expiration date.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>An individual applying for renewal of a certificate shall provide satisfactory evidence of 16 hours of active employment, for compensation, as a nursing assistant within the 2-year period immediately preceding the date of renewal.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>An individual who do not meet the requirement of <cite path="10|39|01|.07|F.">§F of this regulation</cite> are required to successfully complete a Board-approved CNA education program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Upon notification by the Board that a criminal history records check is required before renewal of certification, a renewal applicant shall comply with all requirements under <cite path="|10|39|01|.03|A.">Regulation .03A of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>After notification to the certificate holder at the address provided to the Board that a criminal history records check is required for renewal, the Board may not renew a certificate until the Board has received written documentation that the applicant has submitted to a criminal history record check in accordance with Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-303">8-303</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-6">8-6</cite>A-08(k), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Criminal history records checks for renewal applicants shall be scheduled according to the certificate holder’s birth month as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In 2010 — all applicants with a June birth month;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In 2011 — all applicants with a July birth month;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>In 2012 — all applicants with an August birth month;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>In 2013 — all applicants with a September birth month;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>In 2014 — all applicants with an October birth month;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>In 2015 — all applicants with a November birth month;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>In 2016 — all applicants with a December birth month;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>In 2017 — all applicants with a January birth month;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>In 2018 — all applicants with a February birth month;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>In 2019 — all applicants with a March birth month;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>In 2020 — all applicants with an April birth month; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>In 2021 — all applicants with a May birth month.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>The Board shall mail out to every renewal applicant who is required to have a criminal history records check in the selected birth month, instructions for downloading the forms, completing the renewal application, and how to obtain a criminal history records check.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>If a renewal applicant is out of the state, the Board shall mail a packet to the applicant with the required renewal documents and instructions for completing the documents.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>Expiration of Certificate.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A certificate expires on the 28th day of the certificate holder's birth month.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A certificate holder has a 30-day grace period beyond the expiration of the certificate to renew a certificate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Board may impose a civil fine, not to exceed $50, on a certified nursing assistant who fails to renew a certificate within 30 days after the expiration date and practices as a certified nursing assistant during the period of expiration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Reinstatement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board shall reinstate the certificate of a former certificate holder who has failed to renew the certificate for any reason, if the former certificate holder meets the renewal requirements in <cite path="|10|39|01|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An applicant for reinstatement who has failed to renew the applicant’s certificate for a period of 1 year or more is required to submit to a criminal history records check before the certificate is reinstated.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|39|01|.09">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Categories of CNA.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Geriatric Nursing Assistant.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An applicant for certification as a CNA shall have the status of GNA on the CNA certificate if the applicant:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is certified as a CNA;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Passes the GNA-CE; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Completes the registration process and is listed on the MGNAR.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Status as a GNA shall end on the expiration of the CNA certificate unless the CNA certification is renewed and the requirements for status as a GNA are satisfied.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Status as a GNA on the CNA certification also requires that every 2 years the applicant shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Submit evidence of any hours of active geriatric nursing assistant practice for compensation that are required by the Office of Health Care Quality; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Complete the registration renewal process for inclusion on the MGNAR as required by <cite path="|10.07.02">COMAR 10.07.02</cite>. 42B(8).</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Home Health Aide.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An applicant for certification as a CNA shall have the status of HHA on the CNA certificate if the applicant:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is certified as a CNA; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has successfully completed a home health aide competency evaluation that meets the requirements in 42 CFR §484.36.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The agency offering the home health aide competency evaluation shall submit verification of successful completion within 5 business days.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Status as an HHA shall require that every year the applicant submit evidence of satisfactory completion of 12 hours of in-service training, as required by 42 CFR §483.36(b)(2)(iii), during the 1-year period before the date of renewal.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>HHA status terminates on expiration of the CNA certificate.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>School Health.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An applicant for certification as a CNA shall have the status of School Health on the CNA certificate if the applicant:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is certified as a CNA; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has successfully completed a CNA-School Health training program approved by the Board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Status as a CNA-School Health terminates on expiration of the CNA certificate unless the applicant verifies at the time of renewal that the applicant is currently practicing in school health as a CNA.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Dialysis Technician.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An applicant for certification as a CNA shall have the status of Dialysis Technician on the CNA certificate if the applicant has completed the following requirements:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is certified as a CNA;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has successfully completed a Dialysis Technician training program that:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Is approved by the Board:</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Prepares the applicant for national certification in accordance with 42 CFR §494.140(e); and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Obtains national certification upon eligibility.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The following national dialysis technician certifications are recognized by the Board:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Certified Clinical Hemodialysis Technician (CCHT) by the Nephrology Nursing Certification Commission (NNCC);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Clinical Nephrology Technician (CNT) by the National Nephrology Certification Organization (NNCO); and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Certified Hemodialysis Technician (CHT) by the Board of Nephrology Examiners Nursing Technology (BONENT).</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The status as a CNA-Dialysis Technician terminates on expiration of the CNA certificate unless the applicant verifies at the time of renewal that the applicant:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Has completed 16 hours of practice as a dialysis technician in the 2 years before renewal;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has completed a 3-hour continuing education course approved by the Board; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Has an active national certification from one of the approved certification bodies listed in <cite path="10|39|01|.09|D.|(2)">§D(2) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="10|39|01|.09|D.|(8)">§D(8) of this regulation</cite>, a dialysis technician:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is required to have an active national certification at the time of renewal; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Shall ensure that the Board has a record of a renewed national certification if a certification expires before the renewal date for the dialysis technician.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Certification will be deemed to have lapsed if the Board does not have a record of a current active national certification at the time of renewal.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The dialysis technician certification shall become non-renewed if the renewal applicant fails to provide evidence of a current active national certification.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>An applicant who has let their national certification lapse and does not qualify for recertification shall re-apply for a national certification for dialysis technician.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>If an applicant has not had 18 months to qualify for a national certification before their first renewal, the applicant may renew their certification as a CNA/DT provided that they have a national certification at their next renewal period.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Developmental Disabilities.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An applicant for certification as a CNA shall have the status of Developmental Disabilities (DD) on the CNA certificate if the applicant:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is certified as a CNA; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has successfully completed a CNA-Developmental Disabilities training program approved by the Board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Status as a CNA-DD terminates on expiration of the CNA certificate unless the applicant verifies at the time of renewal that the applicant is currently practicing in a DD setting as a CNA.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-205">8-205</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-206">8-206</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-303">8-303</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-304">8-304</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-308">8-308</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-6">8-6</cite>A-01—8-6A-16,<br/>Annotated Code of Maryland; Ch. 486, Acts of 2012</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-02-05">Effective date: February 5, 2001 (28:2 Md. R. 100)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-05-07"><cite path="|10|39|01|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective January 2, 2007 (34:4 Md. R. 397); amended permanently effective May 7, 2007 (34:9 Md. R. 825)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-02-18">Regulations .02A, .06B, .09B amended as an emergency provision effective November 15, 2001 (28:24 Md. R. 2125); amended permanently effective February 18, 2002 (29:3 Md. R. 221)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-08-27"><cite path="|10|39|01|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended effective February 2, 2004 (31:2 Md. R. 85); August 27, 2007 (34:17 Md. R. 1509)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-04-24"><cite path="|10|39|01|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective April 24, 2006 (33:8 Md. R. 734)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-05-07"><cite path="|10|39|01|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective January 2, 2007 (34:4 Md. R. 397); amended permanently effective May 7, 2007 (34:9 Md. R. 825)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-01-06"><cite path="|10|39|01|.04|D.">Regulation .04D</cite> amended effective January 6, 2014 (40:26 Md. R. 2164)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-05-07"><cite path="|10|39|01|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective January 2, 2007 (34:4 Md. R. 397); amended permanently effective May 7, 2007 (34:9 Md. R. 825)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-04-19"><cite path="|10|39|01|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective August 25, 2008 (35:17 Md. R. 1489); April 19, 2010 (37:8 Md. R. 617)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-01-06"><cite path="|10|39|01|.06|H.">Regulation .06H</cite> amended effective January 6, 2014 (40:26 Md. R. 2164)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-06-13"><cite path="|10|39|01|.06|N.">Regulation .06N</cite> amended effective June 13, 2011 (38:12 Md. R. 705)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-04-19"><cite path="|10|39|01|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective April 19, 2010 (37:8 Md. R. 617)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-04-24"><cite path="|10|39|01|.08">Regulation .08</cite> repealed and Regulation .09 recodified to be Regulation .08 effective April 24, 2006 (33:8 Md. R. 734)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-05-07"><cite path="|10|39|01|.08">Regulation .08</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective January 2, 2007 (34:4 Md. R. 397); amended permanently effective May 7, 2007 (34:9 Md. R. 825)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-04-07"><cite path="|10|39|01|.08|A.">Regulation .08A</cite>, B amended effective April 7, 2008 (35:7 Md. R. 748)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-03-22"><cite path="|10|39|01|.08|D.">Regulation .08D</cite> amended effective March 22, 2010 (37:6 Md. R. 478)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-04-24"><cite path="|10|39|01|.10">Regulation .10</cite> repealed effective April 24, 2006 (33:8 Md. R. 734)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-02-13" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective February 13, 2017 (44:3 Md. R. 189)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-07-02"><cite path="|10|39|01|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective July 2, 2018 (45:13 Md. R. 667)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-03-30"><cite path="|10|39|01|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective September 22, 2022 (49:22 Md. R. 975); emergency status expired effective March 30, 2023</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-03-30"><cite path="|10|39|01|.04|D.">Regulation .04D</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective September 22, 2022 (49:22 Md. R. 975); emergency status expired effective March 30, 2023</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-07-02"><cite path="|10|39|01|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective July 2, 2018 (45:13 Md. R. 667)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-03-30"><cite path="|10|39|01|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective September 22, 2022 (49:22 Md. R. 975); emergency status expired effective March 30, 2023</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-07-02"><cite path="|10|39|01|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective July 2, 2018 (45:13 Md. R. 667)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-07-02"><cite path="|10|39|01|.08">Regulation .08</cite> amended effective July 2, 2018 (45:13 Md. R. 667)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-07-02"><cite path="|10|39|01|.09">Regulation .09</cite> amended effective July 2, 2018 (45:13 Md. R. 667)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-03-30"><cite path="|10|39|01|.09|A.">Regulation .09A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective September 22, 2022 (49:22 Md. R. 975); emergency status expired effective March 30, 2023</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
