<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>General</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Authorization of Regulations.</heading>
    <text>The <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu">Public Utilities Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, provides that the Commission shall have the power to make such reasonable regulations as it deems necessary to carry out the provisions of this law and any other law relating to the Commission.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Application of Regulations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Application. These regulations apply to a gas utility or gas master meter operator operating within the State, under the jurisdiction of the Public Service Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Purpose. These regulations are intended to promote safe and adequate service to the public, to provide standards for uniform and reasonable practices, and to outline the responsibility of the public in requesting and receiving service from a utility.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Exemption. If unreasonable hardship to a utility, gas master meter operator, or to a customer results from the application of any of these regulations, application may be made to the Commission for the modification of the regulation or for temporary or permanent exemption from its requirements.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Modification. The adoption of these regulations does not preclude the Commission from altering or amending them, or from making such modifications with respect to their application as may be found necessary to meet exceptional conditions.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Duties Under Other Statutes. These regulations do not relieve any utility from any of its duties under the laws of this State.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Repealed.</heading>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this subtitle the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Abbreviations.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Btu" means British thermal unit.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"LNG" means liquefied natural gas.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>"LPG" means liquefied petroleum gas.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>"PSIG" means pounds per square inch, gauge.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>"W.C." means water column.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Accuracy" means the degree of conformity of a measure to a standard or true value.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Check flow" means a flow between 20 percent and 50 percent of the rated capacity of a meter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Commission" means the Public Service Commission of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Cubic foot" of gas means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Where gas is supplied and metered to customers at the pressure normally maintained on residential customers' meters, a cubic foot of gas is that quantity of gas which, at the temperature and pressure existing in the meter, occupies 1 cubic foot.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Where gas is supplied and measured with corrections made for pressure or temperature conditions, or both, existing in the meter, a cubic foot of gas is that quantity of gas which occupies a cubic foot after the metered quantity has been corrected to the absolute pressure or the temperature, or both, specified in the utility's tariff (see <cite path="20.55.03.01|B.|(8)">COMAR 20.55.03.01B(8)</cite>).</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The standard cubic foot of gas for testing the gas itself for heating value shall be that quantity of gas, saturated with water vapor, which at a temperature of 60°F and a pressure of 30 inches of mercury occupies 1 cubic foot. (Temperature of mercury = 32°F; acceleration due to gravity = <cite path="|32.17">32.17</cite> feet per second per second; density of mercury = 13.595 grams per cubic centimeter.)</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Customer" means a person, partnership, association, corporation, or governmental agency being supplied with gas service and whose name appears on the application for service.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6-1)</num>
        <text>"Division" means the Engineering Division of the Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Full rated flow" means a flow of approximately 100 percent of the rated capacity of a meter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7-1)</num>
        <text>"Gas master meter operator" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|1-101">Public Utilities Article, §1-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Gas plant" or "pipeline facility" means new and existing pipelines, rights-of-way, and any equipment, facility, or building used in the transportation of gas or in the treatment of gas during the course of transportation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Incident" has the meaning stated in 49 CFR §191.3, as amended, which is incorporated by reference.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Main" means a distribution line that serves as a common source of supply for more than one service line.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Meter", without other qualification, means a device which is used by a utility in measuring a quantity of gas.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>"Percent accuracy" means the ratio expressed in percent of the meter indicated volume (numerator) to the prover or other working standard volume (denominator) obtained in volumetric testing of gas meters.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>"Percent proof" means the ratio expressed in percent of the prover or other working standard volume (numerator) to the meter indicated volume (denominator) obtained in volumetric testing of gas meters.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>"Pipeline" means all parts of those physical facilities through which gas moves in transportation, including pipe, valves, and other appurtenances attached to pipe, compressor units, metering stations, regulator stations, delivery stations, holders, and fabricated assemblies.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>"Places of public assembly" means a building or portions of a building used for gathering together of 100 or more persons, the capacity being designated by the fire department for common purposes of deliberation, worship, or services, such as but not limited to churches, schools, hospitals, halls, theaters, and municipal facilities.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>"Premises" means a tract of land or real estate, including buildings and other appurtenances on it.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>"Rated capacity of a meter" means the capacity of the meter as specified by the manufacturer under the conditions of use.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>"Service line" means a gas pipe owned, operated, or maintained by a utility that runs from a main or a pipeline to the meter serving a customer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>"Utility" or "company" means any gas company operating under the jurisdiction of the Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>"Working standard" means the prover, test meter, or other approved device used to test customer meters or associated devices, or both.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|7-207">State Government Article, §7-207(a)</cite>; Public Utilities Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-113">2-113</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-121">2-121</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|5-101">5-101</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-301">7-301</cite>; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1964-07-01">Effective date: July 1, 1964 (Order No. 55567)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1974-10-21">Chapter revised effective October 21, 1974 (Order No. 60922)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-04-10"><cite path="|20|55|01|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended effective April 10, 1995 (22:7 Md. R. 538)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-02-07"><cite path="|20|55|01|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite>, C amended effective February 7, 2000 (27:2 Md. R. 145)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-05-05"><cite path="|20|55|01|.03">Regulation .03</cite> repealed effective May 5, 1986 (13:9 Md. R. 1031)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-07-20"><cite path="|20|55|01|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective May 5, 1986 (13:9 Md. R. 1031); December 25, 1989 (16:25 Md. R. 2714); July 20, 1992 (19:14 Md. R. 1285)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-03-26"><cite path="|20|55|01|.04|B.">Regulation .04B</cite> amended effective April 10, 1995 (22:7 Md. R. 538); December 29, 1997 (24:26 Md. R. 1759); February 7, 2000 (27:2 Md. R. 145); March 26, 2007 (34:6 Md. R. 629)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
