<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Records and Reports</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Tariff.</heading>
    <text>Each utility shall file with the Commission a copy of its tariff which shall include:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Rates. Each schedule of rates for service together with the applicable riders.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Rules. The utility's rules, or terms and conditions, describing the utility's policies and practices in rendering service. These rules shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Extension Plan. The utility's plan for the installation of extensions of main and service lines where these facilities are in excess of those included in the regular rates for service and for which the customer shall be required to pay all or part of the cost. The customer's payment under this plan should be related to the investment that the utility prudently can make in consideration of the probable revenue.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Heating Value. The total heating value of the gas in Btu per standard cubic foot.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Material Furnished by Utility. A list of the items which the utility furnishes, owns, and maintains on the customer's premises, such as meters, service line, regulators, vents, and shut-off valves.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>No Charge Service. A general statement indicating the extent to which the utility will provide service at no charge for the adjustment of customers' appliances.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Wastage of Gas. A general statement of the utility's policy in making adjustments for wastage of gas when wastage occurs without the knowledge of the customer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Billing Period. A statement indicating the minimum and maximum number of days for which the utility will bill a customer at its regular monthly rates for service.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Payment Period. A statement indicating the minimum number of days allowed for payment of the gross amount of the customer's bill before service will be terminated for non-payment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Measurement Base. A statement indicating the atmospheric pressure, the absolute pressure or temperature, or both, used when pressure or temperature correction is made to the metered volume of gas. (See <cite path="20.55.01.04|B.|(5)">COMAR 20.55.01.04B(5)</cite>)</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Information to be Filed.</heading>
    <text>Each utility shall file with the Commission the following items necessary in the administration of these regulations:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Special Contracts. A copy of each contract for service not covered by the utility's filed tariff.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Installation Rules. A copy of the utility's rules, if any, designed by the utility for the use of engineers, architects, plumbing and heating contractors, etc., covering meter and service installations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Bill Forms. A sample of each type of customer bill form, which shall include the information normally shown on a customer's bill for service.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Monthly Payment Plan. Each utility offering to its customers an even or equal monthly payment plan shall file a copy of the plan with the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Map of System. A map showing the utility's operating area. This map shall be revised annually unless no revision is necessary, to reflect a material change in the items listed below.  The map on file should reflect the current status of the following items:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Source of supply (gate stations and gate meters);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>LNG, LPG and other major storage facilities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Principal mains by size;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Peak shaving plants;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>State boundary crossings;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Franchise service areas approved by the Commission;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Names of all communities (post offices) served.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Persons to Contact. The name, title, address, and telephone number of the person who should be contacted in connection with the following areas of operation:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>General management duties;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Customer relations (complaints);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Engineering operations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Meter tests and repairs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Safety; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Emergencies during non-office hours.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Telephone Notice of Incidents. Each utility or gas master meter operator shall promptly notify a representative of the Public Service Commission by telephone of each incident as defined in <cite path="20.55.01.04|B.|(9)">COMAR 20.55.01.04B(9)</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Written Notice of Incidents. As soon as practicable but not later than 30 days after discovery, a utility shall file a written report of each incident with the Public Service Commission. This report shall be a copy of the report submitted to the U.S. Department of Transportation. An "incident" is defined in <cite path="20.55.01.04|B.|(9)">COMAR 20.55.01.04B(9)</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Annual Reports.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each utility shall submit to the Public Service Commission a copy of the annual report filed with the U.S. Department of Transportation. This report shall be submitted each year not later than March 15 for the preceding calendar year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Those utilities who also operate transmission pipelines shall submit to the Public Service Commission a copy of the annual report filed with the U.S. Department of Transportation. This report shall be submitted each year not later than March 15 for the preceding calendar year.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Construction Notice.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A utility or gas master meter operator shall notify the Engineering Division of the Commission in writing at least 10 days before the estimated start date of major construction projects.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Under this regulation a major construction project includes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>New pressure-regulating stations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Significant modifications to gas supply equipment at existing pressure-regulating stations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>New natural gas, LNG, or peak shaving propane plants;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Significant modifications to process equipment at existing natural gas, LNG, or peak shaving propane plants; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>New pipeline installations of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>500 or more feet of main or transmission pipeline for all gas master meter operators and utilities with 50,000 or less customers, or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>2,000 or more feet of main or transmission pipeline for all utilities with more than 50,000 customers.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The notification as required by this regulation shall be on a form provided by the Division.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Gas Service Monthly Reports. A gas service monthly report, on forms provided by the Commission, showing information concerning the utility's operations. These reports shall be due in the Commission's office within 30 days after the end of the month reported.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Location of Records. The location at which the utility keeps the various classes of records required by these regulations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>Organizations.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each company shall designate a representative to meet with other company representatives on a regular basis, such as with the Maryland Gas Operators Advisory Committee, Maryland-D.C. Utilities Association or other organizations, for the purpose of establishing and maintaining:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Uniform formats and practices for reporting to the Commission and the Office of Pipeline Safety;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A state-of-the-art information and data exchange between companies regarding equipment, facilities, suppliers, practices, and procedures; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Other pertinent programs.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The companies shall from time to time advise the Commission as to the status of the meetings.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Availability of Records.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Records. A utility or gas master meter operator shall make available to the Commission or its authorized representative all records required by these regulations or necessary for the administration of these regulations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Location of Pipeline. The utility or gas master meter operator shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Record and retain records indicating the location of all pipelines which it owns so that the records are as accurate as reasonably practicable;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Update the records so that all pipelines are included within 6 months of being placed in service; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Make the information available, upon reasonable request, to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Contractors,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Other utilities,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Governmental agencies, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Other interested persons.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Pipeline Location Services. A utility shall make available suitable equipment and personnel to provide pipeline location services upon reasonable request of interested persons, in compliance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu">Public Utilities Article, Title 12, Subtitle 1, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Retention of Records.</heading>
    <text>A utility or gas master meter operator shall preserve all records required by these regulations for the time specified in 18 CFR 125, as amended, which is incorporated by reference, unless otherwise specified by the Commission.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|7-207">State Government Article, §7-207(a)</cite>; Public Utilities Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-121">2-121</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|5-101">5-101</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|5-302">5-302</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|6-203">6-203</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|6-207">6-207</cite>; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1964-07-01">Effective date: July 1, 1964 (Order No. 55567)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1974-10-21">Chapter revised effective October 21, 1974 (Order No. 60922)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-07-20"><cite path="|20|55|03|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective May 5, 1986 (13:9 Md. R. 1032); July 20, 1992 (19:14 Md. R. 1285)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-08-25"><cite path="|20|55|03|.02">Regulation .02</cite> adopted effective May 5, 1986 (13:9 Md. R. 1032); amended effective August 25, 1986 (13:17 Md. R. 1924)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-03-18"><cite path="|20|55|03|.02|E.">Regulation .02E</cite> amended effective March 18, 2013 (40:5 Md. R. 412)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-07-31"><cite path="|20|55|03|.02|G.">Regulation .02G</cite> amended effective December 25, 1989 (16:25 Md. R. 2715); July 31, 1995 (22:15 Md. R. 1121)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1997-12-29"><cite path="|20|55|03|.02|H.">Regulation .02H</cite> amended effective December 25, 1989 (16:25 Md. R. 2715); July 31, 1995 (22:15 Md. R. 1121); December 29, 1997 (24:26 Md. R. 1760)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-12-25"><cite path="|20|55|03|.02|I.">Regulation .02I</cite> repealed and new Regulation .02I adopted effective December 25, 1989 (16:25 Md. R. 2715)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-03-26"><cite path="|20|55|03|.02|J.">Regulation .02J</cite> amended effective September 18, 1989 (16:18 Md. R. 2024); July 31, 1995 (22:15 Md. R. 1121); March 26, 2007 (34:6 Md. R. 629)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-02-07"><cite path="|20|55|03|.02|M.">Regulation .02M</cite> amended effective February 7, 2000 (27:2 Md. R. 145)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-05-05">Regulations .03 and .04 adopted effective May 5, 1986 (13:9 Md. R. 1032)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-04-10"><cite path="|20|55|03|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite> amended effective April 10, 1995 (22:7 Md. R. 538)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-02-07"><cite path="|20|55|03|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite> amended effective November 17, 1986 (13:23 Md. R. 2481); April 10, 1995 (22:7 Md. R. 538); February 7, 2000 (27:2 Md. R. 145)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-03-26"><cite path="|20|55|03|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective February 7, 2000 (27:2 Md. R. 145); March 26, 2007 (34:6 Md. R. 629)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
