<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>10</num>
  <heading>Work Approval</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter applies to gas company approval requirements for gas pipeline engineering plans or specifications for engineering work or services on designed projects after January 1, 2022.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This chapter does not apply to small system operators with less complex gas distribution systems as determined in the Guidance Manual for Operators of Small Natural Gas Systems (US Department of Transportation, Pipeline and Hazardous Materials Safety Administration, Office of Pipeline Safety, January 2017), which is incorporated by reference in <cite path="|20|55|10|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>, except for small system operators with multiple pressure distribution main pipeline systems.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Covered project” means natural gas infrastructure project work that is designed and must be approved and stamped by a professional engineer licensed in Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“District regulator awareness zone” means a delineated area around a district regulator station which is reasonably expected to encompass all control lines or other appurtenances necessary for continued safe operation and control where additional precautions are required to control work within the identified zone to minimize the risk of damage to critical facilities.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Division” has the meaning stated in <cite path="20.57.01.02|B.">COMAR 20.57.01.02B</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Gas company” has the meaning stated in <cite path="20.57.01.02|B.">COMAR 20.57.01.02B</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Noncovered project” means natural gas infrastructure project work that is designed and must be approved by a relevant qualified person.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Relevant qualified person” means a person such as an licensed professional engineer, subject matter expert, or other employee who possesses the necessary knowledge, experience, and skills regarding natural gas distribution systems to review and certify construction plans for accuracy, completeness, and correctness.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Incorporation by Reference.</heading>
    <text>In this chapter, the following documents are incorporated by reference:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Guidance Manual for Operators of Small Natural Gas Systems (US Department of Transportation, Pipeline and Hazardous Materials Safety Administration, Office of Pipeline Safety, January 2017); and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>49 CFR Part 192, Transportation of Natural and Other Gas By Pipeline: Minimum Federal Safety Standards, as amended.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|55|10|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Work Approval Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each gas company shall incorporate their work approval requirements for both covered and noncovered projects into their written operations and maintenance procedures under 49 CFR Part 192, Transportation of Natural and Other Gas By Pipeline: Minimum Federal Safety Standards, as amended, which is incorporated by reference in <cite path="|20|55|10|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Each gas company shall incorporate their training, initial qualification, and requalification requirements for a Relevant Qualified Person into their written operations and maintenance procedures under 49 CFR Part 192, Transportation of Natural and Other Gas By Pipeline: Minimum Federal Safety Standards, as amended, which is incorporated by reference in <cite path="|20|55|10|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Licensed professional engineers retained by a gas company shall have the necessary knowledge, experience, and skills regarding natural gas distribution systems to review and certify construction plans for accuracy, completeness, and correctness, but are not subject to <cite path="20|55|10|.04|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The following types of designed natural gas infrastructure project work are designated as covered projects and require documented approval by a licensed professional engineer:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>New installation or modification that creates or alters the designed operating pressure of a district pressure regulator station or gate station.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Installation of new or substantial reconfiguration of compressor stations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Installation, uprating, or abandonment of intrastate transmission lines.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Any distribution main piping modifications or replacement work falling within the established district regulator awareness zones established by each operator.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Any construction work on distribution mains which uprates the piping maximum allowable operating pressure.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Installation of distribution mains, including replacements and extension projects, which attach to bridges or other engineered structures.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Trenchless technology installations where the force used to pull the pipe and the path that the pipe follows while being pulled might result in damage to the pipe as a consequence of using that technology.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Peak shaving facility installations and modifications or reconfigurations that would alter its pressure delivery characteristics.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Any other designed natural gas infrastructure project work that presents a material risk of high consequence to public safety as determined by the gas company.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>All types of designed natural gas infrastructure project work not listed in <cite path="20|55|10|.04|D.">§D of this regulation</cite> are designated as noncovered projects and require documented approval by a relevant qualified person.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>During emergencies, a relevant qualified person may approve a covered project, in which case documented licensed professional engineer approval shall be required as soon as practical after the emergency has been resolved.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The Division may grant a waiver to the regulations in this chapter to a gas company for good cause.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Public Utilities Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-113">2-113</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-121">2-121</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|5-101">5-101</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-207">7-207</cite>(a), and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-301">7-301</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-06-14">Effective date: June 14, 2021 (48:12 Md. R. 474)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
