<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>CCA Pre-Enrollment Information</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|63|03|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>CCA Customer Consent — Pre-Enrollment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A CCA is deemed to have obtained a customer’s consent required by <cite path="20.53.03.01|A.|(2)">COMAR 20.53.03.01A(2)</cite> to request the customer’s pre-enrollment information from the electric company after the Commission has approved the CCA’s Aggregation Plan.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A CCA is not required to notify a customer of its intention to obtain customer information from an electric company if the customer’s consent is deemed to have been obtained according to <cite path="20|63|03|.01|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|63|03|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Pre-Enrollment Information Format.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An electric company shall provide to the CCA customer account pre-enrollment information on a per-account basis using electronic transactions per <cite path="20.53.03.02">COMAR 20.53.03.02</cite> after the Commission has approved the CCA’s Aggregation Plan.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A CCA may not make the request described in <cite path="20|63|03|.02|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> unless the CCA is in possession of a customer’s account number or equivalent retail choice identification number.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|63|03|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>CCA Formation Notice Information.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An electric company shall provide to a county in the process of forming a CCA, upon written request, information regarding each residential and small commercial customer in the county from the applicable electric company.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An electric company shall respond to the request in <cite path="20|63|03|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> within 10 business days.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The electric company shall provide the following information:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Aggregate usage information for each applicable service class, which the CCA may request quarterly; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A list of each residential and small commercial electric customer accounts in the county, including the following information for each account:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Account name;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Service address;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Billing address; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Utility rate class or code.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The electric company shall include, in the information provided, each residential electric customer account and each small commercial electric customer account at the time of the request.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An electric company shall exclude from the list, provided in §§C and D of this regulation, customer account numbers or retail choice identification numbers.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A county may not request the information in <cite path="20|63|03|.03|C.|(2)">§C(2) of this regulation</cite> prior to the effective date of the regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>An electric company shall provide a separate list, as described in <cite path="20|63|03|.03|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, for residential and small commercial customers.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|63|03|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Information Required for the CCA Opt-Out Notice.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An electric company shall provide to a CCA, upon written request, customer account information regarding each customer in the requesting county after the Commission has approved the CCA’s Aggregation Plan.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An electric company shall respond to the request in <cite path="20|63|03|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> within 30 calendar days.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The electric company shall provide the following information for each account:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Account name;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Service address;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Utility rate class or code;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Billing address;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Retail choice status; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Electric company recorded SOS request or CCA opt-out status.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The utility shall include,  in the information provided,  each residential electric customer account and each small commercial electric customer account at the time of the request.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An electric company shall provide a separate list, as described in <cite path="20|63|03|.04|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, for residential and small commercial customers.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|63|03|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Recording Customer Information Decisions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A CCA shall retain records of customer affirmative requests for CCA service, including:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>CCA service requested; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The time and date of the request.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A CCA and a county in the process of forming a CCA shall retain records of the time and date of customer requests to opt-out of CCA service.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An electric company shall retain records of the time and date of customer requests to opt-out of CCA service or request SOS service.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The CCA and electric companies shall retain records in §§A—C of this regulation for at least 3 years after the termination date of the CCA.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The electric company shall provide to the CCA, no more frequently than once per business day, the information in <cite path="20|63|03|.05|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> upon written request from the CCA.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Public Utilities Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|1">1</cite>–<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|101">101</cite>(b), (f), and (k), 7–306(f)(5) and (h), 7–306.2(d)(3), 7–507(a), 7–510(f) and 7–510.3, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-02-05">Effective date: February 5, 2024 (51:2 Md. R. 76)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
