<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>18</num>
  <heading>Recovery of Uncollectible SOS Expense from CCA Customers</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter addresses possible Commission allocation of SOS uncollectible costs to CCA customers, per <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-510">Public Utilities Article, §7-510</cite>.3(p), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|63|18|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Identification of Delinquent Accounts Receivable Attributable to CCA Customers at the CCA Start of Service.</heading>
    <text>No later than 90 days prior to the date established by the Commission to begin enrollment of customers in a CCA, an electric company shall calculate and file with the Commission the following relating to a transfer of the electric company’s customers from SOS to the CCA:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An estimate of the amount of SOS uncollectible expense which would be attributable to all residential and small commercial SOS customers in the county at the start of CCA service.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An estimate of the change in the SOS administrative charge or other charges used to recover SOS uncollectible expense based on a range of expected numbers of accounts that would transfer to the CCA from SOS service.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A proposed allocation or assignment to the CCA of the estimated SOS uncollectible expense identified in <cite path="20|63|18|.02|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, which would, if the change in SOS administrative charges materially adversely impacts the cost of providing SOS, mitigate the change in SOS administrative charges identified in <cite path="20|63|18|.02|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Recovery of CCA Uncollectible Expense.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An electric utility shall propose to the Commission a tariff provision that establishes a means to recover the estimated SOS uncollectible expense proposed in <cite path="|20|63|18|.01">Regulation .01 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An electric utility shall propose the recovery of CCA uncollectible expense as part of a discount rate tariff that is used for purchased receivables for a CCA using utility consolidated billing to be recovered over a 12-month period following enrollment of customers in the CCA or as otherwise accepted by the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An electric utility may propose an alternate tariff method of recovery of CCA uncollectible expense for a CCA using other billing methods.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Public Utilities Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|1">1</cite>–<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|101">101</cite>(b), (f), and (k), 7–306(f)(5) and (h), 7–306.2(d)(3), 7–507(a), 7–510(f) and 7–510.3, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-02-05">Effective date: February 5, 2024 (51:2 Md. R. 76)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
