<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>20</num>
  <heading>CCA Coordination Tariff</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter applies to the use by electric companies of a tariff to govern the requirements for a county serving as a CCA, Aggregation Suppliers, or agents thereof.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Tariffs.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Introduction of a CCA Coordination Tariff.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An electric company serving customers within Montgomery County shall, within 60 days after the Commission adopts the regulations for final publication, file with the Commission proposed tariff language to address the electric company’s interactions with a CCA for the duration of the Pilot.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An electric company may incorporate the tariff provisions required by this chapter in the company’s existing Electricity Supplier Coordination Tariff.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Each electric company serving accounts in Montgomery County shall coordinate with the other electric companies serving accounts in Montgomery County to propose consistent tariff provisions.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An electric company shall include at least the following terms and conditions in its tariff for CCA interactions:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Billing and payment collection;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Dispute resolution;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Financial settlement;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Losses;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Metering services;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>PJM interconnection requirements;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Scheduling; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Utility charges.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|63|20|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Pilot Cost Recovery.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Updates to CCA Uncollected Cost Recovery Methods.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An electric company shall continuously track a CCA’s uncollectible expense, as described in <cite path="|20.63.18">COMAR 20.63.18</cite> for the duration of the Pilot.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An electric company shall file revised tariffs for CCA uncollectible expense recovery at least annually.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Pilot Administrative Expense Recovery. In addition to those required by <cite path="20|63|20|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, an electric company shall propose to the Commission a tariff provision that establishes a means to recover the following estimated expenses attributable to the CCA:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Cash working capital component.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Program development cost component.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Purchase of receivable risk component.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Purchase of Receivables Discount Rates.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An electric company shall propose the recovery of administrative expense required by <cite path="20|63|20|.03|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> as part of a discount rate tariff that is used for purchased receivables for a CCA using utility consolidated billing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An electric company shall continuously track a CCA’s administrative expense, as described in <cite path="20|63|20|.03|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> for the duration of the Pilot.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An electric company shall file revised tariffs for CCA administrative expense recovery at least annually.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An electric company may propose tariff language to establish a method that is different than <cite path="20|63|20|.03|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> for recovery of CCA administrative expense for a CCA.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>All Commission-approved CCA-related costs incurred by an electric company shall be recovered from the CCA through tariff provisions, per §§B—D of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>An electric company may propose costs related to the Pilot in addition to those listed in §§A and B of this regulation for recovery via the methods described in §C or D of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Public Utilities Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|1">1</cite>–<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|101">101</cite>(b), (f), and (k), 7–306(f)(5) and (h), 7–306.2(d)(3), 7–507(a), 7–510(f) and 7–510.3, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-02-05">Effective date: February 5, 2024 (51:2 Md. R. 76)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
