<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Offset Projects</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>The Department shall provide for the award of CO<sub>2</sub> offset allowances to project sponsors of CO<sub>2</sub> emissions offset projects that have demonstrated a reduction or avoidance of atmospheric loading of CO<sub>2</sub>, CO<sub>2</sub> equivalent, or sequestered carbon. These requirements ensure that the awarded CO<sub>2</sub> offset allowances represent real, additional, verifiable, enforceable, and permanent CO<sub>2</sub> equivalent emission reductions or carbon sequestration. Subject to the relevant compliance deduction limitations identified in <cite path="26.09.02.03|K.">COMAR 26.09.02.03K</cite>, CO<sub>2</sub> offset allowances may be used by any CO<sub>2</sub> budget source for compliance purposes.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>General Requirements for CO<sub>2</sub> Emission Offset Projects.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Eligible CO<sub>2</sub> Emissions Offset Projects. In order to qualify for the award of CO<sub>2</sub> offset allowances, the following offset projects shall satisfy all applicable requirements identified in this chapter:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Landfill methane capture and destruction;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Sequestration of carbon due to reforestation, improved forest management, or avoided conversion; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Avoided methane emissions from agricultural manure management operations.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Offset Project Locations. Eligible offset projects may be located in any of the following locations:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In any participating state; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In any state or other United States jurisdiction in which a cooperating regulatory agency has entered into a memorandum of understanding with the appropriate regulatory agencies of all participating states relative to CO<sub>2</sub> emissions offset projects.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>General Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Any person may act as the project sponsor of a CO<sub>2</sub> emissions offset project. The general requirements described in this section apply.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>CO<sub>2</sub> offset allowances may not be awarded to an offset project that is required by any local, state, or federal law, regulation, or administrative or judicial order.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If an offset project receives a consistency determination and is later required by local, state or federal law, regulation, or administrative or judicial order, the offset project remains eligible for the award of CO<sub>2</sub> offset allowances until the end of its current allocation period but its eligibility will not be extended for an additional allocation period.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>CO<sub>2</sub> offset allowances may not be awarded to an offset project that includes an electric generation component if the project is additionally being used for compliance with a renewable portfolio standard or other regulatory requirement.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>CO<sub>2</sub> offset allowances may not be awarded to an offset project that receives funding from the Fund or other incentives derived from the Fund.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>CO<sub>2</sub> offset allowances may not be awarded to an offset project that is awarded credits or allowances under any other mandatory or voluntary greenhouse gas program, except for as described in the forest offset protocol.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Maximum Allocation Periods for CO<sub>2</sub> Emissions Offset Projects.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Department may award CO<sub>2</sub> offset allowances for an initial 10-year allocation period. At the end of the initial 10-year allocation period, the Department may award CO<sub>2</sub> offset allowances for a second 10-year allocation period if the project sponsor has submitted a consistency application before the expiration of the initial allocation period, and the Department has issued a consistency determination.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Reforestation, Improved Forest Management, or Avoided Conversion Projects.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Department may award CO<sub>2</sub> offset allowances for any reforestation, improved forest management, or avoided conversion offset project for an initial 25-year allocation period.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>At the end of the initial 25-year allocation period, or any subsequent crediting period, the Department may award CO<sub>2</sub> offset allowances for a second 25-year allocation period if the project sponsor has submitted a consistency application for the offset project before the expiration of the initial allocation period, and the Department has issued a consistency determination.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Offset Project Audit.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Project sponsors shall, in writing, grant access to the Department to the physical location of the offset project to inspect for compliance. For offset projects located in any state or other U.S. jurisdiction that is not a participating state, project sponsors shall also provide a copy to the Department of the access agreement in which the project sponsor grants the cooperating regulatory agency access to the physical location of the offset project to inspect for compliance.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If at any time the Department determines that a project sponsor or project has not complied with applicable requirements, the Department may revoke and retire all CO<sub>2</sub> offset allowances in the project sponsor's account.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If at any time the Department determines that an offset project does not comply with applicable requirements, the Department may revoke any approvals it has issued relative to an offset project.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Application Process.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Establishment of a General Account. The project sponsor of an offset project shall establish a general account. All submissions to the Department required for the award of CO<sub>2</sub> offset allowances shall be provided by the project sponsor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Consistency Application Deadlines.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>For offset projects not involving reforestation, improved forest management or avoided conversion, the consistency application must be submitted no later than 6 months following the date the offset project is commenced.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For offset projects involving reforestation, improved forest management or avoided conversion, the consistency application must be submitted no later than 1 year after the date the offset project is commenced, except as described in <cite path="|26|09|03|.04|J.">Regulation .04J of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Any consistency application that fails to meet the deadlines shall result in the denial of the consistency application and the continued ineligibility of the offset project.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Consistency Application Contents. The consistency application for an offset project shall include the following information:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The project sponsor's name, address, email address, telephone number, facsimile transmission number, and account number;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The offset project description;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A demonstration that the offset project meets all applicable requirements;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The emissions baseline determination;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>An explanation of how the projected reduction or avoidance of atmospheric loading of CO<sub>2</sub> , CO<sub>2</sub> equivalent, or the sequestration of carbon is to be quantified, monitored, and verified;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A completed consistency application agreement that reads as follows: "The undersigned project sponsor recognizes and accepts that the application for, and the receipt of, CO<sub>2</sub> offset allowances under the CO<sub>2</sub> Budget Trading Program is predicated on the project sponsor complying with all applicable requirements. I have been granted all the necessary authority to carry out the duties and responsibilities for the offset project under this subtitle. I understand that eligibility for the award of CO<sub>2</sub> offset allowances is contingent on meeting all applicable requirements. I authorize the Department or its agent to audit this offset project for purposes of verifying that the offset project, including the monitoring and verification plan, has been implemented as described in this application. I understand that the Department's right to audit shall include the right to enter the physical location of the offset project. I submit to the legal jurisdiction of the State.";</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>A statement and certification report signed by the project sponsor certifying that all offset projects for which the project sponsor has received CO<sub>2</sub> offset allowances under the project sponsor's ownership or control are in compliance with all applicable requirements of this subtitle in all participating states;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>A verification report and certification statement signed by an independent accredited verifier that states that the independent verifier has reviewed the entire application and evaluated the report in relation to all applicable requirements and any applicable guidance issued by the Department;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>A statement regarding the adequacy and validity of information supplied by the project sponsor that demonstrates that the offset project meets the applicable eligibility requirements of this subtitle and baseline emissions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>A statement regarding the adequacy of the monitoring and verification plan and other evaluations and statements as required by the Department;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Disclosure of any voluntary or mandatory programs, other than this subtitle, to which greenhouse gas emissions data related to the offset project has been or will be reported; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>For offset projects located in a state or United States jurisdiction that is not a participating state, a demonstration that the project sponsor has complied with all requirements of the cooperating regulatory agency in the state or United States jurisdiction where the offset project is located.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Filing the Consistency Application.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For an offset project located wholly or in part in a participating state, the consistency application shall be filed with the regulatory agency in that state.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For an offset project located wholly outside all participating states, the consistency application shall be filed with the appropriate regulatory agency in any one participating state, provided a copy of the consistency application is filed with the cooperating regulatory agency in the state or United States jurisdiction where the offset project is located.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>For an offset project located in more than one participating state, the consistency application shall be filed in the participating state where the larger part of the CO<sub>2</sub> equivalent emissions reduction or carbon sequestration due to the offset project is projected to occur.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>For CO<sub>2</sub> emissions credit retirements, the consistency application may be filed with the regulatory agency in any one participating state.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Action on Consistency Applications.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Completeness Determination. Within 30 days following receipt of the consistency application, the Department shall notify the project sponsor whether the consistency application is complete. A complete consistency application is one that is in an approved form and is determined by the Department to be complete for the purpose of commencing review of the consistency application. A completeness determination does not prevent the Department from requesting additional information in order to enable the Department to make a consistency determination.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Consistency Determination. Within 90 days of making the completeness determination, the Department shall issue a determination as to whether the offset project is consistent with all applicable requirements. The Department shall provide its consistency determination to the project sponsor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Landfill Methane Capture and Destruction Project Standards.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Offset projects that capture and destroy methane from landfills qualify for the award of CO<sub>2</sub> offset allowances if they meet the requirements of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Eligibility. Eligible offset projects shall occur at landfills that are not subject to the New Source Performance Standards (NSPS) for municipal solid waste landfills, 40 CFR Part 60, Subpart Cc and Subpart WWW.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Offset Project Description. The project sponsor shall provide a detailed narrative of the offset project actions to be taken, including documentation that the offset project meets the eligibility requirements and includes the following information:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Owner and operator of the offset project;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Location and specifications of the landfill where the offset project will occur, including waste in place;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Owner and operator of the landfill where the offset project will occur; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Specifications of the equipment to be installed and a technical schematic of the offset project.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Emissions Baseline Determination. The emissions baseline represents the potential fugitive landfill emissions of methane (CH<sub>4</sub>) measured in tons of CO<sub>2</sub>e as represented by the CH<sub>4</sub> collected and metered for thermal destruction as part of the offset project and calculated in accordance with the following:</text>
      <text>Emissions (tons CO<sub>2</sub>e) = (V × M x (1-OX) × GWP)/2000</text>
      <text>where:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>V = Volume of CH<sub>4</sub> collected, in cubic feet;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>M = Mass of CH<sub>4</sub> per cubic foot (0.04246 pounds per cubic feet default value at 1 atmosphere and 20°C);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>OX = Oxidation factor (0.10), representing estimated portion of collected CH<sub>4</sub> that would have eventually oxidized to CO<sub>2</sub> if not collected; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>GWP = 28 for the CO<sub>2</sub>e global warming potential of CH<sub>4</sub>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Calculating Emissions Reductions. Emissions reductions shall be determined based on potential fugitive CH<sub>4</sub> emissions that would have occurred at the landfill if metered CH<sub>4</sub> collected from the landfill for thermal destruction as part of the offset project was not collected and destroyed. CO<sub>2</sub>e emissions reductions shall be calculated as follows:</text>
      <text>Emissions Reductions (tons CO<sub>2</sub>e) = (V × M X (1-OX) × C<sub>ef</sub> × GWP)/2000</text>
      <text>where:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>V = Volume of CH<sub>4</sub> collected, in cubic feet;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>M = Mass of CH<sub>4</sub> per cubic foot (0.04246 pounds per cubic feet default value at 1 atmosphere and 20°C);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>OX = Oxidation factor (0.10), representing estimated portion of collected CH<sub>4</sub> that would have eventually oxidized to CO<sub>2</sub> if not collected;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>C<sub>ef</sub> = Combustion efficiency of methane control technology (0.98); and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>GWP = 28 for the CO<sub>2</sub>e global warming potential of CH<sub>4</sub>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Monitoring and Verification Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Offset projects shall employ a landfill gas collection system that provides continuous metering and data computation of landfill gas volumetric flow rate and CH<sub>4</sub> concentration. Annual monitoring and verification reports shall include monthly volumetric flow rate and CH<sub>4</sub> concentration data, including documentation that the CH<sub>4</sub> was actually supplied to the combustion source.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The project sponsor shall submit a monitoring and verification plan as part of the consistency application that includes a quality assurance and quality control program associated with equipment used to determine landfill gas volumetric flow rate and CH<sub>4</sub> composition.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The monitoring and verification plan shall be certified by an independent accredited verifier and include provisions for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Ensuring that measuring and monitoring equipment is maintained, operated, and calibrated based on manufacturer recommendations; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The retention of maintenance records for audit purposes.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The project sponsor shall annually verify landfill gas CH<sub>4</sub> composition through landfill gas sampling and independent laboratory analysis using applicable EPA laboratory test methods.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="26|09|03|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Sequestration of Carbon due to Reforestation, Improved Forest Management, or Avoided Conversion.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Forest Offset Project Standards. Offset projects that involve reforestation, improved forest management, or avoided conversion shall qualify for the award of CO<sub>2</sub> allowances if they meet the requirements of this regulation and the forest offset protocol.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Eligibility. Eligible forest offset projects shall satisfy all eligibility requirements of the forest offset protocol and this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Offset Project Description. The offset project sponsor shall provide a detailed narrative of the offset project actions taken, including documentation that the offset project meets the eligibility requirements of this regulation. The offset project description must include all information identified in sections 8.1 and 9.1 of the forest offset protocol, and any other information deemed necessary by the Department.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Carbon Sequestration Baseline Determination. Baseline onsite carbon stocks shall be determined as required in sections 6.1.1, 6.1.2, 6.2.1, 6.2.2, 6.2.3, 6.3.1, and 6.3.2 of the forest offset protocol, as applicable.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Calculating Carbon Sequestered. Net GHG reductions and GHG removal enhancements shall be calculated as required by section 6 of the forest offset protocol. The project’s risk reversal rating shall be calculated using the Determination of a Forest Project’s Reversal Risk Rating assessment worksheet in Appendix D of the forest offset protocol.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Monitoring and Verification Requirements. Monitoring and verification is subject to the following requirements:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Monitoring and verification reports shall include all forest offset project data reports submitted to the Department, including any additional data required by section 9.2.2 of the forest offset protocol;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The consistency application shall include a monitoring and verification plan certified by an independent verifier accredited pursuant to <cite path="|26|09|03|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>, which shall consist of a forest carbon inventory program, as required by section 8.1 of the forest offset protocol; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Monitoring and verification reports shall be submitted not less than every 6 years, except that the first monitoring and verification report for reforestation projects must be submitted within 12 years of project commencement.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Forest Offset Project Data Reports. A project sponsor shall submit a forest offset Project data report to the Department for each reporting period that shall meet the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each forest offset project data report must cover a single reporting period;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Reporting periods must be contiguous; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>There must be no gaps in reporting once the first reporting period has commenced.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Prior to the award of CO<sub>2</sub> offset allowances pursuant to <cite path="|26|09|03|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite>, or to any surrender of allowances pursuant to <cite path="26|09|03|.04|I.">§I of this regulation</cite>, any quantity expressed in metric tons, or metric tons of CO<sub>2</sub> equivalent, shall be converted to tons using the conversion factor specified in <cite path="26.09.01.02|B.|(93)">COMAR 26.09.01.02B(93)</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Carbon Sequestration Permanence. The offset project shall meet the following requirements to address reversals of sequestered carbon:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Unintentional reversals. Requirements for unintentional reversals are as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The project sponsor must notify the Department of the reversal and provide an explanation for the nature of the unintentional reversal within 30 calendar days of its discovery; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The project sponsor must submit to the Department a verified estimate of current carbon stocks within the offset project boundary within 1 year of the discovery of the unintentional reversal.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Intentional Reversals. Requirements for intentional reversals are as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If an intentional reversal occurs, the project sponsor shall, within 30 calendar days of the intentional reversal:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Provide notice, in writing, to the Department of the intentional reversal; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Provide a written description and explanation of the intentional reversal to the Department.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Within 1 year of the occurrence of an intentional reversal, the project sponsor shall submit to the Department a verified estimate of current carbon stocks within the offset project boundary.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If an intentional reversal occurs, and CO<sub>2</sub> offset allowances have been awarded to the offset project, within 6 months following notification by the Department, the forest owner must surrender to the Department for retirement, the number of CO<sub>2</sub> allowances corresponding to the quantity of CO<sub>2</sub> equivalent tons reversed.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Notification by the Department will occur after the verified estimate of carbon stocks has been submitted to the Department, or after 1 year has elapsed since the occurrence of the reversal if the project sponsor fails to submit the verified estimate of carbon stocks; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>If the forest owner does not surrender valid CO<sub>2</sub> allowances to the Department within 6 months following notification by the Department, the forest owner will be subject to an enforcement action and each CO<sub>2</sub> equivalent ton of carbon sequestration reversed will constitute a separate violation of this regulation and applicable State law.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Project Termination. Requirements for project termination are as follows:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Within 6 months of project termination, the project sponsor shall surrender to the Department or its agent for retirement, a quantity of CO<sub>2</sub> allowances in the amount calculated pursuant to project termination provisions in the forest offset protocol; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>If the project sponsor fails to surrender to the Department a quantity of CO<sub>2</sub> Allowances in the amount calculated pursuant to project termination provisions in the forest offset protocol within 6 months following project termination, the project sponsor shall be subject to enforcement action and each CO<sub>2</sub> offset allowance not surrendered will constitute a separate violation of this regulation and applicable State law.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Disposition of Forest Sequestration Projects After a Reversal. If a reversal lowers the forest offset project’s actual standing live carbon stocks below its project baseline standing live carbon stocks, the forest offset project will be terminated by the Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Timing of Forest Offset Projects. The Department may award CO<sub>2</sub> offset allowances under <cite path="|26|09|03|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite> only for forest offset projects that are initially commenced on or after January 1, 2014.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Projects that Have Been Awarded Credits Under a Voluntary Greenhouse Gas Reduction Program.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For projects that have been awarded credits under a voluntary greenhouse gas reduction program, the number of CO<sub>2</sub> Offset Allowances will be calculated pursuant to the requirements of this regulation, without regard to the number of credits that were awarded to the project under the voluntary program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The provisions of Regulation .02C(6) and F(2)(b) may not apply to forest projects that have been awarded credits under a voluntary greenhouse gas reduction program provided that the following conditions are satisfied:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The project satisfies all other general requirements of this chapter, including all specific requirements of this regulation, for all reporting periods for which the project has been awarded credits under a voluntary greenhouse gas program and also intends to be awarded CO<sub>2</sub> offset allowances pursuant to <cite path="|26|09|03|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>At the time of submittal of the consistency application for the project, the project sponsor submits forest offset data reports and a monitoring and verification report meeting all requirements of §§F and G of this regulation that covers all reporting periods for which the project has been awarded credits under a voluntary greenhouse gas program and also seeks an award of CO<sub>2</sub> offset allowances pursuant to <cite path="|26|09|03|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The voluntary greenhouse gas program has published information on its website to allow the Department to verify the information included in the consistency application, and the consistency application includes information sufficient to allow the Department to make the following determinations:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The offset project has met all legal and contractual requirements to allow it to terminate its relationship with the voluntary greenhouse gas program, and such termination has been completed; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The project sponsor or voluntary greenhouse gas program has cancelled or retired all credits that were awarded for carbon sequestration that occurred during the time periods for which the project intends to be awarded CO<sub>2</sub> offset allowances pursuant to <cite path="|26|09|03|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite>, and such credits were cancelled or required for the sole purpose of allowing the project to be awarded CO<sub>2</sub> offset allowances pursuant to <cite path="|26|09|03|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="26|09|03|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Avoided Methane Emissions from Agricultural Manure Management Operations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Offset projects that capture and destroy methane from animal manure and organic food waste using anaerobic digesters qualify for the award of CO<sub>2</sub> offset allowances if they comply with the requirements of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Eligible offset projects shall consist of the destruction of that portion of methane generated by an anaerobic digester that would have been generated in the absence of the offset project through the uncontrolled anaerobic storage of manure or organic food waste.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Eligible offset projects shall employ only manure-based anaerobic digester systems using livestock manure as the majority of digester feedstock, defined as more than 50 percent of the mass input into the digester on an annual basis. Organic food waste used by an anaerobic digester shall only be that which would have been stored in anaerobic conditions in the absence of the offset project.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Agricultural manure management offset projects may be acceptable if either of the following requirements is met:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The offset project is located in a state that has a market penetration rate for anaerobic digester projects of 5 percent or less; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The offset project is located at a farm with 4,000 or less head of dairy cows, or a farm with equivalent animal units, assuming an average live weight for dairy cows (pounds per cow) of 1,400 pounds, or, if the project is a regional-type digester, total annual manure input to the digester is designed to be less than the average annual manure produced by a farm with 4,000 or less head of dairy cows, or a farm with equivalent animal units, assuming an average live weight for dairy cows (pounds per cow) of 1,400 pounds.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The market penetration determination shall utilize the most recent market data available at the time of submission of the consistency application and determined as follows:</text>
      <text>MP (percent) = MG<sub>AD</sub> / MG<sub>STATE</sub></text>
      <text>where:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>MG<sub>AD</sub> = Average annual manure generation for the number of dairy cows and swine serving all anaerobic digester projects in the applicable state at the time of submission of a consistency application; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>MG<sub>STATE</sub> = average annual manure production of all dairy cows and swine in the state at the time of submission of a consistency application.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Offset Project Description.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The offset project sponsor shall provide a detailed narrative of the offset project actions to be taken, including documentation that the offset project meets the applicable eligibility requirements of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The offset project sponsor shall provide the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Owner and operator of the offset project;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Location and specifications of the facility where the offset project will occur;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Owner and operator of the facility where the offset project will occur;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Specifications of the equipment to be installed and a technical schematic of the offset project; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Location and specifications of the facilities from which anaerobic digester influent will be received, if different from the facility where the offset project will occur.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Emissions Baseline Determination.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The emissions baseline shall represent the potential emissions of the CH<sub>4</sub> that would have been produced in a baseline scenario under uncontrolled anaerobic storage conditions and released directly to the atmosphere in the absence of the offset project.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Baseline CH<sub>4</sub> emissions shall be calculated as follows:</text>
        <text>Eb = (V<sub>m</sub> × M)/2000 × GWP</text>
        <text>where:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Eb = Potential CO<sub>2</sub>e emissions due to calculated CH<sub>4</sub> production under site-specific anaerobic storage and weather conditions (tons);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>V<sub>m</sub> = Volume of CH<sub>4</sub>, in cubic feet, produced each month from decomposition of volatile solids in a baseline uncontrolled anaerobic storage scenario under site-specific storage and weather conditions for the facility at which the manure or organic food waste is generated;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>M = Mass of CH<sub>4</sub> per cubic foot (0.04246 pounds/cubic foot default value at one atmosphere and 20°C); and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>GWP = 28 for the global warming potential of CH<sub>4</sub>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The estimated amount of volatile solids decomposed each month under the uncontrolled anaerobic storage baseline scenario shall be calculated as follows:</text>
        <text>VS<sub>deg</sub> = VS<sub>avail</sub> × f</text>
        <text>where:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>VS = Volatile solids as determined from the equation:</text>
          <text>VS = M<sub>m</sub> × TS<sub>%</sub> × VS<sub>%</sub></text>
          <text>where:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>M<sub>m</sub> = Mass of manure or organic food waste produced per month, in kilograms;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>TS<sub>%</sub> = Concentration (percent) of total solids in manure or organic food waste as determined through USGS I-3750 (USGS, Methods for the Determination of Inorganic Substances in Water and Fluvial Sediments, Techniques of Water-Resources Investigations of the United States Geological Survey, Book 5, Chapter A1, Method Number I-3750, "Solids, residue on evaporation at 105 degrees C, total, gravimetric"); and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>VS<sub>%</sub> = Concentration (percent) of volatile solids in total solids as determined through EPA 160.4 testing method (U.S. EPA, Methods for the Chemical Analysis of Water and Wastes (MCAWW) (EPA/600/4-79/020), Method Number 160.4, "Volatile Residue by Muffle Furnace,");</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>VS<sub>avail</sub> = Volatile solids available for decomposition in manure or organic food waste storage each month as determined from the equation:</text>
          <text>VS<sub>avail</sub> = VS<sub>p</sub> + 1/2 VS<sub>in</sub> - VS<sub>out</sub></text>
          <text>where:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>VS<sub>p</sub> = Volatile solids present in manure or organic food waste storage at beginning of month (left over from previous month), in kilograms;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>VS<sub>in</sub> = Volatile solids added to manure or organic food waste storage during the course of the month, in kilograms; the factor of 1/2 is multiplied by this number to represent the average mass of volatile solids available for decomposition for the entire duration of the month;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>VS<sub>out</sub> = Volatile solids removed from the manure or organic food waste storage for land application or export (assumed value based on standard farm practice); and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>f = van't Hoff-Arrhenius factor for the specific month as determined by the following equation, using a base temperature of 30°C:</text>
          <text>f = exp{[E(T<sub>2</sub> - T<sub>1</sub>)]/[(GC × T<sub>1</sub> × T<sub>2</sub>)]}</text>
          <text>where:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>f = Conversion efficiency of VS to CH<sub>4</sub> per month;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>E = Activation energy constant (15,175 calories per mole);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>T<sub>2</sub> = average monthly ambient temperature for facility where manure or organic food waste is generated (converted from ° Celsius to ° Kelvin) as determined from the nearest National Weather Service certified weather station (if reported temperature °C &gt;5°C; if reported temperature °C &lt;5°C, then F = 0.104);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>T<sub>1</sub> = 303.16 (30°C converted to °K); and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>GC = ideal gas constant (1.987 calories per mole).</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The volume of CH<sub>4</sub> produced, in cubic feet, from decomposition of volatile solids shall be calculated as follows:</text>
        <text>V<sub>m</sub> = (VS<sub>dec</sub> × B<sub>°</sub>) × 35.3147</text>
        <text>where:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>V<sub>m</sub> = volume of CH<sub>4</sub>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>VS<sub>dec</sub> = volatile solids decomposed.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>B<sub>°</sub> = Manure or organic food waste type-specific maximum methane generation constant (m<sup>3</sup> CH<sub>4</sub>/kg VS decomposed). For dairy cow manure, B<sub>°</sub> = 0.24 m<sup>3</sup> CH<sub>4</sub>/kg VS decomposed. The methane generation constant for other types of manure shall be those cited at U.S. EPA, Inventory of U.S. Greenhouse Gas Emissions and Sinks: 1990—2010, Annex 3, Table A-180, April 15, 2012, unless the project sponsor proposes an alternate methane generation constant and the alternate is approved by the Department. If the project sponsor proposes to use a methane generation constant other than the ones found in the above-cited reference, the project sponsor shall provide justification and documentation to the Department.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Calculating Emissions Reductions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Emissions reductions shall be calculated as follows:</text>
        <text>ERt = EB – Ep</text>
        <text>where:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>ERt = CO<sub>2</sub>e emissions reductions due to project activities;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Eb = Potential CO<sub>2</sub>e emissions due to calculated CH<sub>4</sub> production under site-specific anaerobic storage and weather conditions (tons); and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Ep = CO<sub>2</sub>e emissions due to project activities additional to baseline (tons), including, but not limited to manure transportation, flaring, venting, and effluent management.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Emissions reductions may not exceed the potential emissions of the anaerobic digester, as represented by the annual volume of CH<sub>4</sub> produced by the anaerobic digester. CO<sub>2</sub> emissions due to transportation of manure and organic food waste from the site where the manure and organic food waste was generated to the anaerobic digester shall be subtracted from the calculated emissions reduction.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Transport CO<sub>2</sub> emissions shall be determined through one of the following methods:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Documentation of transport fuel use for all shipments of manure and organic food waste from off-site to the anaerobic digester during each reporting year and a log of transport miles for each shipment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Documentation of total tons of manure and organic food waste transported from off-site for input into the anaerobic digester during each reporting year and a log of transport miles and fuel type used for each shipment; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>CO<sub>2</sub> emissions shall be determined through the application of a ton-mile transport emission factor for the fuel type used.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Under <cite path="26|09|03|.05|H.|(3)|(a)">§H(3)(a) of this regulation</cite>, CO<sub>2</sub> emissions shall be determined through the application of an emissions factor for the fuel type used. If this option is selected, the following emissions factors shall be applied as appropriate:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Diesel fuel: 22.912 pounds of CO<sub>2</sub> per gallon;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Gasoline: 19.878 pounds of CO<sub>2</sub> per gallon; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Other fuel: submitted emissions factor approved by the Department.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If the option under <cite path="26|09|03|.05|H.|(3)|(c)">§H(3)(c) of this regulation</cite> is selected, the following emissions factors shall be applied as appropriate for each ton of manure delivered, and multiplied by the number of miles transported:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Diesel fuel: 0.131 pounds CO<sub>2</sub> per ton-mile;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Gasoline: 0.133 pounds CO<sub>2</sub> per ton-mile; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Other fuel: submitted emissions factor approved by the Department.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Monitoring and Verification Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Offset projects shall employ a system that provides metering of biogas volumetric flow rate and determination of CH<sub>4</sub> concentration. Annual monitoring and verification reports shall include monthly biogas volumetric flow rate and CH<sub>4</sub> concentration determination and meet the requirements of this section.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the offset project is a regional-type digester, manure and organic food waste from each distinct source supplying to the anaerobic digester shall be sampled monthly to determine the amount of volatile solids present. Any emissions reduction shall be calculated according to mass of manure and organic food waste in kilograms being digested and percentage of volatile solids present before digestion and apportioned accordingly among sources. The project sponsor shall provide supporting material and receipts tracking the monthly receipt of manure and organic food waste used to supply the anaerobic digester from each supplier.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the offset project includes the digestion of eligible organic food waste, the organic food waste shall be sampled monthly to determine the amount of volatile solids present before digestion and apportioned accordingly.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The project sponsor shall submit a monitoring and verification plan as part of the consistency application that includes a quality assurance and quality control program associated with equipment used to determine biogas volumetric flow rate and CH<sub>4</sub> composition.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The monitoring and verification plan shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be specified in accordance with the applicable monitoring requirements;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Include provisions for:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Ensuring that measuring and monitoring equipment is maintained, operated, and calibrated based on the manufacturer's recommendations; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The retention of maintenance records for audit purposes and;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Be certified by an independent accredited verifier.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Input Monitoring Requirements.</text>
        <text>
          <table class="layout-table">
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="bottom" data-width="166666">Input Parameter <br/>Influent flow (mass) into the digester</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="bottom" data-width="166666">Measurement Unit Kilograms (kg) per month (wet weight)</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="bottom" data-width="166666">Frequency of Sampling <br/>Monthly total into the digester</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="bottom" data-width="500000">Sampling Method(s)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-width="166666"/>
                <td data-width="166666"/>
                <td data-width="166666"/>
                <td data-width="500000">(a)  Average herd population and American Society of Agricultural and Biological Engineers ASABE D384.2, Manure Production and Characteristics; <br/>(b)  Digester influent pump flow; <br/>(c)  Recorded weight</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-width="166666">Influent total solids concentration (TS)</td>
                <td data-width="166666">Percent (of sample)</td>
                <td data-width="166666">Monthly, depending upon recorded variations</td>
                <td data-width="500000">USGS, Methods for the Determination of Inorganic Substances in Water and Fluvial Sediments, Techniques of Water-Resources Investigations of the United States Geological Survey, Book 5, Chapter A1, Method Number I-3750, "Solids, residue on evaporation at 105 degrees C, total, gravimetric"</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-width="166666">Influent volatile solids (VS) content of manure</td>
                <td data-width="166666">Percent (of TS)</td>
                <td data-width="166666">Monthly, depending upon recorded variations</td>
                <td data-width="500000">U.S. EPA, Methods for the Chemical Analysis of Water and Wastes (MCAWW) (EPA/600/4-79/020), Method Number 160.4, "Volatile Residue by Muffle Furnace"</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-width="166666">Average monthly ambient temperature</td>
                <td data-width="166666">Temperature °C</td>
                <td data-width="166666">Monthly (based on farm averages)</td>
                <td data-width="500000">Closest National Weather Service-certified weather station</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Accreditation of Independent Verifiers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Standards for Accreditation. Independent verifiers may be accredited by the Department to provide verification services as required by project sponsors if the independent verifiers meet the requirements of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Verifier Minimum Requirements. Each accredited independent verifier shall demonstrate knowledge of the following topics:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Utilizing engineering principles;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Quantifying greenhouse gas emissions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Developing and evaluating air emissions inventories;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Auditing and accounting principles;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Knowledge of information management systems;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Knowledge of the requirements of this chapter; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>All other qualifications as may be required by the Department to provide competent verification services as required for individual offset categories.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Organizational Qualifications. Accredited independent verifiers shall demonstrate that they meet the following requirements:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Verifiers shall have no direct or indirect financial relationship with any offset project developer or project sponsor beyond a contract for provision of verification services;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Verifiers shall employ staff with professional licenses, knowledge, and experience appropriate to the specific categories of offset projects that they seek to verify;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Verifiers shall hold a minimum of $1,000,000 of professional liability insurance, and if the insurance is in the name of a related entity, the verifier shall disclose the financial relationship between the verifier and the related entity and provide documentation supporting the description of the relationship; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Verifiers shall demonstrate that they have implemented an adequate management protocol to identify potential conflicts of interest with regard to an offset project, offset project developer, project sponsor, or any other party with a direct or indirect financial interest in an offset project that is seeking or has been granted approval of a consistency application and to remedy any conflicts of interest before providing verification services.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Prequalification of Verifiers. Prospective verifiers may be required to successfully complete a training course, workshop, or test developed or approved by the Department, before submitting an application for accreditation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Application for Accreditation. An application for accreditation may not contain any proprietary information. The application shall include the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The applicant's name, address, email address, telephone number, and facsimile transmission number;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Documentation to support that the applicant has at least 2 years of experience in each of the knowledge areas;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Documentation to support that the applicant has successfully completed all applicable requirements;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A sample of at least one work product that provides supporting evidence that the applicant meets the following applicable requirements:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The work product shall have been produced, in whole or part, by the applicant and shall consist of a final report or other material provided to a client under contract in previous work; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For a work product that was jointly produced by the applicant and another entity, the role of the applicant in the work product shall also include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Documentation that the applicant holds professional liability insurance; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Documentation that the applicant has implemented an adequate management protocol to address and remedy any conflict of interest issues that may arise.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Action on Applications for Accreditation.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Department shall approve or deny a complete application for accreditation within 45 days after submission. Upon approval of an application for accreditation, the independent verifier shall be accredited for a period of 3 years from the date of application approval.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Reciprocity. Independent verifiers accredited in other participating states may be deemed to be accredited at the discretion of the Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>General Requirements for Accredited Verifiers.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Before engaging in verification services for a project sponsor, the accredited verifier shall disclose all relevant information to the Department to allow for an evaluation of potential conflict of interest with respect to an offset project, offset project developer, or project sponsor. The accredited verifier shall disclose information concerning its ownership, past and current clients, related entities, and any other facts or circumstances that have the potential to create a conflict of interest.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Accredited verifiers shall have an ongoing obligation to disclose to the Department any facts or circumstances that may give rise to a conflict of interest with respect to an offset project, offset project developer, or project sponsor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Department may reject a verification report and certification statement from an accredited verifier submitted as part of a consistency application or submitted as part of a monitoring and verification report if the Department determines that the accredited verifier has a conflict of interest related to the offset project, offset project developer, or project sponsor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Department may revoke the accreditation of a verifier at any time upon:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Failure to fully disclose any issues that may lead to a conflict of interest situation with respect to an offset project, offset project developer, or project sponsor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The verifier is no longer qualified due to changes in staffing or other criteria;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Negligence or neglect of responsibilities pursuant to the applicants requirements; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Intentional misrepresentation of data or other intentional fraud.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Awarding and Recording of CO<sub>2</sub> Offset Allowances.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>CO<sub>2</sub> Emissions Offset Projects. Following the issuance of a consistency determination and the approval of a monitoring and verification report, the Department shall award one CO<sub>2</sub> offset allowance for each ton of demonstrated reduction in CO<sub>2</sub> or CO<sub>2</sub> equivalent emissions or sequestration of CO<sub>2</sub>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Department shall record awarded CO<sub>2</sub> offset allowances in the project sponsor's general account.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Deadlines for Submittal of Monitoring and Verification Reports.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For CO<sub>2</sub> emissions offset projects undertaken before January 1, 2009, the project sponsor shall submit the monitoring and verification report covering the pre-2009 period by June 30, 2009.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For CO<sub>2</sub> emissions offset projects undertaken on or after January 1, 2009, the monitoring and verification report shall be submitted within 6 months following the completion of the last calendar year during which the offset project achieved CO<sub>2</sub>e reductions or sequestration of CO<sub>2</sub> for which the project sponsor requests the award of CO<sub>2</sub> offset allowances.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Contents of Monitoring and Verification Reports. For an offset project, the monitoring and verification report shall include the following information:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The project sponsor's name, address, email address, telephone number, facsimile transmission number, and general account number;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The CO<sub>2</sub> emissions reduction or CO<sub>2</sub> sequestration determination including a demonstration that the project sponsor complied with the required quantification, monitoring, and verification procedures and those outlined in the approved consistency application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A signed statement that reads "The undersigned project sponsor hereby confirms and attests that the offset project upon which this monitoring and verification report is based is in full compliance with all applicable requirements. I have been granted all the necessary authority to carry out the duties and responsibilities for the offset project under this subtitle. I understand that eligibility for the award of CO<sub>2</sub> offset allowances is contingent on meeting applicable requirements. I authorize the Department or its agent to audit this offset project for purposes of verifying that the offset project, including the monitoring and verification plan, has been implemented as described in the consistency application that was the subject of a consistency determination by the Department. I understand that this right to audit shall include the right to enter the physical location of the offset project and that I shall make available to the Department at its request all documentation relating to the offset project. I submit to the legal jurisdiction of the State.";</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A certification signed by the project sponsor certifying that all offset projects for which the project sponsor has received offset allowances under the project sponsor's ownership or control, or under the ownership or control of any entity which controls, is controlled by, or has common control with the project sponsor, are in compliance with all applicable requirements of this subtitle in all participating states; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A verification report and certification statement signed by an independent accredited verifier that the independent verifier has reviewed the monitoring and verification report and evaluated the following in relation to applicable requirements:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The adequacy and validity of information supplied by the project sponsor to determine CO<sub>2</sub> emissions reductions or CO<sub>2</sub> sequestration pursuant to applicable requirements;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The adequacy and consistency of methods used to quantify, monitor, and verify CO<sub>2</sub> emissions reductions and CO<sub>2</sub> sequestration in accordance with applicable requirements;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Any other evaluations and verification reviews required by the Department to determine the adequacy and validity of information supplied by the project sponsor to demonstrate that the offset project meets applicable eligibility requirements of this chapter;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Disclosure of any voluntary or mandatory programs, other than this subtitle, to which greenhouse gas emissions data related to the offset project has been, or will be reported; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>For offset projects located in a state or United States jurisdiction that is not a participating state, a demonstration that the project sponsor has complied with all requirements of the cooperating regulatory agency in the state or United States jurisdiction where the offset project is located.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Location for Filing Monitoring and Verification Reports. The monitoring and verification report shall be filed with the same department that issued the consistency determination for the offset project.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Action on Monitoring and Verification Reports.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within 30 days of receipt, the Department shall review the monitoring and verification report for completeness and notify the project sponsor if incomplete.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a determination of incompleteness is made, a project sponsor may resubmit an updated report to the Department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Department shall approve or deny a complete monitoring and verification report within 45 days following receipt of a complete report.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Accreditation of Independent Verifiers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Standards for Accreditation. Independent verifiers may be accredited by the Department to provide verification services as required by project sponsors if the independent verifiers meet the requirements of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Verifier Minimum Requirements. Each accredited independent verifier shall demonstrate knowledge of the following topics:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Utilizing engineering principles;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Quantifying greenhouse gas emissions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Developing and evaluating air emissions inventories;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Auditing and accounting principles;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Knowledge of information management systems;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Knowledge of the requirements of this chapter; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>All other qualifications as may be required by the Department to provide competent verification services as required for individual offset categories.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Organizational Qualifications. Accredited independent verifiers shall demonstrate that they meet the following requirements:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Verifiers shall have no direct or indirect financial relationship with any offset project developer or project sponsor beyond a contract for provision of verification services;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Verifiers shall employ staff with professional licenses, knowledge, and experience appropriate to the specific categories of offset projects that they seek to verify;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Verifiers shall hold a minimum of $1,000,000 of professional liability insurance, and if the insurance is in the name of a related entity, the verifier shall disclose the financial relationship between the verifier and the related entity and provide documentation supporting the description of the relationship; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Verifiers shall demonstrate that they have implemented an adequate management protocol to identify potential conflicts of interest with regard to an offset project, offset project developer, project sponsor, or any other party with a direct or indirect financial interest in an offset project that is seeking or has been granted approval of a consistency application and to remedy any conflicts of interest before providing verification services.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Prequalification of Verifiers. Prospective verifiers may be required to successfully complete a training course, workshop, or test developed or approved by the Department, before submitting an application for accreditation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Application for Accreditation. An application for accreditation may not contain any proprietary information. The application shall include the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The applicant's name, address, email address, telephone number, and facsimile transmission number;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Documentation to support that the applicant has at least 2 years of experience in each of the knowledge areas;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Documentation to support that the applicant has successfully completed all applicable requirements;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A sample of at least one work product that provides supporting evidence that the applicant meets the following applicable requirements:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The work product shall have been produced, in whole or part, by the applicant and shall consist of a final report or other material provided to a client under contract in previous work; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For a work product that was jointly produced by the applicant and another entity, the role of the applicant in the work product shall also include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Documentation that the applicant holds professional liability insurance; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Documentation that the applicant has implemented an adequate management protocol to address and remedy any conflict of interest issues that may arise.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Action on Applications for Accreditation.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Department shall approve or deny a complete application for accreditation within 45 days after submission. Upon approval of an application for accreditation, the independent verifier shall be accredited for a period of 3 years from the date of application approval.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Reciprocity. Independent verifiers accredited in other participating states may be deemed to be accredited at the discretion of the Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>General Requirements for Accredited Verifiers.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Before engaging in verification services for a project sponsor, the accredited verifier shall disclose all relevant information to the Department to allow for an evaluation of potential conflict of interest with respect to an offset project, offset project developer, or project sponsor. The accredited verifier shall disclose information concerning its ownership, past and current clients, related entities, and any other facts or circumstances that have the potential to create a conflict of interest.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Accredited verifiers shall have an ongoing obligation to disclose to the Department any facts or circumstances that may give rise to a conflict of interest with respect to an offset project, offset project developer, or project sponsor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Department may reject a verification report and certification statement from an accredited verifier submitted as part of a consistency application or submitted as part of a monitoring and verification report if the Department determines that the accredited verifier has a conflict of interest related to the offset project, offset project developer, or project sponsor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Department may revoke the accreditation of a verifier at any time upon:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Failure to fully disclose any issues that may lead to a conflict of interest situation with respect to an offset project, offset project developer, or project sponsor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The verifier is no longer qualified due to changes in staffing or other criteria;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Negligence or neglect of responsibilities pursuant to the applicants requirements; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Intentional misrepresentation of data or other intentional fraud.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Awarding and Recording of CO<sub>2</sub> Offset Allowances.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>CO<sub>2</sub> Emissions Offset Projects. Following the issuance of a consistency determination and the approval of a monitoring and verification report, the Department shall award one CO<sub>2</sub> offset allowance for each ton of demonstrated reduction in CO<sub>2</sub> or CO<sub>2</sub> equivalent emissions or sequestration of CO<sub>2</sub>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Department shall record awarded CO<sub>2</sub> offset allowances in the project sponsor's general account.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Deadlines for Submittal of Monitoring and Verification Reports.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For CO<sub>2</sub> emissions offset projects undertaken before January 1, 2009, the project sponsor shall submit the monitoring and verification report covering the pre-2009 period by June 30, 2009.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For CO<sub>2</sub> emissions offset projects undertaken on or after January 1, 2009, the monitoring and verification report shall be submitted within 6 months following the completion of the last calendar year during which the offset project achieved CO<sub>2</sub>e reductions or sequestration of CO<sub>2</sub> for which the project sponsor requests the award of CO<sub>2</sub> offset allowances.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Contents of Monitoring and Verification Reports. For an offset project, the monitoring and verification report shall include the following information:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The project sponsor's name, address, email address, telephone number, facsimile transmission number, and general account number;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The CO<sub>2</sub> emissions reduction or CO<sub>2</sub> sequestration determination including a demonstration that the project sponsor complied with the required quantification, monitoring, and verification procedures and those outlined in the approved consistency application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A signed statement that reads "The undersigned project sponsor hereby confirms and attests that the offset project upon which this monitoring and verification report is based is in full compliance with all applicable requirements. I have been granted all the necessary authority to carry out the duties and responsibilities for the offset project under this subtitle. I understand that eligibility for the award of CO<sub>2</sub> offset allowances is contingent on meeting applicable requirements. I authorize the Department or its agent to audit this offset project for purposes of verifying that the offset project, including the monitoring and verification plan, has been implemented as described in the consistency application that was the subject of a consistency determination by the Department. I understand that this right to audit shall include the right to enter the physical location of the offset project and that I shall make available to the Department at its request all documentation relating to the offset project. I submit to the legal jurisdiction of the State.";</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A certification signed by the project sponsor certifying that all offset projects for which the project sponsor has received offset allowances under the project sponsor's ownership or control, or under the ownership or control of any entity which controls, is controlled by, or has common control with the project sponsor, are in compliance with all applicable requirements of this subtitle in all participating states; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A verification report and certification statement signed by an independent accredited verifier that the independent verifier has reviewed the monitoring and verification report and evaluated the following in relation to applicable requirements:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The adequacy and validity of information supplied by the project sponsor to determine CO<sub>2</sub> emissions reductions or CO<sub>2</sub> sequestration pursuant to applicable requirements;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The adequacy and consistency of methods used to quantify, monitor, and verify CO<sub>2</sub> emissions reductions and CO<sub>2</sub> sequestration in accordance with applicable requirements;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Any other evaluations and verification reviews required by the Department to determine the adequacy and validity of information supplied by the project sponsor to demonstrate that the offset project meets applicable eligibility requirements of this chapter;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Disclosure of any voluntary or mandatory programs, other than this subtitle, to which greenhouse gas emissions data related to the offset project has been, or will be reported; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>For offset projects located in a state or United States jurisdiction that is not a participating state, a demonstration that the project sponsor has complied with all requirements of the cooperating regulatory agency in the state or United States jurisdiction where the offset project is located.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Location for Filing Monitoring and Verification Reports. The monitoring and verification report shall be filed with the same department that issued the consistency determination for the offset project.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Action on Monitoring and Verification Reports.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within 30 days of receipt, the Department shall review the monitoring and verification report for completeness and notify the project sponsor if incomplete.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a determination of incompleteness is made, a project sponsor may resubmit an updated report to the Department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Department shall approve or deny a complete monitoring and verification report within 45 days following receipt of a complete report.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Environment Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|1-101">1-101</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|1-404">1-404</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|2-103">2-103</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|2-1002">2-1002</cite>(g), Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-07-17">Effective date: July 17, 2008 (35:14 Md. R. 1247)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-01-06"><cite path="|26|09|03|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective January 6, 2014 (40:26 Md. R. 2165)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-01-06"><cite path="|26|09|03|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective May 18, 2009 (36:10 Md. R. 717); January 6, 2014 (40:26 Md. R. 2165)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-05-03"><cite path="|26|09|03|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective December 28, 2009 (37:4 Md. R. 336); amended permanently effective May 3, 2010 (37:9 Md. R. 674)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-01-06"><cite path="|26|09|03|.04|D.">Regulation .04D</cite> amended effective May 18, 2009 (36:10 Md. R. 717); January 6, 2014 (40:26 Md. R. 2165)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-01-06"><cite path="|26|09|03|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective January 6, 2014 (40:26 Md. R. 2165)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-05-18"><cite path="|26|09|03|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective May 18, 2009 (36:10 Md. R. 717)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-05-03"><cite path="|26|09|03|.06|H.">Regulation .06H</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective December 28, 2009 (37:4 Md. R. 336); amended permanently effective May 3, 2010 (37:9 Md. R. 674)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-05-18"><cite path="|26|09|03|.07|G.">Regulation .07G</cite>, I amended effective May 18, 2009 (36:10 Md. R. 717)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-05-03"><cite path="|26|09|03|.07|G.">Regulation .07G</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective December 28, 2009 (37:4 Md. R. 336); amended permanently effective May 3, 2010 (37:9 Md. R. 674)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-01-06"><cite path="|26|09|03|.09">Regulation .09</cite> amended effective January 6, 2014 (40:26 Md. R. 2165)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-05-18"><cite path="|26|09|03|.09|E.">Regulation .09E</cite> amended effective May 18, 2009 (36:10 Md. R. 717)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-12-31" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective December 31, 2018 (45:26 Md. R. 1249)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
