<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>Licensure</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in §B, of this regulation, these regulations apply to a person seeking to practice dietetics in the State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Exceptions. These regulations do not apply to a person who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provides nonmedical nutrition services and information to the public while:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Employed by or operating a health, weight loss, or fitness program,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Employed by or operating a health food store,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Employed by or operating a business that sells health products, including dietary supplements, foods, or food materials, or provides nonmedical nutritional information or distributes nutritional literature, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Conducting classes or disseminating information relative to nonmedical nutrition;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Distributes nutritional literature; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Provides services related only to the purchasing, preparation, and service of food to groups of people.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|56|01|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Accredited institution” means a college or university accredited by a regional educational accrediting association through the Council for Higher Education Accreditation and the United States Department of Education.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Act” means the Maryland Licensed Dietitian-Nutritionists Act, Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|5-101">5-101</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|5-502">5-502</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2-1)</num>
        <text>Aids in the Practice of Dietetics.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Aids in the practice of dietetics” means an individual directly or indirectly supervised by a licensed dietitian, licensed nutritionist, or licensed physician who assists in the practice of dietetics by following instructions in:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Gathering and recording information for the purposes of assessing individual and community food practices and for assessing nutritional status using anthropometric, biochemical, clinical, dietary, and demographic data;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Providing nutrition information as part of preventive or restorative health care if the nutrition care plan, priorities, goals, and objectives for meeting nutrient needs were developed by a licensed practitioner; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Applying standards for quality control in the areas of menu planning and procurement, food selection, production, assembly, distribution, and food safety and sanitation to ensure high quality nutritional care.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Aids in the practice of dietetics” does not include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Evaluation of nutritional status;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Formulation of nutrition standards;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Development or modification of diet instructions;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Evaluation of patient progress;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Development of menu patterns for therapeutic diets; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Establishing therapeutic diet production policies and procedures.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Applicant” means an individual who applies for licensure to practice dietetics in the State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Board” means the State Board of Dietetic Practice.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4-1)</num>
        <text>“Certified nutrition specialist” means an individual certified by the Board for Certification of Nutrition Specialists.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Commission” means the Commission on Dietetic Registration of the American Dietetic Association.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Coordinated undergraduate program” means a dietetic program that combines didactic and clinical experience within a 4-year baccalaureate program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Department” means the Maryland Department of Health.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Dietetic practice” means a practice through which the principles derived from integrating knowledge of food, biochemistry, physiology, management science, behavioral science, and social science to human nutrition are applied. Dietetic practice includes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Assessing individual and community food practices, and nutritional status for clinical, research, and program planning purposes using:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Anthropometric data,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Biochemical data,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Clinical data,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Dietary data, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Demographic data;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Developing, establishing, and evaluating nutritional care plans that establish priorities, goals, and objectives for meeting nutrient needs for individuals or groups;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Conducting nutrition counseling and education as a part of preventive or restorative health care throughout the life cycle;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Determining, applying, and evaluating standards for food and nutrition services; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Applying scientific research to the role of food for the maintenance of health and the treatment of disease.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“License” means, unless the context requires otherwise, a license issued by the Board to practice dietetics.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>“Licensed dietitian-nutritionist (LDN)” means an individual who is licensed by the Board to practice dietetics in the State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Medical Device.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Medical device” means a health care product used in the diagnosis, treatment, or prevention of disease.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Medical device” does not mean:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A drug;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A surgical or dental instrument;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Physical therapy equipment;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>X-ray apparatus; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>A component part or accessory of any of the items listed in <cite path="10|56|01|.02|B.|(11)|(b)">§B(11)(b) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>“Medical nutrition” means nutritional advice or counsel provided to an individual by a licensee, in the licensee's professional capacity, that is designed for an individual to alleviate a specific physiological complaint, condition, or symptom.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>“Nonmedical nutrition” means the application of basic principles of nutrition to food selection for the purpose of maintaining health.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>“Registered dietitian (RD)” means an individual registered by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>“Supervision” means the management of an individual who aids in the practice of dietetics by a licensed dietitian-nutritionist who may or may not be on the premises.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Application Procedures.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In order to obtain a license, the applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Submit to the Board an application on the form provided by the Board;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Pay to the Board the application fee set forth in <cite path="|10.56.02">COMAR 10.56.02</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Submit evidence that the applicant:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is a registered dietitian, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Meets the requirements of Regulations .04, .05, and .07 of this chapter.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board may not consider an application completed until it has received all required materials.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the application is not complete with all required materials within 30 days after the Board receives the signed application form, the Board:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall notify the applicant of the additional materials required; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>May deny the application.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Academic Requirements.</heading>
    <text>For initial licensure as a dietitian or nutritionist, an applicant shall submit proof of one of the following to the Board:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Registration through the Commission on Dietetic Registration of the American Dietetic Association and receipt of, at a minimum, a degree from a college or university accredited by an educational accrediting association as required by the Commission on Dietetic Registration, including a minimum of 24 semester hours in:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The field of human nutrition;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Food and nutrition;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Dietetics; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Food systems management with at least 3 semester hours from each of the following areas:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Upper-division human nutrition related to disease;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Upper-division food service systems management;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Biochemistry or physiological chemistry, or advanced normal human nutrition; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Food science; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Certification by the Board for Certification of Nutrition Specialists and receipt of a master's or doctoral degree from a college or university accredited by an educational accrediting association as required by the Commission on Dietetic Registration in nutrition sciences with emphasis in:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Human nutrition;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Food and nutrition;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Dietetics;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Community nutrition;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Public health nutrition; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Equivalent academic training such as nutrition education and food science.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Experience Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Before licensure, an applicant shall have completed a preplanned professional experience program as described under <cite path="|10|56|01|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An applicant for licensure shall be considered to have met the experience requirements of this regulation if the applicant is a registered dietitian or a certified nutrition specialist at the time of application.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|56|01|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>A Preplanned, Professional Experience Program.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant shall complete a Board-approved supervised, continuous, preplanned professional experience program. The applicant shall ensure that the experience program is accomplished within a span of 30 months and includes the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A minimum of 100 hours shall be completed in each of the following areas:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Assessing individual and community food practices and nutritional status using anthropometric, biochemical, clinical, dietary, and demographic data for clinical research and program planning purposes;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Developing, establishing, and evaluating nutritional care plans that establish priorities, goals, and objectives for meeting nutrient needs for individuals or groups;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Nutrition counseling and education as part of preventive or restorative health care throughout the life cycle;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Determining, applying, and evaluating standards for food and nutrition services; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Applying scientific research to the role of food in the maintenance of health and the treatment of disease;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An additional 400 hours shall be completed within any combination of the five areas described in <cite path="10|56|01|.06|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>A-1.</num>
      <text>The requirements of <cite path="10|56|01|.06|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> may be satisfied in whole or in part by the clinical or research experience gained while completing a master's or doctoral degree if the experience:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is in human nutrition; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When combined with experience independently qualifying under §A(1) and (2) of this regulation, meets the overall 900-hour requirements.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The preplanned professional experience program shall be under the supervision of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A licensed dietitian;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A licensed nutritionist;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A licensed physician;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A registered dietitian;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A certified nutrition specialist; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>An individual with a doctoral degree with a major course of study in:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Human nutrition;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Nutrition education;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Food and nutrition;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Dietetics; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Food systems management that is conferred by a U.S. regionally accredited college or university.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Each supervisor shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Plan all work assignments, instructions, and dietetic learning experiences to strengthen the competence of the applicant within the scope of practice as described in §A(1) and (2) of this regulation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Keep a record of the applicant's:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Activities;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Program plan;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Evaluation instruments, including the number of hours spent fulfilling curriculum plans; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Transcript of the final evaluation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Receive prior approval from the Board of the preplanned professional experience program or have the program approved by the Commission;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Complete the program within 30 months after the applicant begins the program; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Submit documentation of the program on the documentation form provided by the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Board may waive the requirement for prior approval and preplanning under <cite path="10|56|01|.06|D.|(1)">§D(1) of this regulation</cite> if it determines that either or both could not reasonably have been obtained.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Examination Procedures.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Unless waived by the Board as provided in §§B and C of this regulation, an applicant shall pass a Board-approved written examination before licensure.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Waiver of Examination. The Board may waive the examination requirement for an applicant who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Pays the application fee as provided in <cite path="|10.56.02">COMAR 10.56.02</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A registered dietitian;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A certified nutrition specialist; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Licensed in another state or country to practice dietetics and submits to the Board proof of current licensure which was obtained after passing an examination that the Board determines to be comparable to the examination for which the applicant is seeking waiver.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Types of Examination. To meet the examination requirements, an applicant shall successfully pass an examination approved by the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|56|01|.08">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Action on Application.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board shall review all completed applications within 90 days of receipt of the completed application.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board may delegate the initial review of applications to a committee of the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>At the next regular meeting of the Board, the Board may approve or deny an application reviewed by the Board or its designee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Upon review of an application, the Board shall either:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Approve the applicant for licensure; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Deny a license.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Ineligibility or Denial of Applications.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board may:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Determine an applicant is ineligible for a license if the applicant has:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Not completed the academic requirements in <cite path="|10|56|01|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Not completed the experience requirements in <cite path="|10|56|01|.05">Regulation .05 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Failed the examination requirements in <cite path="|10|56|01|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Failed to remit a fee;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Failed to properly complete the application form;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Deny a license if the applicant has:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Violated the Act or any provision or these regulations; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Been shown to have a lack of good moral character.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the Board denies a license under <cite path="10|56|01|.08|E.|(1)|(b)">§E(1)(b) of this regulation</cite>, the Board or the Board's designee shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Provide the applicant written notification of the Board's intent to deny and the basis for that denial; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Notify the applicant of the applicant's right to request a formal hearing to appeal the denial.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An applicant who has been determined to be ineligible may reapply and shall submit with the new application proof of compliance with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Board regulations; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The applicable provisions of the Act in effect at the time of the new application.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Issuance of License.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If the Board approves an applicant for a license, the Board shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Send the applicant a notice specifying that the applicant has qualified for a license; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Upon receipt of the license fee, issue a license to the applicant.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Board shall include on each license the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Full name of the licensee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Serial number assigned by the Board to the licensee; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Signature of the Chairman of the Board, under the seal of the Board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Unless the Board suspends or revokes the license of a licensed dietitian or licensed nutritionist, the license is effective for at least 2 years from the date issued and authorizes the person to practice dietetics while the license is effective.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|56|01|.09">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Renewal.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board may not renew a license until the Comptroller of Maryland has verified that the individual has paid all undisputed taxes and unemployment insurance contributions, or arranged for repayment, as required by <cite path="|10.31.02">COMAR 10.31.02</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A licensee shall renew the license every 2 years.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Board shall send each licensee a renewal notice that states the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Date on which the current license expires;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Latest date by which the renewal application and documentation can be received by the Board in order for the renewal license to be issued before the current license expires; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Amount of the renewal fee as specified in <cite path="|10.56.02">COMAR 10.56.02</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>At least 30 days before the current license or registration expires, the Board shall send the renewal notice by electronic means or first-class mail to the last known electronic or physical address of the licensee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The failure to receive a renewal notice does not excuse a licensee from complying with <cite path="10|56|01|.09|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Licensees shall satisfactorily complete the minimum continuing education requirements set forth under <cite path="|10.56.05">COMAR 10.56.05</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Licensees applying for renewal are required to meet the current education requirements and be in good standing with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Commission on Dietetic Registration; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Board for Certification of Nutrition Specialists.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>After the expiration date of the license, the dietitian-nutritionist is no longer licensed to practice dietetics in the State.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Reinstatement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board shall reinstate an individual whose license has expired if the individual:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is otherwise entitled to be licensed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Meets the renewal requirements of this chapter and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|5-309">Health Occupations Article, §5-309, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Pays the license reinstatement and renewal fees as specified in <cite path="|10.56.02">COMAR 10.56.02</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Satisfactorily completes the minimum continuing education requirements set forth under <cite path="|10.56.05">COMAR 10.56.05</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Applies to the Board for reinstatement of a license within 5 years of the license expiration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board may not reinstate the license of an individual who fails to apply for reinstatement within 5 years after the license expiration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An individual who fails to apply for reinstatement of a license within 5 years after expiration, may become licensed by meeting the requirements for obtaining an initial license under this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Inactive Status.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|5-309">Health Occupations Article, §5-309, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, a request by an active licensee to transfer a license to inactive status shall be granted upon receipt of the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Completed Board-approved inactive status application; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Payment of the required, non-refundable inactive status fee set forth in <cite path="|10.56.02">COMAR 10.56.02</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An individual:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>May apply for inactive status only if the individual’s license is still active and in good standing at the time the inactive status application request is made; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>On inactive status is not authorized to and may not practice as a licensed dietitian-nutritionist.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An individual seeking to be reactivated shall be required, as a condition of reactivation, to submit:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Proof of having completed the minimum continuing education requirements set forth under <cite path="|10.56.05">COMAR 10.56.05</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Payment of a reactivation fee set forth in <cite path="|10.56.02">COMAR 10.56.02</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Change of Mailing Address, Legal Name, or Email Address.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A licensed dietitian-nutritionist shall give the Board written notice within 30 days of a change of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Mailing address;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Legal name; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Email address if the licensee has previously submitted an email address to the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Failure to notify the Board of any change of mailing address, legal name, or email address within 30 days of the change may result in a $50 fee as set forth under <cite path="|10.56.02">COMAR 10.56.02</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|5-205">5-205</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|5-301">5-301</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|5-303">5-303</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|5-306">5-306</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|5-308">5-308</cite>––<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|5-310">5-310</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1988-02-09">Regulations <cite path="|10|56|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|56|01|.09">.09</cite>, Licensure, adopted as an emergency provision effective February 9, 1988 (15:5 Md. R. 612); emergency status extended at 15:18 Md. R. 2144; emergency status expired December 31, 1988</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1988-08-08">Regulations .04 and .07 amended as an emergency provision effective August 8, 1988 (15:18 Md. R. 2144); emergency status expired December 31, 1988</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-02-20" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|10|56|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|56|01|.08">.08</cite>, General Regulations, adopted effective February 20, 1989 (16:3 Md. R. 344)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1991-02-04"><cite path="|10|56|01|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective February 4, 1991 (18:2 Md. R. 150)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-08-18"><cite path="|10|56|01|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective November 7, 1994 (21:22 Md. R. 1878); September 9, 1996 (23:18 Md. R. 1317); October 29, 2001 (28:21 Md. R. 1856); August 13, 2007 (34:16 Md. R. 1432); August 18, 2025 (52:16 Md. R.847)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-08-18"><cite path="|10|56|01|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective November 7, 1994 (21:22 Md. R. 1878); October 29, 2001 (28:21 Md. R. 1856); August 18, 2025 (52:16 Md. R.847)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-08-18"><cite path="|10|56|01|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective October 29, 2001 (28:21 Md. R. 1856); August 18, 2025 (52:16 Md. R.847)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1996-09-09"><cite path="|10|56|01|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite> amended effective February 4, 1991 (18:2 Md. R. 150); September 9, 1996 (23:18 Md. R. 1317)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-08-13"><cite path="|10|56|01|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite>, B amended effective August 13, 2007 (34:16 Md. R. 1432)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-10-29"><cite path="|10|56|01|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective October 29, 2001 (28:21 Md. R. 1856)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-10-29"><cite path="|10|56|01|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective February 4, 1991 (18:2 Md. R. 150); October 29, 2001 (28:21 Md. R. 1856)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-11-07"><cite path="|10|56|01|.06|A.">Regulation .06A</cite> amended effective November 7, 1994 (21:22 Md. R. 1878)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-02-05"><cite path="|10|56|01|.06|B.">Regulation .06B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective February 5, 1992 (19:4 Md. R. 469); emergency status expired August 7, 1992</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-08-18"><cite path="|10|56|01|.06|B.">Regulation .06B</cite> amended effective August 8, 1992 (19:9 Md. R. 879); October 29, 2001 (28:21 Md. R. 1856); August 13, 2007 (34:16 Md. R. 1432); August 18, 2025 (52:16 Md. R. 847)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-11-07"><cite path="|10|56|01|.06|E.">Regulation .06E</cite> amended effective November 7, 1994 (21:22 Md. R. 1878)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-10-29"><cite path="|10|56|01|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective October 29, 2001 (28:21 Md. R. 1856)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-11-07"><cite path="|10|56|01|.07|B.">Regulation .07B</cite>, H, I amended effective November 7, 1994 (21:22 Md. R. 1878)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-10-29"><cite path="|10|56|01|.08">Regulation .08</cite> amended effective October 29, 2001 (28:21 Md. R. 1856)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-08-18"><cite path="|10|56|01|.08|D.">Regulation .08D</cite> amended and Regulation .09 adopted as an emergency provision effective December 5, 1989 (16:26 Md. R. 2782); adopted permanently effective May 14, 1990 (17:9 Md. R. 1092); August 18, 2025 (52:16 Md. R. 847)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-11-07"><cite path="|10|56|01|.08|E.">Regulation .08E</cite> amended effective November 7, 1994 (21:22 Md. R. 1878)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-10-29"><cite path="|10|56|01|.09|C.">Regulation .09C</cite> amended effective January 6, 1992 (18:26 Md. R. 2830); October 29, 2001 (28:21 Md. R. 1856)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-08-13"><cite path="|10|56|01|.09">Regulation .09</cite> repealed and new Regulation .09 adopted effective August 13, 2007 (34:16 Md. R. 1432)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-08-18"><cite path="|10|56|01|.09">Regulation .09</cite> repealed and new Regulation .09 adopted effective August 18, 2025 (52:16 Md. R. 847)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-08-18"><cite path="|10|56|01|.10">Regulation .10</cite> adopted effective August 18, 2025 (52:16 Md. R. 847)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-08-18"><cite path="|10|56|01|.11">Regulation .11</cite> adopted effective August 18, 2025 (52:16 Md. R. 847 )</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-08-18"><cite path="|10|56|01|.12">Regulation .12</cite> adopted effective August 18, 2025 (52:16 Md. R. 847)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
