<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>General</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Applicability.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The regulations contained in this subtitle govern the use of energy allocation systems which allocate to an occupant of an individual dwelling unit a portion of the cost of gas and electric energy consumed in an apartment house based upon devices which indirectly approximate use of gas or electric energy.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An energy allocation system may not be used unless approved by the Commission under this subtitle.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>This subtitle does not apply to submeters which are governed by the provisions of <cite path="|20.25">COMAR 20.25</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this subtitle, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Apartment house" means a building containing more than two dwelling units all of which are rented primarily for a non-transient use, with rentals paid at intervals of one week or longer. Apartment house includes residential condominiums and cooperatives, whether rented or owner occupied.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Approximate energy use" means the gas or electricity use within a dwelling unit as determined by an energy allocation system.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Commission" means the Public Service Commission of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Dwelling unit" means a room or rooms suitable for occupancy as a residence containing kitchen and bathroom facilities.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Energy allocation equipment" means a measuring device or other equipment used to determine approximate energy use by a means other than the actual measurement of consumption of gas or electricity.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Energy allocation system" means a method of determining the approximate energy use consumed within a dwelling unit with the use of a measuring device.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Estimated energy costs" means the cost of gas or electricity which is reasonably expected to be allocated to an occupant under an energy allocation system.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Measurement unit" means the measure of the characteristic recorded by a measuring device.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Measuring device" means a device which measures furnace operating or running time, baseboard pipe temperature or other characteristics used to determine approximate energy use.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Occupant" means the resident of a dwelling unit in an apartment house.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Owner" means a person or entity holding legal title to an apartment house or the board of directors or similar body of a residential condominium or cooperative. Owner includes an authorized agent of an owner.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>"Utility" means the public service company which supplies gas or electric service to the apartment house.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>"Vendor" means the entity which provides the energy allocation equipment and billing services to an owner.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Filing Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An owner shall file an application with the Commission for approval of an energy allocation system.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The application shall include the following information:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The name and address of the owner;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The name and address of the general partner, if the owner is a partnership;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The name and address of the management agent, if any;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The name and address of the apartment house;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The number of individual dwelling units;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A description of the energy allocation system, including a technical description of the energy allocation equipment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>A description of the method for converting a measurement unit into approximate energy use;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>A description of the method for calculating the energy costs directly billed to an occupant, including the calculation of a per unit energy cost;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>A copy of all written information provided to an occupant including lease terms; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>A copy of the proposed billing format.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Distribution of Application.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The owner shall submit to the Commission an original and 14 copies of the application.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The owner shall mail a copy of the application to the Consumer Protection Division, Office of The Attorney General, c/o "Energy Allocation Systems".</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Waiver of Regulations.</heading>
    <text>The Commission may waive all or a portion of this subtitle if unreasonable hardship results.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-304">Public Utilities Article, §7-304, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1988-07-19">Previously codified as <cite path="20.26.01.01">20.26.01.01</cite>—.03 and <cite path="20.26.02.01">20.26.02.01</cite> and .02, adopted as an emergency provision effective July 19, 1988 (15:17 Md. R. 2046); emergency status extended at 15:27 Md. R. 3125</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-05-15" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|20|26|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|20|26|01|.05">.05</cite> adopted effective May 15, 1989 (16:9 Md. R. 995)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
