<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Disclosure of Estimated Energy Costs and Complaint Procedure</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>General Requirement.</heading>
    <text>An owner shall disclose in writing to a current or prospective occupant prior to the execution or modification of a lease:</text>
    <para>
      <num>(1)</num>
      <text>That the owner will directly bill the occupant for energy costs as determined by an energy allocation system; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>The estimated energy costs reasonably expected to be incurred by the occupant calculated in a manner as described in <cite path="|20|26|03|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Disclosure of the Use of Energy Allocation System.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The owner shall disclose in writing to a current or prospective occupant all material aspects of the energy allocation system including, but not limited to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The measurement unit recorded by the measuring device;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The method for converting measurement units into the approximate energy use and the energy costs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The method for calculating the per unit charge for energy consumed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>How questions and complaints of an occupant concerning bills will be answered by the owner; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A statement that the energy allocation system:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Approximates the amount of gas or electricity consumed in the dwelling unit by use of an energy allocation or conversion formula, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Does not measure the actual use of gas or electricity.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Estimated Energy Costs.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An owner who has previously determined the approximate energy usage for a dwelling unit by the use of an energy allocation system, including use of a system before the promulgation of the regulations, shall disclose to a current or prospective occupant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The highest monthly energy cost billed to the same dwelling unit in a month the dwelling unit was leased during the preceding 12 months;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The lowest monthly energy cost billed to the same dwelling unit in a month the dwelling unit was leased during the preceding 12 months;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The average monthly energy cost billed to the same dwelling unit for the preceding 12 months including only months the dwelling unit was leased for the entire month; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The average monthly energy costs billed to similar sized leased dwelling units in the preceding 12 months.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the owner has not previously used an energy allocation system within the apartment house:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The owner shall disclose estimated energy costs in the following priority based on:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Actual billing to similar sized dwelling units in other apartment houses within the same apartment house complex,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The actual operating experience of the vendor for similar sized dwelling units in other apartment house complexes of comparable age, size, equipment, and geographic location, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A square footage allocation derived from gas or electric bills received by the owner from the utility with a reasonable allowance for common usage and, if necessary, seasonally adjusted;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The owner shall provide the estimated energy costs required in §B(1) in terms of an average monthly bill, the highest monthly bill, and the lowest monthly bill.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Disclosures of Influences on Energy Usage and Costs.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The owner shall provide to the current or prospective occupant the document "Influences on Energy Usage and Costs" prepared by the Consumer Protection Division.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The owner shall disclose in writing to the prospective or current occupant the nature and extent of the weatherization of the apartment unit including, but not limited to the extent of insulation of walls and ceiling, the age of the energy device (for example, furnace) and the directional exposure (for example, north, south) of the unit.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Procedure for Handling Occupant Complaints.</heading>
    <text>If an occupant contacts the owner concerning the correctness of the energy costs billed to an occupant:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The owner shall provide to the occupant a complaint form available from the Commission and request the occupant to complete the form;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The owner shall provide the occupant with the name and address of the apartment house manager or other person who will receive the completed complaint form;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The owner shall provide the occupant with written confirmation from the vendor within 15 business days of receiving a written complaint from an occupant that the bill does not contain a clerical, mathematical, or computational error;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the bill in question does not contain an error described in §C, the owner shall inspect the energy allocation equipment and the dwelling unit of the occupant;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The owner shall provide the occupant with a copy of the written results of the inspections conducted pursuant to the requirement in §D, prepared on forms available from the Commission, within 30 days of the receipt of the complaint;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The failure of the occupant to complete the occupant complaint form does not relieve the owner of the requirements of this section;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The owner shall also provide to the occupant in writing, along with the written reports required under §E, what, if any, remedial actions have been or will be taken.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Referral to Consumer Protection Division.</heading>
    <text>If the complaint has not been resolved, the owner shall advise the occupant in writing that a formal complaint concerning an amount billed to the occupant pursuant to an energy allocation system may be filed with the Consumer Protection Division, Office of the Attorney General.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-304">Public Utilities Article, §7-304, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1988-07-19">Previously codified as <cite path="20.26.04.01">20.26.04.01</cite>—.04 and <cite path="20.26.05.01">20.26.05.01</cite> and .02, adopted as an emergency provision effective July 19, 1988 (15:17 Md. R. 2046); emergency status extended at 15:27 Md. R.</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-05-15" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|20|26|03|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|20|26|03|.06">.06</cite> adopted effective May 15, 1989 (16:9 Md. R. 995)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
