<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>12</num>
  <heading>Use of Quiet Room and Use of Restraint</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>These regulations govern the use of quiet rooms and restraint in all facilities as defined in Health-General Article, §§10-101(e) and 10-701, Annotated Code of Maryland. These regulations are supplemental to any other applicable law and regulation. In the event of conflict between these regulations and any other regulations or laws, the more stringent apply.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Category I Restraint.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Category I restraint" means a device identified by the facility which limits a patient's mobility to the extent that the patient would not be able to independently reposition himself or herself or would otherwise be rendered helpless in an emergency.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Category I restraint" includes, but is not limited to, four-point restraints and safety suits.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Category II restraint" means any device which is not considered by the facility as a category I restraint and includes, but is not limited to, mittens and camisoles.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Chief executive officer (CEO)" means the individual responsible for the overall management of a facility.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Child" means an individual younger than 12 years old.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Clinical director" means the psychiatrist in charge of the clinical care of all psychiatric patients in the facility.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Emergency situation" means a situation in which a patient's behavior poses a serious and imminent danger to the physical safety of self or others.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Facility" means any public or private hospital, clinic, or other institution that provides or purports to provide treatment or other services for a mental disorder, except an acute general hospital that does not have a separately identified inpatient psychiatric service.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Full view" means the unobstructed view by the assigned staff of a restrained patient.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Patient" means an individual receiving services for a mental disorder in a facility and includes any student receiving care and treatment in that facility.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Physician" means an individual who is authorized to practice medicine under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 14, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Protective device" means any adaptive or assistive device or devices which restrict the movement of the whole or a portion of a patient's body for the purpose of preventing unintentional harm to self or others or which are used for promoting or maintaining normative body functions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>"Quiet room" means an unlocked room that patients are not physically prevented from leaving, which is designated for patients' voluntary use to allow them time out of the company of other patients.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>"Registered nurse" means an individual who is licensed to practice registered nursing under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 8, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>Restraint.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Restraint" means a mechanical device or devices approved by the facility which restrict the movement of the whole or a portion of a patient's body for the purpose of preventing intentional harm to self or others and is grouped into two categories, category I and category II.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Restraint" does not include helmets when used as a sole form of restraint, chemotherapy, protective devices, or cold wet sheet packs used as a treatment procedure ordered by a physician.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>"Seclusion" means the involuntary confinement of a patient under the direction of a physician or registered nurse alone in a room which a patient is physically prevented from leaving.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>"Serious disruption to a therapeutic environment" means imminent danger of damage to the physical environment, or behavior of such a grave or protracted nature that significantly interferes with the emotional well-being of other patients or with their treatment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>"Treatment team" means the patient's treatment team as defined in <cite path="10.21.03.02|C.">COMAR 10.21.03.02C</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|21|12|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Use of Restraint.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Staff authorized under the provisions of <cite path="|10|21|12|.05|A.">Regulation .05A of this chapter</cite> shall use a restraint only to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Prevent and reduce serious, destructive, and damaging actions by a patient to the patient or to another;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Prevent serious disruption of the therapeutic environment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Staff may not use a restraint:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>As a mode or course of treatment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>As punishment; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>For convenience.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Staff shall use a restraint:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In a humane, safe, and effective manner; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Without intent to harm or create undue discomfort to the patient.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Staff authorized under the provisions of <cite path="|10|21|12|.05|A.">Regulation .05A of this chapter</cite> may order the use of a restraint only if the physician, following a clinical evaluation of the patient, determines that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The patient's behavior poses:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An emergency situation; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A serious disruption to the therapeutic environment; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Less restrictive or alternative approaches have been considered and, if clinically indicated and reasonable, have been attempted, and are considered ineffective.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The approaches referred to in <cite path="10|21|12|.03|D.|(2)">§D(2) of this regulation</cite> may include, but are not limited to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Clinical interventions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Quiet room; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Medication or medications.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Protective Device Use.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>When the definition of a restraint or a protective device is in dispute, in each case under discussion, the clinical director or the clinical director's physician designee shall clarify and document in the patient's medical record the device's correct purpose.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The patient's treatment team shall document in the treatment plan the team's rationale for use of a protective device.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|21|12|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Procedures in the Use of Restraint.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A physician who is responsible either for the care of the patient or for assessment of the appropriateness of a restraint or, when the appropriate physician is not readily available to assess the patient, a registered nurse shall conduct a clinical evaluation of the patient to determine:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Whether an emergency situation is present; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The degree to which the patient presents a serious disruption to the therapeutic environment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Before using restraint, the physician or registered nurse shall assess whether less restrictive alternative approaches are appropriate and, if so, whether and what approaches have been attempted.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>When a physician, as identified in <cite path="10|21|12|.05|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, is immediately available, the physician shall be responsible for determining a patient's need for a restraint and make the decision whether to restrain.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Authorization in the Absence of a Physician.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>When a physician, as identified in <cite path="10|21|12|.05|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, is not immediately available, a registered nurse shall determine a patient's need for restraint and may initiate and direct the use of restraint.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Within 1 hour of the implementation of the restraint, a physician shall give a written or verbal order for any restraint initiated by a registered nurse and, at that time, shall make the clinical determination to continue or to discontinue the restraint.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|21|12|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Placement of Patient in Restraint.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>When possible, staff shall advise a patient, in a nonthreatening manner, that continuation of a specific behavior may result in the use of restraint.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>When a physician or registered nurse determines that the use of a restraint is appropriate, staff involved shall make a reasonable effort to verbally persuade the patient to be cooperative with the restraint.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Staff shall apply a restraint only in accordance with the facility's policy and procedure manual.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>To the extent consistent with the patient's safety and the safety of others:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Staff shall place the patient in the restraint in as dignified a manner as the situation permits, using the least amount of physical force necessary; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>As necessary, additional staff shall participate in the placement of a patient in seclusion.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Unless a physician or registered nurse determines that it is unsafe to do so, staff shall permit the patient to wear all or a portion of the patient's own clothes or another form of attire.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Staff shall search the patient for potentially harmful objects.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>If staff determine a need for objects to be removed pursuant to <cite path="10|21|12|.06|F.">§F of this regulation</cite>, staff shall ask the patient, in a nonthreatening manner, to surrender the objects.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Unless contraindicated for safety reasons, staff shall permit the patient to wear eyeglasses, hearing aids, dentures, or prosthetic devices.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>When placing a patient in a restraint, staff shall inspect each restraining device and ensure that each restraining device is safely and securely applied.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>As necessary, staff shall ensure that each restraint is padded to provide appropriate protection for the patient.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Limitations and Placement of Children in Restraint.</heading>
    <text>In addition to the requirements outlined in this chapter, when:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Restraining a child, staff may not use four-point restraints; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Applying or repositioning a restraint, staff shall avoid the application of force on long bone joints.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Clinical Interventions During Restraint.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Regardless of the physical setting in which the patient is placed, at a minimum, one staff member shall be assigned continuously while the patient is in a category I restraint.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>While the patient is restrained, in order to provide appropriate clinical care, at a minimum, staff clinically trained to do so shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Keep the patient in full view at all times;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Protect the patient from harm by others;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Closely observe the patient at least every 15 minutes, and document each observation by the observer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Unless contraindicated by circumstances as assessed and documented by a physician or registered nurse, at least hourly, make and document personal contact with the patient for the purpose of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Determining if the patient has any special needs which need attention;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Checking circulation of the extremities restrained;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Adjusting the restraint; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Realigning the body or massaging the extremities restrained, or both;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Unless contraindicated by circumstances as assessed and documented by a physician or registered nurse, offer or provide the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Full range of motion, every 2 hours;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Toilet facilities, at least every 2 hours;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Bathing and oral hygiene, at least once during a 24-hour period;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Meals, at the regularly scheduled hours and under the supervision of nursing personnel; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Fluids, at least every 2 hours; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>As clinically indicated, record temperature, pulse, blood pressure, and respirations.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>At least once every 2 hours, a physician or registered nurse shall assess the appropriateness of continuing the restraint and document the factors supporting the assessment in the patient's medical record.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Unless circumstances suggest a medical problem may exist, staff may not disrupt a patient's sleep during the night to implement the clinical procedures described in §§B and C of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|21|12|.09">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Limitations on Restraint and Continuous Restraint.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Staff may not initiate "standing" or "as needed" orders for restraint.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A physician may write an order for restraint for a period of up to, but not more than, 24 hours.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If a patient in restraint requires continuous restraint for over a 24-hour period, a physician shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Conduct a face-to-face evaluation of the patient to determine whether continuous restraint is appropriate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Document the evaluation in the patient's medical record; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the patient is restrained under the provisions of §§D and E of this regulation, carry out the requirements of §C(1) and (2) of this regulation every 24 hours throughout the period that the patient continues in restraint.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If restraint is required for a period greater than a continuous 48 hours, the physician may continue restraint only:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In conjunction with the requirements outlined in this chapter;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the treating physician's documented clinical opinion is that the patient, if released from restraint, would continue to present a danger to self or others or would present a serious disruption to the therapeutic environment; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>With the authorization of the clinical director or the clinical director's physician designee, neither of whom may be the treating physician.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Upon a request from a patient's treating physician, the clinical director or the clinical director's designee identified in <cite path="10|21|12|.09|D.|(3)">§D(3) of this regulation</cite>, following a face-to-face evaluation of the patient who is restrained, may authorize continued restraint:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For category I restraints, for additional periods of not more than 48 hours each over the initial 48-hour period that a patient is restrained under the provisions of <cite path="10|21|12|.09|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For category II restraints:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>For an initial period of not more than 7 days over the initial 48-hour period that a patient is restrained under the provisions of <cite path="10|21|12|.09|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For additional periods of not more than 7 days each over the 7-day period of restraint authorized under <cite path="10|21|12|.09|E.|(2)|(a)">§E(2)(a) of this regulation</cite>, if the patient's treatment team:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Recommends continued restraint and documents the recommendation in the patient's medical record; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Incorporates into the treatment plan and any subsequent revisions to the plan the proposed strategies to accomplish discontinuance of the restraint.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Each time that restraint is authorized under the provisions of <cite path="10|21|12|.09|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>, the clinical director or the clinical director's designee identified in <cite path="10|21|12|.09|D.|(3)">§D(3) of this regulation</cite> shall countersign the physician's order in the patient's medical record for continued restraint.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Treatment Team Involvement.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Minimally, at regularly scheduled meetings, the patient's treatment team shall examine the use of restraint for that patient.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Within 7 working days from the initiation of continuous restraint, regardless of whether the patient remains in restraint, the treatment team shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>When applicable, review the appropriateness of the continued use of restraint;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Establish and implement a plan calculated to eliminate the need for further restraint; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Identify a team member who shall explain to the patient the potential risks and benefits of continuous restraint.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Documentation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Restraint Orders. A physician shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To initiate the use of restraint:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Enter an order in the patient's medical record; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Authorize an order to be written by a registered nurse on the physician's order sheet in the patient's medical record:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Indicating that physician's verbal order for restraint; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Directing the release of the patient and the rationale for that release;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Countersign all verbal orders within 24 hours of the order's being written; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Include in the order for restraint:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The date and time that the order was written;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The specific type of restraint to be used;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The maximum duration of restraint from the time that the restraint was initiated;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The specific rationale for restraint;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Special precautions, if any, to safeguard the patient;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The physician's signature; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>In the case of a verbal order, the names of both the ordering physician and the registered nurse who received the verbal order.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>As soon as possible after implementation, but not later than the close of the shift, staff shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Document the implementation of restraint in the patient's medical record; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Include in the documentation the following information:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A description of the specific behavior leading to restraint;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Whether and which less restrictive techniques were used, and, if not, why not;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Whether a formal call for facility staff response was required, the names of staff assisting in the restraint, and the circumstances while restraining the patient;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The readily observable physical condition of the patient;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The date and time of the restraint and signature of the recorder;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Whether the patient was permitted to wear the patient's own clothes or other attire and, if not, the reason or reasons for this; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>A description of any physical injury to either the patient or others resulting from placement of the patient in restraint.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>While a patient is restrained, staff shall document the clinical interventions employed, including those listed in <cite path="|10|21|12|.08">Regulation .08 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Release from Restraint.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>When a physician clinically determines that a patient is to be released from restraint, the physician shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Order the release and write, sign, and date a note indicating the rationale for the release; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If verbally ordering the release, write, sign, and date the note not later than 24 hours after a verbal order to release.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When a registered nurse clinically determines that the release of the patient before the maximum period specified on a physician's order is appropriate, the registered nurse shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Order termination of the restraint with or without a physician's order, unless the physician's order specifically requires physician concurrence with the termination; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Document, sign, and date the rationale for the termination of restraint in the patient's medical record.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|21|12|.11">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Use of Quiet Room.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Patient Request.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A patient may request the use of a quiet room and, unless clinically contraindicated, may be granted use of a quiet room.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Unless staff terminates use of the quiet room for clinical reasons, the patient may terminate self-initiated use of the quiet room at any time.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Staff Request.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>When staff, permitted by the facility to initiate and terminate use of a quiet room, determine that the use of the quiet room is clinically indicated, staff may request that a patient voluntarily enter into the quiet room.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Staff may not coerce a patient into entering the quiet room.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>When the patient enters the quiet room, staff shall discuss with the patient:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The recommended length of stay in the quiet room;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The behaviors expected of the patient before and upon return to the milieu; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The primary interventions to be initiated if the use of the quiet room is terminated by the patient before the time recommended by staff or is determined to be ineffective.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Staff shall determine the need for removal of any harmful objects in the room or from the patient.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If staff determine a need for objects to be removed pursuant to <cite path="10|21|12|.11|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, staff shall ask the patient, in a nonthreatening manner, to surrender the objects.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>While a quiet room is in use, the staff shall assure that the quiet room door is not locked or in a position that prevents a patient from exiting the room voluntarily.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Observation and Documentation. Staff shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be assigned to monitor the patient and the safety of the environment while a patient is in the quiet room;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When the quiet room is used as a clinical intervention, observe the patient at least once every 30 minutes and document the observation in the patient's medical record; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>At least every 2 hours, evaluate the effectiveness of the outcome and document the clinical rationale for continued use of the quiet room.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A physician shall review the use of the quiet room after 6 hours and, if use of the quiet room is continued, at least every 24 hours after that.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Use of a quiet room may be terminated at any time:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Upon the decision of the patient; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>As clinically determined by staff.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|21|12|.12">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Quality Assurance.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The clinical director or the clinical director's designee shall review daily all uses of restraint and investigate unusual or possibly unwarranted patterns of use.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The physician involved in the restraint may not function in the capacity outlined in <cite path="10|21|12|.12|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A facility shall identify a committee to review periodically, but not less than quarterly, the use of restraint to assure that the standards maintained by the facility are, at a minimum, consistent with this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Staff who implement orders for restraint:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall have documented annual training in the proper use of restraint including training for special populations which include, but are not limited to, children and the elderly; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>May not implement orders for restraint until trained by the facility to do so unless, in an emergency situation, the safety of the patient or others is threatened.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The facility's chief executive officer or the chief executive officer's designee is responsible for assuring that the restraint devices used in that facility are maintained in accordance with acceptable standards for hygiene and safety.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If seclusion is used in conjunction with restraint, staff shall comply with regulations for the use of seclusion.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Procedures Pertaining to Complaints.</heading>
    <text>Complaints about the individual application of this chapter may be addressed through any patient grievance mechanism.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|21|12|.14">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Variance with Standards.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Excluding the prohibition described in <cite path="10|21|12|.14|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, staff may not vary from the standards identified in this chapter unless the variation is for an extreme crisis.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>There may not be any variance with standards established in this regulation and in Regulations .03 and .04, .06B—G and I—J, .07, .09A, .11, .12A and D—F, .13, and .14 of this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Staff shall document, on the facility's variance report, a variance with standards permitted under this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The CEO shall rule on and document each variance permitted in <cite path="10|21|12|.14|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> to determine whether the variance was:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An extreme crisis;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A deviation from the facility's procedure; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A problem in the facility's policy which is correctable by administrative action.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The CEO shall assure that the facility's quality assurance process incorporates a monthly review of any variance permitted in <cite path="10|21|12|.14|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health-General Article, §§10-101(e) and 10-701, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-10-25">Effective date: October 25, 1993 (20:21 Md. R. 1654)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
