<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>13</num>
  <heading>Use of Quiet Room and Use of Seclusion</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>These regulations govern the use of quiet rooms and seclusion in all facilities as defined in Health-General Article, §§10-101(e) and 10-701, Annotated Code of Maryland. These regulations are supplemental to any other applicable law and regulation. In the event of conflict between these regulations and any other regulations or laws, the more stringent apply.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Chief executive officer (CEO)" means the individual responsible for the overall management of a facility.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Clinical director" means the psychiatrist in charge of the clinical care of all psychiatric patients in that facility.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Emergency situation" means any situation in which a patient's behavior poses a serious and imminent danger to the physical safety of self or others.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Facility" means any public or private hospital, clinic, or other institution that provides or purports to provide treatment or other services for a mental disorder, except an acute general hospital that does not have a separately identified inpatient psychiatric service.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Patient" means an individual receiving services for a mental disorder in a facility and includes any student receiving care and treatment in that facility.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Physician" means an individual who is authorized to practice medicine under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 14, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Quiet room" means an unlocked room that patients are not physically prevented from leaving, which is designated for patients' voluntary use to allow them time out of the company of other patients.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Registered nurse" means an individual who is licensed to practice registered nursing under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 8, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Seclusion" means the involuntary confinement of a patient under the direction of a physician or registered nurse alone in a room which a patient is physically prevented from leaving.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Serious disruption to a therapeutic environment" means imminent danger of damage to the physical environment, or behavior of such a grave or protracted nature that it significantly interferes with the emotional well-being of other patients or with their treatment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Treatment team" means the patient's treatment team as defined in <cite path="10.21.03.02|C.">COMAR 10.21.03.02C</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|21|13|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Use of Seclusion.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Staff authorized under the provisions of <cite path="|10|21|13|.04|A.">Regulation .04A of this chapter</cite> shall use seclusion only to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Prevent and reduce serious, destructive, and damaging actions by a patient to the patient or to another; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Prevent serious disruption of the therapeutic environment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Staff may not use seclusion:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>As a mode or course of treatment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>As punishment; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>For the convenience of staff.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Staff shall conduct seclusion:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In a humane, safe, and effective manner; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Without intent to harm or create undue discomfort to the patient.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Staff authorized under the provisions of <cite path="|10|21|13|.04|A.">Regulation .04A of this chapter</cite> may order the use of seclusion only if that staff person, following a clinical evaluation of the patient, determines that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The patient's behavior poses:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An emergency situation; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A serious disruption to the therapeutic environment; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Less restrictive or alternative approaches have been considered and, if clinically indicated and reasonable, have been attempted, and are considered ineffective.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The approaches referred to in <cite path="10|21|13|.03|D.|(2)">§D(2) of this regulation</cite> may include, but are not limited to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Clinical interventions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Quiet room; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Medication or medications.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|21|13|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Procedures in the Use of Seclusion.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A physician who is responsible either for the care of the patient or for assessment of the appropriateness of seclusion or, when the appropriate physician is not readily available to assess the patient, a registered nurse shall conduct a clinical evaluation of the patient to determine:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Whether an emergency situation is present; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The degree to which the patient presents a serious disruption to the therapeutic environment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Before instituting seclusion, the physician or registered nurse shall assess whether less restrictive alternative approaches are appropriate and, if so, whether and what approaches have been attempted.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>When a physician, as identified in <cite path="10|21|13|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, is immediately available, the physician shall be responsible for determining a patient's need for seclusion and make the decision whether to seclude.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Authorization in the Absence of a Physician.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>When a physician, as identified in <cite path="10|21|13|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, is not immediately available, a registered nurse shall determine a patient's need for seclusion and may initiate and direct the use of seclusion.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Within 1 hour of the implementation of the seclusion, a physician shall give a written or verbal order for any seclusion initiated by a registered nurse and, at that time, shall make the clinical determination to continue or discontinue the seclusion.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|21|13|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Placement of a Patient in a Seclusion Room.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>When possible, staff shall advise a patient, in a nonthreatening manner, that continuation of a specific behavior may result in the use of seclusion.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>When a physician or registered nurse determines that the use of seclusion is appropriate, staff involved shall make a reasonable effort to verbally persuade the patient to enter the seclusion room.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>To the extent consistent with the patient's safety and the safety of others:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Staff shall place the patient in the seclusion room in as dignified a manner as the situation permits, using the least amount of physical force necessary; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>As necessary, additional staff shall participate in the placement of a patient in seclusion.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Unless a physician or registered nurse determines that it is unsafe to do so, staff shall permit the patient to wear all or a portion of the patient's own clothes or another form of attire.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Staff shall search the patient for potentially harmful objects.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If staff determines a need for objects to be removed pursuant to <cite path="10|21|13|.05|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>, staff shall ask the patient, in a nonthreatening manner, to surrender the objects.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Unless contraindicated for safety reasons, staff shall permit the patient to wear eyeglasses, hearing aids, dentures, or prosthetic devices.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Staff shall inspect the seclusion room for potentially dangerous conditions and, as appropriate, shall fully secure the room.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Clinical Interventions During Seclusion.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>While the patient is secluded, in order to provide appropriate clinical care, at a minimum, clinically trained staff shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Observe the patient at least every 15 minutes, and document each observation by the observer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Unless contraindicated by circumstances as assessed and documented by a physician or registered nurse, at least hourly, make and document personal contact with the patient for the purpose of determining if the patient has any special needs which need attention;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Unless contraindicated by circumstances as assessed and documented by a physician or registered nurse, offer or provide the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Toilet facilities, at least every 2 hours;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Bathing and oral hygiene, at least once during a 24-hour period;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Meals, at the regularly scheduled hours and under the supervision of nursing personnel; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Fluids, at least every 2 hours; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>As clinically indicated, record temperature, pulse, blood pressure, and respirations.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>At least once every 2 hours, a physician or registered nurse shall assess the appropriateness of continuing the seclusion and document the factors supporting the assessment in the patient's medical record.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Unless circumstances suggest a medical problem may exist, staff may not disrupt a patient's sleep during the night to implement the clinical procedures described in §§A and B of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|21|13|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Limitations on Seclusion and Continuous Seclusion.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Staff may not initiate "standing" or "as needed" orders for seclusion.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Excluding requirements outlined in <cite path="10|21|13|.07|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>, each order or subsequent order for seclusion may be written for a period up to, but not more than, 24 hours.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If a patient in seclusion requires continuous seclusion for over a 24-hour period, a physician shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Conduct a face-to-face evaluation of the patient to determine whether continuous seclusion is appropriate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Document the evaluation in the patient's medical record; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the patient is secluded under the provisions of <cite path="10|21|13|.07|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>, carry out the requirements of §C(1) and (2) of this regulation every 24 hours throughout the period that the patient continues in seclusion.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If seclusion is required for a period greater than a continuous 48 hours, the physician may continue seclusion only:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In conjunction with the requirements outlined in this chapter;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the treating physician's clinical opinion is that the patient, if released from seclusion, would continue to present a danger to self or others or would present a serious disruption to the therapeutic environment; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>With the authorization of the clinical director or the clinical director's physician designee, neither of whom may be the treating physician.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Following a request from a patient's treating physician, the clinical director or the clinical director's designee identified in <cite path="10|21|13|.07|D.|(3)">§D(3) of this regulation</cite>, following a face-to-face evaluation of the patient in seclusion, may authorize continued seclusion:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For an additional 48 hours over the initial 48-hour period that a patient is secluded under the provisions of <cite path="10|21|13|.07|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For each period of 7 days over the 48-hour period authorized under <cite path="10|21|13|.07|E.|(1)">§E(1) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Each time that seclusion is authorized under the provisions of <cite path="10|21|13|.07|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>, the clinical director or the clinical director's designee identified in <cite path="10|21|13|.07|D.|(3)">§D(3) of this regulation</cite> shall countersign the physician's order in the patient's medical record for continued seclusion.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Treatment Team Involvement.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Minimally, at regularly scheduled meetings, the patient's treatment team shall review the use of seclusion for that patient.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Within 7 working days from the initiation of continuous seclusion, regardless of whether the patient remains in seclusion, the treatment team shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>When applicable, review the appropriateness of the continued use of seclusion;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Establish and implement a plan calculated to eliminate the need for further seclusion; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Identify a team member who shall explain to the patient the potential risks and benefits of continuous seclusion.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Documentation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Seclusion Orders. A physician shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To initiate the use of seclusion:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Enter an order in the patient's medical record; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Authorize an order to be written by a registered nurse on the physician's order sheet in the patient's medical record:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Indicating that physician's verbal order for seclusion; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Directing the release of the patient and the rationale for that release;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Countersign all verbal orders within 24 hours of the order's being written; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Include in the order for seclusion:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The date and time that the order was written;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The maximum duration of seclusion from the time that the seclusion was initiated;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The specific rationale for seclusion;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Special precautions, if any, to safeguard the patient;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The physician's signature; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>In the case of a verbal order, the names of both the ordering physician and the registered nurse who received the verbal order.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>As soon as possible after implementation, but not later than the close of the shift, staff shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Document the implementation of seclusion in the patient's medical record; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Include in the documentation the following information:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A description of the specific behavior leading to seclusion;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Whether and which less restrictive techniques were used, and, if not, why not;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Whether a formal call for facility staff response was required, the names of staff assisting in the seclusion, and the circumstances while secluding the patient;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The readily observable physical condition of the patient;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The date and time of the seclusion and signature of the recorder;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Whether the patient was permitted to wear the patient's own clothes or other attire and, if not, the reason or reasons for this; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>A description of any physical injury to either the patient or others resulting from placement of the patient in seclusion.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>While a patient is in seclusion, staff shall document in the patient's medical record the clinical interventions employed, including those listed in <cite path="|10|21|13|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Release from Seclusion.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>When a physician clinically determines that a patient is to be released from seclusion, the physician shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Order the release and write, sign, and date a note indicating the rationale for the release; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If verbally ordering the release, write, sign, and date the note not later than 24 hours after a verbal order to release.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When a registered nurse clinically determines that the release of the patient before the maximum period specified on a physician's order is appropriate, the registered nurse shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Order termination of the seclusion with or without a physician's order, unless the physician's order specifically requires physician concurrence with the termination; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Document, sign, and date the rationale for the termination of seclusion in the patient's record.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|21|13|.09">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Use of Quiet Room.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Patient Request.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A patient may request the use of a quiet room and, unless clinically contraindicated, may be granted use of a quiet room.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Unless staff terminates use of the quiet room for clinical reasons, the patient may terminate self-initiated use of the quiet room at any time.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Staff Request.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>When staff, permitted by the facility to initiate and terminate use of a quiet room, determine that the use of the quiet room is clinically indicated, staff may request that a patient voluntarily enter into the quiet room.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Staff may not coerce a patient into entering the quiet room.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>When the patient enters the quiet room, staff shall discuss with the patient:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The recommended length of stay in the quiet room;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The behaviors expected of the patient before and upon return to the milieu; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The primary interventions to be initiated if the use of the quiet room is terminated by the patient before the time recommended by staff or is determined to be ineffective.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Staff shall determine the need for removal of any harmful objects in the room or from the patient.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If staff determine a need for objects to be removed pursuant to <cite path="10|21|13|.09|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, staff shall ask the patient, in a nonthreatening manner, to surrender the objects.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>While a quiet room is in use, the staff shall assure that the quiet room door is not locked or in a position that prevents a patient from exiting the room voluntarily.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Observation and Documentation. Staff shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be assigned to monitor the patient and the safety of the environment while a patient is in the quiet room;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When the quiet room is used as a clinical intervention, observe the patient at least once every 30 minutes and document the observation in the patient's medical record; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>At least every 2 hours, evaluate the effectiveness of the outcome and document the clinical rationale for continued use of the quiet room.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A physician shall review the use of the quiet room after 6 hours and, if use of the quiet room is continued, at least every 24 hours after that.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Use of a quiet room may be terminated at any time:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Upon the decision of the patient; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>As clinically determined by staff.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|21|13|.10">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Quality Assurance.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The clinical director or the clinical director's designee shall review daily all uses of seclusion and investigate unusual or possibly unwarranted patterns of use.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The physician involved in the seclusion may not function in the capacity outlined in <cite path="10|21|13|.10|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A facility shall identify a committee to review periodically, but not less than quarterly, the use of seclusion to assure that the standards maintained by the facility are, at a minimum, consistent with this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Staff who implement orders for seclusion:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall have documented annual training in the proper use of seclusion including training for special populations which include, but are not limited to, children and the elderly; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>May not implement orders for seclusion until trained by the facility to do so unless, in an emergency situation, the safety of the patient or others is threatened.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Standards for a Seclusion Room.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The CEO or the CEO's designee is responsible for assuring that the seclusion room or rooms in the facility are maintained in accordance with acceptable standards for hygiene and safety.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Staff shall ensure that each seclusion room:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Unless clinically contraindicated and the record reflects that assessment, has a mattress provided;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>At the beginning of each shift, is inspected and maintained for proper temperature, ventilation, safety, lighting, sanitation, and freedom from dangerous conditions; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Is fitted with a means of observation that affords staff a view of the entire room and permits clinical staff periodically to observe the patient.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If restraint is used in conjunction with seclusion, staff shall also comply with regulations for use of restraint.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Procedures Pertaining to Complaints.</heading>
    <text>Complaints about the individual application of this chapter may be addressed through any patient grievance mechanism.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|21|13|.12">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Variance with Standards.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Excluding the prohibition described in <cite path="10|21|13|.12|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, staff may not vary from the standards identified in this chapter unless the variation is for an extreme crisis.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>There may not be any variance with standards established in this regulation and in Regulations .03 and .04, .05B — E and G, .07A, .09, .10A, D, E(1), and F, .11, and .12 of this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Staff shall document, on the facility's variance report, a variance with standards permitted under this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The CEO shall rule on and document each variance permitted in <cite path="10|21|13|.12|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> to determine whether the variance was:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An extreme crisis;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A deviation from the facility's procedure; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A problem in the facility's policy which is correctable by administrative action.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The CEO shall assure that the facility's quality assurance process incorporates a monthly review of any variance permitted in <cite path="10|21|13|.12|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health-General Article, §§10-101(e) and 10-701, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-10-25">Effective date: October 25, 1993 (20:21 Md. R. 1654)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
