<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>31</num>
  <heading>Maryland Mental Health AND Substance Use Disorder Registry and Referral System</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose and Effective Date.</heading>
    <text>Effective January 27, 2023, there is a Maryland Mental Health and Substance Use Disorder Registry and Referral System to provide a statewide system through which health care providers can identify and access available inpatient and outpatient mental health and substance use services for patients in a seamless manner.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter applies to:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Hospitals under Health-General Article, Title 19, Subtitle 3, Annotated Code of Maryland;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Freestanding medical facilities under Health-General Article, Title 19, Subtitle 3(a), Annotated Code of Maryland; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Any other provider type designated by the Department by issuance of a transmittal sent to all designated providers.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Department” means the Maryland Department of Health.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Facility” means a hospital, freestanding medical facility, or provider designated by the Department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Hospital” means a general or special hospital licensed under Health-General Article, Title 19, Subtitle 3, Annotated Code of Maryland, and <cite path="|10.07.01">COMAR 10.07.01</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Maryland Mental Health and Substance Use Disorder Registry and Referral System” or “Bed Registry and Referral System” means the system operated by the Department through which health care providers can identify and access available inpatient and outpatient mental health and substance use services for patients.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Use.</heading>
    <text>A facility shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Refer an individual who may require additional care coordination for inpatient, outpatient, or community-based behavioral health services, after undergoing an initial psychiatric evaluation, no later than 48 hours after arrival at the facility at a phone number or website address designated by the Department through written directives to implement the Bed Registry and Referral System; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Provide all necessary patient information, including, but not limited to, diagnosis and level of care recommendations to the respective care coordination centers.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Daily Reporting.</heading>
    <text>A facility shall report current bed availability and census information, and any additional relevant information requested by the Department, to populate the inpatient psychiatric bed board as necessary to keep the information updated, but not less than three times per day, during the following periods:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>9 a.m. to 12 p.m.;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>1 p.m. to 3 p.m.; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>4 p.m. to 7 p.m.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Penalties.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A hospital that violates this chapter is subject to the fines, penalties, and actions specified in Health-General Article, Title 19, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A provider who violates this chapter is subject to the fines, penalties, and actions specified in Health-General Article, Title 7.5, Annotated Code of Maryland, and <cite path="|10.63">COMAR 10.63</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health-General Article, §7.5-802, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-07-26">Regulations <cite path="|10|21|31|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|21|31|.05">.05</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective January 27, 2023 (50:4 Md. R. 119); expired effective July 26, 2023</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-06-24" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|10|21|31|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|21|31|.06">.06</cite> adopted effective June 24, 2024 (51:12 Md. R. 619)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
