<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>04</num>
  <heading>Work Rules</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|26|04|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Committee on Work Rules.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Chairman shall appoint one consumer member, one member representing the steamship industry, and one pilot member to serve on the Committee on Work Rules.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Association shall submit to the Committee all proposed changes in the Association's work rules that affect pilot list administration, appointments, assignment intervals, or relief pilots.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Committee may meet in person or through a conference call to consider and discuss whether any of the proposed changes affect safe operations of vessels by Maryland pilots and, if so, what action should be taken on them.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Within 15 days of the submission, the Committee shall notify the Association whether it has determined that any of the proposed changes affect safe operations of vessels by Maryland pilots, and if so, whether those changes have been preliminarily approved or have been referred to the full Board for its consideration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Association may immediately implement the changes which have been preliminarily approved, subject to the Board's subsequent review.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Committee shall promptly report to the Board on the changes in the work rules that it has:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Preliminarily approved; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Referred to the Board for its consideration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The Board shall consider the proposed changes referred to it by the Committee, as well as those changes preliminarily approved by the Committee, at its next scheduled business meeting.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Work rule changes approved by the Board under <cite path="09|26|04|.01|G.">§G of this regulation</cite> shall go into effect immediately upon approval, unless the work rule change specifies a different date.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Work rule changes that had been implemented as a result of preliminary approval by the Committee and that have been subsequently disapproved by the Board shall be discontinued at the earliest possible time after the Board's action.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>The Committee and the Board may not take a position on proposed changes that the Committee determines do not affect safe operations of vessels by Maryland pilots.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo|11-205">Business Occupations and Professions Article, §11-205, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-12-11">Effective date: December 11, 2003 (30:24 Md. R. 1740)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-05-31"><cite path="|09|26|04|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective May 31, 2010 (37:11 Md. R. 765)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
