<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>General Regulations</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>This chapter sets out the requirements and procedures for the registration of household goods movers.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Consumer” means the person who entered into a written contract with a household goods mover for loading, packing, moving, transporting, or storing household goods.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Department” means the Maryland Department of Labor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Household goods” means personal property of the consumer used for personal, family, or household purposes.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Household goods movers” means a person who provides household goods moving services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Household Goods Moving Services.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Household goods moving services“ means the loading, packing, moving, transporting, storing while in transit, unloading, or otherwise taking possession or control from a consumer of household goods for the purpose of moving them to another location at the direction of the consumer for a fee.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Household goods moving services” does not include moving household goods for disposal or destruction.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Registration fee” means the annual fee paid by an applicant or registrant, as applicable, in connection with the issuance or renewal of a registration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Secretary” means the Secretary of the Department, or the Secretary’s designee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“State” means the State of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|30|01|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Application.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A person who intends to provide household goods moving services shall submit an application for registration on the form approved by the Department.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The form shall include at least the following information:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The applicant’s name and all trade names under which the applicant intends to provide household goods moving services in the State;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The applicant’s physical address, telephone number, and e–mail address;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The name of all persons with at least 25 percent ownership in the applicant’s business;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Previous applications:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>For those identified under <cite path="09|30|01|.03|B.|(3)">§B(3) of this regulation</cite> if that person has previously applied for registration for another entity; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Identification of that person and the disposition of the application for the other entity;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The applicant’s Federal Employee Identification Number;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The name of the applicant’s resident agent in the State, if any;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The applicant’s U.S. Department of Transportation or State Department of Transportation number, as applicable;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Insurance carrier and policy number showing liability and cargo coverage with the minimum standards in 49 C.F.R. Part 387.303;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Proof of workers’ compensation coverage for all covered employees;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>A certificate of status, issued by the Maryland Department of Assessment and Taxation, or its equivalent, indicating the business is in good standing and dated not earlier than 30 days before the date of the application; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Other information that may be required by the Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An application for registration shall be accompanied by an application fee in the amount provided in <cite path="|09|30|01|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Registration.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Department shall issue to each qualified applicant who submits a completed application form and the required fee the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A unique registration number; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A registration certificate valid for one year.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A registrant is required to keep a copy of the registration in each of the trucks owned by the registrant when the vehicle is used to perform household goods moving services.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|30|01|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Renewal of Registration.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Unless a registration is renewed for a 1-year term as provided in this regulation, the registration expires on the expiration date.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>At least 1 month before a registration expires:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Department shall mail or electronically transmit to the registrant the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A renewal application form; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A notice that states:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The date on which the current registration expires; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The amount of the renewal fee.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If an electronic transmission under <cite path="09|30|01|.05|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite> is returned to the Department as undeliverable, the Department shall mail to the registrant, at the last known address of the registrant, the materials required under paragraph (1) of this subsection within 10 business days of the date the Department received the notice that the electronic transmission was undeliverable.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Before a registration expires, the registrant periodically may renew it for an additional 1–year term, if the registrant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Submits to the Department a renewal application on the form that the Department provides;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Signs the renewal application under oath;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Updates the information submitted in the original application and states that the information is current;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Complies with each requirement applicable to the original application; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Pays the renewal fee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Failure of the Department to timely notify a registrant of registration renewal does not affect a registrant’s obligation to file a renewal application prior to the expiration of the registration and payment of a renewal fee.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Reinstatement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If a registrant fails to renew a license for any reason, no household goods mover services may be offered or provided until the registration is reinstated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A request for reinstatement shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be in writing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Be on the form required by the Department; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Include payment of the reinstatement fee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|30|01|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Fees.</heading>
    <text>The following non-refundable fees shall be charged by the Department:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Original registration application review—$250;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Original registration—$325;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Registration renewal—$325; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Late Renewal—$75, in addition to the fee set forth in <cite path="09|30|01|.07|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Violations.</heading>
    <text>A person or registrant who violates any of the following provisions regarding the household goods movers registration requirements may be subject to a civil penalty of up to $5,000:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Failure to register as a mover of household goods;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Providing false information on the registration application;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Failure to comply with requirements set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr">Business Regulation Article, Title 8.5, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Failure to comply with requirements set forth in these regulations.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Failure to Respond.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If an applicant or registrant receives from the Department a written communication requesting a response, the applicant or registrant shall respond in writing within 30 days of the date of such communication.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Department shall send a written communication by first class mail or email to the last address or email address furnished to the Department by an applicant or registrant.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>It is the responsibility of an applicant or registrant to notify the Department in writing if there has been a change in the applicant’s or registrant’s address.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Failure to respond as required by this regulation may be considered by the Secretary or the Secretary’s designee to be a violation of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|8">Business Regulation Article, §8</cite>.5-106, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Notice of Change of Licensing Information.</heading>
    <text>In addition to the requirements of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr">Business Regulation Article, Title 8.5, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, an applicant or registrant shall notify the Secretary or the Secretary’s designee, in writing, within 15 days of any change of the:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Business name the applicant or registrant;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Business address of the applicant or registrant; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Address of the business through which an applicant or registrant will provide or provides licensee household goods mover services.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Business Regulation Article, §§8.5-103, 8.5-104, 8.5-105.1, 8.5-105 , 8.5-106, and 8.5-107, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-07-21">Effective date: July 21, 2025 (52:14 Md. R. 712)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
