<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>06</num>
  <heading>Pay Phone Service</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|45|06|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as provided under <cite path="20|45|06|.01|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, this chapter applies to a person operating a pay phone.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The provisions of Regulations <cite path="|20|45|06|.03">.03</cite>—<cite path="|20|45|06|.07">.07</cite> of this chapter do not apply to a person operating a pay phone in a State, local, or federal correctional facility.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Registration.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Registration. Prior to providing pay phone service, a person shall complete and file a pay phone service provider registration form provided by the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Annual Registration Report.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A pay phone service provider shall file an annual registration report with the Commission by April 1 of each year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The annual registration report shall be on a form provided by the Commission and include the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Name of the pay phone service provider;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Location address of each active pay phone owned or operated by the pay phone service provider;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Telephone number of each active pay phone owned or operated by the pay phone service provider; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Local exchange carrier for each active pay phone owned or operated by the pay phone service provider.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Proprietary Information. A pay phone service provider may request that documents filed under §§A and B of this regulation be designated as proprietary.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Annual Assessment. A pay phone service provider shall pay the annual assessment required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-110">Public Utilities Article, §2-110, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|45|06|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Pay Phone Service Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Local Calls.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>After an initial 10 minutes of pay phone use for a local call, a pay phone service provider may impose an additional per-minute charge for the use of the pay phone.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The pay phone service provider shall post the initial charge and any additional per-minute charges as required under <cite path="|20|45|06|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If an additional per-minute charge is associated with a pay phone, the pay phone service provider shall ensure that the pay phone has:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A verbal warning to a user that the initial paid call period is ending; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Instructions on how to continue the call.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Incoming Calls. Except as provided in <cite path="20|45|06|.03|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, all pay phones shall receive incoming calls without charge.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Blocking Incoming Calls. If approved by the Commission, a pay phone service provider may block incoming calls to a pay phone.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Posting and Informational Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Posting Required. A pay phone service provider shall prominently and conspicuously post on or near each pay phone notification of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The proper dialing sequence to complete a call;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The local coin rate or a procedure to obtain free rate information for an exclusively card-operated or coinless pay phone;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The name and address of the pay phone service provider and the operator service provider;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The pay phone service provider's and the operator service provider's toll free number or an equivalent free local or speed-dial number for maintenance and refunds;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A toll free number for the current long distance carrier;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A statement that the Commission has authority over the pay phone service provider, the long distance carrier, and the operator service provider;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The Commission's toll free number; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>If approved by the Commission under <cite path="|20|45|06|.03|C.">Regulation .03C of this chapter</cite>, a statement that incoming calls are blocked.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Directory Assistance Charges. A pay phone service provider shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Post a notice or verbally inform a pay phone user of a charge for directory assistance; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Post notification of the procedure to obtain free rate information for calls to directory assistance.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Attestation to Local Exchange Company.</heading>
    <text>A pay phone service provider shall provide to a local exchange company providing dial tone to the pay phone service provider's pay phone a one-time written attestation that the pay phone service provider has or will obtain the appropriate certification, permit, or authorization from the responsible government entity, property owner, or lessee for placement of a pay phone in Maryland.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Directory Assistance Charges and Charge-Free Calls.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Directory Assistance. A pay phone service provider may charge a user for a directory assistance call.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Charge-Free Calling. A pay phone service provider shall permit a user of its pay phone to reach any of the following without payment:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A toll free number;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Universal Emergency Number 911 Services by dialing "9-1-1";</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The telecommunications relay service; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A local operator by dialing "Zero-Minus" (0-).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|45|06|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Equipment Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Telephone Directories. A pay phone service provider shall provide both white page and yellow page telephone directories on an annual basis for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All indoor pay phone locations; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Outdoor pay phone locations when requested by the site owner.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Height and Hearing Requirements. A pay phone service provider shall comply with Maryland and federal height and hearing aid compatibility regulations when installing a pay phone.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Access to Interexchange Carriers. A pay phone service provider shall ensure that its pay phone:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Permits access to all interexchange carriers; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Allows completion of local and long distance calls in Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Coin Capability.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as provided under <cite path="20|45|06|.07|D.|(2)">§D(2) of this regulation</cite>, a pay phone service provider shall ensure that its pay phone is capable of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Accepting nickels, dimes, and quarters; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Handling sent-paid long distance other than sent-paid person-to-person calls, unless the pay phone is connected to a network-controlled coin line.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A coinless pay phone that is exclusively card operated is not required to accept coin payment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Coin Return. A pay phone service provider shall ensure that a coin-operated pay phone returns a deposited coin if a called telephone number is busy or not answered.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Amplified Handset. A pay phone service provider shall install:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An amplified handset on a pay phone that replaces a phone with an amplified handset; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>One pay phone with an amplified handset for every four pay phones in a single phone bank.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Penalties.</heading>
    <text>Failure to comply with the provisions of this chapter may result in the imposition of a civil penalty or other sanctions under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu">Public Utilities Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, including the disconnection of the pay phone service and the revocation of a pay phone service provider's registration.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Public Utilities Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-113">2-113</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-121">2-121</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|4-201">4-201</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|4-203">4-203</cite>,and 4-301, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1976-01-01">Effective date: January 1, 1976 (Order No. 61496)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-02-26">Regulations <cite path="|20|45|06|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|20|45|06|.03">.03</cite>, Coin Service, repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|20|45|06|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|20|45|06|.08">.08</cite>, Pay Phone Service, adopted effective February 26, 2007 (34:4 Md. R. 403)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
