<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>09</num>
  <heading>Intrastate Switched Access and Pay Phone Dial Around Surcharge Rates</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter applies to a local exchange or interexchange telephone company operating within Maryland.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Dial around" means a method used by a pay phone user to purposely bypass a pay phone company's local exchange or interexchange telephone company services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Effective rate per switched access minute of use" means a rate that results from dividing the total revenue billed over a specific period of time for all rate elements contained in the intrastate switched access tariff of a facilities-based carrier by the total switched access minutes of use recorded by that carrier for the same time period.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Facilities-based carrier" means a local exchange telephone company owning or leasing facilities that consists of switching and transmission equipment used to carry voice or data traffic within Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Intrastate" means services, traffic, or facilities that originate and terminate within Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Local Exchange Telephone Company.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Local exchange telephone company" means a public service company that:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Owns telephone lines to receive, transmit, or communicate voice or data traffic within Maryland; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Leases, licenses, or sells telephone lines to receive, transmit, or communicate voice or data traffic within Maryland.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Local exchange telephone company" does not include a public service company that provides service only between telephone exchange areas.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Interexchange telephone company" means a public service company that receives, transmits, or communicates voice or data traffic between telephone exchange areas within Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Switched access service" means the service provided by a local exchange telephone company to an interexchange telephone company to originate and terminate in-State long distance calls.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|45|09|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Intrastate Switch Access Rates.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The provisions of this regulation are subject to the requirements of federal law.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A local exchange company’s intrastate originating switched access rates may not exceed its interstate originating access rates, as authorized by the Federal Communications Commission. In mirroring its interstate originating access rates, a local exchange company shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Eliminate or zero-rate any intrastate rate element that does not exist in the interstate jurisdiction;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Decrease any intrastate rate element that is higher than its corresponding interstate rate element to equal the interstate rate; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Increase any intrastate rate element that is lower than its corresponding interstate rate element to equal the interstate rate.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Notwithstanding <cite path="20|45|09|.03|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, a local exchange company’s intrastate per-query rate for use of an 8YY database may not exceed the rate of the incumbent local exchange telephone company having the largest number of access lines in Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Pay Phone Dial Around Surcharge Rates.</heading>
    <text>The per-call rate at which an interexchange telephone company subject to this chapter may offer pay phone dial around services to its customers is capped at 50 cents.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|45|09|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Waivers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A local exchange or interexchange telephone company subject to this chapter may request a waiver of the provisions of this chapter by filing an application with the Commission under <cite path="|20.07.04">COMAR 20.07.04</cite>, including supporting cost data.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Commission may waive the provisions of this chapter, if it finds the rate proposed in the application filed under <cite path="20|45|09|.05|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> is just and reasonable.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Fee Waiver.</heading>
    <text>The Commission shall waive the filing fee assessed under <cite path="20.07.05.03|A.|(14)">COMAR 20.07.05.03A(14)</cite> for local exchange or interexchange telephone companies filing revised rates under Regulation .04 or .05 of this chapter.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Penalty for Failure to Comply.</heading>
    <text>Failure to comply with the provisions of this chapter may result in the imposition of a civil penalty or other sanctions under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu">Public Utilities Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Public Utilities Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-113">2-113</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-121">2-121</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|4-201">4-201</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|4-203">4-203</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|4-301">4-301</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-01-06">Effective date: January 6, 2005 (31:26 Md. R. 1865)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-04-06"><cite path="|20|45|09|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective April 6, 2020 (47:7 Md. R. 384)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-04-11"><cite path="|20|45|09|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective April 11, 2005 (32:7 Md. R.684)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
