<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Request for Vote-by-Mail Ballot</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="33|21|02|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>In General.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>No Request Required. Except as provided in <cite path="33|21|02|.01|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, a voter is not required to submit a request for a vote-by-mail ballot to receive a vote-by-mail ballot.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>When Request Required — In General. Except as provided in <cite path="33|21|02|.01|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, a voter shall submit a request for a vote-by-mail ballot if the voter wants to receive the ballot:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At an address other than the voter’s address of record; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Via electronic transmission as defined in <cite path="33.11.01.01|B.|(3)">COMAR 33.11.01.01B(3)</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>When Request Required — Exception. If an absent uniformed services voter or an overseas voter previously submitted an absentee ballot application in the same calendar year as the special election and requested that the absentee ballot be sent to an address other than the voter’s address of record or sent via electronic transmission, the absent uniformed services voter or overseas voter is not required to submit a request for a vote-by-mail ballot.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Additional Request Methods. A voter may submit an informal written request for a vote-by-mail ballot as long as the request meets the requirements of <cite path="33.11.02.03">COMAR 33.11.02.03</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>In-Person Request. A local board may accept from a voter or a voter’s agent an in-person request for a vote-by-mail ballot.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Request Deadline.</heading>
    <text>If a voter submits a request for a vote-by-mail ballot under Regulation .01B, a voter shall submit the request:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>On or before 8 p.m. on the Tuesday before the special election if the voter wants the vote-by-mail ballot by mail or fax; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>On or before 11:59:59 p.m. on the Tuesday before the special election if the voter wants the vote-by-mail ballot by Internet.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Election Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|2-102">2-102</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|9-501">9-501</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|9-502">9-502</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|9-506">9-506</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-09-28">Effective date: September 28, 2015 (42:19 Md. R. 1229)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
