<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>04</num>
  <heading>Voting Centers</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>In General.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Number of Voting Centers. The local board shall establish at least one voting center for a special election.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Location.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A voting center shall be located at the local board office or another location within the constituency where the special election is being held.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The public official responsible for the use of any public building requested by the local board for a voting center shall make available to the local board, without charge, the space that is needed in the building for the proper conduct of an election.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Light, heat, and custodial and janitorial services for the space shall be provided to the local board without charge.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Days and Hours. Except as provided in the proclamation issued by the Governor directing that the special election be conducted by mail or <cite path="|33|21|04|.02">Regulation .02 of this chapter</cite>, a voting center shall be open for voting each day beginning 6 days before the day of a special election through the day of the special election during the hours between:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>10 a.m. and 8 p.m., Monday through Saturday; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>12 noon and 6 p.m. on Sunday.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Applicability. All federal and State laws, regulations, and procedures that apply to voting during early voting and on election day apply to voting at a voting center.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Montgomery County Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Applicability. This regulation only applies to a local special election in Montgomery County.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Location of Voting Centers. The local board shall establish:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For a special election held in a single county council district, at least one voting center in the county council district where the special election is being held; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For a countywide special election, at least one voting center shall be established in each county council district.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Voting Times. A voting center shall be open the days and hours that the county council specified in the resolution issued under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|9-501">Election Law Article, §9-501(d)(2), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Minimum Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Minimum Requirements. A local board shall ensure that each voting center:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Has the Statewide voting system for polling place voting, including an accessible device for voters with disabilities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provides for provisional voting in accordance with Election Law Article, Subtitle 4, Annotated Code of Maryland;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Has the minimum amount of voting equipment as provided in <cite path="|33|21|04|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Satisfies the requirements of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|10-101">Election Law Article, §10-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and accommodates the technical requirements to conduct an election.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Local Board Office. If a local board office is a voting center, the local board office shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Located in the district where the special election is being held;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Accessible for voters with disabilities; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Satisfy the requirements of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|10-101">Election Law Article, §10-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="33|21|04|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Selecting Voting Centers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Form for Proposed Voting Centers.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The State Board shall prescribe a form for a local board to use to provide information about a proposed voting center.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="33|21|04|.04|A.|(3)">§A(3) of this regulation</cite>, the local board shall use the form prescribed by the State Board.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the local board intends to use:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The local board’s office as the voting center for any special election, the local board shall certify that the local board office complies with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|10-101">Election Law Article, §10-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A voting center approved under <cite path="33.17.02.02|F.">COMAR 33.17.02.02F</cite>, the local board shall provide the State Administrator with the name and address of the approved voting center the local board intends to use as a voting center for the special election.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Form Submission for Proposed Voting Centers. At least 45 days before a special election, the local board shall submit to the State Administrator:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A form for each proposed voting center;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A certification that the local board’s office complies with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|10-101">Election Law Article, §10-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The name and address of the approved voting center that the local board is proposing to use as the voting center for the special election.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>State Administrator Approval.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Upon receipt of a form for a proposed voting center, the State Administrator shall review the form or certification and determine whether the proposed voting center is sufficient.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Within 3 business days of receiving the form, the State Administrator shall notify the local board of the State Administrator’s decision.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Security Plan for Voting Center.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Security Plan Required. For the proposed voting center, an election director shall submit to the State Administrator a security plan for approval.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Contents of Plan.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The security plan shall describe in detail how a local board will keep voting equipment, electronic pollbooks, ballots, and other election equipment and supplies secure during voting and nonvoting hours.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The plan shall include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A description of each entrance, including windows, to the area where equipment and supplies will be secured during nonvoting hours and how the entrance is secured;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The names and titles of all individuals who have a key or keys to the room where equipment and supplies will be secured during nonvoting hours;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A description of existing building security, such as alarms and closed circuit or Internet accessible cameras, and armed and unarmed guards at the facility; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Any additional security measures that will be taken during voting and nonvoting hours.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>At the request of the State Administrator or when it is considered necessary, an election director shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Review and update the security plan; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If updated, submit within 2 days of updating the plan a copy of the updated plan to the State Administrator.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Review and Acceptance of Plan.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The State Administrator shall review a local board’s security plan and may require a local board to make changes to the plan, including implementing additional security measures.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Within 3 days of receiving the security plan, the State Administrator shall provide to the local board any feedback.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A local board shall update its plan according to the feedback provided by the State Administrator.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Allocation of Equipment, Personnel, and Supplies.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Submission of Allocation Plan. The local board shall work with the State Administrator to develop a plan for the allocation of equipment, personnel, and supplies.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Plan Requirements. The plan shall include the proposed number of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Voting units, including accessible voting devices;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Electronic pollbooks;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Election judges; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Provisional ballot applications</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Election Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|2-102">2-102</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|9-501">9-501</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|9-503">9-503</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|9-506">9-506</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-09-28">Effective date: September 28, 2015 (42:19 Md. R. 1230)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-07-10"><cite path="|33|21|04|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective July 10, 2023 (50:13 Md. R. 514)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
