<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>04</num>
  <heading>Pre-Canvass Procedures</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Securing Ballots.</heading>
    <text>Until the canvass begins, every provisional ballot returned by a voter shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Remain sealed in the provisional ballot application envelope; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Be placed in a secure location to which the public does not have access.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="33|16|04|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Pre-Canvass Review.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Before the Canvass.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Complete Application.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The election director shall review the provisional ballot application to determine if the application is complete.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An application is complete if:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The application is signed by the voter; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>There is sufficient information on the application for the election director to determine whether the voter is registered to vote.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A special provisional ballot application for extended voting hours is complete if:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The voter's name is printed on the envelope; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The voter signed the oath printed on the envelope.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A provisional ballot application used for the purpose of same day registration or address change during early voting or same day registration on election day is complete if:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The registration and oath document is affixed to the provisional ballot application; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The voter signed the registration and oath document.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The election director shall determine whether:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The voter is a registered voter;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For a primary election, the voter is affiliated with the political party the voter indicated on the provisional ballot application;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The voter returned a voted absentee ballot or already voted in the election;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The voter satisfied the verification or identification requirement as provided in <cite path="33|16|04|.02|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The ballot cast by the voter is the correct ballot style for the voter based on the address listed on the provisional ballot application;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The challenge to the voter’s identity was valid as provided in <cite path="33|16|04|.02|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>If the individual attempted to register and vote during early voting or on election day but was not a pre-qualified voter, the individual is eligible to register to vote and provided proof of residency as provided in <cite path="33|16|04|.02|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>If the individual attempted to register and vote during early voting or on election day but did not provide proof of residency, the individual provided proof of residency as provided in <cite path="33|16|04|.02|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The election director shall complete the election director section of the provisional ballot application.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The election director shall enter into the voter registration system all of the required information.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Satisfying the Verification Requirement.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A voter whose registration status is pending satisfies the verification requirement if the voter:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Provides personal identification information if the voter is pending because a previously submitted driver’s license or partial social security number could not be verified; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Provides an identification number and the number is verified under <cite path="33.05.04.04">COMAR 33.05.04.04</cite> or indicates that the voter does not have an identification number if the voter is pending because the voter had not previously provided a driver’s license or partial social security number.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Personal identification information or identification number shall be provided:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>To an election judge who will record on the provisional ballot application the type of personal identification information the voter provided;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>On the provisional ballot application where the personal identification number is requested; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>To the local board before the start of the provisional ballot canvass.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Satisfying the Identification Requirement. A voter satisfies the identification requirement if the voter provides personal identification information to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An election judge who shall record on the provisional ballot application the type of personal identification information the voter provided; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The local board before the start of the provisional ballot canvass.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Verification of Challenge to Voter's Identity. To determine whether a challenge to a voter's identity is valid, the election director shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Review the voter's signature on the affidavit and compare it to the signature on file with the local board or scanned into the voter registration system; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If, after reviewing the documents, the challenge is inconclusive, contact the voter and request personal identification information.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Satisfying the Proof of Residency Requirement. An individual satisfies the proof of residency requirement if the individual provides proof of residency to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An election judge who shall record the type of proof of residency information the individual provided; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The local board before the start of the provisional ballot canvass.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Election Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|2-102">2-102</cite>(b)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|4">4</cite>), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|2-202">2-202</cite>(b), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|3-305">3-305</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|3-306">3-306</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|9-402">9-402</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|9-403">9-403</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|9-404">9-404</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|9-406">9-406</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|11-303">11-303</cite>(c) and (e), Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-10-19">COMAR Chapter <cite path="|33.16.04">33.16.04</cite> Canvass of Ballots — Procedures recodified to <cite path="|33.16.05">COMAR 33.16.05</cite> and Regulations .01 and .02 adopted under new COMAR Chapter <cite path="|33.16.04">33.16.04</cite> Pre-Canvass Procedures effective October 19, 2009 (36:21 Md. R. 1595)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-07-10"><cite path="|33|16|04|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended effective February 29, 2016 (43:4 Md. R. 338); December 2, 2019 (46:24 Md. R. 1104); July 10, 2023 (50:13 Md. R. 514)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-11-23"><cite path="|33|16|04|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite>, B amended effective November 23, 2017 (44:23 Md. R. 1079)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-02-29"><cite path="|33|16|04|.02|E.">Regulation .02E</cite> adopted effective February 29, 2016 (43:4 Md. R. 338)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
