<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>General Regulations</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this subtitle, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Accredited educational institution” means a college or university in the United States or an equivalent which has been accredited by an accrediting organization or agency that is recognized by the United States Department of Education.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Approved experience” means experience which classifies as practice as an environmental health specialist.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Approved Training.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Approved training” means Board-approved courses of study or programs of instruction in an area of environmental health sciences and related subjects designed to improve, advance, or extend professional skill and knowledge relating to the practice of an environmental health specialist.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Approved training” includes, for licensees applying for renewal of a license for the first time, in-training or prior work experience as specified under <cite path="10.60.03.01|C.|(7)">COMAR 10.60.03.01C(7)</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Board” means the State Board of Environmental Health Specialists.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Certificate” means any of the following certificates issued by the Board:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A certificate of eligibility for obtaining employment; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An environmental health specialist-in-training certificate.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Environmental health specialist-in-training” means an individual who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Meets the educational qualifications set forth in <cite path="|10|60|01|.03|B.">Regulation .03B of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has a valid environmental health specialist-in-training certificate.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Environmental health specialist-in-training program” means a program which provides an environmental health specialist-in-training with approved experience under the supervision of an environmental health sponsor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Environmental Health Sponsor.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Environmental health sponsor” means an individual who is responsible for overseeing the implementation and progress of an applicant's environmental health specialist-in-training program.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Environmental health sponsor” includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>For public employees, an environmental health director, equivalent agency officer, or their designee; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>For private sector employees, an environmental professional, who, like an environmental health director or equivalent agency supervisor, makes discretionary decisions affecting food safety, water quality, air quality, sewage systems, and other aspects of the environment affecting the public health.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“Environmental science degree” means a baccalaureate or master’s degree inclusive of sufficient course and lab work consistent with semester credits or equivalent in quarter credits in physical and biological sciences acceptable to the Board.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>“Full-time employment” means employment of at least 34 hours per week.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>“Hours of approved training” means the value given by the Board for participation in continuing education or experience.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>“Internship” means an environmental health specialist-in-training program that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Consists of 3 months of approved experience; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has been completed by an individual who has graduated from an accredited educational institution with a master’s degree in public or environmental health.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>“Laboratory course” means a traditional on-site setting or virtual setting where an individual conducts practical experiments by either:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Hands on; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Simulation relative to the subject area.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>“License” means a license issued by the Board to practice as an environmental health specialist.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>“License renewal period” means the 24-month period immediately preceding the expiration date of the license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>“Licensed environmental health specialist” means an individual who is licensed by the Board to practice as an environmental health specialist.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>Major Component of Employment.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Major component of employment” means a job duty or responsibility that:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>An individual may be reasonably expected to perform;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Is identified and listed separately on a position description form such as a Maryland State form MS-22; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Entails significant decision-making responsibility and authority in the process of securing compliance with federal, State, or local health and environmental laws and regulations specifically relating to the control of the public health aspects of the environment.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Major component of employment” does not include a job duty or responsibility identified as miscellaneous or other duties as assigned.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>Party.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Party” means a person or agency named or admitted as a party, or properly seeking and entitled to the right to be admitted as a party, in formal hearings.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Party” includes a person or agency admitted for limited purposes.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>“Permanent employee” means an individual who is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Employed to practice as an environmental health specialist; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Not a temporary employee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>“Practice as an environmental health specialist” means, as a major component of employment, to apply academic principles, methods, and procedures of the environmental, physical, biological, and health sciences to the inspections and investigations necessary to collect and analyze data and to make decisions necessary to secure compliance with federal, State, and local health and environmental laws and regulations specifically relating to control of the public health aspects of the environment including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The manufacture, preparation, handling, distribution, or sale of food and milk;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Water supply and treatment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Wastewater treatment and disposal;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Solid waste management and disposal;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Vector control;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Insect and rodent control;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Air quality;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Noise control;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Product safety;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Recreational sanitation; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Institutional and residential sanitation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>“Subject matter expert” means an individual with in-depth knowledge or expertise in performing a specialized job, duty or skill within an organization.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>“Temporary employee” means an individual who is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Employed to practice as an environmental health specialist on a temporary basis for a length of time not to exceed 6 consecutive months within a consecutive 12-month period; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Not required to complete the total months of experience in an environmental health specialist-in-training program under <cite path="|10|60|01|.03|B.">Regulation .03B of this chapter</cite> on a consecutive monthly basis.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Prohibitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An individual may not practice as an environmental health specialist in the State unless the individual:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is licensed by the Board; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is employed under a valid environmental health specialist-in-training certificate issued by the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An individual may not practice as an environmental health specialist under an environmental health specialist-in-training certificate for more than a total of 3 years, unless approved by the Board in accordance with <cite path="10.60.02.05|B.">COMAR 10.60.02.05B</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|21">Health Occupations Article, §21</cite>–401, Annotated Code of Maryland, unless an individual is licensed under this chapter, an individual may not use the title “environmental health specialist” or “licensed environmental health specialist” or the initials “E.H.S.” or “L.E.H.S.” after the name of the individual or any other title with the intent to represent that the individual is licensed to practice as an environmental health specialist.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|60|01|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Licensing and Examination.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board shall license an applicant if the applicant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Qualifies for examination as provided in <cite path="10|60|01|.03|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Takes and passes the examination;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Has not committed an act which, under Health Occupation Article, §21-312, would subject the applicant to disciplinary action by the Board; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Pays the necessary fees as specified in <cite path="|10.60.06">COMAR 10.60.06</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An applicant is eligible to take the examination if the applicant has satisfied one of the following combinations of education and experience:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Combination 1:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Graduated from an accredited educational institution with a baccalaureate degree that includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A minimum of 30 semester  credit hours or the equivalent quarter [credits] credit hours of chemical, physical, biological, and environmental sciences acceptable to the Board;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A course in mathematics; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Laboratory coursework as required in <cite path="10|60|01|.03|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Obtained 12 months of experience in an environmental health specialist-in-training program approved by the Board; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Combination 2:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Graduated from an accredited educational institution with a master’s degree in public or environmental health science that includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A minimum of 30 semester credit hours or 45 quarter credit hours of chemical, physical, biological, or environmental sciences acceptable to the Board;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A course in mathematics; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Laboratory coursework as required in <cite path="10|60|01|.03|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Completed an internship.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Laboratory Coursework.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="10|60|01|.03|C.|(2)">§C(2) of this regulation</cite>, laboratory coursework shall be in the following fields:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Chemistry;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Physics;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Biology;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Geographic information systems;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Soil science; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Geological science.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Board may accept a health or environmental field not listed in <cite path="10|60|01|.03|C.|(1)">§C(1) of this regulation</cite> if the Board determines that the field is sufficiently related to the practice of an environmental health specialist.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An applicant shall have completed at least:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>One laboratory course in two of the fields listed in <cite path="10|60|01|.03|C.|(1)">§C(1) of this regulation</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Four laboratory courses in one of the fields listed in <cite path="10|60|01|.03|C.|(1)">§C(1) of this regulation</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Two laboratory courses in one or more of the fields accepted by the Board in accordance with <cite path="10|60|01|.03|C.|(2)">§C(2) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|60|01|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Waivers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board may waive any examination requirement under this chapter if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board considers the applicant to be recognized as outstanding in the field of environmental health as stated in <cite path="10.60.02.04|L.">COMAR 10.60.02.04L</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The applicant has:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Satisfied the education and experience requirements set forth in <cite path="|10|60|01|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Passed an examination as a condition of licensure or registration in another state;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Been licensed or registered as an environmental health specialist or its equivalent in another state; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Performed at least 24 months of compensated work as an environmental health specialist or its equivalent in the other state.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An applicant who satisfies <cite path="10|60|01|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall pay to the Board the application and license fees established by <cite path="|10.60.06">COMAR 10.60.06</cite> before receiving a license.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|60|01|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Environmental Health Specialist-in-Training Program.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The purpose of an environmental health specialist-in-training program shall be to prepare the environmental health specialist-in-training to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Perform in a competent manner assigned job duties and responsibilities which constitute practice as an environmental health specialist; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Demonstrate proficiency in all areas of public and environmental health on a written examination required by the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>At a minimum, an environmental health specialist-in-training program shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provide the environmental health specialist-in-training with approved experience that is in accordance with <cite path="10|60|01|.05|E.">§E of this regulation</cite> and which includes the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Conducting inspections and investigations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Collecting and analyzing data;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Making decisions necessary to secure compliance with federal, State, and local laws and regulations that relate to control of the public health aspects of the environment; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Reviewing and approving plans for compliance or process changes; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide the environmental health specialist-in-training with an opportunity for education and training in the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Areas identified in <cite path="|10|60|01|.01|B.|(20)">Regulation .01B(20) of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Subject areas included in the recognized examination approved by the Board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The environmental health sponsor of an environmental health specialist-in-training program shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Ensure that the program complies with <cite path="10|60|01|.05|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide in house training and opportunities for outside training events; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Define and track progress through the performance evaluation process.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>As part of the implementation of the in-training program, the environmental health specialist-in-training shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Review recommended resource materials;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Attend recommended training events to improve breadth and depth of knowledge;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Receive satisfactory or above performance evaluation ratings for the entire in-training program; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>With the sponsor’s input, establish a timeline for when to take the examination.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Experience Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Experience obtained under the direction of the environmental health sponsor shall be credited toward the experience requirements of an environmental health specialist-in-training program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The amount of approved experience required for each environmental health specialist-in-training program shall be in accordance with <cite path="|10|60|01|.03|B.">Regulation .03B of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Board may approve and apply experience that was obtained from prior employment as part of an environmental health specialist-in-training program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Approved experience shall be credited to an environmental health specialist-in-training as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Each month of full time employment is credited as 1 month of experience;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Each month of less than full-time employment is credited on a prorated basis; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>No experience credit is given for any month during which the environmental health specialist-in-training's job performance is rated as unsatisfactory in writing by that individual’s supervisor.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Except for an internship approved by an environmental health sponsor, approved experience does not include experience obtained to satisfy the degree requirements of an academic institution.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|21-101">21-101</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|21-502">21-502</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-04-15">Regulations <cite path="|10|60|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|60|01|.05">.05</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective January 3, 2013 (40:6 Md. R. 469); adopted permanently effective April 15, 2013 (40:7 Md. R. 612)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-05-01"><cite path="|10|60|01|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective November 9, 2015 (42:22 Md. R. 1379); June 28, 2021 (48:13 Md. R. 508); May 1, 2023 (50:8 Md. R. 338)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-11-09"><cite path="|10|60|01|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective November 9, 2015 (42:22 Md. R. 1379)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-03-13"><cite path="|10|60|01|.02|C.">Regulation .02C</cite> adopted effective March 13, 2017 (44:5 Md. R. 294)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-08-05"><cite path="|10|60|01|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite> amended effective November 9, 2015 (42:22 Md. R. 1379); March 13, 2017 (44:5 Md. R. 294); June 28, 2021 (48:13 Md. R. 508); August 5, 2024 (51:15 Md. R. 710)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-08-05">Regulation ,03C adopted effective August 5, 2024 (51:15 Md. R. 710)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-06-28"><cite path="|10|60|01|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite> amended effective November 9, 2015 (42:22 Md. R. 1379); March 13, 2017 (44:5 Md. R. 294); June 28, 2021 (48:13 Md. R. 508)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-03-13"><cite path="|10|60|01|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective November 9, 2015 (42:22 Md. R. 1379); March 13, 2017 (44:5 Md. R. 294)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-06-28"><cite path="|10|60|01|.05|A.">Regulation .05A</cite>, B amended effective June 28, 2021 (48:13 Md. R. 508)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-08-05"><cite path="|10|60|01|.05|E.">Regulation .05E</cite> amended effective April 23, 2018 (45:8 Md. R. 422); August 5, 2024 (51:15 Md. R. 710)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
