<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Licensing Procedures</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|60|02|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Application Procedure.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An individual applying for a license or certificate of eligibility shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Submit the appropriate application in writing on a form provided by the Board;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Pay the application fee established by <cite path="|10.60.06">COMAR 10.60.06</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Have official transcripts of all baccalaureate and post-baccalaureate studies submitted in accordance with <cite path="10|60|02|.01|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Have verification of previous experience, if applicable, submitted in accordance with <cite path="10|60|02|.01|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Transcripts.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Official transcripts of all baccalaureate and post-baccalaureate studies shall be submitted directly to the Board from the appropriate educational institutions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If official transcripts are not available, the Board may accept other evidence certifying successful completion of course work considered equivalent by the Board.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A graduate of a college or university that is not an accredited educational institution shall provide written documentation from an evaluation service, or other source acceptable to the Board, which:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>States that the institution’s program of study is substantially equivalent to that of accredited educational institutions; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Shows that the course work completed by the applicant satisfies the requirements of <cite path="10.60.01.03|B.">COMAR 10.60.01.03B</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An applicant for a license who claims experience as an environmental health specialist shall provide to the Board independent written verification from the applicant’s employer describing the nature and duration of the applicant’s experience.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Incomplete Application.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>May not take any action on an incomplete application; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shall notify the applicant of the need for additional information within 45 days of receipt of the application.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An application is not complete until all required material, including the fee and supporting documentation, is received by the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An incomplete application shall be held for 1 year from the date of initial receipt, after which the application is invalid.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|60|02|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Action on an Application.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board shall notify an applicant in writing that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The applicant qualifies for a license under <cite path="10.60.01.03">COMAR 10.60.01.03</cite> or .04;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The applicant qualifies for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Examination under <cite path="10.60.01.03">COMAR 10.60.01.03</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A certificate of eligibility under <cite path="10.60.02.05">COMAR 10.60.02.05</cite>;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The applicant does not qualify to receive a license or a certificate of eligibility, or to take the examination, for one or more of the reasons set forth in <cite path="10|60|02|.03|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The application is incomplete, the reasons the application is incomplete, and that the application will be invalid in 1 year.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Payment of License Fee.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Following notification of license approval, the applicant shall pay to the Board the licensing fee established in <cite path="|10.60.06">COMAR 10.60.06</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The license may not be issued until the fee is paid to the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Denial of an Application.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board shall deny an application if the Board determines that the applicant:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Has failed to demonstrate that the applicant qualifies for licensure, examination, or issuance of a certificate in accordance with §A(1) or (2) of this regulation; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has committed any act which, under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|21-312">Health Occupations Article, §21-312, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, would subject the licensee to disciplinary action by the Board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the Board denies an application, the Board shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Notify the applicant by first-class mail and electronic means of the reasons for denial;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Advise the applicant of the procedures for reconsideration under <cite path="10|60|02|.03|D.">§D of this regulation</cite> if the application was denied under <cite path="10|60|02|.03|C.|(1)|(a)">§C(1)(a) of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Follow the procedures set forth in <cite path="|10.60.04">COMAR 10.60.04</cite> if the application was denied under <cite path="10|60|02|.03|C.|(1)|(b)">§C(1)(b) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Reconsideration.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If the Board denies an application for licensure under <cite path="|10|60|02|.03|C.|(1)|(a)">Regulation .03C(1)(a) of this chapter</cite>, or denies an application to renew a license under <cite path="|10|60|02|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>, the applicant may request reconsideration of the denial by submitting new or additional information to the Board.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Requests for reconsideration under <cite path="10|60|02|.03|D.|(1)">§D(1) of this regulation</cite> shall be based on one or more of the following grounds:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Clerical errors in the minutes, decisions, or other parts of the record related to the denial;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Mistake of fact or law by the Board;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Irregularity in the administrative proceedings related to, or in the consideration of, the application;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Newly discovered or additional evidence that the applicant could not have discovered by due diligence in time to be considered as part of the initial denial.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Requests for reconsideration shall be submitted to the Board in writing by certified mail within 30 days of receipt of the denial under <cite path="10|60|02|.03|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|60|02|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Examination.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Authorize a recognized examination agency to administer the examination on behalf of the Board; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Administer an examination prepared by a recognized examination agency.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The examination shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Standardized and prepared by a recognized examination agency; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Held at least once a year.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Board shall provide the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>List of eligible applicants and their eligibility expiration date to an authorized examination agency;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For applicants who have satisfied education and experience requirements set forth under <cite path="10.60.01.03">COMAR 10.60.01.03</cite>, notice of eligibility to sit for the examination;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Examination information for eligible applicants on the Board’s website;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Results of the examination to the applicant; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>For applicants who receive a passing score, instructions on securing a license.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The notice of eligibility to an applicant shall include the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Date the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Applicant is eligible to sit for the examination; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Eligibility to sit for the examination expires; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Procedure to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Register to sit for the examination;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Pay the fee for examination; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Retake the examination.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The authorized examination agency shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Collect the examination fee from the applicant; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide examination results to the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Passing Score. The passing score for the examination shall be determined by the recognized examination agency.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>An applicant who has not previously taken the written examination is permitted to sit for an examination if the applicant has:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Received a notice of eligibility from the Board; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Paid an examination fee as established by <cite path="|10.60.06">COMAR 10.60.06</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>An applicant who fails the examination may retake the examination if the applicant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Submits an application on a form required by the Board; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Pays any applicable examination fees.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>An applicant, who receives an in-training certificate after January 1, 2022, may not sit for the examination after their in-training certificate expires.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>The Board may not accept examination results unless all eligibility requirements set forth in this regulation are met.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>The Board may waive any examination requirement under this regulation if the Board considers the applicant to be recognized as outstanding in the field of environmental health.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>To be recognized as outstanding in the field of environmental health by the Board, an applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Meet the criteria set forth in <cite path="10.60.01.03">COMAR 10.60.01.03</cite> and <cite path="10.60.02.01">10.60.02.01</cite> for an environmental health specialist-in-training;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Be considered a subject matter expert by the Board in one or more of the following areas:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The manufacture, preparation, handling, distribution, or sale of food and milk;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Water supply and treatment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Wastewater treatment and disposal;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Solid waste management and disposal;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Vector control;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Insect and rodent control;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Air quality;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Noise control;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Product safety;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Recreational sanitation; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Institutional and residential sanitation;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Demonstrate at least one of the following career pathways with a minimum of 15 years of progressive responsibilities with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Technical knowledge and experience, including obtaining a master’s or doctoral degree in an environmental or public health-related area, wherein the time devoted to technical scientific research may be applied towards the minimum time criteria as follows:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>If obtaining a master’s degree, 1 year; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>If obtaining a doctoral degree, 2 years;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A managerial hierarchy similar to that of an environmental health specialist, such as:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Health specialist in training;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Licensed environmental health specialist;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Supervisor;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Program manager; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Director; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A combination of §L(3)(a) or (b) of this regulation; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Demonstrate and document involvement in an area listed in <cite path="10|60|02|.04|L.|(2)">§L(2) of this regulation</cite>, in at least one of the following activities:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Research;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has been published in peer review publications;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Has given court testimony or served as an expert witness qualified by a court system;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Has teaching experience; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Where applicable, received a professional license through a Maryland or other recognized licensure body in the applicant’s field.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|60|02|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Certificates.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Certificate of Eligibility for Obtaining Employment.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board shall issue a certificate of eligibility for obtaining employment to an applicant who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Meets the educational requirements set forth in <cite path="10.60.01.03">COMAR 10.60.01.03</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has submitted an application in accordance with <cite path="|10|60|02|.01">Regulation .01 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Is not currently practicing as an environmental health specialist in Maryland; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Has not previously completed an environmental health specialist-in-training program under an environmental health specialist-in-training certificate issued by the Board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The certificate of eligibility for obtaining employment shall expire 12 months after the issuance date and may be renewed at 12-month increments if the certificate holder:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Submits a request for renewal on a form provided by the Board; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Forwards the form to the Board together with the renewal fee established by <cite path="|10.60.06">COMAR 10.60.06</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Environmental Health Specialist-In-Training Certificates.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board shall issue an environmental health specialist-in-training certificate to an applicant who has been employed to practice as an environmental health specialist under a certificate of eligibility for obtaining employment issued by the Board if the applicant:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Has returned a completed certificate of eligibility for obtaining employment to the Board; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is participating in an environmental health specialist-in-training program.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The environmental health specialist-in-training certificate shall expire 36 months after its effective date unless the expiration date has been extended in writing by the Board in accordance with §B(4) or (6) of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Board may not renew an environmental health specialist-in-training certificate for which the expiration date has been extended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Upon a written request from the holder of an environmental health specialist-in-training certificate, the Board may extend an environmental health specialist-in-training certificate for up to 6 months due to physical incapacitation of the environmental health specialist-in-training or for other reasons acceptable to the Board.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Board may place the environmental health specialist-in-training certificate on inactive status due to reasons acceptable to the Board upon a written request from the holder of an environmental health specialist-in-training certificate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The Board may reactivate the environmental health specialist-in-training certificate within the original 36 month period with an expiration date that reflects the balance of remaining time for training:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Upon a written request from an individual whose environmental health specialist-in-training certificate is inactive; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Along with a letter of support from a sponsor.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>If the holder of an environmental health specialist-in-training certificate is a temporary employee as defined in <cite path="10.60.01.01">COMAR 10.60.01.01</cite>, the Board, upon written request from the holder of the environmental health specialist-in-training certificate and upon receipt of the renewal fee as required by <cite path="|10.60.06">COMAR 10.60.06</cite>, may renew a valid certificate for a period of 24 months.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>If a temporary employee is hired as or otherwise converted to a permanent employee:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The employee shall submit the employee’s current environmental health specialist-in-training certificate to the Board within 30 days;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Upon receipt of the certificate referenced in <cite path="10|60|02|.05|D.|(6)|(a)">§D(6)(a) of this regulation</cite>, the Board shall renew a new environmental health specialist-in-training certificate that is valid for 36 months; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Board may reduce the required number of months of experience in an environmental health specialist-in-training program.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|60|02|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Expiration and Renewal of Licenses.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Expiration. After June 30, 2023, licenses shall expire pursuant to the following schedule:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The license of a licensee with an even-numbered birth year shall expire on June 30 of an even-numbered year; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The license of a licensee with an odd-numbered birth year shall expire on June 30 of an odd-numbered year</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Conditions for License Renewal.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in §B(2) and (3) of this regulation, the Board shall renew a license for a 2-year period if the licensee has:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Submitted an application for renewal to the Board before the expiration date of the license;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Paid the renewal fee established by <cite path="|10.60.06">COMAR 10.60.06</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Submitted satisfactory proof to the Board that the licensee has completed at least 20 clock hours of approved training during the license renewal period; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Not committed any act which, under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|21-312">Health Occupations Article, §21-312, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, would subject the licensee to disciplinary action by the Board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For licenses expiring on June 30, 2023 only, the Board shall renew the license of a licensee with an even-numbered birth year for a 1-year period if the licensee meets the requirements set forth under <cite path="10|60|02|.06|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>For licenses expiring on June 30, 2024 only, the Board shall renew a license for a 2-year period if the licensee has:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Submitted an application for renewal to the Board before the expiration date of the license;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Paid the renewal fee established by <cite path="|10.60.06">COMAR 10.60.06</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Submitted satisfactory proof to the Board that the licensee has completed at least 10 clock hours of approved training during the 1-year period immediately preceding the license expiration date; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Not committed any act which, under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|21-312">Health Occupations Article, §21-312, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, would subject the licensee to disciplinary action by the Board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Board may deny the application to renew a license if the applicant has failed to satisfy the requirements of  <cite path="10|60|02|.06|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Renewal Notification.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Before the expiration of a license, the Board shall notify the licensee of the need to renew the license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The failure of a licensee to receive a renewal notice does not:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Relieve the licensee of the obligation to renew the license; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Affect the expiration of the license.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Duplicate License.</heading>
    <text>A licensee may obtain a duplicate license to replace a license that has been lost, destroyed, or mutilated if the licensee:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Makes a written request to the Board that states the reason for requesting a duplicate license; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Pays to the Board the duplicate license fee established by <cite path="|10.60.06">COMAR 10.60.06</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Inactive Status.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board shall place a licensed environmental health specialist on inactive status for a period not to exceed 4 years if the licensee:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Submits to the Board a written application for inactive status on a form the board requires; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Pays to the Board the inactive status fee set by the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board shall provide to a licensed environmental health specialist who is placed on inactive status written notification of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The date the license has or will expire;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The date the inactive status became effective;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The date the inactive status expires; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The consequences of not reactivating the license before the inactive status expires.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="|10|60|02|.10">Regulation .10 of this chapter</cite>, the Board shall reactivate the license of a licensed environmental health specialist who is on inactive status if the licensee:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Applies to the Board for reactivation of the license before the inactive status expires;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Complies with the license renewal requirements that are in effect when the licensee applies for reactivation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Has completed 20 credit hours of approved continuing education in the past 24 month period; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Pays to the Board the reactivation fee established by <cite path="|10.60.06">COMAR 10.60.06</cite>(7).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An applicant for reactivation of a license shall submit to the Board documentation of completion of approved training as set forth in <cite path="10.60.03.04|E.">COMAR 10.60.03.04E</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Non-Renewed Status.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board shall place a licensed environmental health specialist on non-renewed status for a period not to exceed 4 years if the licensed environmental health specialist fails to renew the license for any reason.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board shall provide to the licensee who is placed on nonrenewed status written notification of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The date the license expired;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The date the non-renewed status became effective;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The date the non-renewed status expires; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The consequences of not reactivating the license before the non-renewed status expires.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="|10|60|02|.10">Regulation .10 of this chapter</cite>, the Board shall reactivate the license of a licensed environmental health specialist who is on non-renewed status if the individual:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Applies to the Board for reactivation of the license before the non-renewed status expires;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Complies with the license renewal requirements that are in effect when the individual applies for reactivation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Has completed 20 credit hours of approved continuing education in the past 24 month period; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Pays to the Board the reactivation fee established by <cite path="|10.60.06">COMAR 10.60.06</cite>.D. An applicant for reactivation of a license shall submit to the Board documentation of completion of approved training as set forth in <cite path="10.60.03.04|E.">COMAR 10.60.03.04E</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An applicant for reactivation of a license shall submit to the Board documentation of completion of approved training as set forth in <cite path="10.60.03.04|E.">COMAR 10.60.03.04E</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Reactivation.</heading>
    <text>Notwithstanding Regulations .08 and .09 of this chapter, the Board shall reactivate the license of a licensed environmental health specialist who was placed on inactive or non-renewed status if the individual:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Applies to the Board for reactivation after the inactive or non-renewed status expired;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Pays to the Board the reactivation fee established by <cite path="|10.60.06">COMAR 10.60.06</cite>;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Provides any documentation required by the Board; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Passes the examination that is required at time of reactivation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|21-101">21-101</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|21-502">21-502</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-04-15">Regulations <cite path="|10|60|02|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|60|02|.08">.08</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective January 3, 2013 (40:6 Md. R. 469); adopted permanently effective April 15, 2013 (40:7 Md. R. 612)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-06-28"><cite path="|10|60|02|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective June 28, 2021 (48:13 Md. R. 508)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-11-09"><cite path="|10|60|02|.01|C.">Regulation .01C</cite> amended effective November 9, 2015 (42:22 Md. R. 1379)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-11-09"><cite path="|10|60|02|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite>, B amended effective November 9, 2015 (42:22 Md. R. 1379)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-11-09"><cite path="|10|60|02|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite> amended effective November 9, 2015 (42:22 Md. R. 1379)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-03-13"><cite path="|10|60|02|.03|C.">Regulation .03C</cite> amended effective March 13, 2017 (44:5 Md. R. 294)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-06-28"><cite path="|10|60|02|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective June 28, 2021 (48:13 Md. R. 508)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-11-09"><cite path="|10|60|02|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite>, E amended effective November 9, 2015 (42:22 Md. R. 1379)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-11-09"><cite path="|10|60|02|.04|F.">Regulation .04F</cite>, G adopted effective November 9, 2015 (42:22 Md. R. 1379)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-03-13"><cite path="|10|60|02|.04|G.">Regulation .04G</cite> amended effective March 13, 2017 (44:5 Md. R. 294)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-11-09"><cite path="|10|60|02|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective November 9, 2015 (42:22 Md. R. 1379)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-03-13"><cite path="|10|60|02|.05|B.">Regulation .05B</cite> amended effective March 13, 2017 (44:5 Md. R. 294)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-05-01"><cite path="|10|60|02|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective May 1, 2023 (50:8 Md. R. 338)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-05-20"><cite path="|10|60|02|.06|C.">Regulation .06C</cite> repealed effective May 20, 2019 (46:10 Md. R. 490)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-11-09"><cite path="|10|60|02|.08">Regulation .08</cite> repealed and new Regulation .08 adopted effective November 9, 2015 (42:22 Md. R. 1379)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-08-05"><cite path="|10|60|02|.08|D.">Regulation .08D</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective January 9, 2024 (51:3 Md. R. 153); emergency status expired effective July 7, 2024; adopted permanently effective August 5, 2024 (51:15 Md. R. 710)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-11-09"><cite path="|10|60|02|.09">Regulation .09</cite> adopted effective November 9, 2015 (42:22 Md. R. 1379)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-08-05"><cite path="|10|60|02|.09|A.">Regulation .09A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective January 9, 2024 (51:3 Md. R. 153); emergency status expired effective July 7, 2024; amended permanently effective August 5, 2024 (51:15 Md. R. 710)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-08-05"><cite path="|10|60|02|.09|D.">Regulation .09D</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective January 9, 2024 (51:3 Md. R. 153); emergency status expired effective July 7, 2024; adopted permanently effective August 5, 2024 (51:15 Md. R. 710)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-11-09"><cite path="|10|60|02|.10">Regulation .10</cite> adopted effective November 9, 2015 (42:22 Md. R. 1379)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
