<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>Examination and Licensure</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Active nursing practice” as used in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-312">Health Occupations Article, §8-312, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The practice of registered nursing or licensed practical nursing as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-101">Health Occupations Article, §8-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Related nursing activities approved by the Board, including but not limited to a generic nursing education program, degree completion programs, or graduate programs within the last 5 years; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Completion of a generic nursing education program, degree completion program, or a graduate program within the last 5 years.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Advanced practice registered nurse” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-101">Health Occupations Article, §8-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Biennial renewal” means renewal of a license every 2 years in the licensee’s birth month.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Board” means the Maryland Board of Nursing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Central Repository” means the Maryland Criminal Justice Information System Central Repository of the Department of Public Safety and Correctional Services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Certified Nursing Assistant.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Certified nursing assistant” means an individual, regardless of title, who routinely performs nursing tasks delegated by a registered nurse or licensed practice nurse for compensation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Certified nursing assistant” does not mean a certified medication technician.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Continuing education” means planned, organized learning experiences designed to augment the knowledge, skill, and ability to enhance nursing practice and therefore improve health care delivered to the public.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Continuing education unit (CEU)” means 1 contact hour of 50—60 minutes.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“Cosign” means a registered nurse verifies that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An activity was performed safely and accurately by the nursing graduate; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The documentation is complete and accurate.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>“Criminal history records check” means the performance of both a State criminal history check by the Central Repository, and a national criminal history check by the Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>“Criminal history records information” means information provided by the criminal history records check regarding an applicant's criminal arrests, charges, and convictions, and other dispositions of criminal charges.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>“Educational qualifications” means that at the time the applicant graduated from a registered nursing or licensed practical nursing education program, that program was substantially equivalent to the registered nursing or practical nursing education programs approved in this State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>“Endorsement” means, for qualified applicants who have an unencumbered license from another state or country to practice registered nursing or licensed practical nursing, a waiver of the initial licensure requirement to take the national licensure examination in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-307">Health Occupations Article, §8-307, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>“English language competency examination” means an examination that tests an individual’s written and oral competency in the English language.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>“Geriatric nursing assistant” means a certified nursing assistant who has successfully completed the requirements for geriatric nursing assistant mandated under federal law and the regulations of the Board.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>“Former licensee” means an individual who once had an active license with the Board who is no longer active.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>“Multistate licensure privilege” means an authorization to practice registered nursing or licensed practical nursing in Maryland that is granted to a registered nurse or licensed practical nurse who has an active multistate license issued by another state in accordance with the Nurse Licensure Compact.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>“NCLEX” means the National Council Licensure Examination for initial licensure as a registered nurse or licensed practical nurse.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>“Nursing assistant” means either:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A certified nursing assistant; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A geriatric nursing assistant.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>“Preceptor” means a registered nurse who meets the qualifications of faculty as described in <cite path="|10|27|01|.16">Regulation .16 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>“Preceptorship” means an individualized refresher course approved by the Board and offered by an institution employing nurses which complies with <cite path="|10|27|01|.16">Regulation .16 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>“Student” means a registered nurse or licensed practical nurse who is required to complete a refresher course in order to maintain or reestablish an active license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>“Substantially equivalent” has the meaning stated in §§C and D of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(24)</num>
        <text>“Volunteer” means a licensee who, at the time of licensure renewal, elects to receive a license which only allows the licensee to provide professional services without remuneration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(25)</num>
        <text>“Written and oral competency in the English language” means the ability to demonstrate proficiency in listening, reading, speaking, and writing the English language.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>“Substantially equivalent” means a registered nursing or licensed practical nursing education program that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Contains theoretical learning experiences and related clinical learning experiences that include direct patient care within various settings consistent with program objectives, outcomes, or competencies conducted either concurrently with or after the theoretical learning experience; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Meets the curriculum requirements for Maryland schools of nursing at the time of the applicant’s graduation, including, but not limited to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The appropriate level of the graduate's intended scope of practice;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Didactic and clinical learning experiences that are diverse and consistent with program objectives, outcomes, or competencies;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Didactic and clinical instruction in nursing care of families and clients throughout the life span in a variety of care settings requiring nursing measures appropriate for:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The maintenance or restoration of mental and physical health;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Preventive, rehabilitative, and curative aspects of health care;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Biophysical, psychosocial, cultural, and spiritual components of health and illness; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Professional issues content; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Didactic and clinical instructional content that includes, but is not limited to, the areas of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Medical and surgical nursing;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Maternal and child health;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Psychiatric nursing; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Geriatric nursing.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>“Substantially equivalent” does not mean a registered nurse or licensed practical nursing education program in another state or country that does not have a supervised clinical learning experience requirement.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation app="2025-08-26" doc="Maryland Register, Volume 52, Issue 20" eff="2025-10-13" path="regulations|emergency|25-163-E" type="History" display="false"/>
      <annotation app="2025-10-13" doc="Maryland Register, Volume 52, Issue 20" eff="2025-10-13" path="regulations|final|25-163-F" type="History" display="false"/>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Fees.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The fees listed in this regulation are not refundable.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Licensure by examination fees are as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Registered nurse licensure — $187;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Licensed practical nurse licensure — $187; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An examination fee for registered nurse and licensed practical nurse licensure shall be paid by the candidate directly to the testing service.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Licensure by endorsement fees are as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Registered nurse licensure — $230; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Licensed practical nurse licensure — $230.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Temporary registered nurse or licensed practical nurse licensure fee —<em>$70.</em></text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Advanced practice registered nurse certification fees are as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Initial advanced practice certification — $50; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Each additional initial advanced practice certification — $25.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Specialty nursing practice certification fees are as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Initial forensic nurse examiner certification — $25; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Initial workers’ compensation medical case manager certification — $25.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Biennial renewal fees are as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Renewal of a registered nurse license — $165;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Renewal of a licensed practical nurse license — $165;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Renewal of a registered nurse or licensed practical nurse volunteer license — $73;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Renewal of an inactive license for a registered nurse or licensed practical nurse — $60;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Renewal of each advanced practice registered nurse certification is in addition to the registered nurse license renewal fee and is — $10; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Renewal of certification for specialty nursing practices regulated by the Board is in addition to the registered nurse license renewal fee and is as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Forensic nurse examiner certification — $10; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Workers’ compensation medical case manager certification — $10.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Health Care Practitioner User Fee.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In addition to a license fee, each registered nurse shall pay a non-refundable health care practitioner user fee assessed by the Maryland Health Care Commission in accordance with Health-General Article, §19-111(b)(4), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The health care practitioner user fee shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Included in the licensing fee paid to the Board; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Collected with the application for an initial or renewal license.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The amount of the assessed health care practitioner user fee shall be double the amount of the annual health care practitioner user fee for biennial licensure.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Board shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Account for the user fees; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Transfer the fees to the Maryland Health Care Commission on a quarterly basis.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Nurse Practitioner Preceptorship Tax Credit Fund.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>This fee applies only to nurse practitioners.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Board shall assess a separate $15 fee for the renewal of a nurse practitioner, regardless of the number of certifications held by the nurse practitioner.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Board shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Account for the fees collected under this section; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Transfer the fee to the Nurse Practitioner Preceptorship Tax Credit Fund.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Other fees are as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Verification of licensure — $45;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Copies of transcripts — $25; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Returned check fee —$30.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|27|01|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Licensure Exceptions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Registered nurses or licensed practical nurses who hold a current active license in any other state or jurisdiction may render nursing care:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For not more than 30 days, to an individual who is visiting the State for medical, educational, or personal reasons;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For the purpose of the interstate transport and care of patients traveling to and from Maryland; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>During an emergency situation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A registered nurse or licensed practical nurse who holds a multistate licensure privilege under the Nurse Licensure Compact may practice nursing in this State in accordance with the laws of this State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Nursing Graduate.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A nursing graduate is a graduate of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A Board-approved registered nursing or licensed practical nursing education program; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An out-of-state nursing education program determined to be equivalent by the Board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A nursing graduate may practice as set forth in §C(5)—(7) of this regulation if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The nursing graduate has an application for a license pending before the Board; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>One of the following circumstances exists:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The nursing graduate has not taken the NCLEX examination;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The nursing graduate has taken the NCLEX examination, but the results of the NCLEX examination are not yet known;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The nursing graduate has taken and passed the NCLEX examination but is waiting for the completion of the criminal history records check; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>The nursing graduate has taken and failed the NCLEX examination but has not failed the NCLEX examination more than one time within the 120 day period immediately following the submission of the application to the Board.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A nursing graduate shall cease practice as a nursing graduate:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>No later than 120 days after the date the nursing graduate submitted an application to the Board; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Immediately if the nursing graduate fails the second NCLEX examination.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the nursing graduate fails the NCLEX examination, the nursing graduate may practice as a nursing assistant provided the individual obtains certification as a nursing assistant and practices according to <cite path="|10.39.01">COMAR 10.39.01</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A nursing graduate shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Practice only under the direct supervision of a registered nurse who is physically present on the unit to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Cosign medication transcription, medication administration, and nursing documentation; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Continually observe, assist, coordinate, evaluate, and monitor the nursing graduate; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Use the initials "NG" after the nursing graduate's name as credentials.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>After successful completion of an organized staff development program which includes an evaluation that the nursing graduate is competent and in compliance with <cite path="10|27|01|.03|C.|(5)">§C(5) of this regulation</cite>, the nursing graduate may:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Transcribe medication orders if:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Written policies and procedures are available on the unit of care; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>An organized staff development program which includes skill validation has been successfully completed by the nursing graduate;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>After competency has been validated by the facility:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Administer medications and controlled substances; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Sign controlled substances sheets;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Document in the medical record with the abbreviation "NG";</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Perform patient assessments after the initial assessment or after the first assessment of the shift performed by the registered nurse; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Perform and document routine procedures taught within the nursing graduate's generic nursing program, including but not limited to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Placing nasal gastric tubes;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Performing urinary catheterizations;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Applying sterile dressings;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Performing blood sugar checks; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Obtaining specimens.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>A nursing graduate may not:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Work without the physical presence of and direct supervision by a registered nurse;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Refer to oneself or practice as a registered nurse (RN) or licensed practical nurse (LPN);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Be considered a staff person for purposes of a staffing pattern;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Accept charge responsibilities; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Perform initial patient assessment or the first patient assessment of a shift, develop patient plans of care, evaluate or document patient discharge, or independently administer medications or intravenous therapy.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation app="2025-08-26" doc="Maryland Register, Volume 52, Issue 20" eff="2025-10-13" path="regulations|emergency|25-163-E" type="History" display="false"/>
      <annotation app="2025-10-13" doc="Maryland Register, Volume 52, Issue 20" eff="2025-10-13" path="regulations|final|25-163-F" type="History" display="false"/>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|27|01|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>General Provisions for Applications.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant shall submit:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A completed application to the Board on the form that the Board requires;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>To a criminal history records check (CHRC) in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8">Health Occupations Article, §8</cite>–303, Annotated Code of Maryland;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Written evidence satisfactory to the Board that the applicant has submitted to a CHRC as required by <cite path="10|27|01|.04|A.|(2)">§A(2) of this regulation</cite> by submitting:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Two sets of fingerprints, as required by the Central Repository and the FBI; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>All fees required by the Central Repository and the FBI;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Any documentation requested from the applicant by the Board including, but not limited to, official certified or true test court documents and a signed, dated explanation written by the applicant, regarding the facts and circumstances, outcome, and current status of any criminal history record information received by the Board:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-303">Health Occupations Article, §8-303, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>In an answer to a question on the Board’s application form; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>From any other source; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Any additional documentation requested by the Board if the documentation received from the applicant under §A(4) this regulation is incomplete or insufficient.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If an application is not complete when initially submitted to the Board by the applicant, the applicant shall have no longer than 12 months from the date the application is received by the Board to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Complete the application; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide all information and documents required in <cite path="10|27|01|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If an applicant fails to provide to the Board a complete application and any additional documentation requested by the Board in <cite path="10|27|01|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> within 12 months from the date the application is received by the Board, then the application:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall be considered abandoned; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>May be destroyed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Once an application is deemed abandoned under <cite path="10|27|01|.04|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, an individual seeking licensure shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Submit a new application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Meet all of the requirements for licensure; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Pay the required fees that are in effect at the time of re-application.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|27|01|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Qualifications of Applicants for Examination.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant for the registered nurse licensure examination shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Complete satisfactorily and meet all requirements for a diploma or degree from a registered nursing education program approved by the Board; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Have a diploma or degree from a registered nursing education program in another state, territory, or country determined by the Board to be substantially equivalent to the registered nursing education program approved in this State at the time of the applicant's graduation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An applicant for the licensed practical nurse licensure examination shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Meet all requirements for a high school diploma or its equivalent and complete satisfactorily and meet all requirements for a diploma from:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A licensed practical nursing education program approved by the Board; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A licensed practical nursing education program in any other state, territory, or country determined by the Board to be substantially equivalent to the licensed practical nursing education programs approved in this State at the time of the applicant's graduation; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Meet the requirements of <cite path="10|27|01|.05|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Applicants who are unable to prove written and oral competency in the English language in accordance with Health Occupation Article, §8-302(e)(2) or (4), Annotated Code of Maryland, shall submit evidence of proficiency in listening, reading, speaking, and writing the English language by obtaining a minimum passing score on one of the following Board-approved English language competency examinations:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Test of English as a Foreign Language Internet Based Test (TOEFL iBT) with minimum passing scores of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Listening — 21;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Reading — 19;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Speaking — 26;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Writing — 19; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Overall score of at least 84;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>International English Language Testing System (IELTS) with minimum passing scores of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Listening — 6;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Reading — 6;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Speaking — 6;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Writing — 6; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Overall score of at least 6.5;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Michigan English Test (MET) with minimum passing scores of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Listening — 53;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Reading — 53;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Speaking — 53; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Writing — 53;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Pearson Test of English (PTE) Academic with minimum passing scores of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Listening — 50;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Reading — 50;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Speaking — 50;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Writing — 50; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Overall score of at least 55; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Occupational English Test (OET) with minimum passing scores of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Listening — 300;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Reading — 300;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Speaking — 300; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Writing — 300.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An applicant whose basic nursing education was completed in another country shall have the applicant's transcript evaluated by the Commission on Graduates of Foreign Nursing Schools.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Application for Licensure by Examination.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Comply with all of the requirements in <cite path="|10|27|01|.04|A.">Regulation .04A of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>File and submit a completed application to the National Council of State Boards of Nursing on the form required; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Pay any required fees.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Each application shall be signed by the nurse administrator of the school or program or an officer of the school to whom this responsibility has been designated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Applications may be signed before graduation and it shall be the responsibility of the person signing the application to submit written verification of program completion before the licensure examination.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Applicants whose applications are complete and who, for any reason, fail to take the examination within 6 months shall be required to reapply and pay all fees.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The authorization to test card shall be valid for a period of 6 months. If the applicant fails to complete the examination within that time frame the applicant is required to re-register and pay the NCLEX testing fee.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Examination Procedures.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Examinations shall be held at least once per year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board will participate with the National Council of State Boards of Nursing, Inc., in preparing and administering the National Council Licensure Examination for registered nurse and practical nurse licensure.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The results of the NCLEX shall be reported as pass or fail.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An authorization to test card shall be sent to each candidate that the Board determines to be eligible for the examination.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Examination scores shall be released only to the candidate and to the school of nursing from which the candidate graduated, except on written authorization of the candidate.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Candidates for Maryland licensure may write the licensure examination in any jurisdiction.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Candidates applying for licensure in other jurisdictions may write the licensure examination in Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Applicants Requiring Special Accommodation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant with a disability may request modifications in examination materials or procedures. The applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Make the request for modifications in writing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Include in the request the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The candidate's name;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The date of the examination to be modified;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A letter from the appropriate medical professional which:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Confirms the disability; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Provides information describing the accommodations required; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A letter from the candidate's education program, indicating what modifications, if any, were granted by the program.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Requests for modification and supporting documentation shall be received by the application deadline.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Speech-Impaired Applicants.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant who claims a speech impairment shall fulfill all requirements for application, and shall submit to the Board documentation of the applicant's impairment, from:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An otolaryngologist who has current certification from the American Board of Otolaryngology; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A speech-language pathologist who has current certification from the American Speech-Language-Hearing Association.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board shall require a speech-impaired applicant to prove the applicant's ability to communicate adequately with patients and other health care professionals by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Submitting letters from instructors in a nursing program, attesting to the applicant's ability to communicate in a professionally competent manner; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Meeting with the Board to demonstrate the manner in which communication with patients will occur.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A speech-language pathologist or otolaryngologist may be asked to attend the meeting in an advisory capacity to the Board to aid in assessing an applicant's ability to communicate.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A foreign-educated, speech-impaired applicant shall notify the Board before taking a Board-approved standardized test for competency in the English language.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Board shall attempt to locate a speech-language pathologist fluent in the applicant's native language to assess the impairment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A foreign-educated applicant who is in need of foreign accent reduction, but who has competency in the applicant’s native language, may obtain assistance from a bilingual speech-language pathologist before attempting to pass a test for competency in the English language.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Licensure by Endorsement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant licensed to practice registered nursing or practical nursing in another state, territory, or country is eligible for licensure without examination if the applicant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Complies with all of the requirements under <cite path="|10|27|01|.04|A.">Regulation .04A of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Pays the required fee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Submits the following verifications directly to the Board from the appropriate authority:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>That at the time that applicant graduated from the nursing education program, it was approved as a registered nursing or licensed practical nursing education program in that state, territory, or country;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>That the applicant meet the educational qualifications of this State at the time of the applicant's graduation from the nursing education program;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Verification of successful completion of the licensure examination under the laws of another state, territory, or country;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>That the examination used for licensure was the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>"State Board Test Pool Examination — Registered Nurse or Practical Nurse", from 1952—1982;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>"National Council Licensure Examination — Registered Nurse or Practical Nurse", from 1982 to the present;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>"National League for Nursing State-Constructed Board Examination, Registered Nurse or Practical Nurse", before 1952; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>"Canadian Nurses Association Test Service Examination for Registered Nurses" taken before 1982; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Proof of written and oral competency in the English language in accordance with <cite path="|10|27|01|.05|C.">Regulation .05C of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Whose basic nursing education was completed in another country, has the applicant's transcript evaluated by the Commission on Graduates of Foreign Nursing Schools; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Presents evidence of 1,000 hours of active nursing practice within the last 5 years or successful completion of a Board-approved refresher course or preceptor program.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An applicant who is unable to prove proficiency in the English language in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-302">Health Occupations Article, §8-302(e), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, may be required to submit evidence of competency in the English language by obtaining a minimum passing score on a Board-approved English language competency examination in accordance with <cite path="|10|27|01|.05|C.">Regulation .05C of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Those applicants who cannot present evidence of 1,000 hours of active nursing practice within the last 5 years, or successful completion of a Board-approved refresher course or preceptor program, may apply for inactive license.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Issuance of Licenses.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An initial license shall be issued to each applicant passing the licensure examination or qualifying for licensure by endorsement provided that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The applicant meets all the requirements of this chapter; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Board has:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Received and reviewed the criminal history record information; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Approved the application.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An initial license may not be issued for less than 90 days.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An incorrect license issued as a result of a Board error will be corrected in the Board’s data base at no charge to the licensee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A licensee who requests a change of name for a license shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Make the request in writing on the form required by the Board; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide appropriate legal documentation supporting the change.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Temporary Licensure.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board may issue a temporary license to an applicant who passed the licensure examination and is waiting for the criminal history records check to be completed or who is licensed as a registered nurse or licensed practical nurse in any other state provided that the applicant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Completes the required application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If licensed in another state, presents a copy of a current, active license in another state;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Presents positive personal identification;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Pays the required fee; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Provides written, verified evidence that the applicant has submitted to a criminal history records check in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-303">Health Occupations Article, §8-303, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in §§C and E of this regulation, temporary licenses expire 90 days after date of issuance and are not renewable.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A temporary license may be extended for an additional 90 days if the applicant is waiting for the completion of the criminal history record information.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Board shall revoke a temporary license if the criminal history records check reveals that the applicant has been convicted of or pled guilty or nolo contendere to an act that would be cause for discipline under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-316">Health Occupations Article, §8-316(a), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If an applicant does not meet the practice requirement in <cite path="|10|27|01|.10|A.|(5)">Regulation .10A(5) of this chapter</cite>, a temporary license may be extended every 90 days:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Pending completion of the practice requirement; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provided that the total length of the temporary license does not exceed 12 months from the original date of issuance.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|27|01|.13">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Renewal of License.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board shall renew the license of a licensee who meets all the requirements of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-312">Health Occupations Article, §8-312, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite> and of this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board shall renew licenses biennially according to the following schedule:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A registered nurse or licensed practical nurse with an odd-numbered birth year shall always renew in an odd-numbered year not later than the 28th day of the licensee’s birth month; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A registered nurse or licensed practical nurse with an even-numbered birth year shall always renew in an even-numbered year not later than the 28th day of the licensee’s birth month.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>At least 3 months before a license expires, the Board shall send the licensee a renewal notice by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>First-class mail to the last known address of the licensee; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Electronic means to the last known electronic address of the licensee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>It shall be the responsibility of the licensee to notify the Board if a renewal notice is not received.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Board cannot guarantee that renewal applications received later than 30 days before the expiration date will be processed before the expiration date.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Board shall issue a volunteer license to any registered nurse or licensed practical nurse who meets the licensure renewal requirements provided the licensee:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Certifies to the Board that the licensee provides professional services only as a volunteer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Completes the required application; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Pays the required fee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Active Licensure Renewal.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An individual applying for active licensure renewal shall show evidence of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>1,000 hours of active nursing practice within the 5 years immediately preceding the date of the renewal application;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Satisfactory completion of all requirements for a diploma or degree from a Board-approved nursing education program within the 5 years immediately preceding the date of the renewal application; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Completion of 30 continuing education units (CEUs) within the 2 years immediately preceding the date of the renewal application.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>College or University Coursework.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A renewal applicant may submit qualifying college or university coursework to fulfill the requirement under <cite path="10|27|01|.13|G.|(1)|(c)">§G(1)(c) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>15 CEUs shall be awarded for each semester hour completed of a qualifying college or university course.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>For the coursework to qualify:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The college or university course shall be related to the renewal applicant’s nursing practice; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The renewal applicant shall receive a grade of C or higher, or the numeric equivalent in the course.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>An official transcript shall be acceptable as proof of completion of a qualifying college or university course.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Continuing Education.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="10|27|01|.13|G.|(2)">§G(2) of this regulation</cite>, CEUs shall be approved by an entity listed in <cite path="10|27|01|.13|H.|(5)">§H(5) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>CEUs used for the purpose of renewing a license are subject to random audits by the Board or the Board’s designee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>CEUs that are used for the purpose of renewing a license shall be earned within the 2 years immediately preceding the date of the renewal application.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The renewal applicant shall be responsible for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Ensuring that a CEU course, forum, or meeting has been approved for CEUs by one of the entities listed in <cite path="10|27|01|.13|H.|(5)">§H(5) of this regulation</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Retaining evidence of completed CEUs that are submitted for the purpose of renewing a license for 6 years after the license is renewed; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Producing evidence of completed CEUs for an audit by the Board or the board’s designee within 30 days of the request.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Board shall accept CEUs awarded or approved by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Area Health Education Centers (AHEC), including all local, state, and national centers;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The American Nurses Association (ANA);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The American Nurses Credentialing Center (ANCC);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Professional organizations offering CEUs for the purpose of renewing a national certification for advanced practice registered nursing;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>A local, state, or national professional nursing association that provides educational programs;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The Maryland Nurses Association (MNA);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>The National Council of State Boards of Nursing; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>The National League for Nursing.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>CEUs may not be carried forward into the next renewal period.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>An individual applying for active licensure renewal who do not meet the requirements of <cite path="10|27|01|.13|G.">§G of this regulation</cite> shall be required to successfully complete a Board-approved refresher program or Board-approved preceptorship program prior to renewal of the license.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Tax Deficiencies.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>On a monthly basis, the Board shall notify the Office of the Comptroller of any licensee or certificate-holder:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Whose license expires within the next 4-month period; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Whose identity has not previously been provided to the Office of the Comptroller.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Upon notification by the Office of the Comptroller of any licensee or certificate-holder who is delinquent in the payment of undisputed taxes or unemployment insurance contributions, the Board shall notify the licensee or certificate-holder that renewal processing shall be delayed until the Office of the Comptroller verifies that the licensee or certificate-holder has made arrangements for payment of the undisputed taxes or unemployment insurance contributions that are satisfactory to the unit responsible for collection.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Upon notification by the Office of the Comptroller that the licensee or certificate-holder has made satisfactory arrangements for payment of the undisputed taxes or unemployment insurance contributions, and where the licensee or certificate-holder is otherwise qualified for licensure, the Board shall renew the license or certificate.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Along with the renewal notice in accordance with <cite path="10|27|01|.13|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, the Board shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notify every renewal applicant who is required to have a criminal history records check in the selected birth month; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Send the renewal applicant instructions for downloading and completing the documents needed to submit to a criminal history records check.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>If a renewal applicant is out of the state, the Board shall mail a packet to the applicant with the required documents and instructions for completing the documents.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>Upon notification by the Board that a criminal history records check is required before a license can be renewed, a renewal applicant shall comply with all of the requirements under <cite path="|10|27|01|.04|A.">Regulation .04A of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>Criminal history record checks for renewal applicants shall be scheduled according to the licensee's birth month as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In 2025 — all applicants with an August or September birth month;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In 2026 — all applicants with a September or October birth month;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>In 2027 — all applicants with an October or November birth month;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>In 2028 — all applicants with a November or December birth month;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>In 2029 — all applicants with a December or January birth month;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>In 2030 — all applicants with a January or February birth month;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>In 2031 — all applicants with a February or March birth month;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>In 2032 — all applicants with a March or April birth month;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>In 2033 — all applicants with an April or May birth month;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>In 2034 — all applicants with a May or June birth month;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>In 2035 — all applicants with a June or July birth month; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>In 2036 — all applicants with a July or August birth month.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>For renewal applicants who are required to submit to a criminal history records check, the Board may not renew a license without written documentation that the applicant has submitted to a criminal history record check in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-303">Health Occupations Article, §8-303, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Inactive Status.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board shall place the license of any registered nurse or licensed practical nurse on inactive status if the licensee:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Has not satisfactorily completed 1,000 hours of active nursing practice or graduated from an approved nursing program within the 5-year period immediately preceding the date of anticipated renewal or chooses inactive status;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Completes the biennial application for inactive status; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Pays all fees.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A licensee on inactive status may not practice nursing in this State. However, a registered nurse on inactive status may use the title "registered nurse", and a practical nurse on inactive status may use the title "licensed practical nurse".</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A licensee on inactive status may apply for an active status license provided that the licensee:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Meets the renewal requirements of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-312">Health Occupations Article, §8-312, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Submits to the Board:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The required application; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Written, verified evidence that the licensee has submitted to a criminal history records check in accordance with <cite path="|10|27|01|.13">Regulation .13 of this chapter</cite> by:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Submitting two sets of fingerprints required by the Central Repository and the FBI; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Paying all fees required by the Central Repository and the FBI.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An additional fee may not be charged to change from inactive to active status.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Expiration of License.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A license expires on the 28th day of the licensee's birth month.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A licensee has a 30-day grace period beyond the expiration date of a license to renew a license.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Refresher Course and Preceptorship Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Refresher courses and preceptor programs, as defined in <cite path="|10|27|01|.01|B.">Regulation .01B of this chapter</cite>, shall be approved by the Board before their implementation and at least every 5 years after that.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The registered nurse curriculum shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Have a minimum of 80 theory hours, 60 clinical hours, and 8 hours of a classroom laboratory training before the on-site clinical experience;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Include the following content areas:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The nursing process;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Management and delegation of patient care;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Documentation and information management;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Pharmacology, including calculation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Nursing care of patients with alterations in body systems;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Emergency procedures;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Disaster response; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Professional responsibilities, which include, but are not limited to, the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Trends in nursing and the health care system;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Legal aspects of nursing; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Development and initiation of patient and community health education.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The practical nurse curriculum shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Have a minimum of 60 theory hours, 60 on-site clinical hours, and 8 hours of a classroom laboratory training before the on-site clinical experience;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Include the following content areas:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The nursing process with the licensed practical nurse as a contributor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Provision and delegation of patient care under the supervision of a registered nurse;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Documentation and information management;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Pharmacology, including calculations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Nursing care of patients with common health problems;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Emergency procedures;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Disaster response; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Professional responsibilities, which include, but are not limited to, the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Trends in nursing;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Legal aspects of nursing; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Contribution to patient health teaching.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The organization and utilization of curriculum materials shall be based on accepted educational principles.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Faculty Qualifications.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Faculty shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be a registered nurse as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-101">Health Occupations Article, §8-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Have a baccalaureate degree in nursing.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A minimum of 3 years of clinical and teaching experience is recommended.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Faculty shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Plan, implement, evaluate, and revise the educational program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Select and evaluate clinical facilities used to achieve program objectives.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Develop and utilize:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Written examinations to measure achievement of program objectives.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An evaluation tool to measure achievement of clinical competencies. The clinical competencies shall be based upon the registered nurse and licensed practical nurse standards of practice.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A mechanism for student evaluation of the course.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Students shall complete theoretical instruction either before or concurrent with clinical instruction.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>All program requirements including required clinical hours shall be completed within 12 months of the starting date of the refresher course.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Clinical facilities shall provide sufficient opportunities to meet the learning objectives of the refresher course.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>The faculty/student ratio may not exceed 1:10 in the clinical area.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|27|01|.17">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.17</num>
    <heading>Reinstatement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board shall reinstate the license of a former licensee who has failed to renew the license for any reason if the former licensee meets the renewal requirements.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>After January 1, 2010, an applicant for reinstatement who has failed to renew the applicant's license for a period of 1 year or more shall submit to a criminal history records check before the license is reinstated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Temporary License.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board shall issue a temporary license to a former licensee who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Applies for reinstatement in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-313">Health Occupations Article, §8-313, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Meets the renewal requirements of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-312">Health Occupations Article, §8-312, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Is awaiting the completion of the criminal history records check.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The temporary license issued pursuant to <cite path="10|27|01|.17|C.|(1)">§C(1) of this regulation</cite> is effective until the earlier of 90 days after the date of issue or the date the Board issues an active license.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation app="2025-08-26" doc="Maryland Register, Volume 52, Issue 20" eff="2025-10-13" path="regulations|emergency|25-163-E" type="History" display="false"/>
      <annotation app="2025-10-13" doc="Maryland Register, Volume 52, Issue 20" eff="2025-10-13" path="regulations|final|25-163-F" type="History" display="false"/>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.18</num>
    <heading>Violation of Regulations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If a program is thought to be in violation of this chapter, the following steps shall be taken:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board shall notify the program of the regulations it is violating;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The program shall submit a plan with a proposed time frame for correcting the violations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The plan shall be due within 30 days of receipt of notification of the violations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Board's professional staff may, at the request of the Board, visit the program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>After receipt of the plan, the Board shall provide the program with a reasonable time frame within which to correct the violations; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Upon expiration of the time period for correcting violations, a member of the Board's staff shall visit the program to determine if the school is in compliance with the regulations, and report to the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the program does not correct the violations within the time frame established by the Board, the Board:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall notify the program that it has not corrected violations in a reasonable time and schedule a hearing in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If, after a hearing, determines that the program or preceptorship is in violation of the regulations, may place a program on either conditional approval or remove it from the approved list of programs. If the Board places the program on conditional approval, the Board may request that a program suspend admission of students. A program placed on conditional approval shall remain in that status until the Board determines it has complied with the regulations.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Unless authorized to practice as a nursing graduate under this chapter, an individual may not use the words "nursing graduate", the abbreviation "NG", or any other title, symbol, abbreviation, sign, card, device, or other representation with the intent to represent that the individual practices as a nursing graduate.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|1-213">1-213</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-201">8-201</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-205">8-205</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-206">8-206</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-301">8-301</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-315">8-315</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-6">8-6</cite>A-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|05">05</cite>(a), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-701">8-701</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-7">8-7</cite>A-01, Article 1116(b)(2), and 8-703; Tax-General Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtg|10-738">10-738</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtg|10-739">10-739</cite>(b)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtg|1">1</cite>); Annotated Code of Maryland; Ch. 486, Acts of 2012; Chs. 281 and 282, Acts of 2013; Chs. 385 and 386, Acts of 2016; and Chs. 234 and 234, Acts of 2017</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1978-05-05"><cite path="|10|27|01|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite>, C amended effective May 5, 1978 (5:9 Md. R. 684)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1976-01-07"><cite path="|10|27|01|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended effective January 7, 1976 (3:1 Md. R. 40)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1976-10-13"><cite path="|10|27|01|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite>, F amended effective October 13, 1976 (13:21 Md. R. 1206)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1975-05-14"><cite path="|10|27|01|.02|G.">Regulation .02G</cite> amended effective May 14, 1975 (2:10 Md. R. 752)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1976-01-07"><cite path="|10|27|01|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective January 7, 1976 (3:1 Md. R. 40)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1979-03-23"><cite path="|10|27|01|.08">Regulation .08</cite> repealed effective March 23, 1979 (6:6 Md. R. 512)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|10|27|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|27|01|.07">.07</cite> renumbered as Regulations .02, .03, .04, .05, .07, .08, and .09, respectively</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1979-03-23"><cite path="|10|27|01|.01">Regulation .01</cite> adopted effective March 23, 1979 (6:6 Md. R. 512)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1979-03-23"><cite path="|10|27|01|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite>, C, E, G, H amended effective March 23, 1979 (6:6 Md. R. 512)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1979-06-29"><cite path="|10|27|01|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite>, C amended effective June 29, 1979 (6:13 Md. R. 1128)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1979-03-23">Regulations .03A—F, H and .05A amended effective March 23, 1979 (6:6 Md. R. 512)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1979-03-23"><cite path="|10|27|01|.06">Regulation .06</cite> adopted effective March 23, 1979 (6:6 Md. R. 512)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1979-03-23">Regulations .08A, C and .09 amended effective March 23, 1979 (6:6 Md. R. 512)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-08-11">Regulations <cite path="|10|27|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|27|01|.09">.09</cite> repealed effective August 11, 1986 (13:16 Md. R. 1827)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-08-11" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|10|27|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|27|01|.11">.11</cite> adopted effective August 11, 1986 (13:16 Md. R. 1827)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-08-15">Regulations <cite path="|10|27|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|27|01|.06">.06</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective April 11, 1994 (21:9 Md. R. 744); amended permanently effective August 15, 1994 (21:16 Md. R. 1384)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-05-10"><cite path="|10|27|01|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective December 11, 1989 (16:24 Md. R. 2620); May 10, 1993 (20:9 Md. R. 779)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-05-10"><cite path="|10|27|01|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended effective December 11, 1989 (16:24 Md. R. 2620); October 1, 1990 (17:19 Md. R. 2321); May 10, 1993 (20:9 Md. R. 779)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-01-02"><cite path="|10|27|01|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 1, 1991 (18:14 Md. R. 1606); adopted permanently effective January 2, 1992 (18:25 Md. R. 2751)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1996-02-12"><cite path="|10|27|01|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective October 27, 1995 (22:23 Md. R. 1795); amended permanently effective February 12, 1996 (23:3 Md. R. 169)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-03-09"><cite path="|10|27|01|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective November 14, 1997 (24:25 Md. R. 1717); amended permanently effective March 9, 1998 (25:5 Md. R. 369)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-11-15"><cite path="|10|27|01|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective August 2, 1999 (26:17 Md. R. 1314); amended permanently effective November 15, 1999 (26:23 Md. R. 1777)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-11-08"><cite path="|10|27|01|.04|D.">Regulation .04D</cite> adopted effective November 8, 1993 (20:22 Md. R. 1707)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1988-03-01"><cite path="|10|27|01|.06|G.">Regulation .06G</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective November 1, 1987 (14:23 Md. R. 2412); adopted permanently effective March 1, 1988 (15:3 Md. R. 304)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-05-10"><cite path="|10|27|01|.06|G.">Regulation .06G</cite> amended effective May 10, 1993 (20:9 Md. R. 779)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-05-10"><cite path="|10|27|01|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective October 1, 1990 (17:19 Md. R. 2321); May 10, 1993 (20:9 Md. R. 779)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-11-08"><cite path="|10|27|01|.07|A.">Regulation .07A</cite> amended effective December 11, 1989 (16:24 Md. R. 2620); November 8, 1993 (20:22 Md. R. 1707)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-10-01"><cite path="|10|27|01|.08|E.">Regulation .08E</cite> adopted effective October 1, 1990 (17:19 Md. R. 2321)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1996-02-12"><cite path="|10|27|01|.09">Regulation .09</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective October 27, 1995 (22:23 Md. R. 1795); amended permanently effective February 12, 1996 (23:3 Md. R. 169)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-05-10"><cite path="|10|27|01|.09|C.">Regulation .09C</cite> amended effective May 10, 1993 (20:9 Md. R. 779)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-12-11"><cite path="|10|27|01|.10">Regulation .10</cite> amended effective December 11, 1989 (16:24 Md. R. 2620)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-10-01"><cite path="|10|27|01|.10|D.">Regulation .10D</cite> amended and H adopted effective October 1, 1990 (17:19 Md. R. 2321)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-05-10"><cite path="|10|27|01|.10|I.">Regulation .10I</cite> adopted effective May 10, 1993 (20:9 Md. R. 779)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-12-11"><cite path="|10|27|01|.11">Regulation .11</cite> recodified to Regulation .12 and new Regulation .11 adopted effective December 11, 1989 (16:24 Md. R. 2620)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-12-11"><cite path="|10|27|01|.13">Regulation .13</cite> adopted effective December 11, 1989 (16:24 Md. R. 2620)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-05-10">Regulations .14 and .15 adopted effective May 10, 1993 (20:9 Md. R. 779)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-04-30" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective April 30, 2001 (28:8 Md. R. 760)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-03-01"><cite path="|10|27|01|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective March 1, 2004 (31:4 Md. R. 316)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-05-07"><cite path="|10|27|01|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective January 2, 2007 (34:4 Md. R. 397); amended permanently effective May 7, 2007 (34:9 Md. R. 825)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-09-22"><cite path="|10|27|01|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective September 22, 2008 (35:19 Md. R. 1717)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-09-22"><cite path="|10|27|01|.01|C.">Regulation .01C</cite> adopted effective September 22, 2008 (35:19 Md. R. 1717)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-04-01"><cite path="|10|27|01|.02">Regulation .02</cite> repealed and new Regulation .02 adopted effective April 1, 2013 (40:6 Md. R. 474)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-08-27"><cite path="|10|27|01|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended effective September 3, 2001 (28:17 Md. R. 1556); August 27, 2007 (34:17 Md. R. 1508)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-03-01"><cite path="|10|27|01|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective March 1, 2004 (31:4 Md. R. 316)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-09-22"><cite path="|10|27|01|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite> amended effective September 22, 2008 (35:19 Md. R. 1717)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-09-22"><cite path="|10|27|01|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective September 22, 2008 (35:19 Md. R. 1717)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-09-03"><cite path="|10|27|01|.04|B.">Regulation .04B</cite> amended effective September 3, 2001 (28:17 Md. R. 1556)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-09-27"><cite path="|10|27|01|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective March 1, 2004 (31:4 Md. R. 316); September 27, 2004 (31:19 Md. R. 1433)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-05-07"><cite path="|10|27|01|.05|A.">Regulation .05A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective January 2, 2007 (34:4 Md. R. 397); amended permanently effective May 7, 2007 (34:9 Md. R. 825)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-09-22"><cite path="|10|27|01|.05|D.">Regulation .05D</cite> amended effective September 22, 2008 (35:19 Md. R. 1717)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-05-07"><cite path="|10|27|01|.05|I.">Regulation .05I</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective January 2, 2007 (34:4 Md. R. 397); amended permanently effective May 7, 2007 (34:9 Md. R. 825)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-05-07"><cite path="|10|27|01|.09|A.">Regulation .09A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective January 2, 2007 (34:4 Md. R. 397); amended permanently effective May 7, 2007 (34:9 Md. R. 825)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-01-06"><cite path="|10|27|01|.09|A.">Regulation .09A</cite> amended effective January 6, 2014 (40:26 Md. R. 2164)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-05-07"><cite path="|10|27|01|.09|D.">Regulation .09D</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective January 2, 2007 (34:4 Md. R. 397); amended permanently effective May 7, 2007 (34:9 Md. R. 825)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-05-07"><cite path="|10|27|01|.11">Regulation .11</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective January 2, 2007 (34:4 Md. R. 397); amended permanently effective May 7, 2007 (34:9 Md. R. 825)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-04-19"><cite path="|10|27|01|.11">Regulation .11</cite> amended effective April 19, 2010 (37:8 Md. R. 617)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-04-01"><cite path="|10|27|01|.12">Regulation .12</cite> amended effective April 1, 2013 (40:6 Md. R. 474)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-04-24"><cite path="|10|27|01|.12|F.">Regulation .12F</cite>, G amended effective April 24, 2006 (33:8 Md. R. 733)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-10-11"><cite path="|10|27|01|.12|H.">Regulation .12H</cite> adopted effective October 11, 2004 (31:20 Md. R. 1485)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-05-07"><cite path="|10|27|01|.12|I.">Regulation .12I</cite>, J, K adopted as an emergency provision effective January 2, 2007 (34:4 Md. R. 397); amended permanently effective May 7, 2007 (34:9 Md. R. 825)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-04-19"><cite path="|10|27|01|.12|I.">Regulation .12I</cite> amended effective April 19, 2010 (37:8 Md. R. 617)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-04-19"><cite path="|10|27|01|.12|I.">Regulation .12I</cite>-1, I-2, J-1 adopted effective April 19, 2010 (37:8 Md. R. 617)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-06-13"><cite path="|10|27|01|.12|I.">Regulation .12I</cite>-1 amended effective June 13, 2011 (38:12 Md. R. 705)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-05-07"><cite path="|10|27|01|.13">Regulation .13</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective January 2, 2007 (34:4 Md. R. 397); amended permanently effective May 7, 2007 (34:9 Md. R. 825)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-04-24"><cite path="|10|27|01|.13|A.">Regulation .13A</cite> amended effective April 24, 2006 (33:8 Md. R. 733)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-01-06"><cite path="|10|27|01|.13|C.">Regulation .13C</cite> amended effective January 6, 2014 (40:26 Md. R. 2164)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-04-24"><cite path="|10|27|01|.15">Regulation .15</cite> amended effective April 24, 2006 (33:8 Md. R. 733)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-04-19"><cite path="|10|27|01|.16">Regulation .16</cite> amended effective April 19, 2010 (37:8 Md. R. 617)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-03-01"><cite path="|10|27|01|.17|C.">Regulation .17C</cite> amended effective March 1, 2004 (31:4 Md. R. 316)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-02-13" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective February 13, 2017 (44:3 Md. R. 189)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-07-03"><cite path="|10|27|01|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective July 2, 2018 (45:13 Md. R. 667); June 17, 2019 (46:12 Md. R. 544); August 23, 2021 (48:17 Md. R. 669); Regulation .01B amended as an emergency provision effective January 4, 2022 (49:4 Md. R. 297); emergency status expired effective July 3, 2022</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-03-05"><cite path="|10|27|01|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective September 7, 2022 (49:21 Md. R. 940); emergency status expired effective March 5, 2023</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-10-31"><cite path="|10|27|01|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective May 4, 2023 (50:10 Md. R. 405); emergency status expired effective October 31, 2023</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-10-13"><cite path="|10|27|01|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective August 26, 2025 (52:20 Md. R. 999); amended permanently effective October 13, 2025 (52:20 Md. R. 1001)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-08-23"><cite path="|10|27|01|.01|D.">Regulation .01D</cite> adopted effective August 23, 2021 (48:17 Md. R. 669)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-07-01"><cite path="|10|27|01|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective January 29, 2018 (45:2 Md. R. 69); July 1, 2025 (52:10 Md. R. 436)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-07-02"><cite path="|10|27|01|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective July 2, 2018 (45:13 Md. R. 667)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-07-03"><cite path="|10|27|01|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite>, C amended as an emergency provision effective January 4, 2022 (49:4 Md. R. 297); emergency status expired effective July 3, 2022</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-10-31"><cite path="|10|27|01|.03|C.">Regulation .03C</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective September 7, 2022 (49:21 Md. R. 940); emergency status expired effective March 5, 2023; Regulation .03C amended as an emergency provision effective May 4, 2023 (50:10 Md. R. 405); emergency status expired effective October 31, 2023</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-10-13"><cite path="|10|27|01|.03|C.">Regulation .03C</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective August 26, 2025 (52:20 Md. R. 999); amended permanently effective October 13, 2025 (52:20 Md. R. 1001)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-07-02"><cite path="|10|27|01|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective July 2, 2018 (45:13 Md. R. 667)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-08-23"><cite path="|10|27|01|.05|C.">Regulation .05C</cite> amended effective August 23, 2021 (48:17 Md. R. 669)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-04-03"><cite path="|10|27|01|.05|C.">Regulation .05C</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective October 6, 2023 (50:22 Md. R. 972); emergency status expired effective April 3, 2024</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-06-24"><cite path="|10|27|01|.05|C.">Regulation .05C</cite> amended effective June 24, 2024 (51:12 Md. R. 619)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-07-02"><cite path="|10|27|01|.06|F.">Regulation .06F</cite> repealed effective July 2, 2018 (45:13 Md. R. 667)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-07-02"><cite path="|10|27|01|.09|D.">Regulation .09D</cite>, F amended effective July 2, 2018 (45:13 Md. RR. 667)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-08-23"><cite path="|10|27|01|.10">Regulation .10</cite> amended effective August 28, 2017 (44:17 Md. R. 835); July 2, 2018 (45:13 Md. R. 667); August 23, 2021 (48:17 Md. R. 669)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-07-02"><cite path="|10|27|01|.11">Regulation .11</cite> amended effective July 2, 2018 (45:13 Md. R. 667)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-07-02"><cite path="|10|27|01|.12">Regulation .12</cite> amended effective July 2, 2018 (45:13 Md. R. 667)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-06-17"><cite path="|10|27|01|.13">Regulation .13</cite> amended effective July 2, 2018 (45:13 Md. R. 667); June 17, 2019 (46:12 Md. R. 544)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-08-18"><cite path="|10|27|01|.13|N.">Regulation .13N</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective June 24, 2025 (52:15 Md. R. 810); amended permanently effective August 18, 2025 (52:16 Md. R. 846)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-07-02"><cite path="|10|27|01|.14">Regulation .14</cite> amended effective July 2, 2018 (45:13 Md. R. 667)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-07-02"><cite path="|10|27|01|.15|B.">Regulation .15B</cite> amended effective July 2, 2018 (45:13 Md. R. 667)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-07-02"><cite path="|10|27|01|.16|E.">Regulation .16E</cite> amended effective July 2, 2018 (45:13 Md. R. 667)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-07-03"><cite path="|10|27|01|.17|C.">Regulation .17C</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective January 4, 2022 (49:4 Md. R. 297); emergency status expired effective July 3, 2022</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-03-05"><cite path="|10|27|01|.17|C.">Regulation .17C</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective September 7, 2022 (49:21 Md. R. 940); emergency status expired effective March 5, 2023</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-10-31"><cite path="|10|27|01|.17|C.">Regulation .17C</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective May 4, 2023 (50:10 Md. R. 405); emergency status expired effective October 31, 2023</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-10-13"><cite path="|10|27|01|.17|C.">Regulation .17C</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective August 26, 2025 (52:20 Md. R. 999); adopted permanently effective October 13, 2025 (52:20 Md. R. 1001)</annotation>
    <annotation app="2025-08-26" doc="Maryland Register, Volume 52, Issue 20" eff="2025-10-13" path="regulations|emergency|25-163-E" type="History" display="false"/>
    <annotation app="2025-10-13" doc="Maryland Register, Volume 52, Issue 20" eff="2025-10-13" path="regulations|final|25-163-F" type="History" display="false"/>
  </annotations>
</container>
