<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>24</num>
  <heading>Compelling Purpose Disclosure</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Disclosure for Compelling Public Purpose.</heading>
    <text>A custodian of Board records may find that a compelling public purpose warrants disclosure of information in a certification, licensing, or investigative file, whether or not there has been a request for the information under the following circumstances:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>There is possible criminal activity and the disclosure is to a federal, state, or local law enforcement or prosecutorial official or authority;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>There is possible violation of law and the disclosure is to a federal, state, or local authority that has jurisdiction over the individual whose conduct may be a violation or over a facility in which the individual has practiced and the information disclosed is limited to that information relevant to the possible violation by that individual; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>There is conduct by an individual that the Board reasonably believes may pose a risk to the public health, safety, or welfare and the disclosure is to a law enforcement authority, administrative official, or agency that regulates the individual or regulates a facility in which the individual has practiced, or to a hospital or other health care facility where the individual has privileges.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Other Disclosures.</heading>
    <text>This chapter does not prevent or limit the ability of the Board to disclose general licensing information as provided in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-617">State Government Article, §10-617(h), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or any information which the Board may otherwise disclose by law.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-617">State Government Article, §10-617(h)(3), </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-07-23">Effective date: July 23, 2001 (28:14 Md. R. 1322)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
