<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>25</num>
  <heading>Cosmetic Procedures</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Exclusion from Regulations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter is not applicable to, and does not restrict or limit, other health care practitioners who are authorized to perform these duties under their respective practice acts.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This chapter does not restrict or limit a Maryland Certified Registered Nurse Practitioner from possessing, prescribing, evaluating, or performing the procedures under this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Body treatment” means cellulite lymphatic drainage and cellulite vacuum massage.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Cellulite lymphatic drainage”  means a therapy in which the practitioner uses a range of specialized and gentle rhythmic pumping techniques to move the skin in the direction of the lymph flow.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Cellulite vacuum massage” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The massage of peripheral blood, lymph, and inter-tissue liquid with the goal of reducing stagnation of these fluids and increasing the skin’s elasticity; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The external use of a vacuum component directly on the area to be massaged followed by a straight line, circular, or zigzag movement to massage the area.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Chemical peels” also called deep skin peels, means the removal of the top layers of skin using chemicals applied directly to the skin.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Clinical preceptor” means a licensed or certified individual who is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Proficient in the procedure for which they are precepting; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Permitted by the appropriate health occupation licensing board to provide care and treatment for cosmetic services.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Cryotherapy” means the application of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Extreme cold to destroy abnormal or diseased tissue, warts, moles, skin tags, and solar keratoses; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Liquid nitrogen to freeze tissues at the cellular level.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Dermal fillers” means various types of natural or man-made materials which are injected intradermally to correct imperfections in the skin and subcutaneous tissue.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Direct supervision” means on site, physically present, accessible in the immediate patient care area and available to intervene if necessary.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“Injectable treatments” means the use of FDA approved medication and includes the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Dermal fillers;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Micropigmentation, also known as cosmetic tattoo or permanent make-up; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Neuromuscular agents.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>“Laser treatment” means a technique in which exposure to low-level laser light or light emitting diodes are used to stimulate or inhibit cellular function possibly leading to beneficial clinical effects.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Light Treatment.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Light treatment” also known as phototherapy, means the use of non-ionizing electro-magnetic radiation for therapeutic benefit.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Light treatment” does not mean laser treatment.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>“Lipodissolve” means a procedure that uses subcutaneous micro-injections of drugs with the sole purpose of dissolving fat for body contouring.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Magenta Light.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Magenta light” means a non-invasive technique that combines infrared and magenta light with subdermal tissue massage to produce a penetrating light that affects the epidermis, alters cellulite formation,  and controls cellulite formation at the cellular level.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Magenta light” does not mean laser or intensive pulse light.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>“Mesotherapy” also known as intradermotherapy, means a non-invasive cosmetic treatment which employs multiple intra or subcutaneous injections of pharmaceutical and homeopathic medications, plant extracts, vitamins, and other ingredients for the treatment of fat or cellulite.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>“Micro current treatment” means passing radio frequency electricity through the skin to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Heat up tissue;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Cause the tissue to contract; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Stimulate collagen production.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>“Neuromuscular agents” means injectable drugs that cause muscle weakness for the purpose of cosmetic softening of wrinkles and includes, but is not limited to, Botox and Dysport.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>“Nurse” means a registered nurse (RN) or a licensed practical nurse (LPN).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>“Peels” or “Topicals” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Chemicals peels;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Cryotherapy; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Microdermabrasion.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>“Photochemotherapy” means the use of a photodynamic light source to destroy dystrophic cells.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>“Photodynamic (PDT)” means the use of a light source, combined with a light-sensitive drug to destroy dystrophic cells.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>“Photosensitizing agent” means a drug used with a photodynamic light source to produce a therapeutic photosensitivity.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>“Precepted clinical practice” means after theoretical learning and until competency is achieved:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Working directly with patients;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Performing cosmetic or dermatologic procedures on patients; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Working under the direct supervision of a clinical preceptor who has the knowledge and ability to perform the procedure independently.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>Radio Frequency and Current.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Radio frequency and current” means:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Magenta light;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Microcurrent treatment;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Photochemotherapy;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Photodynamic;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Thermage; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Ultrasound (therapeutic only).</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Radio frequency and current” does not mean laser.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(24)</num>
        <text>Theory.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Theory” means the body of knowledge regarding the principles underlying the safe execution of a cosmetic procedure and is obtained through didactic instruction provided by a licensed health care provider who has the knowledge and skill to perform the procedure.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Theory” includes didactic instruction by the licensed health care provider which may be augmented by a manufacturer’s representative.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(25)</num>
        <text>“Thermage” means the use of radio frequency technology to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Target collagen in the dermis layer of the skin around the eyes and forehead; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Cause the dermis and underlying tissue to tighten.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(26)</num>
        <text>Ultrasound.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Ultrasound” means the therapeutic use of inaudible sound in the frequency range of approximately 20,000 to 10,000,000,000 cycles per second for therapeutic use at low intensity producing a heating effect to stimulate collagen production.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Ultrasound” does not mean the use of ultrasound for diagnostic purposes.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Procedural Categories.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Procedures designated as Category A shall include body treatments with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Cellulite lymphatic drainage; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Cellulite vacuum massage.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Procedures designated as Category B shall include light treatments with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Infrared light;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Magenta light;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Photochemotherapy;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Photodynamic;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Photosensitizing agents;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>UVA light; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>UVB light.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Procedures designated as Category C shall include laser treatments administered by a selective laser.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Procedures designated as Category D shall include injectable treatments with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Dermal fillers;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Micropigmentation with topical anesthetics only; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Neuromuscular agents.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Procedures designated as Category E shall include radio frequency and current treatments with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Micro current;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Thermage; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Ultrasound.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Procedures designated as Category F shall include peels or topicals with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Chemical peels;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Cryotherapy;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Microdermabrasion; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Power peel.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Education.</heading>
    <text>To administer medication or to perform cosmetic and dermatologic treatments, a nurse shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Complete a program of study that includes theory appropriate to the medication to be administered and the procedure to be performed that includes, but is not limited to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Anatomy, physiology, and pathophysiology related to the integumentary system as well as systems specific to the procedure being performed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Appropriate technique for each cosmetic procedure;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Nursing assessment, cosmetic indications, and contraindications for treatment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Pharmacology intervention specific to the cosmetic procedure including, but not limited to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Assessment and monitoring of the receiving the medication;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Effects and potential side effects of the medication;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Contraindications to the administration of the medication;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The ability to anticipate and recognize potential complications of the medication;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The ability to recognize emergency situations and institute appropriate interventions;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Preparation, storing, and handling of the medication; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Proficiency in administering the medication by the required route;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Selection, maintenance, and utilization of equipment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Identification of realistic and expected outcomes of the procedure;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Identification of complications or adverse reactions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Nursing care required and appropriate nursing interventions in the event of complications or untoward outcomes;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Infection control procedures;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Safety precautions appropriate to each procedure;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Documentation appropriate to the type of the procedure being performed; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Precepted clinical practice by a clinical preceptor that includes documented initial and annual competency of the nurse in each cosmetic procedure the nurse is to perform;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Document evidence of clinical and psychomotor proficiency competency before independently performing each cosmetic procedure;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Perform the procedures on a frequent routine predictable basis in order to retain practice proficiency;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Be evaluated for continued clinical competency at periodic intervals; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Obtain additional education when the population changes or new procedures are introduced into the practice.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Cosmetic Procedures in General.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The nurse shall comply with the employment settings written cosmetic policies and procedures that comply with this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The nurse shall be guided by and comply with the written policies and procedures in keeping with recognized standards of care that include, but are not limited to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Care and maintenance of appropriate equipment and safe operation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Description of how the procedure is to be performed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Education;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Assessment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Emergency procedures;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Monitoring guidelines;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Operator and safety when utilizing equipment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>A continuous quality improvement process which includes, but is not limited to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Unexpected outcomes;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Side effects; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Complications;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Obtaining or ensuring that the client’s informed consent has been obtained that documents the patient’s awareness that it is the licensed nurse who will perform the cosmetic procedure; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Documenting the performance of the cosmetic procedure including, but not limited to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Patient response;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Patient education; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Safety precautions taken on behalf of the patient.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The nurse may perform the identified cosmetic procedure when there is a completed prescriptive order from an authorized prescriber that includes, but is not limited to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The procedure to be performed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Identification of the specific treatment area;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Identification of medication, dosage, route, and time interval for administration of the medication for the specific cosmetic procedure;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Identification of the light source and the radio frequency, current dosage, intensity, and time period it is to be applied; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The use of any topical anesthetic.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Before a nurse performs any of these cosmetic procedures, the authorized prescriber shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Complete an initial assessment and evaluation of the patient before the procedure is performed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Develop a treatment plan for the specific patient;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Be physically present in the setting; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Be immediately available:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>At the time the procedure is performed; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Post-treatment to evaluate the patient.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The nurse shall maintain medical records in accordance with Health-General Article, Title 4, Subtitle 4, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation app="2025-10-13" doc="Maryland Register, Volume 52, Issue 20" eff="2025-10-13" path="regulations|final|25-159-F" type="History" display="false"/>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Cosmetic Procedures — Licensed Practical Nurse.</heading>
    <text>Except for Category C, the LPN may perform the cosmetic procedures identified in <cite path="|10|27|25|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Cosmetic Procedures — RN.</heading>
    <text>The RN may perform all of the procedures identified in <cite path="|10|27|25|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Exceptions.</heading>
    <text>Except for cryotherapy, the nurse may perform the cosmetic procedures identified in Regulation .03 Category F independent of the requirements stated in <cite path="|10|27|25|.05|D.">Regulation .05D of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Prohibited Acts.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The licensed nurse may not:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Perform cosmetic procedures on a standing order or protocol;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Perform the pre-procedure medical assessment or evaluation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Perform medical diagnosis or prescribe cosmetic procedures;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Develop the client treatment plan;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Prescribe medications for cosmetic or dermatological procedures;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Perform the post-procedure medical evaluation of the client; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Administer injections for the purpose of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Mesotherapy; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Lipodissolve.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The nurse may not perform:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Liposuction;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Hair transplants;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Invasive radiofrequency procedures;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Phenopeels;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Sculptra injections; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Lipostabil or phosphatidycholine for the purpose of lipodissolve.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health-General Article, §4-403; <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|8-205">Health Occupations Article, §8-205(a)(1) </cite>and (2); Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-05-30">Effective date: May 30, 2011 (38:11 Md. R. 671)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-10-13"><cite path="|10|27|25|.05|E.">Regulation .05E</cite> adopted effective October 13, 2025 (52:20 Md. R. 1002)</annotation>
    <annotation app="2025-10-13" doc="Maryland Register, Volume 52, Issue 20" eff="2025-10-13" path="regulations|final|25-159-F" type="History" display="false"/>
  </annotations>
</container>
