<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>Regulations Governing Licensure</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope and Purpose.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter applies to individuals practicing social work in the State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The purpose of this chapter is to protect the public by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Providing minimum criteria for licensure under the law for those who seek to practice social work; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Promoting and maintaining high standards of professional activity in social work.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Accredited” means receiving:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Accreditation from the Council on Social Work Education;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Approval of a program for an individual applicant by the Council on Social Work Education's Foreign Equivalency Determination Service that the program is equivalent to a program accredited by the Council on Social Work Education; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Approval of a program in candidacy for accreditation by the Council of Social Work Education.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Board” means the State Board of Social Work Examiners.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Board-approved supervisor” means a licensed bachelor social worker (LBSW), licensed certified social worker (LCSW), licensed certified social worker-clinical (LCSW-C) or licensed master social worker (LMSW) approved by the Board to supervise social workers as set forth in <cite path="|10.42.08">COMAR 10.42.08</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Central repository” means the criminal justice information system central repository of the Maryland Department of Public Safety and Correctional Services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Clinical course work” means clinical social work courses offered by an accredited or provisionally accredited program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Clinical Social Work.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Clinical social work” means the professional application of social work knowledge, skills, values, theories, and methods for the treatment and prevention of psychosocial dysfunction, disability, or impairment, including emotional, mental disorders, and substance use disorders with individuals, groups and families.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Clinical social work” includes formulating a diagnostic impression or a diagnosis based on standard diagnostic criteria.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Clinical social work experience” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Completing assessments;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Formulating diagnostic impressions or a diagnosis;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Treating mental disorders and other conditions;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Treating behavioral health disorders, including but not limited to substance use disorders, addictive disorders and other conditions; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Providing psychotherapy.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Criminal history records check” means the performance of both State criminal history check by the central repository and national criminal history check by the Federal Bureau of Investigation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“Criminal history records information” means information obtained:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>From the criminal history records check regarding an applicant’s criminal arrests, charges, convictions, and the disposition of pending criminal charges; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Through the Rap Back service which allows the Board to receive notification of charges thus eliminating the need for repeated background checks on a licensee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>“Documentation of clinical course work” means providing transcripts indicating the completion of clinical course work from a college or university whose bachelor’s or master’s program is accredited, in candidacy, or deemed equivalent by the Council on Social Work Education.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>“Licensed” means that the individual possesses a license to practice social work issued by the Board.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>“Licensed in any other state” means to be licensed, registered, or certified by a government authority charged with licensing, registering, or certifying social workers.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>“Licensee” means an individual licensed by the Board.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>“Licensee in another state” means an applicant that is licensed, registered, or certified by a government authority charged with licensing, registering, or certifying social workers.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>“Licensure by endorsement” means that an individual holds or held a license, registration, or certification to practice social work in another state after passing, in that state, a social work licensing examination and after meeting the licensing requirements for social work practice in that state.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>Practice Social Work.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Practice social work” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|19-101">Health Occupations Article, §19-101(m), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Practice social work” includes supervising a candidate for advanced licensure and a licensee in the practice of social work, when appropriate.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>“Rap Back service” means a service which allows the Board to receive notifications from the Federal Bureau of Investigation on applicants and licensees who may have future criminal charges thus eliminating the need for repeated background checks on the same applicant or licensee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>“Reactivation” means the process of obtaining a license less than 5 years after the Board placed the license on inactive status.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>“Reinstatement” means the process of obtaining a license less than 5 years after the Board placed the license on a non-renewed status.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>“Reissuance” means the process of obtaining a license more than 5 years after the Board placed the license on inactive or non-renewed status.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>“Social Work” means the professional activity of helping individuals, families, groups, organizations, or communities to enhance or restore their capacity for social and psychosocial functioning.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>“Social worker” means an individual:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Licensed under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 19, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and who represents to the public by a title or description which incorporates the words “social worker”, “social work”, or a similar designation; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Who, under the title or description, offers to render, attempts to render, or renders services involving the application of principles, methods, and procedures of the profession of social work to individuals or groups.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>“Supervision” means a formalized professional relationship between a supervisor and supervisee in which the supervisor directs, monitors, and evaluates the supervisee's social work practice while promoting development of the supervisee's knowledge, skills, and abilities to provide social work services in an ethical and competent manner.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Use of Title.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An individual shall be licensed by the Board in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 19, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and this chapter, before that individual may be identified as a social worker and practice social work.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The title "social worker" shall be used only by a licensed social worker.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Except as otherwise provided in this chapter or provided in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|19-301">Health Occupations Article, §19-301(b), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, an individual licensed as a social worker in another state may not practice social work in this State unless licensed by the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Licensure.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>To obtain an initial license or a license for renewal, reactivation, reinstatement, or reissuance, an applicant shall complete a criminal history records check through the central repository. In accordance with Criminal Procedure Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcp|10-201">10-201</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcp|10-228">10-228</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland, the central repository shall provide criminal history records information to the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board shall review the criminal history records information provided for any positive results from the criminal history records check.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An applicant is not required to complete a criminal history records check provided the applicant completes a criminal history records check under the Rap Back service, which will automatically alert the Board of any future criminal charges.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Bachelor Social Worker.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board shall issue a bachelor social worker’s license to an applicant who has met the qualifications in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|19-302">Health Occupations Article, §19-302(a) </cite>and (b), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a bachelor social worker applies for licensure in a different category, the application shall be treated as an initial application subject to the appropriate fees.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Master Social Worker.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board shall issue a master social worker license to an applicant who has met the applicable qualifications in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|19-302">Health Occupations Article, §19-302(a) </cite>and (c), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a master social worker applies for licensure in a different category, the application shall be treated as an initial application subject to the fees set forth in <cite path="|10.42.05">COMAR 10.42.05</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Certified Social Worker-Clinical.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board shall issue a certified social worker-clinical license to an applicant who has met the requirements in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|19-302">Health Occupations Article, §19-302(a) </cite>and (e), Annotated Code of Maryland, with documentation of clinical course work.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An applicant for a certified social worker-clinical license shall have completed 12 academic credits of clinical course work from an accredited program with a minimum of six of the 12 academic credits obtained in a Master's of Social Work program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The applicant for a certified social worker-clinical license shall have 2 years of supervised clinical social work experience as a licensed master social worker with supervised clinical social work experience of at least 3,000 hours while licensed as a master social worker which is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In compliance with <cite path="|10.42.08">COMAR 10.42.08</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Performed in not less than 2 years and not more than 6 consecutive years; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Obtained by the candidate while performing social work activities professionally and for compensation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A candidate shall have obtained a master social worker license before applying for a certified social worker-clinical license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A candidate shall have obtained a master social worker license before beginning to obtain the 3,000 hours of supervised social work experience.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A licensed master social worker shall formulate a diagnostic impression while under the supervision of a licensed certified social worker — clinical while obtaining the requisite 3,000 hours of supervised clinical social work experience.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Clinical social work experience for the purpose of obtaining a certified social worker-clinical license shall be in direct service to clients and may not consist solely of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Telephonic clinical assessment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Triage;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Continued stay reviews; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Discharge planning.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The supervisor and supervisee shall conform to the requirements in <cite path="|10.42.08">COMAR 10.42.08</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Half of the supervised clinical social work experience required to obtain a certified social worker-clinical license shall consist of face-to-face client contact.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Required Hours of Supervised Social Work Experience.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A candidate with experience obtained in Maryland shall have obtained a licensed master social worker license before beginning to obtain the requisite 3,000 hours of supervised social work experience.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A candidate with 3,000 hours of supervised social work experience from another state or jurisdiction of the United States or another country shall provide documentation that the candidate met the licensing, certification, or registration requirements in that state or jurisdiction or country while acquiring the requisite supervised social work experience.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Examinations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The general requirements for examination are:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Completion of the application form;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Payment of the application fee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Either:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A receipt of an official transcript indicating completion of an accredited program from the university or school awarding the applicable social work degree attained; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For applicants who are expected to receive the applicable social work degree at the end of the semester, indication on the Board’s form of the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Degree that the applicant is expected to receive; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Date that the applicant is expected to receive the degree; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>For candidates for examination for certified social worker—clinical or certified social worker licenses, documentation of social work experience and social work supervision.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Applicants may request special accommodations if disabled or if English is the applicant's second language.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|42|01|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Approval Notification.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An application packet for licensure is complete when the application packet is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Submitted to the Board signed and dated; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Accompanied by the required non-refundable application fee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The application packet shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The completed application form answering all questions on the application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Official transcripts containing the date the degree was conferred by a program approved or deemed equivalent by the Council of Social Work Education;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A passing score from the required examination administered by the Association of Social Work Boards; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Criminal history records check reports.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>LCSW and LCSW-C applications shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The contractual agreement form for supervision which has been signed and dated by the supervisor, supervisee and agency administrator before supervision was initiated;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Documentation of supervised social work experience; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The information and documentation required in <cite path="10|42|01|.07|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Board shall notify an applicant whether the applicant has been approved to take the pertinent licensure examination within 60 days of receiving the application.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Approval shall be valid for 2 years from the date of approval.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>After 2 years, the applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Reapply to take the appropriate licensure examination;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Submit all of the required documentation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Meet the current licensure requirements under this chapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>An applicant shall submit any additional required documentation needed to complete the application within 1 year of the Board’s receipt of the application.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Examinations — Use of National Examination Boards Permitted.</heading>
    <text>The Board may use a national examination board such as the Association of Social Work Boards as the Board's agent in examining applicants.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Passing Score for Examination.</heading>
    <text>The passing grade for an examination is a scaled score of 75.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Reexamination.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant who fails the examination:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>May retake the examination four times within the 12-month period after a failed examination; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>May not retake the examination within 3 months of failing the examination.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An applicant may request and be granted or denied a waiver of the 3-month waiting period after failure of an examination upon proof of exceptional circumstances.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Licensure by Endorsement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant who holds or held a license or registration to practice social work in another state is eligible to be licensed in Maryland at the same level of licensure as the license the applicant holds or held in the other state.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Bachelor Social Worker.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board shall issue a bachelor social worker’s license to an applicant who has met the qualifications in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|19-302">Health Occupations Article, §19-302(a) </cite>and (b), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a bachelor social worker applies for licensure at a different level, the application shall be treated as an initial application subject to the fees set forth in <cite path="|10.42.05">COMAR 10.42.05</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Master Social Worker.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board shall issue a master social worker license to an applicant who has met the applicable qualifications in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|19-302">Health Occupations Article, §19-302(a) </cite>and (c), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a master social worker applies for licensure at a different level, the application shall be treated as an initial application subject to the fees set forth in <cite path="|10.42.05">COMAR 10.42.05</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Certified Social Worker—Clinical.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board shall issue a certified social worker—clinical license to an out-of-State applicant who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Has more than 5 years of clinical social work practice;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Holds an active clinical license comparable to the certified social worker—clinical licensure level; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Who has met the qualifications under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|19-302">Health Occupations Article, §19-302</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Board shall issue a certified social worker—clinical license to an out-of-State applicant who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Has less than 5 years of social work practice;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Holds or held an active license comparable to the certified social worker—clinical licensure level; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Has met the requirements in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|19-302">Health Occupations Article, §19-302(a) </cite>and (e), Annotated Code of Maryland, with documentation of clinical course work.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An applicant for a certified social worker—clinical license with less than 5 years of clinical social work experience shall have completed 12 academic credits of clinical course work from an accredited program with a minimum of six of the 12 academic credits obtained in a Master’s of Social Work program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The applicant for a certified social worker—clinical license shall have 2 years of at least 3,000 hours of supervised clinical social work experience, which shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Obtained after receiving a master’s degree in social work and as a licensed master social worker, if a licensed master social worker license was required in the jurisdiction where the supervised experience was obtained;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Performed in not less than 2 years and not more than 6 consecutive years; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Obtained by the candidate while performing social work activities professionally and for compensation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A candidate shall have obtained a master social worker license before applying for a certified social worker—clinical license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A candidate shall have obtained a master social worker license in the jurisdiction where the experience was obtained if required in that jurisdiction, before beginning to obtain the 3,000 hours of supervised social work experience.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>A licensed graduate social worker may render a diagnosis in the jurisdiction where the experience was obtained if in compliance with the laws in that jurisdiction, while obtaining the requisite 3,000 hours of supervised clinical social work experience.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Clinical social work experience for the purpose of obtaining a certified social worker—clinical license shall be in direct service to clients and may not consist solely of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Telephonic clinical assessment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Triage;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Continued stay reviews; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Discharge planning.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>The supervisor shall be a license social worker with a license comparable to the licensed certified social worker—clinical in Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Half of the supervised clinical social work experience required to obtain a certified social worker—clinical license shall consist of face-to-face client contact.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>License Without Examination.</heading>
    <text>An individual who obtained licensure without examination under Ch. 853, Acts of 1975, Ch. 787, Acts of 1978, Ch. 189, Acts of 1983, or Ch. 393, Acts of 1984, is eligible to retain licensure at the level for which that individual was originally licensed if the license is renewed under the provisions of <cite path="|10|42|01|.15">Regulation .15 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|42|01|.13">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>To Practice Social Work While a License Application is Pending.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant may practice social work in Maryland without a license issued by the Board if the applicant has met the requirements established by this regulation and:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Licensed in any other state to practice social work;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Qualified to practice social work by another country; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Qualified to practice social work by a federal entity of the United States;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Has submitted a complete written application for a State social worker's license in the form prescribed by the Board and the application for a license is pending with the Board;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Has received verification from the Board that a complete written application for a State social worker's license has been received by the Board;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Is 18 years old or older at the time the application is submitted to the Board;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Is of good moral character;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Has passed, or expects to pass within 5 months of applying for licensure, an Association of Social Work Boards examination in compliance with <cite path="|10|42|01|.12">Regulation .12 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Has paid applicable fees.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>To practice as a bachelor social worker under this regulation, the applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Meet the requirements of <cite path="10|42|01|.13|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Possess a baccalaureate degree in social work from a program accredited by the Council on Social Work Education.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>To practice as a master social worker under this regulation, the applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Meet the requirements of <cite path="10|42|01|.13|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Possess a master's degree in social work from a program accredited by the Council on Social Work Education.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>To practice as a certified social worker under this regulation, the applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Meet the requirements of <cite path="10|42|01|.13|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Possess a master's degree in social work from a program accredited by the Council on Social Work Education;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Provide documentation in a form prescribed by the Board:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Of having completed 2 years of supervised experience of at least 3,000 hours after receiving the master's degree, with a minimum of 100 hours of periodic face-to-face supervision in the practice of social work:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>As a licensee in another state;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>As a social worker who is in compliance with the laws of another country; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>As a social worker who is in compliance with a federal entity of the United States;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Indicating that the supervision complied with the supervision requirements of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Another state;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Another country; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A federal entity of the United States; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Indicating that the supervisor possessed a master's degree in social work from a program accredited by the Council on Social Work Education while supervising the applicant.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>To practice as a certified social worker—clinical under this regulation, the applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Meet the requirements of <cite path="10|42|01|.13|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> and Regulation .05D(2), (7), and (9) of this chapter;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Possess a master's degree in social work from a program accredited by the Council on Social Work Education;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Document the completion of clinical course work from a program accredited by the Council on Social Work Education;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Provide documentation in a form prescribed by the Board:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Of having completed 2 years of supervised experience of at least 3,000 hours after receiving the master's degree, with a minimum of 144 hours of periodic face-to-face supervision in the assessment, formulation of a diagnostic impression, and treatment of mental disorders and other conditions in:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Another state;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Another country; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A federal entity of the United States;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Indicating that the supervision complied with the supervision requirements of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The other state;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The other country; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A federal entity of the United States; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Indicating that the supervisor possessed a master's degree in social work from a program accredited by the Council on Social Work Education while supervising the applicant.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>An applicant may not:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Practice social work under this regulation for more than 6 months; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Represent to the public by title or representation that the applicant is a social worker who is licensed in Maryland to practice social work.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Licenses.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In addition to the requirements of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|19-306">Health Occupations Article, §19-306, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the licensee shall be assigned a permanent license number that shall be in the official files of the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>At the time of initial license, the Board shall issue a wall certificate which is not to be considered a license to practice social work in Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Board shall maintain an electronic record on its website of all licensees and the electronic record is to be considered the official license to practice social work in Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|42|01|.15">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Renewal of License.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Licenses shall be renewed by October 31, every 2 years.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>For renewal purposes, a new license issued during a given year shall be treated as if it had been issued on November 1 of that same year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Notification of renewal shall be sent to each licensee at the last known electronic or physical address on file with the Board at least 1 month before the expiration of the license.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Before expiration of the license, the licensee shall submit to the Board the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Application for renewal;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Continuing education report form; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>License fee, as set forth in <cite path="|10.42.05">COMAR 10.42.05</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If a licensee does not file the application by the date specified in <cite path="10|42|01|.15|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>, the licensee's right to practice shall terminate automatically on the expiration of the license.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Board may not renew a bachelor or master social worker license to a licensee who holds a baccalaureate or master’s degree from a provisionally accredited program that was denied full accreditation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>If a licensee fails to renew a license, the license and the licensee's right to practice:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall terminate; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>May not be reinstated except by application for a reinstatement provided in <cite path="|10|42|01|.17">Regulation .17 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Change of Address.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A licensee shall notify the Board within 60 days of a change in the licensee's address or before July 1 of the licensee's renewal year, whichever occurs first, to ensure that the notice of renewal and renewed license are properly addressed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The written notification shall include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A statement that the licensee has changed addresses;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The licensee's new address; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The licensee's signature.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Change of Name.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A licensee shall notify the Board of a change in name within 60 days or before July 1 of the licensee’s renewal year, whichever occurs first, to insure that the renewed license documents the licensee’s legal name.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The notification shall include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Legal documentation of the change in name;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A statement of how the legal name should appear in the Board’s record including last name, first name, and middle name; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The licensee’s signature.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>If a licensee fails to receive a renewal notice, it is the responsibility of the licensee to contact the Board before October 31 of the year the license expires.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Reinstatement After Failure to Renew.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board shall reinstate the license of an individual who has failed to renew a license which expired for any reason if the individual:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Otherwise is entitled to be licensed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Complies with the continuing education requirements established by the Board for this purpose;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Submits the application for reinstatement;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Submits the continuing education report form with copies of the required continued education documentation as set forth in <cite path="|10.42.06">COMAR 10.42.06</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Pays to the Board a reinstatement processing fee in <cite path="|10.42.05">COMAR 10.42.05</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Applies to the Board within 5 years of the date the license expired.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Failure to Reinstate Within 5 Years.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board may not reinstate the license of a social worker who fails to apply for reinstatement within 5 years after the license expired.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Board may issue a license after 5 years if the individual:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is otherwise entitled to be licensed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Submits the required application;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Pays all applicable fees set forth in <cite path="|10.42.05">COMAR 10.42.05</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Submits an official transcript indicating the date the degree was awarded or conferred;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Submits three general professional references; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Passes the respective examination required for initial licensure.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.17</num>
    <heading>Inactive Status.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A licensee who wishes to place a license on inactive status may do so by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Submission of a written application which contains the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Date the license is to be placed on inactive status;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>License number; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Signature of the licensee requesting the inactive status of the license; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Payment of the appropriate fee for the status set forth in <cite path="|10.42.05">COMAR 10.42.05</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A license may be placed on inactive status for a maximum of 5 years from the expiration date of the license.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Board shall reactivate a license of an individual who placed the license on inactive status for any reason if the individual:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Otherwise is entitled to be licensed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Complies with the continuing education requirements established in <cite path="|10.42.06">COMAR 10.42.06</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Submits an application for reactivation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Submits a continuing education report form with copies of the required documentation established in <cite path="|10.42.06">COMAR 10.42.06</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Pays to the Board a reactivation fee set forth in <cite path="|10.42.05">COMAR 10.42.05</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Applies to the Board within 5 years of the date the license expired.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Failure to Reactivate Within 5 years.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board may not reactivate the license of a social worker who fails to apply for reactivation within 5 years after the license expired.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Board may issue a license after 5 years if the individual:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is otherwise entitled to be licensed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Submits the required application;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Pays all applicable fees set forth in <cite path="|10.42.05">COMAR 10.42.05</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Submits an official transcript indicating the date the degree was awarded or conferred;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Submits three general professional references; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Passes the respective examination required for initial licensure.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A licensee may place a license on inactive status for a maximum of 5 years per application for inactive status.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Each period of inactive status may not exceed 5 years.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.18</num>
    <heading>Replacement of Wall Certificates.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board shall issue a replacement wall certificate upon written request by a licensee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If an original wall certificate is replaced, the licensee shall retain the original license number issued.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|19-101">19-101</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|19-502">19-502</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1976-11-10">Effective date: November 10, 1976 (3:23 Md. R. 1302)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1983-05-23">Regulations .07, .13, and .16 amended effective May 23, 1983 (10:10 Md. R. 873)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-04-30" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective April 30, 1990 (17:8 Md. R. 976)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-12-01">Regulations <cite path="|10|42|01|.02">.02</cite>—<cite path="|10|42|01|.04">.04</cite> and .16 amended, and new Regulation .04-1 adopted as an emergency provision effective September 15, 1993 (20:20 Md. R. 1565); adopted  permanently effective December 1, 1993 (20:22 Md. R. 1707)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-04-12" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|10|42|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|42|01|.22">.22</cite> repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|10|42|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|10|42|01|.19">.19</cite> adopted effective April 12, 2004 (31:7 Md. R. 585)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-04-14"><cite path="|10|42|01|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective April 4, 2011 (38:7 Md. R. 432); April 14, 2014 (41:7 Md. R. 422)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-04-14"><cite path="|10|42|01|.04|B.">Regulation .04B</cite>, c amended effective April 14, 2014 (41:7 Md. R. 422)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-04-14"><cite path="|10|42|01|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective April 14, 2014 (41:7 Md. R. 422)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-04-14"><cite path="|10|42|01|.06|A.">Regulation .06A</cite> amended effective April 14, 2014 (41:7 Md. R. 422)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-02-08"><cite path="|10|42|01|.08">Regulation .08</cite> amended effective February 8, 2010 (37:3 Md. R. 176)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-04-04"><cite path="|10|42|01|.12">Regulation .12</cite> repealed and new Regulation .12 adopted effective April 4, 2011 (38:7 Md. R. 432)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-04-14"><cite path="|10|42|01|.12">Regulation .12</cite> amended effective April 14, 2014 (41:7 Md. R. 422)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-04-14"><cite path="|10|42|01|.14|B.">Regulation .14B</cite>, D amended effective April 14, 2014 (41:7 Md. R. 422)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-04-14"><cite path="|10|42|01|.15">Regulation .15</cite> amended effective April 14, 2014 (41:7 Md. R. 422)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-04-14"><cite path="|10|42|01|.16">Regulation .16</cite> amended effective February 8, 2010 (37:3 Md. R. 176); April 14, 2014 (41:7 Md. R. 422)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-04-14"><cite path="|10|42|01|.17">Regulation .17</cite> amended effective February 8, 2010 (37:3 Md. R. 176); April 14, 2014 (41:7 Md. R. 422)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-04-14"><cite path="|10|42|01|.18">Regulation .18</cite> amended effective February 8, 2010 (37:3 Md. R. 176); April 14, 2014 (41:7 Md. R. 422)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-04-14"><cite path="|10|42|01|.19">Regulation .19</cite> amended effective April 14, 2014 (41:7 Md. R. 422)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-02-08"><cite path="|10|42|01|.19|A.">Regulation .19A</cite> amended effective February 8, 2010 (37:3 Md. R. 176)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-06-17" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective June 17, 2019 (46:12 Md. R. 544)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-06-09"><cite path="|10|42|01|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective June 9, 2025 (52:11 Md. R. 533)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-06-09"><cite path="|10|42|01|.04|F.">Regulation .04F</cite>, G amended effective June 9, 2025 (52:11 Md. R. 533)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-06-09"><cite path="|10|42|01|.11|D.">Regulation .11D</cite>, E amended effective June 9, 2025 (52:11 Md. R. 533)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
