<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Procedures for License Denials and Disciplinary Sanctions</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>This chapter describes the procedures for a license denial and disciplinary action against a licensee.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In addition to the definitions set forth in <cite path="|10.22.01">COMAR 10.22.01</cite>, in this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Isolated scope" means that the identified deficiency has occurred only once, in only one location, or for only one individual.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Low scope" means that the deficiency has occurred only occasionally, in sporadic locations, or for only a few individuals.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Minor impact" means there has been little or no negative effect on an individual's health, safety, rights, or quality of life.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Moderate impact" means an individual has experienced a significant health or safety consequence, a violation of rights, or infringement on quality of life, or that these consequences may likely occur in the near future.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Repeated scope" means that the deficiency has occurred on a regular basis, in several locations, or for several individuals.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Severe impact" means an individual has experienced a deterioration in the individual's medical or psychological condition, has been exposed to a serious safety risk, has experienced frequent rights violations, or infringements on the individual's quality of life, or that these consequences may likely occur in the near future.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Widespread scope" means that the deficiency has occurred consistently, in most locations, or for a majority of people.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Failure to Submit Acceptable Plan of Correction.</heading>
    <text>A licensee, including a licensee with deficiencies having only a minor impact, is subject to any intermediate sanction set forth in <cite path="|10|22|03|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite> for failure to comply with <cite path="10.22.02.04|E.">COMAR 10.22.02.04E</cite> and F.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|22|03|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Intermediate Sanctions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>After notice and an opportunity for a hearing, the Director may impose any intermediate sanctions listed in <cite path="10|22|03|.04|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Deficiencies have a moderate impact and the scope of the deficiencies occurs on an isolated, low, repeated, or widespread basis; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Deficiencies have a severe impact and the scope of the deficiencies occurs on an isolated, low, repeated, or widespread basis.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>For purposes of <cite path="10|22|03|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, intermediate sanctions include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A directed plan of correction, when the licensee is directed to take a specific action by a certain date;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A mandatory staffing pattern, when the Administration defines for the licensee the level of individual supervision required at a particular site or program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Mandatory training, when the Administration identifies deficient areas in which training is needed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Individual relocation, when the Administration reserves the right to relocate an individual to another licensee in order to protect the health or safety of the individual;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Expansion ban, when the Administration retains the authority to prohibit the licensee from obtaining additional sites, admitting individuals, or providing additional services at the site;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Imposition of an intensive monitoring protocol by the Administration; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Imposition of a temporary site monitor, when the Administration maintains an on-going physical presence for the purpose of providing assistance and evaluating the extent of the licensee's corrective actions.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Summary Suspension.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-226">State Government Article, §10-226(c)(2), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and if appropriate, after a pre-deprivation hearing, the Director may summarily order the suspension of a license if the Administration finds that the public health, safety, or welfare imperatively requires emergency action.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Director shall notify the licensee in writing of the suspension, the findings, and the reasons that support the findings, and, when appropriate, the opportunity for a pre-deprivation hearing. The notice shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The proposed order for summary suspension which includes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The statutory and regulatory authority upon which the order is based,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The facts supporting the alleged violations of law,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The facts supporting the belief that there is an imminent danger to the health, safety, and welfare of individuals, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The licensee's right to appeal the summary suspension, if executed by the Director; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A show cause notice providing an opportunity for the licensee to show cause as to why the order should not be issued if the public health, safety, and welfare permits.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Director may suspend a license without prior notice and the opportunity to be heard if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Director determines that the health, welfare, and safety of the public imperatively requires immediate suspension;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Notice of an opportunity to be heard before the action is not feasible; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Administration provides the licensee with a post-deprivation hearing opportunity within 15 working days of the suspension.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notify the individuals being served by the licensee and, if appropriate, their families or proponents, regarding the summary suspension; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Assist the individuals in finding alternative services if the license is summarily suspended.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|22|03|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Denial, Probation, Suspension, or Revocation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In addition to any intermediate sanctions, the Director may deny a license or take disciplinary action against a licensee if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An applicant fails to meet the regulations governing the services for which it is applying for a license;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A licensee fails to comply with the regulations governing its services; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A licensee fails to cooperate with the Department during an investigation or licensing survey.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the Director proposes to deny approval to an applicant or take disciplinary action against a licensee, the Director shall give written notice to the governing body, the executive director, the regional director, the Health Care Financing Administration, and, as appropriate, other interested parties.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In the written notice under <cite path="10|22|03|.06|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, the Director shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The statutory and regulatory authority upon which the proposed action is based;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The facts supporting the alleged violations of law; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The applicant's or licensee's right to a hearing under <cite path="|10|22|03|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite> before final action.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Procedures for Hearings.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If the Secretary proposes to deny a license or take disciplinary action against a licensee, the Director shall give the licensee written notice according to <cite path="|10|22|03|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Within 10 working days of receipt of the notice, the governing body or health officer may file a written request for a hearing with the Office of Administrative Hearings with copies of the request to the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Director;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Regional director; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Administrative prosecutor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the governing body or the health officer does not file a request for a hearing within 10 working days of receipt of the notification, the licensee waives its right to request a hearing, and the Director may implement the proposed action.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If a timely request for a hearing has been received, the Office of Administrative Hearings shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notify the Director, the governing body or health officer, the regional director, and administrative prosecutor of the date, time, and location of the hearing; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In accordance with <cite path="|28.02.01">COMAR 28.02.01</cite>, hold a hearing and, unless the final decision is delegated to the Office of Administrative Hearings, render a proposed decision to the Director.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>After giving the parties the opportunity to file exceptions under the provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-216">State Government Article, §10-216, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the Secretary shall issue a final decision according to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-221">State Government Article, §10-221, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and send notice to the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Governing body or the health officer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Regional director;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Medical Care Programs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Individual and, if appropriate, their family or proponents; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Health Care Financing Administration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A licensee may appeal a final decision from a contested case by following the provisions of Health-General Article, §2-207, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 10, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>In addition to disposing of a case by a hearing, the Director may dispose of a contested case by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Stipulation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Settlement;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Consent order;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Default;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Withdrawal;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Summary disposition; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Dismissal.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>If disciplinary action is taken against a licensee, the Director shall notify the appropriate parties which include, but are not limited to the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Health Care Financing Administration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Medical Care Programs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Licensing and Certification Administration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>MDH Corporate Compliance Office; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Maryland Disability Law Center.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health-General Article, §7-904, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1974-01-07">Effective date: January 7, 1974</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1980-07-25">Regulations <cite path="|10|22|03|.01">.01</cite> — <cite path="|10|22|03|.27">.27</cite> amended effective July 25, 1980 (7:15 Md. R. 1425)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-09-21">Regulations <cite path="|10|22|03|.01">.01</cite> — <cite path="|10|22|03|.27">.27</cite>, Group Homes for the Mentally Retarded, repealed effective September 21, 1986 (13:19 Md. R. 2121)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-09-12" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|10|22|03|.01">.01</cite> — <cite path="|10|22|03|.07">.07</cite>, Community Residential Services for Mentally Retarded and Nonretarded Developmentally Disabled Individuals, adopted effective September 12, 1986 (13:19 Md. R. 2121)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1988-12-26" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective December 26, 1988 (15:26 Md. R. 2983)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-07-26" discontinuity="true">Chapter, Community Residential Services for Individuals with Developmental Disability, repealed and new chapter, General Provisions for Sanctions and Appeals, adopted effective July 26, 1999 (26:15 Md. R. 1148)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
