<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>09</num>
  <heading>Resource Coordination Program Service Plan</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Additional Regulatory Compliance.</heading>
    <text>In addition to this chapter, a person who provides resource coordination to an individual shall comply with the following regulations of this subtitle:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text><cite path="|10.22.01">COMAR 10.22.01</cite>;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text><cite path="|10.22.02">COMAR 10.22.02</cite>, except <cite path="10.22.02.05">COMAR 10.22.02.05</cite>, .06, .07, .11, .12, and .14E(1)(d);</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text><cite path="|10.22.03">COMAR 10.22.03</cite>;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text><cite path="|10.22.04">COMAR 10.22.04</cite>; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text><cite path="|10.22.05">COMAR 10.22.05</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Rationale.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Resource coordination is provided by a resource coordinator.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The resource coordinator assists individuals in obtaining the best quality and most appropriate services and supports within available resources.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The resource coordinator is responsible to individuals and their families for providing assistance in implementing individual choice, addressing individual satisfaction, and assuring that an individual's needs and preferences are addressed.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Resource coordination may be provided to individuals determined eligible for services from the Administration, including individuals on the waiting list.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Resource coordination may only be provided by licensees who do not provide direct services to individuals.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The level and intensity of resource coordination may vary according to the individual's needs and desire for resource coordination.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>In the State residential center, a resource coordinator shall be provided for all individuals for the purpose of participating in the development of the written plan of habilitation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Functions of the Resource Coordination Licensee.</heading>
    <text>The resource coordination licensee shall carry out the following functions:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Determine an individual's needs, preferences, desires, satisfaction, and the most integrated setting appropriate to meet the individual's needs;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Assist the individual through planning in choosing goals and outcomes, the services needed to accomplish these goals and outcomes, and the establishment of realistic time frames for meeting these goals and outcomes;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Broker services in consultation with the regional office to obtain generic services, services funded by the Administration, and natural supports;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Advocate for the individual to assure that the individual's rights are protected and the individual's needs and preferences are considered;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Monitor and act as a third-party advocate for implementation of the IP; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If requested by the Administration, provide utilization review of services being provided to individuals.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Responsibilities of the Resource Coordinator.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The resource coordinator is responsible for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Ensuring that each individual receives an IP that is designed to meet the individual's needs, preferences, desires, goals, and outcomes in the most integrated setting appropriate to meet the individual's needs and in the most cost effective manner;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Documenting that the IP is being implemented as designed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Communicating information with the Administration in an effort to achieve a responsive service delivery system;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Assisting the individual in applying for services; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Providing education to individuals and their families concerning:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The range of most integrated setting service and support options that may be appropriate to meet the individual's needs;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>How to access services, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>How to coordinate and advocate for services.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Resource coordinators shall have personal knowledge of each individual served and make every effort to effectively accommodate the individual's needs and preferences.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Resource coordinators shall personally meet with each individual served, at least every 6 months, in an effort to effectively meet the individual's needs and preferences.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>In the State residential center, the resource coordinator shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Ensure that communication devices and techniques, including the use of sign language, as appropriate, are used to facilitate the involvement of the individual in the development of the written plan of habilitation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Recommend the most integrated setting appropriate to meet the individual's needs; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Conduct an annual update on the status and progress toward addressing and resolving the barriers to receiving services and supports in the most integrated setting.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Staffing and Training.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A resource coordinator shall have the skills necessary to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Determine the most integrated setting appropriate to meet the individual's needs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Coordinate planning meetings;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Negotiate and resolve conflicts;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Assist individuals in gaining access to services and supports;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Coordinate services; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Monitor the provision of services to individuals.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The resource coordination licensee shall ensure through appropriate documentation that the resource coordinator receives training in:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Fundamental rights;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Communication skills;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Specific disabilities of the individuals the resource coordinator serves;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Development of the IP;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Facilitating individual choice;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Determining individual satisfaction; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Developing opportunities for individuals to establish relationships, friendships, and connections in the community.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Setting.</heading>
    <text>To the extent feasible, individuals may select:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Their own resource coordinator; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The time, place, and frequency of meetings.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health-General Article, §§7-903 and 7-904, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-08-25">Effective date: August 25, 1986 (13:17 Md. R. 1922)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-07-26" discontinuity="true">Chapter, Services Coordination Programs for Mentally Retarded and Nonretarded Developmentally Disabled Individuals, repealed and new chapter, Resource Coordination Program Service Plan, adopted effective July 26, 1999 (26:15 Md. R. 1148)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-05-05"><cite path="|10|22|09|.03|D.">Regulation .03D</cite> adopted effective May 5, 2008 (35:9 Md. R. 897)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-05-05"><cite path="|10|22|09|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite> amended effective May 5, 2008 (35:9 Md. R. 897)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-05-05"><cite path="|10|22|09|.05|A.">Regulation .05A</cite> amended effective May 5, 2008 (35:9 Md. R. 897)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-05-05"><cite path="|10|22|09|.05|D.">Regulation .05D</cite> adopted effective May 5, 2008 (35:9 Md. R. 897)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-05-05"><cite path="|10|22|09|.06|A.">Regulation .06A</cite> amended effective May 5, 2008 (35:9 Md. R. 897)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
