<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>19</num>
  <heading>Special Programs</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Day services" means services provided by a licensed provider under <cite path="10.22.07.03|E.">COMAR 10.22.07.03E</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Enclave" means a group of eight or fewer individuals with developmental disabilities that works as a single team in a single community work site.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Fiscal Incentive Program for Employment (FIPE)" means the program that provides a one-time fiscal incentive to eligible programs to assist individuals with developmental disabilities in securing and maintaining a job of the individual's choice in the community.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Mobile crew" means a group of eight or fewer individuals with developmental disabilities that operates as a single team moving from one work site to another, performing contracted tasks such as custodial and ground maintenance.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Self-employed" means an individual who owns and operates a business that generates revenue.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Sheltered environment" means a setting that is segregated to include only individuals with disabilities who perform work or simulated work training activities for subminimum wages.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Supported employment" has the meaning stated in <cite path="10.22.07.03|C.">COMAR 10.22.07.03C</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Fiscal Incentive Program for Employment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Provider Eligibility. A provider is eligible to be included in the FIPE if the provider:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is licensed as a vocational or day services program under <cite path="|10.22.07">COMAR 10.22.07</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provides services to an eligible individual.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Individual Eligibility. An individual is eligible to be included in the FIPE if the individual:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Has a developmental disability;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Has not received a day service funded by the Administration before July 1, 2003;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Is employed in the same job for 6 months which commenced on or after July 1, 2003, or if the individual was employed before entering DDA supported employment services, the 6 months of employment at the same job begins on the day in which the individual begins services, which is on or after July 1, 2003;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Is receiving ongoing supports and services that are individually determined in order to attain and maintain a job of the individual's choice; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Has not been previously included in the FIPE.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Employment Eligibility. A job is an eligible job under the FIPE if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The job is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Located in the community;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Individualized;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Not an enclave, mobile crew, or in a segregated environment; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Based on the individual's interests; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The individual:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is paid a competitive salary and, if available, offered benefits directly by the employer;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Does not receive salary and, if available, benefits from the provider or any organization affiliated with the licensee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Deals directly with the employer regarding working conditions such as work schedule;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Has the opportunity for increased responsibility, career advancement, and increased wages based on performance; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>If self-employed, the business generates revenue.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Reimbursement.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If the provider wishes to seek reimbursement through the FIPE, the provider shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Complete the application form provided by the Administration;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Provide:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Pay stubs for the last 6 months showing that an individual was employed in the community, as requested by the Administration; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>If the individual is self-employed, cash flow or other financial statements for the last 6 months;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Provide evidence that ongoing supports and services that are individually determined in order to maintain the job of the individual's choice have been provided;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Provide a written statement from the individual or the individual's proponent indicating that the individual is satisfied with the current job and working conditions, including pay, work schedule, and benefits; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Provide any other information required by the Administration.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Administration Approval. In deciding whether to authorize an individual for inclusion in the FIPE, the Administration shall consider the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Application and supporting documentation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Availability of State funds.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Payment.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For each preauthorized and eligible individual, the Administration may approve a payment to the provider in the amount of 10 percent of the individual's annual funding, excluding add-on components and supplemental services, for the year the individual entered the FIPE.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Administration shall approve only one payment for each preauthorized and eligible individual.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The provider shall submit an invoice to the Administration to receive payment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health-General Article, §§2-104(b), 7-306.1, and 7-904, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-12-22">Effective date: December 22, 2003 (30:25 Md. R. 1846)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
