<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>General</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Authorization of Regulations.</heading>
    <text>The <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu">Public Utilities Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, provides that the Commission shall have the power to make such reasonable regulations as it deems necessary to carry out the provisions of this law and any other law relating to the Commission.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Application of Regulations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Application. These regulations apply to any sewage disposal utility operating within the State, under the jurisdiction of the Public Service Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Purpose. These regulations are intended to promote safe and adequate service to the public, to provide standards for uniform and reasonable practices by utilities, and to outline the responsibility of the public in requesting and receiving service from the utilities.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Exemption. If unreasonable hardship to a utility or to a customer results from the application of any of these regulations, application may be made to the Commission for the modification of the regulation or for temporary or permanent exemption from its requirements.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Modification. The adoption of these regulations does not preclude the Commission from altering or amending them, or from making such modifications with respect to their application as may be found necessary to meet exceptional conditions.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Duties Under Other Statutes. These regulations do not relieve any utility from any of its duties under the laws of this State.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this subtitle, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Commission" means the Public Service Commission of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Customer" means a person, partnership, association, corporation, or government agency being provided with sewage disposal service by a utility.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Main" means a sewage pipe owned, operated, or maintained by a sewage disposal company, which is used to transport sewage, but does not include "service pipe."</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Premises" means a tract of land or real estate, including buildings and other appurtenances thereon.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Service pipe" means the pipe which runs from the customer's premises to the main, and which receives sewage from the customer's premises.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Sewage" means ground garbage, human and animal excretions, and all other domestic type waste normally disposed of by a domicile, or commercial establishment, through the sanitary drainage system.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Sewage plant" means a plant and property owned by a sewage disposal utility, used in its business operations of providing sewage disposal service to its customers.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Utility" means a "sewage disposal company" as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|1-101">Public Utilities Article, §1-101, Annotated COde of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Public Utilities Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-113">2-113</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-121">2-121</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|5-101">5-101</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|5-303">5-303</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1965-09-01">Effective date: September 1, 1965 (Order No. 55971)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
