<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>04</num>
  <heading>Customer Relations</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Applications for Service.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Applications. All applications for sewerage service should be made in writing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Application Constitutes Contract. The accepted application shall constitute a contract between the company and the applicant, obligating the applicant to pay for sewerage service in accordance with the utility's tariff currently on file with the Public Service Commission, and to comply with this subtitle.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Termination of Service. When a customer desires to have his service terminated, he shall notify the utility and the notification should be in writing.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Information for Customers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>System Maps or Records. Each utility shall maintain up-to-date maps, plans, or records of its entire force main and collection systems, with such other information as may be necessary to enable the utility to advise prospective customers, and others entitled to the information, as to the facilities available for serving any locality.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Selecting Rate Schedule. Each utility shall assist the customer or prospective customer in selecting the most economical rate schedule.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Notifying Customers. Each utility shall notify customers affected by a change in rates or schedule classification.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Tariff Notice. Each utility shall post a notice in a conspicuous place in each office of the utility where applications for service are received, informing the public that a copy of its tariff, as filed with the Commission, is available for inspection.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Other Information. Each utility shall furnish such additional information as the customer may reasonably request.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Customer Deposits.</heading>
    <text>Each utility may require from a customer a deposit to be applied against any unpaid balance due the utility for service at the time service is terminated, in accordance with the provisions of <cite path="|20.30">COMAR 20.30</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Bill Forms.</heading>
    <text>The bill forms shall show:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Amount. The gross or net amount, or both, of the bill.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Payment Date. The date by which the customer must pay the bill in order to benefit from a discount or to avoid a penalty.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Estimated Bill. A distinct marking to identify an estimated bill.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Rate Schedule. The applicable rate schedule, or identification of the applicable rate schedule. If the actual rates are not shown, the bill shall carry a statement to the effect that the applicable rate schedule will be furnished on request.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Metering Data. If the rate for sewerage service is based on the reading of the water meter, the bill forms shall show:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Meter Reading. The reading of the meter at the end of the period for which the bill is rendered.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Meter Reading Date. The date on which the meter was read.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Units Used. The number and kind of units metered.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Billing Records.</heading>
    <text>The utility shall retain customer billing records for the length of time necessary to permit the utility to comply with <cite path="|20|75|04|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite> but not less than 3 years.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Adjustment of Bills.</heading>
    <text>When the charge for sewerage service is based on the charge for water used, and it is necessary to adjust the bill for water service, then the bill for sewerage service shall be adjusted in the same rate.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Refusal to Serve Applicant.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Noncompliance with Regulations. A utility may decline to serve an applicant until he has complied with this subtitle, and any other applicable State or municipal regulations governing sewer service, and the rules of the utility on file with the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Utility's Facilities Inadequate. A utility may decline to serve an applicant if it does not have adequate facilities to render the service applied for, or if the intended use is of a character that is likely to adversely affect service to the other customers.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Applicant's Facilities Inadequate. The utility may refuse to serve an applicant if, in its judgment, the applicant's installation of sewer piping is regarded as hazardous or of such character that satisfactory service cannot be given.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Failure to Provide Deposit. The utility may refuse to serve an applicant or customer if he fails to provide the utility with a deposit as authorized in <cite path="|20|75|04|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Failure to Comply with Service Conditions. A utility may refuse to serve an applicant until he furnishes such service equipment, permits, certificates, or rights-of-way, as shall have been specified by the utility as a condition to obtaining service, or if the equipment or permissions are withdrawn or terminated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Utility's Discontinuance of Service. Considerations of health and sanitation require that sewer service should not be discontinued because of non-payment of service charges. The sewerage utility should make use of such legal remedies as may be available for the collection of delinquent accounts.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Applicant's Recourse. If the utility refuses to serve an applicant under the provisions of this regulation or any other regulation, the utility shall inform the applicant of the basis of its refusal, and the applicant may appeal to the Commission for a ruling.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Right of Access.</heading>
    <text>The authorized agents of the utility shall have the right of access to the customer's premises, at reasonable hours, for the purpose of inspecting the customer's sewerage connections and for any other purpose which is proper and necessary in the conduct of the utility's business.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Identification of Employees.</heading>
    <text>Every employee, whose duties require him to enter the customer's premises, should wear a distinguishing uniform, or other insignia identifying him as an employee of the utility. The minimum requirement shall be a badge or identification card, carried on his person, certifying him as an employee of the utility authorized to enter the premises to perform necessary inspections or work.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Investigation of Complaints.</heading>
    <text>The utility shall investigate promptly and thoroughly any complaint concerning its charges, practices, facilities, or service.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Records of Complaints.</heading>
    <text>The utility shall keep such records of customer complaints as will enable it to review and analyze its procedures and actions as an aid in rendering improved service.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Public Utilities Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-121">2-121</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|5-101">5-101</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1965-09-01">Effective date: September 1, 1965 (Order No. 55971)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1981-01-23"><cite path="|20|75|04|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective January 23, 1981 (8:2 Md. R.117)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
