<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>Inspection and Copying of Public Records</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter sets forth procedures for the disclosure, inspection, or copying of public records maintained by the Maryland Longitudinal Data System Center.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This chapter does not apply to aggregate data requests. The procedures for aggregate data requests by the public from data maintained by the Maryland Longitudinal Data System Center are set forth in <cite path="|14.36.04">COMAR 14.36.04</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Policy.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>It is the policy of the Maryland Longitudinal Data System Center to facilitate public access to the Center’s public records when access is authorized by law.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Center’s policy is to make all public records easily accessible on the agency’s website.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Act” means the Public Information Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp">General Provisions Article, Title 4, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Applicant” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-101">General Provisions Article, §4-101(b), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Center” means the Maryland Longitudinal Data System Center, its advisory boards, its committees, any other public bodies under the authority and acting on behalf of the Maryland Longitudinal Data System Center, and any employees, agents, or contractors acting on behalf of the Maryland Longitudinal Data System Center.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Custodian” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-101">General Provisions Article, §4-101(d), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Data partner” means a State agency, an industry certifier, or other entity that originally collects student and workforce data and provides that data to the Center under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|27-707">Education Article, §27-707, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Executive Director” means the Executive Director of the Maryland Longitudinal Data System Center.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Governing Board” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|24-701">Education Article, §24-701, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Official custodian” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-101">General Provisions Article, §4-101(f), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“Person in interest” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A person or governmental unit that is the subject of a public record;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An authorized designee of the person or governmental unit that is the subject of a public record; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If the person has a legal disability, a parent or legal representative of the person that is the subject of a public record.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>“Public record” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-101">General Provisions Article, §4-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>“Working day” means a day other than Saturday, Sunday, or a State holiday or service reduction day.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Official Custodian.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Executive Director shall designate an official custodian of public records for the Center.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The website for the Center shall provide the name and contact information for the custodian of public records.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Who May Request Public Records.</heading>
    <text>Any person may request to inspect or copy public records of the Center.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Necessity for Written Request.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Inspection.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as otherwise provided in this chapter, the custodian shall make public records of the Center available for inspection by an applicant without demanding a written request.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The custodian shall require a written request if the custodian reasonably believes that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Act or any other law may prohibit the disclosure of the public record to the applicant; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A written request will materially assist the Center in responding.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Copies. If the applicant requests a copy of any public record of the Center, the custodian may require a written request.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Contents of Written Request.</heading>
    <text>A written request shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Contain the applicant’s name and address;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Be signed by the applicant; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Reasonably identify, by brief description, the public record sought.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Addressee.</heading>
    <text>A request to inspect or copy a public record shall be addressed to the custodian of the record. If the custodian is unknown, the request may be addressed to the Executive Director.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="14|36|01|.09">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Response to Request.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If the custodian decides to grant a request for inspection, the custodian shall produce the public record for inspection, without unreasonable delay, as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Immediately for records designated by the Center for inspection, as set forth in <cite path="14|36|01|.09|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If additional time is needed to retrieve the public record and conduct any necessary review, within a reasonable time period, not to exceed 30 days after the date of the request.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The custodian shall designate the following public records for immediate inspection:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Bylaws of the Governing Board;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Minutes of the Governing Board; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Data sharing agreements entered into by the Center and data partners<em>.</em></text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the custodian decides to deny a request for inspection, the custodian shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Do so within 30 days after the request; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Immediately notify the applicant of the denial.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If a request is denied, the custodian shall provide the applicant, at the time of the denial or within 10 working days, a written statement that gives:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The reason for the denial;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The legal authority for the denial; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Notice of the remedies available for review of the denial.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If a requested public record is not in the custody or control of the custodian to whom application is made, the custodian shall, within 10 working days after receipt of the request, notify the applicant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>That the custodian does not have custody or control of the requested public record; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the custodian knows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The name of the custodian of the public record; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The location or possible location of the public record.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>With the consent of the applicant, any time limit imposed by §§A—C of this regulation may be extended for an additional period of up to 30 days.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Notice to Person Possibly Affected by Disclosure.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Unless prohibited by law, the custodian may provide notice of a request for inspection or copying of any public record of the Center to any person who, in the judgment of the custodian, could be adversely affected by disclosure of the public record.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The custodian may consider the views of the possibly affected person before deciding whether to disclose the public record to an applicant.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Public Record Temporarily Unavailable.</heading>
    <text>If a requested public record of the Center is not immediately available for inspection or copying, the custodian shall promptly:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Notify the applicant that the public record is not immediately available; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Schedule a date within a reasonable time for inspection or copying.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Public Record Destroyed or Lost.</heading>
    <text>If the custodian knows that a requested public record of the Center has been destroyed or lost, the custodian shall promptly:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Notify the applicant that the public record is not available; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Explain the reasons why the public record cannot be produced.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Review of Denial.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If the custodian denies a request to inspect or copy a public record of the Center, the applicant may file an action for judicial enforcement under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-362">General Provisions Article, §4-362, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, without pursuing the remedies set forth in §§B and C of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the custodian charges a fee of more than $350 under <cite path="|14|36|01|.15">Regulation .15 of this chapter</cite>, the applicant may, within 90 days after the date the fee is imposed, file a written complaint with the State Public Information Act Compliance Board under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-1">General Provisions Article, §4-1</cite>A-05(a), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The applicant and the custodian each may contact the Public Access Ombudsman to resolve, under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp">General Provisions Article, Title 4, Subtitle 1B, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, a dispute relating to requests for public records.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Disclosure Against Public Interest.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Denial Pending Court Order.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If, in the opinion of the custodian, disclosure of a public record of the Center otherwise subject to disclosure under the Act would do substantial injury to the public interest, the custodian may temporarily deny the request to obtain a court order allowing nondisclosure.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A temporary denial shall be in writing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Circuit Court Review.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within 10 working days after the denial, the custodian shall apply to the appropriate circuit court for an order permitting continued denial or restriction of access.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Notice of the custodian’s complaint, on behalf of the Center, shall be served on the applicant in the manner provided for service of process under the Maryland Rules.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="14|36|01|.15">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Fees.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in §§B and C of this regulation, the fee schedule for responding to requests of public records of the Center is as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For each copy made by a photocopying machine within the Center, 25 cents per page;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For each copy made other than by a photocopying machine within the Center, the actual cost of reproduction;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>For certification as a true copy of a public record, an additional fee of $1 per page or, if appropriate, per item; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>For electronic records provided in an electronic format, no fee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Minimum Fee. A charge may not be made if the total fee is $1 or less.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the fee for copies or certified copies of any public record of the Center is specifically set by a law other than the Act or this regulation, the custodian shall charge the prescribed fee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the custodian cannot copy a public record within the Center, the custodian shall make arrangements for the prompt reproduction of the record at public or private facilities outside the Center. The custodian shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Collect from the applicant a fee to cover the actual cost of reproduction; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Direct the applicant to pay the cost of reproduction directly to the facility making the copy.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Before copying a public record of the Center, the custodian shall estimate the cost of reproduction and either:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Obtain the agreement of the applicant to pay the cost; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Require prepayment of the cost.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="14|36|01|.15|G.">§G of this regulation</cite> the custodian may charge a reasonable fee for time that an official or employee of the Center spends to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Search for requested public records; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Prepare public records for inspection and copying.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The custodian may not charge a search or preparation fee for the first 2 hours that an official or employee of the Center spends to respond to a request for public records.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The Center may charge a reasonable hourly fee based upon the actual cost to the Center for staff services for additional time required to search for or prepare public records for inspection or copying.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Waiver or Reduction of Fee.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The custodian may waive or reduce any fee under this regulation if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The applicant requests a waiver; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The custodian determines that the waiver or reduction is in the public interest.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In making a decision under this section, the custodian shall consider, among other relevant factors, the ability of the applicant to pay the fee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>If the applicant requests that copies of a public record be mailed or delivered to the applicant or to a third party, the custodian may charge the applicant for the actual cost of postage or delivery, and the cost of any electronic media used to provide the copies.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Time and Place of Inspection.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant may inspect any public record of the Center that the applicant is entitled to inspect, by appointment<em>,</em> during the normal working hours of the Center.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The inspection shall occur where the public record is located, unless the custodian, after taking into account the applicant’s expressed wish, determines that another place is more suitable and convenient.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|24-703">24-703</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|24-706">24-706</cite>; General Provisions Article, Title 4; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-01-19">Effective date: January 19, 2015 (42:1 Md. R. 18)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-10-14"><cite path="|14|36|01|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective October 14, 2024 (51:20 Md. R. 899)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-10-14"><cite path="|14|36|01|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective October 14, 2024 (51:20 Md. R. 899)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-10-14"><cite path="|14|36|01|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite> amended effective February 26, 2018 (45:4 Md. R. 207); October 14, 2024 (51:20 Md. R. 899)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-10-14"><cite path="|14|36|01|.09|B.">Regulation .09B</cite> amended October 14, 2024 (51:20 Md. R. 899)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-10-14"><cite path="|14|36|01|.11">Regulation .11</cite> amended October 14, 2024 (51:20 Md. R. 899)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-02-26"><cite path="|14|36|01|.13">Regulation .13</cite> amended effective February 26, 2018 (45:4 Md. R. 207)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-10-14"><cite path="|14|36|01|.13|A.">Regulation .13A</cite> amended effective October 14, 2024 (51:20 Md. R. 899)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-10-14"><cite path="|14|36|01|.14">Regulation .14</cite> amended October 14, 2024 (51:20 Md. R. 899)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-10-14"><cite path="|14|36|01|.15|A.">Regulation .15A</cite> amended October 14, 2024 (51:20 Md. R. 899)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-10-14"><cite path="|14|36|01|.16|A.">Regulation .16A</cite> amended October 14, 2024 (51:20 Md. R. 899)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
