<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Meetings.</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Center” means the Maryland Longitudinal Data System Center<strong>.</strong></text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Governing Board” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|24-701">Education Article, §24-701, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Open session” means a meeting of the Governing Board that is required to be open to the public pursuant to the Open Meetings Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 10, Subtitle 5, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Public Attendance.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The general public is invited to attend and observe any open sessions of the Governing Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Meetings shall be held in a manner or location that is reasonably accessible to individuals who would like to attend and observe an open session of the Governing Board.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Public Participation Limited.</heading>
    <text>A member of the public attending an open session may not participate in the session unless:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Governing Board expressly invites public testimony, questions, comments, or other forms of public participation;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The person is entitled by law to participate; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>As provided by the bylaws of the Governing Board, the individual has received prior approval from the chairman of the Governing Board to participate, subject to a time limit set by the chairman.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="14|36|03|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Disruptive Conduct.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An individual attending an open session may not engage in any conduct, including but not limited to visual demonstrations such as the display of placards, signs, or banners, that disrupts the session or interferes with the right of members of the public to attend and observe the session.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Authority of the chair of the Governing Board.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The chair of the Governing Board may order an individual who violates <cite path="14|36|03|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, or who violates any other regulation or resolution concerning the conduct of the open session, to be removed from the session, and may request police assistance to restore order.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The chair of the Governing Board may recess the session while order is restored.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An individual who is asked to leave the session in accordance with these regulations and who refuses to do so may be subject to arrest as provided by law.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Recording, Photographing, and Broadcasting of Open Sessions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A member of the public, including a representative of the news media, may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Record the discussions at an open session using a tape recorder or other recording device if the device used does not create excessive noise that disturbs the open session or other individuals attending the session; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Photograph or videotape the proceedings of an open session using any type of camera if the camera is operated without excessively bright artificial light or excessive noise that disturbs the open session or other individuals attending the session.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A representative of the news media may broadcast or televise the open session if the equipment used is operated without excessively bright artificial light or excessive noise that disturbs the open session or other individuals attending the session.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The chair of the Governing Board may restrict the movement of an individual who is using a recording device, a camera, or broadcasting or televising equipment if the restriction is necessary to maintain the orderly conduct of the open session.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A member of the public who intends to record the discussions at an open session is requested to provide notice to the Executive Director of the Center in advance of the meeting advising of the intention to record the proceedings and specifying the type of equipment to be used to record the proceedings.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Recordings Not Part of Record.</heading>
    <text>A recording of an open session made by a member of the public including a representative of the news media or any transcript derived from a recording is not a part of the record of the open session.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|24-706">Education Article, §24-706</cite>; State Government Article, Title 10, Subtitle 5; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-01-19">Effective date: January 19, 2015 (42:1 Md. R. 18)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-10-14"><cite path="|14|36|03|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective October 14, 2024 (51:20 Md. R. 899)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-10-14"><cite path="|14|36|03|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective October 14, 2024 (51:20 Md. R. 899)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-10-14"><cite path="|14|36|03|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective October 14, 2024 (51:20 Md. R. 899)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
