<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>06</num>
  <heading>Center Staff</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="14|36|06|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Authorized Staff.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Scope. <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|24-703">Education Article, §24-703(h), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, restricts access to data in the Maryland Longitudinal Data System to authorized staff of the Center. This regulation sets out a procedure for authorizing Center staff.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>General. Authorized staff of the Center shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>State employees of the Center; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Individuals authorized by the Executive Director pursuant to <cite path="14|36|06|.01|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Authorization by Executive Director.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Limitations.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Executive Director may only authorize individuals to serve as staff of the Center who are necessary to carry out the mission of the Center.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Center staff shall be restricted in number for the purpose of maintaining control over access to the Maryland Longitudinal Data System in strict compliance with State and federal privacy laws.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Executive Director may designate the following individuals as authorized staff of the Center:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Researchers, including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Faculty staff, and graduate students, from a public senior higher education institution who are identified by the Director of the Research Services Branch to provide research and analysis as part of  the Research Services Branch of the Center; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Additional researchers who, pursuant to the MLDS Center’s Project Approval and Management Procedures, have applied for and received approval to conduct a project using MLDS data consistent with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|24-703">Education Article, §24-703(f)(4) </cite>and (5), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Information technology experts and technicians necessary to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Install, maintain, and repair data center equipment;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Provide assistance in maintaining system security; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Provide system development support; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A State agency employee or contractor as needed to provide information technology expertise to assist with data sharing or system administration.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Background Investigations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>All staff of the Center shall have a State and federal criminal history background check within 5 business days of starting as staff of the Center.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An individual is not eligible to have access to the longitudinal data system until the individual has completed and passed the criminal history background investigation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An individual is deemed to have an unsatisfactory criminal history background investigation if the individual:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Has been convicted of a felony of any nature; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Within the last 10 years, has been convicted of a crime that qualifies as an infamous crime under Maryland law.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="14|36|06|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Security Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General. The Center’s Executive Director shall require all authorized staff of the Center to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Comply with the rules of security behavior that are provided to staff;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Receive and review the MLDS Center’s Data Security and Safeguarding Plan, data sharing agreements, the Maryland Department of Labor—Confidentiality Certification Form, and other documents required by the Executive Director; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Periodically take security and privacy training classes.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Required Compliance. The Executive Director shall remove a staff member’s system access if the staff member fails to remain in compliance with the requirements in <cite path="14|36|06|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|24-703">24-703</cite>(h) and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|24-706">24-706</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-07-06">Effective date: July 6, 2015 (42:13 Md. R. 796)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-10-14"><cite path="|14|36|06|.01|A.">Regulation .01A</cite>, C amended effective October 14, 2024 (51:20 Md. R. 899)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-10-14"><cite path="|14|36|06|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite> amended effective October 14, 2024 (51:20 Md. R. 899)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
