<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Innovative and Alternative On-Site Sewage Disposal System Grant Program</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purposes and Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The purpose of this program is to identify additional types of on-site sewage disposal systems that can be used in Maryland. The Department is authorized to make grants available to political subdivisions for the purpose of constructing innovative and alternative on-site sewage disposal systems.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The subdivisions shall use the State grants to provide grants to owners of improved properties with failed conventional systems and owners of previously recorded land that has failed a soil percolation test.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Grants shall be used only for installing experimental systems using Department approved innovative and alternative system design criteria.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>This chapter establishes eligibility criteria for participation by local political subdivisions and property owners in the program.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Department" means the Department of the Environment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Includes or including" means includes or including by way of illustration and not by way of limitation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Innovative and alternative on-site sewage disposal system" means any new, experimental, or non-conventional technology that is added to or used in place of a conventional septic or other on-site sewage system.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Program" means the innovative and alternative on-site sewage disposal system grant program.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>General Provisions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This program may not be applied to the development of an unimproved parcel of land that is proposed to be subdivided into building lots.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Department shall manage and supervise the program and make grant available to political subdivisions under conditions listed in <cite path="|26|03|05|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A project for which State financial assistance is granted shall comply with all applicable State laws and regulations governing the safe and adequate disposal of sewage.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>State financial assistance may not provide more than $10,000 or 50 percent of the anticipated construction costs of the project, whichever is less.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Department shall request comment from the Department of State Planning or any community planning agency regarding demographics, land use, and fiscal impact or any other pertinent information regarding program projects.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Political Subdivision Eligibility.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>To be eligible for State funds, a political subdivision shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Have local funding and manpower resources available to establish and maintain local innovative and alternative on-site sewage disposal system programs including the ability to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Collect data;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Prepare technical reports; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Inspect the operation and performance of the systems installed.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Submit an agreement to be signed with the Department as outlined in <cite path="|26|03|05|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>, and their innovative and alternative program plan within 3 months of their notification by the Department of the availability of program funds. The program plan and agreement shall detail the role of the local county health department in the innovative and alternative program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Have known hydrogeological problems, such as permanently high or seasonally high water table conditions, shallow soils, or slowly permeable soils, which can be addressed by innovative and alternative sewage disposal systems.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Submit a final eligibility and priority list of applicants to the Department for review and approval as outlined in <cite path="|26|03|05|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite> within 1 year of the execution of the Department agreement with the political subdivision.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Priority for allocating funds to eligible political subdivisions shall be given to those subdivisions whose collective innovative and alternative program plans offer the best opportunity to satisfy the purpose of the program, as defined in Regulation .01A, of this chapter, on a Statewide basis.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Funds not dispensed to applicants by political subdivisions within 6 months of their receipt shall be returned to the Department for reallocation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Applicant Eligibility.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>To be eligible for State funds from a political subdivision under the program an applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Own property in this State that is included in the county master water and sewer plan as an area where individual on-site water and sewer systems may be used that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Has an existing failed septic system, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is unimproved, was platted before 1972, and has failed percolation testing requirements;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Have made a good faith effort to obtain approval of, or to use a conventional septic system;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Agree to conditions of the experiment as outlined in <cite path="|26|03|05|.07">Regulation .07 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Be limited to one grant to serve one homesite to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Upgrade an existing system;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Abate an existing pollution or public health problem related to sewage disposal; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Improve one unimproved site with a new home and innovative and alternative on-site sewage disposal system.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Priority for program participation shall be given to applicants who have:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An existing failed on-site sewage disposal system which cannot be repaired using conventional methods;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An existing pollution or public health problem related to sewage disposal; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Property which offers a significant opportunity for providing useful data to the experimental effort.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Department Agreements with Political Subdivisions.</heading>
    <text>Political subdivisions receiving grants under this program are required to enter into an agreement with the Department. This agreement shall provide for:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The political subdivision to commit adequate resources for establishing a local innovative and alternative on-site sewage disposal system program to be conducted in accordance with requirements established by the Department and including:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Applicant screening and site evaluations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Input to and review of system design;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>System inspection and monitoring;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Technical reporting on system performance in accordance with requirements established by the Department; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Review by the local planning agency for relation to land use or other pertinent information.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The role the local county health departments will serve in the program including a description of their participation in:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Applicant screening;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Site evaluation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Review of system design; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Monitoring and reporting.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A selection process for choosing projects to be funded when the number of eligible, priority applicants exceeds available funding levels. With the concurrence of the Department, State grant participation may be established at less than 50 percent of the project costs for any individual project.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The political subdivision to screen and list applications for project eligibility and priority ranking in accordance with requirements in this chapter. The screening process shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A site evaluation and determination of the nature of the project and its suitability to receive grant assistance including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The applicant's name;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A plat description of site to be served, including size, property boundaries, and location;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A statement as to whether the property is improved or unimproved;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The number of bedrooms in the house;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The estimated sewage flow;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Site characteristics including slope, soil data, surface and subsurface drainage, vegetation and well location; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Relation of the project to the local comprehensive plan and relation to other State or local programs for management of development, including the Chesapeake Bay Critical Areas Program and Agricultural Land Preservation Program;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Preparation of a site location map or maps which identify the location of the eligible sites in relation to the nearest roads and topographical features; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Prioritization of eligible applicants.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The political subdivision to conduct in-depth site evaluations for each site meeting eligibility and priority requirements to ascertain ability of the site to support an innovative and alternative system. Site evaluation shall be conducted in accordance with Department requirements and include description or assessment of the following site characteristics:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Soil depth to ground water or bedrock, or both;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Soil profiles;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Soil permeability;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Extent of tree cover; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Any other site characteristics which may affect the performance of innovative and alternative sewage disposal systems considered applicable for the site.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The political subdivision to make recommendations for each site evaluated, including the type of innovative and alternative sewage disposal system best suited to the site, and a relisting of eligible and priority applicants given in-depth evaluation findings. This listing shall be submitted in accordance with the timetable outlined in <cite path="|26|03|05|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The Department to approve of political subdivisions' screening listing and in-depth evaluation results before State grant awards to political subdivisions. The Department's approval process shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Review of screening, prioritization, and site evaluation procedures and results;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Consideration of the ability of available technologies to meet site constraints;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Consideration of the potential of the site to support feasible and economical monitoring systems and provide useful experimental data; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Consideration of comments received from the Department's submittal of the final priority listing of eligible projects and the site location map or maps of the eligible sites to the State Clearinghouse for intergovernmental review in accordance with the process described in <cite path="|16.02.01">COMAR 16.02.01</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The political subdivision to make progress reports to the Department on the administration of the local programs, including status reports on the performance of funded projects.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Political Subdivision Agreements with Applicants.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Before Department and political subdivision approval of funding for innovative and alternative on-site sewage disposal systems, an agreement shall be signed by the applicant, political subdivision, and the Department which:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Identifies project elements and fixes their cost based upon a fair assessment of project installation costs, and establishes that the amount of State grant participation may not exceed 50 percent of the anticipated total project cost.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Establishes financial responsibility of homeowners for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Costs incurred in installation above the fixed amount; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>All operating and maintenance costs.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Limits the State's share of the project installation cost to $10,000 or less.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Establishes applicant repayment requirements for the full amount of funds provided under this agreement if, for reasons of neglect, the innovative and alternative system is not adequately maintained or is damaged beyond repair.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Establishes the applicant's financial responsibility for system modification which may be required by the Department or the political subdivision when failure of the system to operate satisfactorily poses a threat to the public health, safety, or comfort. In these cases, necessary system modifications shall be in accordance with the requirements established by the Department or the local health department. System modifications may include requirements for installing holding tanks and regular pumping and hauling of sewage wastes from the holding tanks.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Establishes salvage rights of the State upon default of the applicant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Establishes access for the political subdivision and the Department to enter the applicant's land in order to make periodic inspection and to monitor the system for at least 2 years from initiation of system use or for the duration of the project.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Requires installation by the applicant of either a water meter or cycle counter (for effluent pumping systems), which shall be monitored.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Acknowledges that the proposed innovative and alternative sewage system is experimental and that the applicant's participation is voluntary.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Acknowledges that the political subdivision, the Department and any of their agents or employees do not, either officially or individually, underwrite the operation of any innovative and alternative system approved under this program or incur any liability to the applicant if the innovative and alternative system fails.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Requires that the applicant assure continued, efficient, and effective operation of the system.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Requires the terms of this agreement to run with the land and bind the applicant, his heirs, successors or assigns, and that this agreement shall be recorded in the land records of the political subdivision where the property is located.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Provides for this agreement to be voided at the discretion of the Department if the system construction is not completed within 6 months of the grant award and requires the applicant to repay all funds with interest.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>Establishes any special requirements or conditions deemed necessary by the Department and the political subdivision.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Representatives of the Department and the political subdivision shall meet with program participants, individually or in groups, before the signing of the agreement to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Outline applicant responsibilities in the program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Describe the innovative and alternative system most appropriate for the site; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Explain any special design or maintenance features of the system which may require applicant involvement beyond that required for a conventional septic system.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Environment Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|9-1401">9-1401</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|9-1406">9-1406</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-12-02">Effective date: December 2, 1985 (12:24 Md. R. 2348)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Chapter recodified from <cite path="|10.17.16">COMAR 10.17.16</cite> to <cite path="|26.03.05">COMAR 26.03.05</cite></annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
