<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>06</num>
  <heading>Emissions Equipment Standards</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Applicability.</heading>
    <text>The standards, requirements, and procedures set forth in this chapter are applicable to equipment originally installed by a vehicle manufacturer or required by federal or State requirements on all vehicles designated as a 1968 or newer model year.  Each vehicle has an emissions label in the engine compartment which indicates the emissions equipment originally installed on the vehicle. If the label is not present, refer to an emissions control application guide.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Catalytic Converter.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Most 1975 and newer passenger cars and 1975 through 1978 light-duty trucks with a manufacturer's GVW of 6,000 pounds or less were originally equipped with a catalytic converter. Some passenger cars were not originally equipped with a converter until later model years, and 1979 and newer light-duty trucks with a manufacturer's GVW of 8,501 pounds or more may not have been originally equipped with a catalytic converter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>U.S. Environmental Protection Agency Program for Converter Replacement.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a vehicle is less than 5 model years old and has been driven less than 50,000 miles, any catalytic converter shall be replaced with OEM equipment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a vehicle is more than 5 model years old or has been driven more than 50,000 miles, an EPA-approved new after market catalytic converter designed for the vehicle may be installed on the vehicle. An approved, reconditioned (used) catalytic converter may be installed provided the catalytic converter is an original type for the vehicle and has been certified by an EPA-approved testing facility.</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th>Procedures:</th>
                <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td>(a) Inspect for presence of a proper catalytic converter.</td>
                <td>(a) Catalytic converter is required and is missing or replaced with an unapproved catalytic converter.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(b) Inspect for presence and condition of original air tubing from the engine to the converter.</td>
                <td>(b) The original air tubing is missing, disconnected, or restricted.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(c) Inspect for location of the catalytic converter.</td>
                <td>(c) Catalytic converter is not installed in the original location in the exhaust system.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(d) Inspect vehicle for exhaust systems modifications.</td>
                <td>(d) Dual exhausts have been installed on the vehicle and dual exhausts were not originally available from the vehicle manufacturer.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Fuel Filler Inlet Restrictor (INRES).</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Vehicles originally equipped with a catalytic converter were also equipped with a fuel filler inlet restrictor to prevent the entry of a leaded fuel pump nozzle.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Some later model light-duty trucks were not equipped with a catalytic converter but were equipped with a fuel filler inlet restrictor. The fuel filler inlet restrictor is required on these vehicles.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Inspect for presence of fuel filler inlet restrictor.</td>
              <td>(1) Fuel filler inlet restrictor is required and is missing.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Inspect for condition of fuel filler inlet restrictor.</td>
              <td>(2) Inside diameter of fuel filler inlet restrictor is larger than 0.950 inch.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Positive Crankcase Ventilation System (PCV).</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>All 1968 and newer passenger cars and 1968 through 1978 light-duty trucks with a manufacturer's GVW of 6,000 pounds or less, and 1979 and newer light-duty trucks with a manufacturer's GVW of 8,500 pounds or less are equipped with a crankcase ventilation system.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Early model vehicles may be equipped with an open crankcase ventilation system where air is drawn in through the oil filler tube. Later model vehicles are equipped with a closed crankcase ventilation system where air is drawn in through the carburetor air cleaner. On this type system, the oil filler cap is sealed.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Inspect for presence of the positive crankcase ventilation system.</td>
              <td>(1) Positive crankcase ventilation system is required and any part is missing.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Inspect for presence and condition of positive crankcase ventilation system hoses, tubing, and connections.</td>
              <td>(2) Hoses, tubing, or connections are missing, disconnected, cracked, plugged, leaking, or improperly connected.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Air Injection System (AIS).</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Many 1968 and newer model vehicles are equipped with an air injection system which supplies air to the exhaust ports to extend the combustion process in the exhaust system. The system may be equipped with an external air pump. The pulse, aspirator, suction, or reed injection systems are not equipped with an air pump. Newer model vehicles may be equipped with an air pump which supplies air directly to the catalytic converter.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Inspect for presence of air injection system.</td>
              <td>(1) Air injection system is required and any part is missing.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Inspect for condition of air injection system.</td>
              <td>(2) Hoses, pipes, tubing, fittings, manifolds, or valves are disconnected, plugged, crimped, cracked, leaking, or improperly connected.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Exhaust Gas Recirculation System (EGR).</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Most 1973 and later model vehicles are equipped with an exhaust gas recirculation system to recirculate proper amounts of exhaust gases into the air/fuel mixture in the intake manifold. This recirculation into the manifold reduces combustion temperatures, thus reducing oxides of nitrogen (NOx).  There are several types of EGR systems: a back pressure system which operates in conjunction with exhaust back pressure, a conventional system which operates on carburetor venturi vacuum, an electronically controlled system which operates from the engine computerized emissions control system, or a floor jet system which operates through jets in the floor of the intake manifold.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Inspect for presence of exhaust gas recirculation system.</td>
              <td>(1) Exhaust gas recirculation system is required and any part is missing.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Inspect for condition of exhaust gas recirculation system.</td>
              <td>(2) Hoses, pipes, tubing, valves, or jets are damaged, disconnected, plugged, cracked, leaking, or improperly connected.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Evaporative Emissions System (EVP).</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Most 1971 and newer vehicles and some older models are equipped with an evaporative emissions system to collect and store gasoline vapors and gasoline from the carburetor and fuel system during engine operation or shut down.  The vapors are collected and stored in a canister containing a charcoal filter and gasoline is returned to the fuel tank. The vapors are purged from the canister and drawn into the engine when the engine is started. A pressure vacuum gas cap is essential to the proper operation of this system.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Inspect for presence of evaporative emissions system.</td>
              <td>(1) Evaporative emissions system is required and any part is missing.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Inspect for condition of evaporative emissions system.</td>
              <td>(2) Hoses, pipes, tubing, valves, or connections are plugged, cracked, leaking, or disconnected or gas cap is not the proper type.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-104">12-104</cite>(b) and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|23-104">23-104</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1991-04-01">Effective date: April 1, 1991 (18:6 Md. R. 686)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
