<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>09</num>
  <heading>Safety Standards for Low Speed Vehicles</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Applicability.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The standards, requirements, and procedures set forth in this chapter are applicable to originally manufactured low speed vehicles with originally installed equipment or equipment manufactured and installed to meet the federal and State requirements for low speed vehicles. Any questions regarding low speed vehicle standards or specifications shall be referred to the Automotive Safety Enforcement Division of the Department of State Police.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A low speed vehicle shall comply with federal standards under 49 CFR §571.500. A federal motor vehicle safety certification label shall be affixed to the vehicle identifying it as a "Low Speed Vehicle" for the regulations of this chapter to apply.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The vehicle shall be equipped with the manufacturer's owner's/operator's manual at the time the vehicle is undergoing a State inspection. The vehicle owner or agent may be required to present to the inspection station any manufacturer's testing procedures or specifications required for inspection.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>It is recommended that the vehicle owner or agent, before presenting the vehicle for inspection, charge the battery systems as prescribed by the vehicle manufacturer to ensure the vehicle operates at peak efficiency to prevent unnecessary rejection of components due to a weak or low battery.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Incorporation by Reference.</heading>
    <text>In this chapter, Surface Vehicle Standards for Low Speed Vehicles, SAE J2358 (Society of Automotive Engineers, Inc., March 2002) is incorporated by reference.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Performance.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Due to the vehicle's required speed limitations and the restricted highways where operation is permitted, a road test is not required. The vehicle, however, must be capable of moving under its own power in and out of the inspection area. The vehicle will be required to function as designed in all operational settings. Observe for any adverse steering, handling, or braking reactions.</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Inflate tires to recommended pressures. While maneuvering the vehicle on the parking lot of the inspection facility and in and out of inspection area, observe for any adverse steering, handling, or braking reactions.</td>
              <td>(1) Any adverse steering, handling, or braking reactions are noted.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(2) Inspect the vehicle's ability to function as designed in all operational settings, for example, forward, neutral, reverse, road and turf/high and low, etc.</td>
              <td>(2) The vehicle fails to function as designed in any operational setting.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|14|09|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Steering, Alignment, and Suspension.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Steering. Inspect the entire steering system including steering wheel, steering column, lash, linkage, free play, and power steering, if so equipped, for missing, loose, damaged, or worn parts.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Steering Wheel. The steering wheel shall be inspected to determine if it is circular (complete rim) and free of cracks, breaks, or objects that will interfere with the safe steering of the vehicle. The inspection must determine that the steering wheel is original equipment or equivalent, including diameter.</text>
        <text>
          <table class="layout-table">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th>Procedures:</th>
                <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td>(a) Inspect for missing, broken, or altered rim.<br/>(b) Inspect for cracks or breaks that would interfere with safe steering.<br/>(c) Inspect for objects that would interfere with safe steering.<br/>(d) Inspect for hand controls of vehicles equipped for physically disabled persons.<br/>(e) Inspect steering wheel for size and equivalency to original equipment.</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(a) Steering wheel rim is broken, cut, severely bent, or altered to the point it is not continuous.<br/>(b) There are cracks or breaks large enough to grasp clothing, jewelry, hand, or fingers. <br/>(c) There are cracks, breaks, or objects attached that would interfere with safe steering. If vehicle is equipped with hand controls for physically disabled, special equipment is acceptable if it is part of the manual controls, including steering knobs.<br/>(d) Any controls are not readily accessible (within arm's length) or are binding, damaged, or jammed.<br/>(e) Steering wheel is not original or equivalent including size.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="2" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Agency Note: After market steering wheel covers must be removed for inspection.</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Steering Column. Inspection of steering column shall be made to determine if there are any missing, broken, or worn parts and if the column is securely attached to vehicle. If equipped with an energy absorbing steering column, inspect to determine if steering column is capable of functioning as designed and shows no indication of having been collapsed.</text>
        <text>
          <table class="layout-table">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th>Procedures:</th>
                <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(a) Inside Passenger Compartment.</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(a) Inside Passenger Compartment.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle" class="text-indent-1">(i) Inspect steering column for missing, worn, or damaged parts. Inspect for looseness or play in steering wheel and column.<br/>(ii) Inspect attachment of steering column to dash for evidence of looseness, damage, or worn parts. <br/>(iii) If equipped with energy absorbing steering column, inspect for separation or looseness of shear capsule from bracket. Inspect for general looseness of wheel and column. <br/>(iv) Inspect for objects mounted on energy absorbing steering column that would prevent it from collapsing upon impact.</td>
                <td class="text-indent-1">(i) Steering column contains any missing, worn, or damaged parts, or looseness, or play is noted in steering wheel and column.<br/>(ii) Attachment of steering column to dash reveals loose, damaged, or worn parts.<br/>(iii) Shear capsule is separated from bracket, or if wheel and column can be moved as a unit.<br/>(iv) Objects are mounted on energy absorbing steering column.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(b) Under Hood.</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(b) Under Hood.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle" class="text-indent-1">(i) Inspect steering column for missing, damaged, or worn parts.<br/>(ii) Inspect for worn, loose, or damaged U joints or similar connecting joints.<br/>(iii) If equipped with an energy absorbing steering column, inspect for condition of shear pins or similar type collapsible portion.</td>
                <td class="text-indent-1">(i) Column contains missing, damaged, or worn parts. <br/>(ii) U joints or similar connecting joints are worn, loose, or damaged.<br/>(iii) Column shows indication of having been collapsed.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Lash.</text>
        <text>
          <table class="layout-table">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th>Procedures:</th>
                <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td>(a) With front wheels in straight ahead position, turn steering wheel until the turning motion can be observed at the road wheels. Measure lash. If vehicle is equipped with power steering, inspect with the system functioning as designed.</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(a) A total movement in excess of that shown in the following table is measured at the steering wheel rim before the front wheels move:<br/>    Steering System                             Lash <br/>Rack and pinion steering           0.4 inches (10 mm) <br/>All other steering                        2 inches</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Travel.</text>
        <text>
          <table class="layout-table">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th>Procedures:</th>
                <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(a) Turn steering wheel through a full right and left turn and feel for binding or jamming conditions. If vehicle is equipped with power steering, inspect with the system functioning as designed.</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(a) Any roughness, jamming, binding, or any excessive play in the steering linkage is present when turning the wheels from full right to full left.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Linkage.</text>
      </para>
      <aftertext>Linkage Play. Excessive free play causes wheel shimmy, erratic brake action, and steering control problems. Make sure any looseness detected is not wheel bearing free play.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>Spring or Torsion Bar Height. Optimum spring height is established as part of the overall design of wheel alignment angles. Rack and Pinion Assembly, or Steering Box. Lack of proper lubrication caused by leakage will lead to excessive wear and free play in these components.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle" class="text-indent-1">(a) Steering Linkage Play. With the vehicle raised on approved lift and the wheels in a straight-ahead position, grasp front and rear of each tire and attempt to rock wheel and tire assembly right and left. Inspect for any looseness or adverse movement at any steering linkage joint.</td>
              <td class="text-indent-1">(a) Any looseness or adverse movement is detected in any steering linkage balls and sockets noted while rocking wheel and tire assembly right and left by hand.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle" class="text-indent-1">(b) Grasp each steering linkage joint by hand and check for looseness or adverse movement.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle" class="text-indent-1">(b) Any looseness or adverse movement is detected in any steering linkage balls and sockets tested by hand.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td class="text-indent-1">(c) Visually inspect steering linkage for any missing, worn, loose, damaged, or misaligned parts.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle" class="text-indent-1">(c)<br/>  (i) Tie rod, tie rod ends, center or drag link, pitman or idler arm, if so equipped, are missing, worn, loose, damaged, or misaligned.<br/>  (ii) Joints are not secured with cotter pins or other locking devices.<br/>  (iii) Any dust or grease retainer boot is missing or damaged to permit loss of grease or contamination of joint.<br/>  (iv) Steering stops allow tire to rub frame, metal, or other chassis parts.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle" class="text-indent-1">(d) Visually inspect the rack and pinion assembly or, if so equipped, steering box for loose or worn mounting bolts or bushings, leakage, and general condition.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle" class="text-indent-1">(d) The rack and pinion assembly or, if so equipped, steering box contains loose or worn mounting bolts or bushings, structural damage affecting operation, or is damaged, or deteriorated to cause leakage.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </aftertext>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Power Steering (If so equipped).</text>
        <text>
          <table class="layout-table">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th>Procedures:</th>
                <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(a) Inspect power steering system for its ability to function as designed by vehicle manufacturer, and for general condition. Perform testing/inspection procedures necessary to determine if power steering system is in proper condition and functioning as designed. Consult vehicle manufacturer if necessary.</td>
                <td>(a) Power steering system fails to function as designed by vehicle manufacturer or contains loose, damaged, or worn parts, low fluid, or leakage.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Wheel Alignment.</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Observe whether rear wheels follow front wheels in "straight ahead" travel.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Rear wheel does not follow the front wheel track in "straight ahead" travel, or if frame is bent, broken, or rusted to affect tracking. Warning: Do not reject if vehicle is designed with different tread widths—front and rear.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(2) Wheelbase Measurement. Using a tape measure, determine the distance between the center of the front wheel spindle or hub, and the center of the rear axle or hub, and compare from side to side. Front wheels shall be in the straight-ahead position.</td>
              <td>(2) The wheelbase on one side is different from the wheelbase on the other side by more than 1 inch.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(3) Visually inspect for obvious misalignment of front or rear axle.</td>
              <td>(3) Front or rear axle is obviously misaligned.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td colspan="2" data-vertical-align="middle">
                <em>Agency Note: Not applicable if vehicle specifications indicate different left and right wheel base dimensions.</em>
              </td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Suspension. Inspect the suspension system for missing, broken, damaged, worn, rusted, or modified wheel bearings, ball joints, control arms, springs, torsion bars, or frame that would affect vehicle stability.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Frame/Unibody.</text>
        <text>
          <table class="layout-table">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th>Procedures:</th>
                <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td>(a) With the vehicle properly lifted, inspect condition of frame and unibody construction and suspension mountings. If necessary, frame or unibody construction and suspension mountings may be probed to determine structural integrity. The use of a 1/4-inch flat screwdriver under hand pressure is recommended.</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(a)<br/>  (i) Frame or unibody or suspension mounting is cracked, broken, or otherwise not structurally sound. <br/>  (ii) Frame or unibody or suspension mounting is damaged, or deteriorated to the extent that it affects steering, suspension, braking, alignment, body mounts, or any other component. <br/>  (iii) The body is not securely attached to the frame. <br/>  (iv) Repairs, when permitted, are not made with the same type of material that was originally used by the manufacturer, or any weld does not appear to be of sufficient strength or quality. <br/>  (v) Modifications have been made which weaken frame or unibody or other suspension components, or otherwise affects vehicle stability or operation.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(b) Inspect condition of control arms, locator bars, radius and strut rods, trailing arms, sway bars, stabilizer bars, or similar components, and all related bushings.</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(b) Any control arm, locator bar, radius or strut rod, trailing arm, sway bar, stabilizer bar, or similar component is cracked, broken, or missing any related parts, or is otherwise damaged to affect safe operation of vehicle. Any related bushing is missing any portion of bushing, or bushing is deteriorated or dry rotted to a point that the bushing is broken or loose.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(c) With the vehicle on the ground, inspect for any object or equipment extending below the bottom edge of a wheel rim.</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(c) Any object or equipment extends below the bottom edge of a wheel rim.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="2" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Agency Note: If repairs are required the vehicle owner or agent shall be advised not to apply undercoating to the repaired area prior to re-inspection. If undercoating exists in areas of required inspection, removal of undercoating may be required to permit a proper inspection.</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Ball Joints. In checking for motion of ball joints, check in accordance with manufacturer's procedures and specifications. When required for testing, a 12-inch to 18-inch pry bar shall be utilized which is sufficient to lift the weight of the wheel assembly and prevent excessive pressure or leverage resulting in a possible false reading.</text>
        <text>
          <table class="layout-table">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th>Procedures:</th>
                <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(a) Ball Joint Wear. <br/>    (i) Check in accordance with manufacturer's procedures and specifications when available. See exception noted in <cite path="11|14|09|.04|C.|(2)|(b)">§C(2)(b) of this regulation</cite>, below. <br/>    (ii) If manufacturer's ball joint specifications are not available, inspect ball joints for any perceptible movement in both axial up and down, and radial in and out direction.<br/>    (iii) Lift vehicle in a manner that would unload the ball joints. Consult vehicle manufacturer if necessary: <br/>    (iv) Radial Play—Grasp tire at top and bottom and rock in and out. Inspect for any perceptible movement in ball joints;<br/>    (v) Axial Play—Using a 12-inch to 18-inch pry bar, raise and lower under center of tire. Inspect for any perceptible movement in ball joints.</td>
                <td>(a) Ball Joint Wear. <br/>     (i) Manufacturer's specifications are exceeded. <br/>     (ii) Absent manufacturer's specifications, any perceptible movement is noted in any ball joint. <br/>  (b) Any perceptible movement is noted in any ball joint having turning torque specifications by manufacturer. <br/>  (c) Ball joint contains any missing, broken, or damaged components. Ball joint is equipped with a tightener or repair kit, or ball joint has been repaired by heating or bending the socket assembly to eliminate movement. <br/>  (d) Ball joint boot is missing, cut, torn, or otherwise damaged, if originally equipped with boot.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(b) Exception—Ball Joints Having Turning Torque Specifications. <br/>     (i) Ball joints having turning torque procedures and specifications will not be disassembled as prescribed by the vehicle manufacturer, but instead will be inspected with the ball joints fully assembled for any perceptible movement. <br/>     (ii) Inspect ball joints for any perceptible movement in both axial (up and down), and radial (in and out) direction. Lift vehicle in a manner that would unload the ball joints. Consult vehicle manufacturer if necessary. <br/>     (iii) Radial Play—Grasp tire at top and bottom and rock in and out. Inspect for any perceptible movement in ball joints. <br/>     (iv) Axial Play—Using a 12-inch to 18-inch pry bar, raise and lower under center of tire. Inspect for any perceptible movement in ball joints.</td>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(c) Visually inspect ball joints for any missing, broken, or damaged components.</td>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(d) Inspect condition of ball joint boot.</td>
                <td/>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Wheel Bearings. Wheel bearings worn or out of adjustment can cause wander, unequal brake action, and noise due to interference of parts.</text>
        <text>
          <table class="layout-table">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th>Procedures:</th>
                <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(a) Wheel Bearings and Suspension. With the vehicle lifted properly, grasp tire at the top and bottom and rock it in and out, and observe for movement. To verify any looseness detected is in the wheel bearing, notice movement between the brake disc or drum, and the splash shield or backing plate.</td>
                <td>(a) Wheel bearings are loose, rough, galled, or otherwise defective.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Springs and Torsion Bars. Loose, sagging, or broken springs or torsion bars, worn or deteriorated bushings, loose or extended shackles, and loose or mislocated U-bolts, suspension modifications, or broken center bolts, can cause vehicle handling instability and brake pull.</text>
        <text>
          <table class="layout-table">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th>Procedures:</th>
                <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td>(a) Springs and Torsion Bars. With unloaded vehicle on level surface, visually inspect for obvious height differences of the four corners of the vehicle. If necessary, use measuring tape and determine differences from side to side. With the vehicle properly lifted, check for loose, worn, or broken coil springs, leaf springs, or torsion bars, if so equipped. Inspect all shackles, bushings and U-bolts.</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(a)<br/>    (i) Any coil spring, leaf spring, or torsion bar is missing, cracked, cut, sagging, broken, or loose. <br/>    (ii) Any spring or torsion bar is not seated properly in mounting. <br/>    (iii) Any leaf spring center bolt is broken, or spring alignment clamps are missing. <br/>    (iv) Shackles or U-bolts are worn, loose, or extended causing misalignment of steering linkage or driveline angles. U-bolts are not of sufficient length to protrude at least 1/4 inch beyond nut when tightened. <br/>    (v) Any bushing is missing any portion of the bushing or is damaged, deteriorated, or dry rotted to a point that the bushing is broken or loose. Superficial cracks are not cause for rejection.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(b) Inspect for modifications to springs or torsion bars.</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(b) Any spring or torsion bar is not the original or equivalent or has been modified.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Shock Absorbers and Struts.</text>
        <text>
          <table class="layout-table">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th>Procedures:</th>
                <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(a) With vehicle on a level surface, push down on each corner of the vehicle and release. Vehicles not equipped with bumpers or fenders of sufficient strength to permit required jounce testing will be evaluated during the performance test for evidence of excessive free rocking motion or vehicle instability.</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(a) <br/>    (i) Vehicle continues free rocking motion for two or more cycles after release. <br/>    (ii) Shock absorbers or struts are worn, damaged, or leaking to the extent vehicle stability is affected.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(b) With vehicle on an approved lift, inspect shock absorbers and struts for missing, broken, worn, loose, or damaged mounting brackets, bolts, bushings, and bearings. Inspect for leakage.</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(b)<br/>   (i) Shock absorbers or struts, mounting bolts, bushings, bearings, or mounts are missing, broken, worn or loose. <br/>   (ii) Any bushing is missing any portion of the bushing or is damaged, deteriorated, or dry rotted to a point that the bushing is broken or loose. Superficial cracks are not cause for rejection. <br/>   (iii) Excessive leakage not slight dampness is present.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(c) Inspect for modifications to shock absorbers and strut assemblies.</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(c) Any shock absorber or strut assembly is not the original or equivalent or has been modified.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Brakes.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Hydraulic System.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Tests and Visual Inspection Procedures. Results will indicate whether or not a vehicle has reasonably safe brakes at the time of inspection. These procedures are applicable to vehicles equipped with hand controls for the physically handicapped. If equipped with power assisted hydraulic brakes, system shall be functioning as designed.</text>
        <text>
          <table class="layout-table">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th>Procedures:</th>
                <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(a) Hydraulic System Leakage Test. While the vehicle is stopped, depress brake pedal under moderate foot force. The pedal height shall remain constant for 1 minute.</td>
                <td>(a) Brake pedal height cannot be maintained for 1 minute.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(b) Pedal Reserve Test. While the vehicle is stopped, depress brake pedal under moderate foot force.</td>
                <td>(b) Less than 1/3 of the total available pedal travel remains.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All four wheels shall be removed for brake inspection. Do not remove wheel cylinder dust boots for inspection. Leakage can be determined by pushing on the outside of the boot.</text>
        <text>
          <table class="layout-table">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th>Procedures:</th>
                <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td>(a) Hydraulic System. Visually inspect condition of hydraulic system.<br/>    (i) Inspect wheel cylinders and calipers for leakage and operation. Do not pry or remove dust boot.<br/>    (ii) Inspect hydraulic hoses for leaks, cracks, knots, bubbles, chafing, flattened or restricted sections, improper support, and improper material. Proper inspection of rubber brake hoses would be to gently flex the hose to determine if there are cracks.<br/>    (iii) Inspect brake lines for leaks, flattened or restricted sections, improper support, rusting causing pitting, and improper material and connections. Any repairs must meet or exceed manufacturer's standards.<br/>    (iv) Inspect master cylinder for leakage and fluid level of all sections of reservoir. Be sure no dirt gets into reservoir when cover is removed and the gasket is serviceable.</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(a)<br/>    (i) Wheel cylinder or caliper leaks or fails to operate.<br/>    (ii) Hoses are leaking, chafed, flattened, restricted, contain knots or bubbles, or are improperly supported. Cracked brake hoses if the second layer, that is the cord layer, is cut or exposed.<br/>    (iii) Brake lines are leaking, flattened, restricted, or rusted and pitting is visible, improperly supported, or lines have been repaired or replaced with copper tubing or other material not designed for hydraulic brake lines.<br/>    (iv) There are improper connections, for example, compression fittings in the brake lines. Hoses or brake lines are mounted to allow contact with wheel, tire, or body during steering or suspension movement.<br/>    (v) Master cylinder leaks.<br/>    (vi) Fluid level in any section of master cylinder reservoir is below the manufacturer's minimum specification, or is less than 1/2 full when no minimum is specified.<br/>    (vii) The gasket does not properly seal master cylinder.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(b) Dual Hydraulic Circuits—In addition to the above, if vehicle is equipped with a brake warning light:<br/>    (i) Follow the manufacturer's testing procedure for operation of light; and<br/>    (ii) With power key switch on, apply moderate foot force to brake pedal and observe light.</td>
                <td>(b)<br/>    (i) Brake warning light fails to function as designed by vehicle manufacturer, or lights indicating a malfunction.<br/>    (ii) Light comes on when brake pedal is depressed.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Drums and Discs.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All four wheels shall be removed for brake inspection. On vehicles equipped with disc brakes some drag can be felt when turning the wheel and tire. This drag is not excessive if the wheel can be turned readily with one hand.</text>
        <text>
          <table class="layout-table">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th>Procedures:</th>
                <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td>(a) Brake Drums.<br/>    (i) Inspect the condition of the drum friction surface for substantial cracks extending to the open edge of the drum. Short hairline heat cracks should not be considered.<br/>    (ii) Inspect for cracks on the outside of the drum.<br/>    (iii) Inspect for mechanical damage.<br/>    (iv) Inspect for contaminated friction surface.<br/>    (v) Measure inside diameter of drum.</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(a) Brake Drums.<br/>    (i) There is a substantial crack on the friction surface extending to the open edge.<br/>    (ii) There is an external crack.<br/>    (iii) There is evidence of excessive mechanical damage other than wear. <br/>    (iv) Friction surface is contaminated with oil, grease, or brake fluid. <br/>    (v) Inside drum diameter is greater than the maximum diameter stamped on the drum. If the drum is not stamped, refer to the Agency Note below.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>(b) Brake Discs.<br/>    (i) Inspect for substantial cracks extending to edge of disc. Short hairline heat cracks should not be considered.<br/>    (ii) Inspect for mechanical damage. <br/>    (iii) Inspect for contaminated friction surface.<br/>    (iv) Measure thickness of disc.</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(b) Brake Discs. <br/>    (i) There are substantial cracks extending to edge. <br/>    (ii) There is evidence of excessive mechanical damage other than wear.<br/>    (iii) Friction surface is contaminated with oil, grease, or brake fluid.<br/>    (iv) Thickness of disc is less than manufacturer's minimum thickness stamped on the assembly. If the disc is not stamped, refer to the Agency Note below.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="2" data-vertical-align="middle">
                  <em>Agency Note: Brake discard specifications for brake drums and brake discs may not be provided by all manufacturers of low speed vehicles. If brake drums are not stamped with a maximum diameter specification, or brake discs are not stamped with a minimum thickness specification visible without disassembly of the rotor, the determination of passing or failing the brake drum or brake disc based upon measurements obtained in comparison to brake discard specifications will therefore be waived. The recording of maximum specifications of brake drums or minimum specifications of brake discs, will also not be required as stated in <cite path="11.14.01.11|B.|(7)">COMAR 11.14.01.11B(7)</cite> on the vehicle inspection report. All brake drums and brake discs will be inspected as otherwise required and measurements recorded on the vehicle inspection report along with corresponding brake lining and pad thickness readings.</em>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Linings and Pads. Remove all wheels and drum assemblies for inspection of linings on drum brakes. On vehicles equipped with disc brakes, only removal of the wheels is necessary.</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Condition of Linings and Pads.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Condition of Linings and Pads.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle" class="text-indent-1">(a) Bonded Linings. Measure the lining thickness at the thinnest point.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle" class="text-indent-1">(a) Bonded Linings. Thinnest point of lining is less than 2/32 inch.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td class="text-indent-1">(b) Riveted Linings. Inspect for loose or missing rivets. Measure lining thickness above rivet head at thinnest point.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle" class="text-indent-1">(b) Riveted Linings.<br/>    (i) Any rivets are loose or missing.<br/>    (ii) Lining is worn to where less than 2/32 inch remains above any rivet head.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td class="text-indent-1">(c)  All Linings.<br/>    (i) Inspect for broken or cracked linings, and parts of linings not firmly attached to shoe or pad backing.<br/>    (ii) Inspect for contamination and excessively uneven lining wear.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle" class="text-indent-1">(c)  All Linings.<br/>    (i) Lining is broken, cracked, or not firmly and completely attached to shoe or pad backing. <br/>    (ii) Friction surface is contaminated with oil, grease, or brake fluid.<br/>    (iii) Lining wear is extremely uneven.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle" class="text-indent-1">(d) Pads (Disc Brakes). Inspect thickness of friction pads. If the pad thickness cannot be determined with pad thickness gauge, caliper shall be removed for measurement.<br/>    (i)  Bonded pads—measure thinnest point of lining.<br/>    (ii)  Riveted pads—measure thickness of lining above rivet head at thinnest point.</td>
              <td class="text-indent-1">(d) Lining on any bonded pad is less than 2/32 inch, or less than 2/32 inch lining remains above rivet head.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Mechanical Linkage. Mechanical linkage includes the service brake mechanism, parking brake, and manual controls on vehicles equipped for physically handicapped persons.</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Condition of Mechanical Components.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Condition of Mechanical Components.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle" class="text-indent-1">(a) Inspect for worn pins and missing or defective cotter pins.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle" class="text-indent-1">(a) Mechanical parts are missing, broken, or badly worn.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle" class="text-indent-1">(b) Inspect for broken, missing, or worn springs, cables, clevises, couplings, rods, and anchor pins.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle" class="text-indent-1">(b) Grease retainers or axle seals are leaking. Slight dampness is not cause for rejection.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle" class="text-indent-1">(c) Inspect for frozen, rusted, or inoperative connections, missing spring clips, and defective grease retainers or axle seals.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle" class="text-indent-1">(c) There is excessive friction in pedal and linkage, or in brake components.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle" class="text-indent-1">(d) Inspect pedal shaft and bearings for high friction, wear, and misalignment.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle" class="text-indent-1">(d) Pedal levers are improperly positioned or misaligned.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle" class="text-indent-1">(e) Inspect for restricted shoe movement at backing plate, and for binding between brake shoes and anchor pins.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle" class="text-indent-1">(e) Rubber service brake pedal pad is excessively worn to expose metal pedal or rubber pad is missing.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle" class="text-indent-1">(f) Foot operated controls shall have a slip resistant surface. Inspect service brake pedal rubber pad for excessive wear or missing pad.</td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Power Assisted Brake Systems (If so equipped).</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Inspect power assisted brake system for its ability to function as designed and for general condition. Perform testing/inspection procedures necessary to determine power assisted brake system is in proper condition and functioning as designed. Consult vehicle manufacturer if necessary.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Power assist brake system fails to function as designed by vehicle manufacturer or contains any loose, leaking, low fluid, damaged, or worn parts.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Parking Brake.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Parking Brake Function. A positive locking brake shall be provided. It shall be either a hand or foot operated type mechanism as described in SAE J2358, which is incorporated by reference in <cite path="|11|14|09|.02">Regulation .02 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Any parking brake shall hold a stopped vehicle firmly on all normal road grades.</text>
        <text>
          <table class="layout-table">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th>Procedures:</th>
                <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(a) Parking Brake Function.<br/>    (i) Set the parking brake firmly and check the ability of parking brake to hold the vehicle.<br/>    (ii) Vehicle shall have a mechanical parking brake, which will hold the vehicle to the limit of traction in either direction on any grade. <br/>    (iii) Due to the inability to road test vehicle and if no grade is present at inspection facility, set parking brake and attempt to push vehicle forward and backward by hand.<br/>    (iv) Inspect for operation of manufacturer's warning devices designed to remind operator to set parking brake, if so equipped.</td>
                <td>(a) Parking Brake Function. <br/>    (i) Parking brake fails to hold the vehicle on any grade on which it is operated, or absent a grade, the vehicle is capable of being moved by hand.<br/>    (ii) Manufacturer's warning device reminding operator to set parking brake fails to function as designed, when equipped.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(b) Linings and Drums. <br/>    (i) If the vehicle is equipped with parking brakes, which are separate from the service brakes, inspect the linings and drums in the same manner that those on the service brakes are inspected.</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(b) Linings and Drums. <br/>    (i) Parking brake drums are cracked, broken, or otherwise damaged.<br/>    (ii) Linings are loose, worn out, or contaminated with grease, oil, or brake fluid.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Definitions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Brake system" means a combination of one or more brakes and their related means of operation and control and is equipped with brakes acting on all wheels.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Emergency brake system" means a brake system used for retarding and stopping the vehicle in the event of a malfunction in the service brake system. This function may be performed by the parking brake system or by a portion of the service brake system, or by a separate brake system.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Parking brake system" means a brake system used to hold and maintain a vehicle in a stationary position with a positive mechanical means employed to hold the brake applied when the vehicle is unattended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Pedal reserve", as applied to hydraulic, mechanical, or power-assisted hydraulic brakes, means the amount of total pedal travel left in reserve when the pedal is depressed to the brake-applied position. The pedal reserve check is to ascertain the degree of the brake adjustment and to demonstrate satisfactory brake actuating system condition.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Service brake system" means a brake system used for retarding, stopping, and controlling the vehicle under normal operating conditions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Stopping distance" means the distance traveled by a vehicle from the point of application of force to the brake control, to the point at which the vehicle reaches a full stop.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Wheels and Tires.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This inspection requires the vehicle to be raised on an approved lift.</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Inspect for tire wear.<br/>  (a) Tires with tread wear indicators will be inspected using the tire's tread wear indicators.<br/>  (b) Tires not equipped with tread wear indicators will be measured using an approved tire tread depth gauge at the thinnest point in any major tread groove.<br/>  (c) Inspect for cord or belting exposure.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Inspect for tire wear.<br/>  (a) Tire is worn so that the tread wear indicators are flush with the tread at any place on the tire. <br/>  (b) Tire is worn so that less than 2/32 inch tread remains when measured in any major tread groove. <br/>  (c) Tire has a worn spot that exposes the cord or belting material through the tread.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Inspect for tread cuts, snags, or sidewall cracks.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(2) Tire has tread cuts, snags, or sidewall cracks in any direction and deep enough to expose cord or belting material.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(3) Inspect for bumps, bulges, or knots.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(3) Tire has visible bumps, bulges, or knots indicating partial failure or separation of the tire structure.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(4) Inspect for fabric breaks, and exposed or damaged body cords.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(4) Tire has unrepaired fabric break, or sidewall has damaged body cords.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(5) Inspect for regrooved or recut tires.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(5) Tire has been regrooved or recut below original groove depth, except as authorized by Transportation Article, 22-405.1, Annotated Code of Maryland, and can be readily identified as regroovable.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(6) Visually inspect for mismatching of tires.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(6)<br/>  (a) Tires are not the same type of construction or size on the same axle of the vehicle. (Difference in brand or tread design is not cause for rejection.) Tire construction types are mismatched.<br/>  (b) If vehicle is equipped with radial-type tires, all four shall be radials.<br/>  (c) If vehicle is equipped with conventional-type tires, bias ply, or bias belted, all four shall be conventional, bias ply, or bias belted.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(7) Visually inspect tire placard, federal motor vehicle safety certification label, or vehicle owner's/operator's manual for information regarding tire size, inflation pressure, and any required speed rating and load carrying capacity. Inspect tires.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(7) Tire size, speed rating, or load carrying capacity is not the same as originally installed by the vehicle manufacturer, a vehicle manufacturer's upgrade, or an acceptable substitute by tire industry standards. Tires may not be of a size which cause tire and vehicle contact during different vehicle attitudes.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(8) Visually inspect tires for the symbol "DOT" (Department of Transportation). Visually inspect for restricted usage marking on tires.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(8) Tire is:<br/>  (a) Not labeled with the symbol "DOT" (Department of Transportation); <br/>  (b) Marked "For farm use only";<br/>  (c) Marked "Off highway use only";<br/>  (d) Marked "For racing use only";<br/>  (e) A metal studded snow tire in Allegany, Carroll, Frederick, Garrett, and Washington counties during period when prohibited, April 1 thru October 31; reject in other areas at any time.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(9) Inspect wheel bolts, studs, nuts, and lugs.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(9) Wheel bolts, studs, nuts, or lugs are loose, missing, damaged, or of improper design to properly secure the type of wheel.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(10) Inspect valve stems for leaks, damage, or cracks.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(10) Valve stem is leaking, cracked, or damaged, or shows evidence of wear.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(11) Inspect wheels.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(11) Any wheel is not the original or equivalent, or a manufacturer's upgrade when applicable. Any part of the wheel is visibly cracked, rewelded, or has elongated bolt holes. Any part of the wheel is bent or otherwise damaged to affect safe operation of the vehicle.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Bumpers (If so equipped).</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Bumpers are not required on low speed vehicles. However, if so equipped, they shall be inspected for broken or missing parts, sharp edges, or other conditions that could be hazardous to individuals. The bumpers shall be securely mounted to the vehicle.</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Bumpers. Inspect bumpers for condition and mounting.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Bumpers or protective coverings contain sharp edges, or conditions are present that could be hazardous to individuals.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td/>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(2) Bumpers are broken, have missing parts, or are not securely mounted.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Fenders and Flaps.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A low speed vehicle shall be equipped with fender coverage of front and rear wheels. Inspection shall include condition, mounting, and coverage of wheels and tires.</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Fenders shall be securely attached to the vehicle and inspected for tears, sharp or jagged edges that extend outward from the fender, and sufficient coverage of the wheel and tire both from the body outward and to the front and rear of tires and wheels. Fenders may be extended outward to compensate for tire or wheel changes provided the extensions: <br/>  (a) Provide required coverage of wheels and tires; <br/>  (b) Are constructed of substantial materials; <br/>  (c) Are securely attached to the body;<br/>  (d) Have all edges rolled to eliminate sharp or jagged edges; and <br/>  (e) Do not contact tires during different vehicle attitudes.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1)<br/>  (a) Fenders have tears, sharp, or jagged edges that extend outward from the fender that present a hazard to a pedestrian.<br/>  (b) Fenders are not securely fastened to the body. <br/>  (c) Fender does not extend outward from the body to cover the top of the wheel and tire excluding the sidewall.<br/>  (d) The rear of all fenders do not extend downward to the horizontal centerline of the wheel, or as designed by the vehicle manufacturer.<br/>  (e) Fronts of all fenders do not extend forward from the vertical centerline of the wheel to at least within a 45-degree angle of the horizontal centerline, or as designed by the vehicle manufacturer.<br/>  (f) Fenders are missing.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(2) If the bed of a low speed vehicle has been changed and a rear fender is impractical, the vehicle shall be equipped with flaps behind the rear wheels and tires of the vehicle, and extend at least to the horizontal centerline of the wheels.</td>
              <td>(2) Flaps do not cover the width of the wheels and tires or do not extend at least to the horizontal centerline of the wheels.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Lighting.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definitions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Asymmetrical beam (nonsymmetrical)" means a beam in which both sides are not symmetrical with respect to the median vertical plane of the beam. All lower beams are asymmetrical.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Auxiliary driving lamp, auxiliary upper beam lamp, or auxiliary high beam lamp" means a lighting device mounted to provide illumination forward of the vehicle and intended to supplement the upper beam of a standard headlamp system. It is not intended for use alone or with the lower beam of a standard headlamp system.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Backup lamp" means a lamp used to provide illumination behind the vehicle, and to provide an indicator when the vehicle is in reverse gear.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Charge indicator" means a light, gauge, or other source indicating battery charge remaining.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Cornering lamp" means a steadily burning lamp used when the turn signal system is operating to supplement the headlamps by providing additional road illumination in the direction of the turn.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Emergency warning lamp" means a lamp that provides a flashing light to identify an authorized vehicle on an emergency mission. The emergency signal may be an oscillating lamp, a rotating beacon, or pairs of alternately or simultaneously flashing lamps.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Fog lamp" means a lamp that may be used with the lower beam headlights to provide illumination under condition of rain, snow, dust, or fog.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Hazard warning lamp" means a turn signal lamp that flashes simultaneously to warn of the presence of a vehicular hazard.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Headlamps.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>5 3/4 Inch Round Sealed Beam Unit.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>"Type 1 sealed beam" means a sealed beam unit 5 3/4 inches in diameter having a single filament and providing only an upper beam distribution of light. This unit is identified by the number 1 on the lens and is aimed on the upper beam.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>"Type 2 sealed beam unit" means a sealed beam unit 5 3/4 inches in diameter having two filaments, one filament providing the lower beam and one filament providing fill-in light for the upper beam. This unit is identified by the number 2 on the lens and is aimed on the lower beam.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"7 inch round sealed beam unit" means a sealed beam unit 7 inches in diameter providing an upper and lower beam. This unit is identified by the number 2 on the lens and is aimed on the lower beam. If there is no identifying number on the lens, it means the sealed beam unit is 7 inches in diameter providing upper and lower beams.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>"8 inch by 5 inch rectangular sealed beam unit" means a sealed beam unit providing an upper and lower beam. This unit is identified by the number 2B on the lens and is aimed on the lower beam.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>6 1/2 by 4 1/4 Inch Rectangular Sealed Beam Unit.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>"Type 1A" means a sealed beam unit having a single filament and providing only an upper beam distribution of light. The unit is identified by the number 1A on the lens and is aimed on the upper beam.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>"Type 2A" means a sealed beam unit having two filaments, one of which provides fill-in light for the upper beam. This unit is identified by the number 2A on the lens and is aimed on the lower beam.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>5.93 X 3.64 inch Rectangular Sealed Beam Units.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>"Type LF" means a sealed beam unit having a single beam filament and providing only a lower beam distribution of light. The unit is identified by the designation LF on the lens.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>"Type UF" means a sealed beam unit having a single beam filament and providing only an upper beam distribution of light. The unit is identified by the designation UF on the lens.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>"Replaceable bulb headlamp" means a headlamp unit comprised of one or two replaceable standard light sources such as a bulb and a headlamp housing or a lens/reflector unit.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Headlamp lower beam" means a distribution of light as directed to avoid glare in the eyes of oncoming drivers while providing illumination ahead of the vehicle, and intended for use in congested areas and on highways when meeting other vehicles within a distance of 500 feet.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Headlamp upper beam" means a distribution of light intended primarily for distant illumination and for use on the open highway when not meeting other vehicles.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>"Indicator lamp" means a lamp visible to the operator of a vehicle that indicates:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Appropriate electrical circuits are in operation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Malfunction of vehicle performance; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Requirement for remedial action by the operator of the vehicle.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>"Lamp" means a device used to produce artificial light.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>"Lane changer" means a device, usually incorporated in the turn signal switch, which will actuate the turn signal lamps when held by the driver. It is intended for momentary use for signaling a lane change. When released by the operator, it will return to neutral and deactivate the signal lamp.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>"License-plate lamp" means a lamp used to illuminate the license plate on the rear of a vehicle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>"Operating units or switches" means devices by which the functioning of lamps is controlled.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>"Parking lamp" means lamps used to designate the front of a parked vehicle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>"Reflective device" means a device used on vehicles to give an indication to an approaching driver by reflected light from the headlamps of approaching vehicles.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>"SAE Lighting Identification Code" means a series of standardized markings for lighting devices that a manufacturer or a supplier may use to mark a product to indicate the SAE lighting standard or standards to which the device is designed to conform. The code is not intended to limit the manufacturer or supplier in applying other markings to the devices.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>"Sealed beam headlamp assembly" means a major lighting device used to provide general illumination ahead of the vehicle. It consists of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>One or more sealed beam units (bulb assembly);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Means for mounting securely to the vehicle; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Means to permit required aim adjustment.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>"Sealed beam unit" means an integral and hermetically sealed optical assembly with the name "Sealed Beam" molded in the lens.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>"Side marker lamp" means a lamp on the left and right sides, beamed to the side and intended to indicate vehicle length. They are located near the front and rear on each side and, for vehicles 30 feet or more in overall length, are also located at the midpoint (intermediate side marker).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>"Stop lamp" means a lamp giving a steady warning light to the rear of the vehicle, to indicate the intention of the operator of the vehicle to reduce speed or stop.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(24)</num>
        <text>"Symmetrical beam" means one in which both sides are symmetrical with respect to the median vertical plane of the beam. Lamps having symmetrical beams are:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>5 3/4 inch diameter type 1, 1C, or 1C1;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>5 3/4 inch diameter type 2, 2C, or 2C1 (upper beam filament);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>6 1/2 by 4 1/4 inch type 1A or 1A1;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>6 1/2 by 4 1/4 inch type 2A, 2A1, 2G1, 2E1, or 2H1 (upper beam filament);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>8 by 5 inch type 2B or 2B1 (upper beam filament);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>All 7 inch diameter units (upper beam filament); and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Replaceable bulb headlamp (upper beam filament).</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(25)</num>
        <text>"Tail lamp" means a lamp used to designate the rear of a vehicle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(26)</num>
        <text>"Turn signal lamp" means a lamp that provides a flashing warning light to indicate the intended direction of the turn.</text>
      </para>
      <aftertext>Agency Note: The following are some examples of replaceable bulb headlamps, Type—HB1—9004 (low and high beam); HB2—9003 (low and high beam); HB3—9005 (high beam); HB4—9006 (low beam); and HB5—9007 (low and high beam). For more information and a complete list of replaceable bulb headlamps, consult an automotive lighting reference or specification guide, or vehicle manufacturer.</aftertext>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>General Lamp and Reflector Inspection. This includes all original or required equipment, exterior lighting plus whatever lights are authorized.</text>
      <text>Agency Note: Due to the limited federal standards for governing lighting requirements on low speed vehicles, lighting installed by manufacturers of low speed vehicles may conflict with the standardized lighting listed in SAE Lighting Identification Code J759 and lighting requirements under Federal Motor Vehicle Safety Standard 49 CFR §571.108 for vehicles other than low speed vehicles. Lighting devices installed or supplied by the vehicle manufacturer will be considered in compliance under this chapter, provided the lighting device meets the color, mounting location (excluding height requirements), candle power for headlamps when applicable, and functions as designed by the vehicle manufacturer and as required under these regulations. Any additional lighting device required to be installed to meet these regulations, or is otherwise permitted, shall be in compliance with standardized lighting listed in SAE Lighting Identification Code J759 and requirements established under 49 CFR §571.108 pertaining to passenger cars or other appropriate applications, and comply with lighting requirements established under this chapter. Any questions regarding lighting shall be referred to the Automotive Safety Enforcement Division of the Department of State Police.</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Visual Check of Lamp Function. Inspect the operation of the following as designed by the vehicle manufacturer:<br/>(a) Turn signals—Actuate turn signal lever to right and left, and observe function of turn signal lights. Turn signals shall be mounted: At or near the front—One amber on each side of the vertical centerline, at the same height, and as far apart as practicable. On the rear—One red or amber on each side of the vertical centerline, at the same height, and as far apart as practicable. Turn signals shall be mounted not less than 15 inches nor more than 83 inches from the ground.<br/>(b) Backup lamps, if so equipped. Place vehicle in all forward gears and check backup lamps. Backup lamps, if so equipped, are required to function automatically when vehicle is in reverse, but may not function when vehicle is in any forward gear. Vehicle may be equipped with one or more backup lamps on the rear, either separately or in combination with other lamps. Backup lamps shall emit a white light.<br/>(c) Actuate the following and observe lamps as follows: <br/>(i) Hazard warning lamps, if so equipped.<br/>(ii) Indicator lamps for: turn signals; high beam indicator, if so equipped with high beam headlamps; hazard warning flashers, if so equipped with hazard warning lamps; brake system warning lamps, if so equipped; and charge indicator lamp or gauge, if so equipped. <br/>(iii) Stop lamps—At least two stop lamps shall be mounted on the rear of the vehicle, one on each side of the vertical centerline, at the same height, and as far apart as practicable. The stop lamps shall be actuated on application of the service (foot) brake and shall display a red light. Stop lamps shall be mounted not less than 15 inches nor more than 72 inches from the ground.<br/>(iv) Headlamps—Low beam, and upper beam if so equipped. On the front, each headlamp providing the lower beam, at the same height, one on each side of the vertical centerline, each headlamp providing the upper beam, at the same height, one on each side of the vertical centerline. Corresponding headlamps shall be mounted as far apart as practicable. Headlamps shall emit a white light. Headlamps shall be mounted not less than 24 inches nor more than 54 inches from the ground.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1)<br/>(a) Any of the following required lamps fails to light: Headlamp, tail lamp, stop lamp, turn signal, and license plate lamp.<br/>(b) Any of the following lamps, when so equipped, fails to light: Side marker lamp, parking lamp, backup lamp, or hazard warning lamp. <br/>(c) Any of the following indicator lamps fails to function: Turn signal, high beam indicator when equipped with high beam headlamps, hazard warning flasher when equipped with hazard warning lamps, brake system warning lamp when equipped, and charge indicator lamp, gauge, or other source when equipped.<br/>(d) Turn signals do not properly indicate right or left when so switched, or do not stay in position or self-cancel, if so designed.<br/>(e) Backup light system, if so equipped, functions when the vehicle is in any forward gear, or backup light system fails to function automatically when vehicle is in reverse.<br/>(f) Any lamp shows color contrary to law, red or blue to the front, white light to the rear, except license plate lamp and backup lamp when vehicle is in reverse gear. Tail lamps shall be red, stop lamps red, turn signals amber to the front and red or amber to the rear, and headlamps white. <br/>(g) Any lamp fails to light the proper filament when switched on, or the color of the bulb has been altered.<br/>(h) Any required or permitted lamp, lens, or reflector is obscured by any object or shielded by a nontransparent material, or any headlamp is equipped with aftermarket clear, tinted, or screen-type covers. <br/>(i) Any lamp, lens, or reflector is loose or improperly mounted.<br/>(j) Any lamp, lens, or reflector, including headlamp, whether separate or combined components, has a cracked, broken, or missing lens, or is otherwise damaged or in a condition preventing it from directing or reflecting light as designed and required.<br/>(k) Except as otherwise permitted, any lamp, lens, or reflector is not an approved type.<br/>(l) Equipped with any unauthorized emergency lamp, warning lamp, or neon lighting device.<br/>(m) Headlamp output is less then 5,000 candlepower on high beam, if so equipped, or less then 3,500 candlepower on low beam.<br/>(n) Dash lamps, if so equipped, do not illuminate speedometer and odometer as designed.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(2) With night driving lights turned on, observe function of:<br/>(a) Tail lamps—At least two tail lamps shall be mounted on the rear, one on each side of the vertical centerline, at the same height, and as far apart as practicable. Tail lamps shall emit a red light. Tail lamps shall be mounted not less than 15 inches nor more than 72 inches above the ground. <br/>(b) Parking lamps, if so equipped. Parking lamps shall display two white or amber lights mounted on the front, one on each side of the vertical centerline, at the same height, and as far apart as practicable. Parking lamps shall be mounted not less than 15 inches nor more than 72 inches from the ground.<br/>(c) Side marker lamps, if so equipped. On each side—Shall display one red light as far to the rear as practicable, and one amber light as far to the front as practicable. Side marker lamps shall be mounted not less than 15 inches from the ground.<br/>(d) Reflex reflectors—Reflex reflectors shall be mounted on the vehicle in the following manner:<br/>(i) On the rear—One red on each side of the vertical centerline, at the same height, and as far apart as practicable.<br/>(ii) On each side—One red as far to the rear as practicable, and one amber as far to the front as practicable.<br/>(iii) Reflex reflectors shall be mounted not less than 15 inches nor more than 60 inches from the ground.<br/>(e) License plate lamp. Either a tail lamp or a separate lamp shall be constructed and placed to illuminate, with a white light, the rear registration plate. Any tail lamp or tail lamps, together with any separate lamp or lamps for illuminating the rear registration plate, shall be wired to be lighted whenever the headlamps or auxiliary driving lamps are lighted.<br/>(f) Dash Lamps, if so Equipped.<br/>(g) Red, white, or blue lights are used on law enforcement vehicles. Red lights, white lights, or both are used on emergency, fire department, and emergency rescue vehicles. Amber lights are used on service and maintenance vehicles.</td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td colspan="2" data-vertical-align="middle">Agency Note: Measuring mounted height of lamps. Whenever a requirement is declared as to the mounted height of lamps or devices, it means from the center of the lamp or device to the level ground on which the vehicle stands when the vehicle is without a load.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
      <para>
        <num proof="done">(3)</num>
        <text>Aim Inspection.</text>
        <text>
          <table class="layout-table">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th>Procedures:</th>
                <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(a) Inflate tires to recommended pressures.<br/>(b) Be sure that lenses are clean. Check for burned out bulbs and proper beam switching. <br/>(c) Check for improper tracking of the rear axle.<br/>(d) Headlamps shall be mounted not less than 24 inches or more than 54 inches above the level surface on which the vehicle stands, measured to the center of the lamp.<br/>(e) Visually check headlamp adjusters for presence and capability of holding an adjustment.<br/>(f) Check for presence of after-market headlamp covers.</td>
                <td>(a) Headlamps are equipped with any aftermarket clear, tinted or screen-type cover.<br/>(b) Headlamps have no aiming capability.<br/>(c) Headlamps are mounted lower than 24 inches or higher than 54 inches.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Headlamps. Only low beam headlamps are currently required on low speed vehicles. If a low speed vehicle is equipped with high and low beam headlamps, both lamps are required to function. A low beam headlamp shall have a minimum of 3,500 candlepower and a high beam headlamp a minimum of 5,000 candlepower. Headlamps that incorporate both high and low beam in the same assembly will be aligned on low beam. Headlamp inspection and aiming by computer image processing method requires a level area sufficient for the vehicle and test equipment. The test equipment shall be accurately calibrated to the floor and accurately aligned to the vehicle.</text>
      <text>Agency Note: Manufacturers of low speed vehicles may equip their vehicles with lamps which are not identified as approved headlamps by federal motor vehicle safety standards established for vehicles other than low speed vehicles, for example: required marking symbol of "DOT" (Department of Transportation) on headlamp lens, and any additional manufacturer's markings of headlamp type and SAE identification code. Manufacturers of low speed vehicles utilizing lighting in their vehicles as headlamps, which are not properly identified with the appropriate marking, however, are equipped with multibeam road lighting (high and low beam headlamps), will be treated as headlamps and aligned by using the Division's approved headlight testers. Lighting utilized by manufacturers of low speed vehicles as headlamps which are identified as a type lighting other than a headlamp, for example: SAE "Y", auxiliary driving lamp, or by lighting utilized as headlamps which fails to contain the appropriate headlamp marking and is not multibeam road lighting as noted above, will not be inspected and aligned by the use of the Division's approved headlight testers. These lamps will instead be visually inspected and rejected under "Non-Headlamps", inspection procedures listed below.</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Low Beam.<br/>  (a) Low Beam. With the vehicle in the approved inspection area and the test equipment properly calibrated and aligned to the vehicle, switch headlamps to low beam. Follow headlamp aimer's procedures for low beam headlamp alignment.<br/>  (b) When properly aimed: Edges of high intensity zone—Top edge centered on horizontal centerline. Left edge centered on vertical centerline.</td>
              <td class="text-indent-1">(a) High intensity zone:<br/>  (i) Left edge is horizontally more than 4 inches right or left of the vertical centerline; or<br/>  (ii) Top edge is vertically more than 4 inches above or below the horizontal centerline.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
      <para>
        <num proof="done">(2)</num>
        <text>High Beam. Required to function, if so equipped. Inspect aim of high beam lamp only if high beam lamp has separate adjustment from low beam lamp.</text>
        <text>
          <table class="layout-table">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th>Procedures:</th>
                <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td>(a) High Beam. Follow same set up procedure as low beam aim-inspection. Switch headlamps to high beam and follow headlamp aimer's procedures for high beam headlamp alignment.<br/>(b) When properly aimed, the center of the high intensity zone of the beam pattern is set on the vertical and horizontal centerlines of the lamp.</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(a) Center of high intensity zone is horizontally:<br/>  (i) More than 4 inches right; or<br/>  (ii) More than 4 inches left of the vertical centerline.<br/>(b) Center of high intensity zone is vertically:<br/>  (i) More than 4 inches above; or<br/>  (ii) More than 4 inches below the horizontal centerline.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Non-Headlamps. Lighting installed by the vehicle manufacturer and used as headlamps, which are not properly marked as headlamps, excluding multibeam road lighting (high and low beam headlamps) that are improperly marked, or are types of lamps identified as other than headlamps. See Agency Note in §C Headlamps.</text>
        <text>
          <table class="layout-table">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th>Procedures:</th>
                <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td>(a) Non-headlamp. With the vehicle in the approved inspection area and following general headlamp aim inspection procedures previously noted, switch headlamps on and visually inspect headlamps. To assist in visually inspecting headlamp aim, the vehicle should be positioned a minimum distance of 5 feet or further when practical, from in front of a plain vertical surface, for example, bay wall or tool box, etc., to provide a view of the headlamps beam pattern.</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(a) Non-headlamp.<br/>  (i) Fails to emit a white light and function as designed when activated;<br/>  (ii) Is not properly mounted in vehicle or fails to provide a means of adjustment;<br/>  (iii) Fails to display an adjusted beam pattern of sufficient intensity determined by visual observation. Examples: Is obviously misaligned permitting the high intensity portion of the beam pattern to be directed in the eyes of on coming drivers, or is unequal in height to the opposite lamp, fails to cast light in the path of vehicle travel, or light emitted from lamp is obviously dim.<br/>  (iv) Lens is cracked or broken;<br/>  (v) Is mounted less than 24 inches or more than 54 inches above the level surface on which the vehicle stands measured to the center of the lamp; or<br/>  (vi) Fails to comply with any applicable required condition of a headlamp noted in this chapter.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Fog Lamp and Auxiliary Driving Lamps. Only one spot lamp is allowed. It is not considered an auxiliary driving lamp and has no set mounting height by law. Therefore, it need not be inspected. If a vehicle is equipped with either fog lamps or auxiliary driving lamps, they shall be properly aimed. Fog lamps shall be mounted on the front of the vehicle at a height not more than 30 inches or less than 12 inches above the level surface on which the vehicle stands. Only two fog lamps are allowed by law. Auxiliary driving lamps shall be mounted on the front of the vehicle at a height not more than 42 inches or less than 16 inches above the level surface on which the vehicle stands. Only two auxiliary lamps are allowed by law. The mounting heights of auxiliary driving lamps do not apply to emergency vehicles. Whenever a motor vehicle equipped with required headlamps also is equipped with any auxiliary lamps or a spot lamp or any other lamp on its front, projecting a beam of intensity greater than 300 candlepower, not more than four of these lamps on the front of a vehicle may be lighted at any one time when on a highway.</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Auxiliary Driving or Fog Lamp Aim—Inspection. Under the same procedures as for headlamp inspection, follow headlamp aimer's procedures for auxiliary or fog lamp alignment. Switch on the lamps and observe color emitted and the location of the high intensity zone.<br/>  (a) Symmetrical Beam. When properly aimed, the center of the high intensity zone is set 4 inches below the horizontal centerline of the lamp and centered on the vertical centerline.<br/>  (b) Asymmetrical Beam. When properly aimed, the center of the high intensity zone is set 7 inches below the horizontal centerline of the lamp and centered on the vertical centerline.</td>
              <td>(1) Symmetrical Beam: Center of high intensity zone is more than:<br/>  (a) Horizontally:<br/>    (i) 4 inches left; or<br/>    (ii) 4 inches right of the vertical centerline; or<br/>  (b) Vertically-Less than 4 inches below the horizontal centerline.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Measure height of auxiliary driving or fog lamps. After-market auxiliary driving lamps shall be mounted not less than 16 inches or more than 42 inches above the level surface on which the vehicle stands. Fog lamps shall be mounted not less than 12 inches or more than 30 inches above the level surface on which the vehicle stands.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(2) Asymmetrical Beam. Same as low beam headlamps. Center of high intensity is more than:<br/>  (a) Horizontally:<br/>    (i) 4 inches left, or <br/>    (ii) 4 inches right of the vertical centerline; or<br/>  (b) Vertically-Less than 7 inches below the horizontal centerline.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td/>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(3) Fog lamps or auxiliary driving lamps are mounted higher or lower than allowed. Auxiliary driving lamps mounted on roll bar or roof for off-road use may remain but may not be connected to an electrical source. Reject if:<br/>  (a) After-market fog lamps are mounted lower than 12 inches or higher than 30 inches;<br/>  (b) After-market auxiliary lamps are mounted lower than 16 inches or higher than 42 inches; or<br/>  (c) Fog lamps when lit emit a color other than white or yellow.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td/>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(4) Vehicle is equipped with more than two operable fog lamps.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td/>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(5) Vehicle is equipped with more than two auxiliary driving lamps.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td/>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(6) Vehicle is equipped with more than one spot lamp.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>SAE Identification Code (J759 SAE Handbook).</text>
      <text>Devices marked prior to the adoption of this SAE Specification need not be remarked.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The following list is an identifying code for lights and signaling devices:</text>
        <text>
          <table class="layout-table">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th>Device</th>
                <th>SAE Identification Code Designation</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Reflex reflector</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">A</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Reflex reflector for use on vehicles 2,032 millimeters or more in overall width</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">A2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Reflex reflector for conspicuity treatment (CT), for use on vehicles 2,032 millimeters or more in overall width</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">A3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Reflex reflector for CT (vehicle &gt; 2,032 millimeters width)󈠂 millimeters wide Truck/Trailer</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">A4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Reflex reflector for CT (vehicle &gt; 2,032 millimeters width)󈠛 millimeters wide Truck/Trailer</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">A5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Reflex reflector for CT (vehicle &gt; 2,032 millimeters width)#8212100 millimeters wide Truck/Trailer</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">A6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Reflex reflector for CT (vehicle &gt; 2,032 millimeters width)󈟩 millimeters wide School bus</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">A7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Motorcycle auxiliary front lamp</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">C</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Motorcycle and motor-driven cycle turn signal lamp</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">D</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Distributed lighting system (headlamp)</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">DL</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Side turn signal lamp—vehicles (12 meters) or more in length</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">E</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Side turn signal lamp—vehicles less than (12 meters) in length</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">E2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Siren—interior location</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">EVS1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Siren-exterior location</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">EVS2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Siren-under hood location</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">EVS3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Front fog lamp</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">F</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Fog tail lamps</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">F2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Truck cargo lamp</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">G</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Sealed beam headlamp</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">H</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Headlamp cleaner</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">HC</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Discharge forward lighting (headlamp)</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">HG</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Sealed beam headlamp housing</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">HH</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Replaceable bulb headlamp</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">HR</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Turn signal lamp spaced greater than 100 millimeters from headlamp</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">I</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Turn signal lamp spaced from 75 millimeters to less than 100 millimeters from headlamp</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">I3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Turn signal lamp spaced from 60 millimeters to less than 75 millimeters from headlamp</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">I4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Turn signal lamp spaced less than 60 millimeters from headlamp</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">I5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Rear mounted turn signal lamp and front mounted turn signal lamps mounted 100 millimeters or more from the headlamp, for use on vehicles 2,032 millimeters or more in overall width</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">I6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Front mounted turn signal lamp mounted less than 100 millimeters from the headlamp, for use on vehicles 2,032 millimeters or more in overall width</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">I7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Flasher</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">J1690</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Front cornering lamp</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">K</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Rear cornering lamp</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">K2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">License plate lamp</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">L</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Motorcycle and motor-driven cycle headlamp—motorcycle type</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">M</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Motorcycle and motor-driven cycle headlamp—motor-driven cycle type</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">N</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Spot lamp</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">O</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Parking lamp</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">P</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Side marker lamp for use on vehicles 2,032 millimeters or less in overall width</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">P2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Clearance, side marker, and identification lamp for use on vehicles 2,032 millimeters or more in overall width.</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">P3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Combination clearance and side marker lamp for use on vehicles 2,032 millimeters or more in overall width</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">PC2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Turn signal operating unit-Class A</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Q</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Turn signal operating unit—Class B</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">QB</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Vehicular hazard warning signal operating unit</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">QC</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Turn signal operating unit for use on vehicles 2,032 millimeters in overall width—Type 1</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">QD1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Turn signal operating unit for use on vehicles 2,032 millimeters in overall width—Type 2</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">QD2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Hazard warning operating unit for use on vehicles 2,032 millimeters in overall width—Type 1</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">QE1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Hazard warning operating unit for use on vehicles 2,032 millimeters in overall width—Type 2</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">QE2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Reversing (backup) lamp</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">R</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Stop lamp</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">S</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Stop lamp for use on vehicles 2,032 millimeters or more in overall width</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">S2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Tail lamp (rear position lamp)</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">T</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Tail lamp (rear position lamp) for use on vehicles 2,032 millimeters or more in overall width</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">T2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Supplemental high-mounted stop and turn signal lamp</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">U</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">High-mounted stop lamp for trucks 2,032 millimeters or more in overall width</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">U2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Center high-mounted stop lamp for passenger cars, light trucks, and MPV's</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">U3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Warning lamp for emergency, maintenance, and service vehicles</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">W</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Warning lamp for school buses</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">W2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Optical warning device—Class 1</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">W3-1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Optical warning device—Class 2</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">W3-2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Optical warning device—Class 3</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">W3-3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Emergency warning device (triangular shape)</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">W4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">360 degree gaseous discharge lamp—Class 1</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">W5-1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">360 degree gaseous discharge lamp—Class 2</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">W5-2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">360 degree gaseous discharge lamp—Class 3</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">W5-3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Adaptive (forward) lighting system</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">X</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Auxiliary high beam lamp</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Y</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Daytime running lamp</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Y2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Auxiliary low beam lamp</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">Z</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All equipment for testing headlamps shall comply with the Society of Automotive Engineers Recommended Practice for Headlamp Inspection Equipment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Electrical System.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The electrical system includes the key/ignition switch, battery pack, power cables, wiring, and necessary connections to power the unit, lighting system, and accessories.</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Visually examine each battery for evidence of leakage, loose connections, low in fluid if applicable, or improperly secured.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Any battery that:<br/> (a) Is cracked, broken, or leaking;<br/> (b) Has connections that are loose or show signs of excessive corrosion;<br/> (c) Is not held down securely;<br/> (d) Has vents not open, if equipped; or<br/> (e) Has low fluid level, if applicable.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(2) Visually inspect batteries for proper voltage and type, for example, 12-volt deep cycle or equivalent. Automotive batteries should never be used. Consult vehicle manufacturer for required voltage and type batteries. Agency Note: Some manufacturers may use an automotive battery to power vehicle accessories.</td>
              <td>(2) Any battery is a voltage or type not approved for use by the vehicle manufacturer.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(3) Visually inspect condition of electric power cables and all visible wiring. Cables and wiring shall be well insulated, properly mounted, or secured.<br/><strong>Caution</strong>—Follow manufacturer's safety warnings.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(3) Wiring:<br/> (a) Insulation on power cables or any wiring is bare, frayed, cracked, or broken.<br/> (b) Power cable or wiring is improperly mounted or secured.<br/> (c) Shows evidence of burning or short-circuiting.<br/> (d) Power cables do not conform to manufacturer's standards.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(4) All connections shall be tight and secure.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(4) Connections are loose or show signs of excessive corrosion.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(5) Any switch that operates regulated equipment shall function properly.</td>
              <td>(5) Switches fail to function.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(6) Horn. A horn shall be securely fastened, produce an audible but not harsh or unreasonably loud sound or whistle, and be audible for a distance of at least 200 feet under normal conditions. A horn button or actuator shall be readily accessible to the operator.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(6) Horn:<br/> (a) Is loose;<br/> (b) Fails to function;<br/> (c) Produces an unreasonably loud or harsh sound, or whistle;<br/> (d) Is not audible 200 feet away under normal conditions; or<br/> (e) Is not equipped with a horn button or actuator within arm's reach of the operator.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(7) Safety Signs. Inspect for safety signs/warnings installed by the vehicle manufacturer in the battery compartment and battery-charging compartment of the vehicle.<br/>Agency Note:—Consult vehicle manufacturer for any additional information.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(7) Any safety sign/warning, if originally installed by the manufacturer, has obviously been removed, tampered with, or is otherwise not permanently attached and visible as designed by the vehicle manufacturer.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(8) Key/Ignition Switch—Inspect operation of key/ignition switch as designed by the vehicle manufacturer.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(8) Key/ignition switch fails to function as designed or permits vehicle to operate other than as designed by the vehicle manufacturer.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(9) Accelerator Control—Accelerator control shall return to off position when activating force is removed from the control. The accelerator control shall be located for right foot operation, shall be positioned to the right of the service brake pedal, and shall be free of interference from the service brake pedal.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(9) Accelerator control:<br/> (a) Fails to return to the off position when activating force is removed from the control;<br/> (b) Fails to meet required mounting; or<br/> (c) Fails to function properly.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Mirrors.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Outside Mirrors. As required by 49 CFR §571.500, all vehicles shall be equipped with an exterior mirror mounted on the driver's side of the vehicle and either an exterior mirror mounted on the passenger's side of the vehicle or an interior mirror.</text>
      <text>All exterior mirrors shall provide a view of the highway for a distance of at least 200 feet to the rear. A vehicle with add-on tint must have an outside rearview mirror on the passenger side.</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Rearview Mirror or Mirrors. From the driver's position, visually inspect all exterior mirrors for a clear and reasonably unobstructed view of at least 200 ft. to the rear. Look for correct location, stable mounting, cracks, sharp edges, ease of adjustment, and ability to hold an adjustment.</td>
              <td>(1) Mirror:<br/> (a) Is missing, when required;<br/> (b) Mounting is loose so that rear vision is impaired;<br/> (c) Is obscured by windshield pillar or unwiped portion of the windshield;<br/> (d)  Is cracked, pitted, has sharp edges, or is clouded to the extent that rear vision is obscured;<br/> (e) Does not provide an unobstructed view to the rear of at least 200 feet; or<br/> (f) Cannot be adjusted or will not hold an adjustment.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Inside Mirrors. All vehicles not equipped with an inside rearview mirror shall be equipped with an exterior mirror mounted on the passenger side. The inside rearview mirror shall be adjustable and equipped with clear view glass providing a clear stable reflected view 200 feet to the rear.</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Interior Rearview Mirror.<br/> (a) From the driver's position, visually inspect interior mirror for proper mounting, location, cracks, sharp edges, ease of adjustment, and ability to hold an adjustment.<br/> (b) If vehicle is designed or constructed where the view through an inside rearview mirror is obstructed, the inside rearview mirror is not required, however, the vehicle shall be equipped with outside rearview mirrors on both sides.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Mirror:<br/> (a) Is missing, when required;<br/> (b) Mounting is loose so that rear vision is impaired;<br/> (c) Is cracked, pitted, has sharp edges, or is clouded to the extent that rear vision is obscured;<br/> (d) Does not provide an unobstructed view to the rear of at least 200 feet; or<br/> (e) Cannot be adjusted or will not hold an adjustment.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Vehicle Glazing.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>As required under Federal Motor Vehicle Safety Standards, 49 CFR §571.500 "Low Speed Vehicles", all low speed vehicles shall be equipped with a windshield that conforms to the federal motor vehicle safety standard on glazing materials, 49 CFR §571.205. Windshields of low speed vehicles must meet the ANSI/SAE Z26.1 —1996 specifications for either AS-1 or AS-4 glazing (incorporated by reference; see 49 CFR §571.5). Safety glazing is marked with the manufacturer's trademark and the letters "AS" followed by a number from 1 through 16B. Only AS-1 or AS-4 composition may be used in the windshield. Safety glazing for 1966 and later models also has a glass manufacturer's model number or a DOT (Department of Transportation) code number. Any questions regarding glazing shall be referred to the Automotive Safety Enforcement Division of the Department of State Police.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Definitions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Cloudiness" means any degree of visible discoloration or separation, except tinting that does not affect clear vision.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Critical area" means the normal windshield wiper sweep, except the area obscured by hood, fenders, or rearview mirror.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Non-critical area" means all windshield area outside the critical area.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Normal windshield wiper sweep" means the area of windshield cleaned by the windshield wiper, excluding return position on both passenger's and driver's side.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Proper Marking. Inspect glass for proper markings.</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Windshield—Inspect for AS-1 or AS-4 composition. Any windows, if so equipped, must contain safety glazing labeled AS-2, or other approved materials installed or permitted by the vehicle manufacturer for the appropriate application allowing for adequate visibility.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Windshield composition is other than AS-1 or AS-4. Any window is not equipped with safety glazing as required, or is equipped with other than approved materials installed or permitted by the vehicle manufacturer providing required visibility.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(2) Window on Driver's Side-Inspect operation of window at driver's side. Window shall open and close readily as designed even though the vehicle has approved turn signals.</td>
              <td>(2) Window on driver's side cannot be readily opened and closed as designed.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(3) Add on Tinting and Stickers.<br/>    (a) Low speed vehicles equipped with windows must have at least 35 percent light transmittance after the application of add on tint. When add on tint is applied to any side or rear window, the vehicle must be equipped with an outside rearview mirror on each side. Add on tint to windshield may not be below the AS1 line or below 5 inches from the top of the windshield, whichever is less. Add on tint may not be mirrored or have a one-way vision effect, may not be red, yellow, or amber in color, may not have a sparkling effect, or may not change to a color that is prohibited.<br/>    (b) All side and rear windows equipped with add on tint meeting the 35 percent light transmittance requirements, shall have labels affixed to the tint approved by the Division. These labels shall be 1/2 inch by 1 1/2 inch, containing the Maryland State Police shield, Maryland Department of Transportation logo, and marked 35 percent. Labels are to be located in close proximity to and not obscuring the glazing manufacturer's trademark and AS indicator. On the rear window, the label shall be affixed in the upper left corner as viewed from the outside. For vehicles equipped with unmarked glazing in side windows, the label shall be placed in the lower rear corner of window as viewed from the outside. Inspection and certification of add on window tinting will be performed as per established regulations. <br/>    (c) Inspect all glass for unauthorized material or conditions that obscure the driver's vision. Stickers, signs, posters, cards, or other nontransparent materials are to be placed on the windshield or rear window within a 7-inch square in the lower corner or upon the side windows of the vehicle to the rear of the driver, and so placed that the materials will not obstruct the driver's clear view of traffic. Agency Note: Materials placed on the windshield of a vehicle in compliance with security measures required by a federal or State government agency and approved by the Administration, are exempt from the requirements explained in this paragraph.</td>
              <td class="text-indent-1">(a) Glazed surfaces contain any stickers not permitted by law or regulation.<br/>    (b) Tinting is not incorporated into the glazing except as noted in the procedures and as permitted by federal law.<br/>    (c) Driver's vision is obscured.<br/>    (d) Any glazing contains after-market material that causes a mirror or one-way vision effect or is a prohibited color.<br/>    (e) A vehicle is equipped with allowed add on tinting and is not equipped with an outside rearview mirror on each side.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Glazing Damage.</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Cracks, Chips, Discoloration. Inspect windshield and any windows, if so equipped, for damage and discoloration from both inside and outside of the vehicle.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Cracks, Chips, Discoloration.<br/> (a) There are cracks, discolorations, scratches, or conditions that interfere with the driver's view to the right or left.<br/> (b) Any window is broken or has exposed sharp edges.<br/> (c) Rear window is discolored or in a condition preventing driver from having a clear view 200 feet to the rear of the vehicle.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Windshield. Inspect windshield for cracks, nicks, pits, chips, star breaks, half moons or bull's-eye fractures, discoloration, sharp edges, and wiper blade scratches.<br/><br/>(3) Window Modification. Inspect all windows for modification. Modification of windshield or any side or rear windows of a low speed vehicle is prohibited.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(2) Windshield.<br/> (a) Driver's Side. <br/>    (i) Cloudiness exceeds 1 inch from the top or sides or 1 inch into the critical area from the bottom. If the windshield is divided, the cloudiness may not exceed 1/2 inch from the center divider. <br/>    (ii) Critical area contains wiper blade scratches, severe enough to distort vision, or any one crack, nick, pit, chip, star break, or half moon or bull's-eye fracture in excess of 1/2 inch diameter or length, or any combination of individual cracks, nicks, pits, chips, star breaks, or half moon or bull's-eye fractures that cumulatively exceed 1/2 inch in diameter or length or any permanent condition other than listed above that significantly interferes with the driver's vision, for example, sand blasting or etching.<br/>    (iii) Non-critical area contains any one crack or combination of intersecting or individual cracks, which cumulatively exceed 1 inch diameter or length, or any permanent condition that significantly interferes with the driver's vision.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td/>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle" class="text-indent-1">(b) Passenger Side. <br/>    (i) Cloudiness exceeds 2 inches from the top or outer edges or extends more than 2 inches into the critical area from the bottom. If the windshield is divided, the cloudiness may not exceed 1/2 inch from the center divider.<br/>    (ii) Critical area contains wiper blade scratches severe enough to distort vision, or any one crack, nick, pit, chip, star break, or half moon or bull's-eye fracture in excess of 1/2 inch diameter or length, or any combination of cracks, nicks, pits, chips, star breaks, or half moon or bull's-eye fractures which cumulatively exceed 1/2 inch diameter or length, or any permanent condition other than listed above which significantly interferes with the driver's vision.<br/>    (iii) Non-critical area contains any one crack or combination of intersecting or individual cracks, which cumulatively exceed 2 inches diameter or length, or any permanent condition that significantly interferes with the driver's vision.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td/>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(3) Modification. Windshield or any side or rear window has been modified from its original manufacturer's design.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Windshield Wipers and Washers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The windshield wipers shall be inspected for operation, control, condition of blades and arms, or any missing part. Vehicle manufacturers may design vehicle to be equipped with only one windshield wiper.</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Windshield Wipers.<br/> (a) Inspect for operation as designed. Windshield shall be free of insects, oil film, or other foreign matter, and should be continuously wet when tested.<br/> (b) Inspect for damaged, torn, or hardened rubber elements of blades. <br/> (c) Inspect for damaged metal parts of wiper blades or arms.<br/> (d) Inspect for proper contact of blades with windshield. Raise arm away from windshield and release. Arms should return to original position and cause the wiper blades to firmly contact the windshield.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Windshield Wipers.<br/> (a) Wipers do not operate as designed or cannot be controlled by the driver.<br/> (b) A wiper arm or blade is broken or missing.<br/> (c) There is insufficient tension of arm to hold blade against windshield.<br/> (d) There are worn or deteriorated blades that do not clean the windshield within 5 cycles.<br/> (e) Wiper arms and blades are not the proper size for the windshield or have been relocated from original design.<br/> (f) Not equipped with on or off switch within arm's length of driver.<br/> (g) Arms fail to automatically return to park position.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Windshield Washer(s) (If so equipped).<br/> (a) Inspect for proper operation of controls and for an effective amount of fluid delivered to the outside of the windshield. System shall function regardless of outside temperatures.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(2) Windshield Washer(s).<br/> (a) Reservoir is empty.<br/> (b) System fails to function.<br/> (c) Fluid in system is frozen.<br/> (d) System does not provide fluid to the wiper area.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Hood and Catches.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Inspection shall consist of operation and presence of hinges, latches, release mechanisms, safety catches, or fasteners, if so equipped, insuring that the hood encloses the motor compartment.</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Open hood and inspect for proper operation. Inspect all hinges, latches, release mechanism, safety catch, or fasteners, for condition and proper operation. Close hood and inspect for proper full closure. If motor is rear mounted, make a similar inspection of motor compartment and hood door.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Hood does not enclose the motor compartment. <br/>(2) Hood latch and keeper are not original equipment or equivalent. <br/>(3) Any hinge, latch, release mechanism, or fastener of the hood or motor cover is broken, missing, or improperly adjusted preventing the hood or motor cover from being properly opened and closed.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(2) Inspect for any hood scoop more than 1/3 the vertical height of the windshield.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(4) Hood is not equipped with a proper operating safety latch if originally equipped.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td/>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(5) Any hood scoop is higher than 1/3 the vertical height of the windshield.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Doors, Handles, and Latches (If so equipped).</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Inspection of doors, handles, latches, and hinges applies to all vehicles originally manufactured with doors and all other vehicles that are equipped with doors.</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Inspect all doors, latches, hinges, and handles for broken or missing parts, proper operation, and improper adjustment.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Doors or door parts are missing, broken, or sagging so that the door cannot be closed as designed.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Inspect all doors for tears or sharp or jagged edges which would present a hazard to pedestrians or passengers.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(2) Latch or handles not original equipment or equivalent.<br/>(3) Door handles and latches do not provide a means of readily opening door.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td/>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(4) Secondary or safety catch does not function properly, if so equipped.<br/>(5) Door has tears, or sharp or jagged edges which would present a hazard to pedestrians or passengers.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Floor and Trunk Pans.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Floor and trunk pans shall be inspected for structural integrity and general condition.</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Inspect floor and trunk pans for structural integrity and general condition.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Floor or trunk pan of unibody construction is cracked or broken, or is otherwise damaged or in a condition that would affect structural integrity.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td/>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(2) Floor or trunk pan is otherwise damaged or deteriorated to cause a hazard to an occupant, or affects the secure mounting of seats, seat belt anchorages, or any other component.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td/>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(3) Repairs to floor and trunk pan are not made with the same type of material that was originally used by the manufacturer or approved for use by the vehicle manufacturer.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td/>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(4) Repairs to floor and trunk pan of unibody are not welded.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td/>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(5) Repairs to the areas of seat mountings, seat belt anchorages, or other components are not welded.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td/>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(6) Repairs to floor and trunk pan, other than unibody construction, are not welded, riveted, or screwed.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td/>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(7) Any repairs to floor or trunk pan does not appear to be of sufficient strength or quality or is not sealed to prevent moisture from entering the vehicle. Agency Note: Undercoating alone is not an approved sealant.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td/>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(8) Floor in occupant area is not equipped with a slip resistant surface, or is not properly attached, or presents a hazard.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td colspan="2" data-vertical-align="middle">Agency Note: If repairs are required the vehicle owner or agent shall be advised not to apply undercoating to the repaired area prior to reinspection. If undercoating exists in areas of required inspection, removal of undercoating may be required to permit a proper inspection.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.17</num>
    <heading>Speedometer and Odometer.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Speedometer and odometer shall be inspected to determine if they are connected and speedometer is operable. The dial and speed increments of speedometer are legible, and calibrated in miles or kilometers.</text>
      <text>Agency Note: Odometer readings in kilometers shall be converted and recorded in miles on inspection check sheet and inspection certificate.</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="5">(1) Visually inspect speedometer for operation and legibility. Due to the inability of conducting a road test of the vehicle, a determination of the ability of the odometer to operate and register distance traveled will not be an inspection requirement. The odometer will however, be required to display a registered distance reading in miles or kilometers. The speedometer may register speed in miles per hour or kilometers per hour, or both. If the odometer records a distance in kilometers, the vehicle shall be placarded in view of the driver with a wording "kilometers divided by 1.609 equals miles".</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Speedometer or odometer, or both, are disconnected, or speedometer is inoperable.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(2) Dial and speed increments are not legible.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(3) Speedometer does not register speed in miles per hour or kilometers, or both.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(4) Odometer does not display a registered distance reading in miles or kilometers that is legible.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(5) Odometer records distance in kilometers and is not placarded with wording "kilometers divided by 1.609 equals miles".</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.18</num>
    <heading>Driver's Seat and All Passenger Seating.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The vehicle shall provide securely fastened seating arrangements, including a backrest for each intended occupant. The driver's seat shall be inspected for proper operation of the adjusting mechanism, along with any adjustable passenger seat if so equipped.</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Inspect for presence and condition of all seating.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Any seating shows indication of being loose, damaged, or broken, or not equipped with a backrest for each intended occupant. Driver's seat or any passenger seating is missing or unsafe.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(2) Inspect required seat adjustment of driver's seat along with any passenger seat equipped with adjustment mechanism.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(2) Driver's seat, or any passenger seat equipped with adjustment mechanism, slips out of position or does not provide for and hold adjustment.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(3) Inspect all seat mounting brackets, anchor bolts, and related hardware.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(3) All seat mounting brackets, anchor bolts, or related hardware, are not securely fastened as designed or are missing.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(4) Inspect all seating for protruding springs or other objects that could catch clothing or cause injury.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(4) Any seat has protruding springs or other objects that could catch clothing or cause injury.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(5) Inspect for any hand hold or hip restraint installed in vehicle.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(5) Any hand hold or hip restraint, if originally installed by vehicle manufacturer, is missing, broken, or loose anywhere in the occupant area.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.19</num>
    <heading>Safety Belts.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>As required under Federal Motor Vehicle Safety Standards 49 CFR §571.500, Standard No. 500 Low Speed Vehicles, all low speed vehicles shall be equipped with a Type 1 or Type 2 seat belt assembly conforming to §571.209 of this part, Federal Motor Vehicle Safety Standard No. 209, Seat belt assemblies, installed at each designated seating position. Seat belt assembly means any strap, webbing, or similar device designed to secure a person in a motor vehicle in order to mitigate the results of an accident, including all necessary buckles and other fasteners, and all hardware designed for installing the seat belt assembly in a motor vehicle.</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Inspect for required type seat belt assembly, Type 1 or Type 2, as installed by the vehicle manufacturer for each designated seating position. Type 1 seat belt assembly is a lap belt for pelvic restraint. Type 2 seat belt assembly is a combination of pelvic and upper torso restraints.</td>
              <td>(1) Not equipped with required type seat belt assembly as installed by the vehicle manufacturer for each designated seating position.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(2) Inspect for proper mounting location of seat belt assembly.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(2) Seat belt assembly is mounted improperly.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(3) Inspect for frayed, split or torn webbing or strap.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(3) Safety belt webbing or strap is frayed, split, or torn.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(4) Inspect for malfunctioning buckles.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(4) Belt buckles do not operate properly.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>(5) Inspect for loose or damaged anchorages.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(5) Belt anchorages are loose, badly corroded, missing, or not fastened to belt.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(6) Inspect mounting surfaces.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(6) Belt mounting surface is badly deformed, damaged, or corroded.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(7) Inspect retracting and release mechanisms.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(7) Retracting or release mechanisms do not operate properly.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.20</num>
    <heading>Motor, Transaxle, and Transmission Mounts.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Motor, transaxle, and transmission mounts include any mounting or securing device designed to hold the motor, transaxle, or transmission in a stable position.</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">Inspect for missing, worn, loose, or broken motor, transaxle, or transmission mounts and securing devices.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">Any motor, transaxle, or transmission mount or securing device is missing, worn, loose, or broken.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.21</num>
    <heading>Directional Control.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Inspect the directional control and reverse warning device.</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Directional Control (Forward and Reverse)—The directional forward and reverse control shall be clearly marked as to its directional position. Directional Control (Forward and Reverse) as described in SAE J2358, is incorporated by reference in <cite path="|11|14|09|.02">Regulation .02 of this chapter</cite>.</td>
              <td>(1) Directional control is not clearly marked as to its position.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(2) With the key/ignition switch in the on position, test the directional control positions for accuracy.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(2) Directional control does not accurately indicate the correct position and direction of travel.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(3) Reverse Warning Device—Every vehicle shall be equipped with a sound-producing device capable of 60db(A) minimum at the operator's ear level. The reverse warning device shall function at all times when the directional control is in the reverse position. Reverse Warning Device is described in SAE J2358, which incorporated by reference in <cite path="|11|14|09|.02">Regulation .02 of this chapter</cite>.</td>
              <td>(3) Reverse warning device fails to function when directional control is in the reverse position, or fails to emit a sound audible under normal conditions for a distance of at least 100 feet.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.22</num>
    <heading>Constant Velocity Joints and Universal Joints.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Constant velocity joints are generally found on drive axles. Universal joints are generally found on drive shafts and drive axles of vehicles.</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Inspect for attachment and worn, damaged, or loose universal joints and constant velocity joints.</td>
              <td>(1) Joint is not securely attached to the driving and/or driven member.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(2) Inspect for attachment and worn, damaged, or loose center support bearings on multisection drive shafts.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(2) There is any movement of a universal joint between the joint, bearing cap or cross bar, or both, or constant velocity joint is worn or has adverse movement.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td/>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(3) Any joint is frozen.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td/>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(4) Any constant velocity joint boot is torn or otherwise damaged so that lubrication cannot be contained.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td/>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(5) Center support bearing or attachment is worn, damaged, or loose.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.23</num>
    <heading>Modifications.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Modifications&amp;#151;The controlling party, owner, person, or organization responsible for the conduct of the operator and maintenance of the low speed vehicle may not perform, or allow to be performed, any modifications or additions which affect capacity, safe operation, maximum speed, or any change not in accordance with the operator's manual without the manufacturer's prior written authorization. Where authorized modifications have been made, the controlling party shall ensure that capacity, operation, warning, and maintenance instruction plates, tags, and decals are changed accordingly. Modifications are described in SAE J2358, which is incorporated by reference in <cite path="|11|14|09|.02">Regulation .02 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Inspect vehicle for signs of obvious modifications or additions that would affect capacity, safe operation, maximum speed, or changes not in accordance with vehicle owner's/operator's manual without the manufacturer's prior written authorization.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Vehicle contains any obvious modification that would affect capacity, safe operation, maximum speed, or other change not in accordance with vehicle owner's/operator's manual without the manufacturer's prior written authorization.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(2) Where authorized modifications have been made, the controlling party shall ensure that capacity, operation, warning, and maintenance instruction plates, tags, and decals are changed accordingly.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(2) Authorized modifications have been made, and the capacity, operation, warning, and maintenance instruction plates, tags, and decals are not changed accordingly.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(3) Vehicle owner's/operator's manual must accompany vehicle during inspection.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(3) Vehicle is presented for inspection without required owner's/operator's manual applicable for vehicle being inspected.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.24</num>
    <heading>Vehicle Identification Number.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>As required under Federal Motor Vehicle Safety Standards 49 CFR §571.500, Standard No. 500 Low Speed Vehicles, the manufacturers of all low speed vehicles shall legibly inscribe the vehicle identification number (VIN) that conforms to the requirements of 49 CFR Part 565 Vehicle Identification Number. Each VIN shall consist of 17 characters.</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Inspect vehicle for manufacturer's vehicle identification number.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Manufacturer's vehicle identification number is missing, altered, or fails to contain the properly required 17 characters.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td colspan="2" data-vertical-align="middle">Agency Note: State assigned VIN plates when attached in place of manufacturer's VIN are acceptable.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.25</num>
    <heading>Certification Label.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The federal motor vehicle safety certification label shall be affixed to the vehicle and identify it as a Low Speed Vehicle for the regulations under this chapter to apply.</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Inspect vehicle's federal motor vehicle safety certification label.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Vehicle's federal motor vehicle safety certification label is missing, altered, or fails to identify the vehicle as a Low Speed Vehicle.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.26</num>
    <heading>Safety Signs and Low Speed Vehicle Disclosure Decal.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Safety signs, when installed by the vehicle manufacturer, shall be permanently affixed to the vehicle and visible to the operator and occupants as designed by the vehicle manufacturer.</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Inspect for safety signs/warnings installed by the vehicle manufacturer.</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Any safety sign/warning, if originally installed by the manufacturer, has obviously been removed, tampered with, or is otherwise not permanently attached and visible as designed by the vehicle manufacturer.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Low Speed Vehicle Disclosure Decal. A low speed vehicle disclosure decal shall be permanently affixed to the underside of the roof of the vehicle near the windshield on the driver's side. This decal shall be approximately 3 inches high by 5 inches wide and contain the disclosure statement information noted below.</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Procedures:</th>
              <th>Reject Vehicle If:</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>(1) Inspect low speed vehicle disclosure decal for presence, mounting requirements, legibility, and the following required wording:</td>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">(1) Low speed vehicle disclosure decal is missing, not permanently affixed, improperly located, not clearly legible, or fails to contain the required wording.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td data-vertical-align="middle">LOW SPEED VEHICLE DISCLOSURE<br/>THIS VEHICLE IS CLASSIFIED AS A<br/>LOW SPEED VEHICLE. THIS VEHICLE:<br/>  •   Has a maximum speed of greater than 20 miles per hour, but less than<br/>     25 miles per hour;<br/>  •   May not be operated on a public highway with a speed limit in excess<br/>      of 30 miles per hour;<br/>  •   May be a hazard on the roadways if it impedes traffic; and<br/>  •   May subject the driver to citations for impeding traffic.</td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td colspan="2" data-vertical-align="middle">Agency Note: Consult vehicle manufacturer for any additional information.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-104">12-104</cite>(b), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|21-1104">21-1104</cite>(d), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|22-101">22-101</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|23-101">23-101</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|23-105">23-105</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland; 49 CFR §571.500</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-01-01">Regulations <cite path="|11|14|09|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|11|14|09|.27">.27</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective January 1, 2006 (33:4 Md. R. 349); emergency provision extended at 33:15 Md. R. 1275; emergency status expired December 28, 2006</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-03-09">Regulations <cite path="|11|14|09|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|11|14|09|.27">.27</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective March 9, 2007 (34:9 Md. R. 824); emergency provision expired September 5, 2007</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-09-10">Regulations <cite path="|11|14|09|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|11|14|09|.26">.26</cite> adopted effective September 10, 2007 (34:18 Md. R. 1580)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
