<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>Reporting Requirements</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="21|13|01|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Sole Source, Emergency, and Expedited Procurement Reports.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Requirements. The procedures for approval and reporting the award of a contract under sole source, emergency, or expedited situations are provided under <cite path="|21.05.05">COMAR 21.05.05</cite> when there is only one source and <cite path="|21.05.06">COMAR 21.05.06</cite> for all emergency and expedited procurements except for certain architectural services and engineering services which are governed by <cite path="|21.12.02">COMAR 21.12.02</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Annual Report of Sole Source, Emergency, and Expedited Procurements. Each Department shall prepare and submit an annual written report within 60 days following the close of the fiscal year to the Chief Procurement Officer of contracts awarded during the preceding fiscal year under sole source, emergency, or expedited procurement procedures (<cite path="|21.05.05">COMAR 21.05.05</cite> and <cite path="|21.05.06">21.05.06</cite>), whether the procurement was conducted by the Department or subject to review by the Department. The report shall, at a minimum:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Name each contractor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>State the amount and type of each contract;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Describe the supplies, services, maintenance, construction, or construction-related services procured or real property leased;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Describe the basis for the award;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Identify the Department or agency that awarded the contract;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Identify any agency official required to authorize the contract for award;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>State the award date of the procurement contract and the final date of the contract term;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>State the date the contract award notice was posted to eMaryland Marketplace; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>For procurements awarded under the emergency procurement method:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>State the number of days between the agency declaration of an emergency procurement and the contract award date;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>State the date of the emergency declaration; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The date the award was reported to the Board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Chief Procurement Officer shall submit to the Governor, the Legislative Policy Committee, the Senate Budget and Taxation Committee, the Senate Education, Health, and Environmental Affairs Committee, the House Appropriations Committee, the House Health and Government Operations Committee, and the Joint Audit and Evaluation Committee a consolidated report that includes each report required under <cite path="21|13|01|.01|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> within 90 days following the close of the fiscal year. A report to the General Assembly or a committee of the General Assembly under this regulation is subject to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|2-1257">State Government Article, §2-1257, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="21|13|01|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Annual Report of Service Contracts Exceeding $100,000 in Value.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each Department shall prepare and submit an annual written report within 60 days following the close of the fiscal year to the Chief Procurement Officer of contracts for services, construction-related services, architectural services, and engineering services that exceed $100,000 during the preceding fiscal year, whether the procurement was conducted by the Department or subject to review by the Department. The report shall, at a minimum:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Name each contractor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>State the amount and type of each contract; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Describe the work procured.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Chief Procurement Officer shall submit to the Governor, the Legislative Policy Committee, the Senate Budget and Taxation Committee, the Senate Education, Health, and Environmental Affairs Committee, the House Appropriations Committee, the House Health and Government Operations Committee, and the Joint Audit and Evaluation Committee a consolidated report that includes each report required under <cite path="21|13|01|.02|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> within 90 days following the close of the fiscal year. A report to the General Assembly or a committee of the General Assembly under this regulation is subject to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|2-1257">State Government Article, §2-1257, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="21|13|01|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Reports of the Small Business Reserve Program.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each procurement unit shall submit an expenditure plan on the small business reserve program as set forth in <cite path="21.11.01.06|D.">COMAR 21.11.01.06D</cite> to the Governor's Office of Small, Minority &amp; Women Business Affairs within 60 days after enactment of the annual budget bill by the General Assembly. The format of the expenditure plan shall be determined by the Governor's Office of Small, Minority &amp; Women Business Affairs.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Each procurement unit shall submit a report on the small business reserve program to the Governor’s Office of Small, Minority &amp; Women Business Affairs within 90 days after the end of each fiscal year, in a format determined by the Governor’s Office of Small, Minority &amp; Women Business Affairs, that includes at a minimum:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The total number and the dollar value of awards the unit made to certified small businesses under contracts designated as small business reserve contracts;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The total number and the dollar value of awards the unit made to certified small businesses under contracts not designated as small business reserve contracts, including purchase card procurements;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The total dollar value of awards the unit made under procurement contracts; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Other information required by the Governor's Office of Small, Minority &amp; Women Business Affairs.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>By December 31 of each year, the Governor's Office of Small, Minority &amp; Women Business Affairs shall summarize the information required in <cite path="21|13|01|.03|D.">§D of this regulation</cite> and report to the Board of Public Works and, subject to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|2-1257">State Government Article, §2-1257, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the Legislative Policy Committee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>On or before December 1 each year, the certification agency designated under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|14-303">State Finance and Procurement Article, §14-303</cite>b, Annotated Code of Maryland, in consultation with the Governor's Office of Small, Minority &amp; Women Business Affairs, shall submit to the Board of Public Works and, subject to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|2">State Government Article, §2</cite>–1257, Annotated Code of Maryland, to the Legislative Policy Committee a report on:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The status of the outreach program required under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|14-504">State Finance and Procurement Article, §14-504</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The total number and dollar value of awards made to small businesses owned by economically disadvantaged individuals under designated small business reserve contracts.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Repealed.</heading>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Annual Summary Report of Property Leased to the State.</heading>
    <text>The Secretary of General Services shall prepare and submit annually to the General Assembly a written report summarizing all new and renewal leasehold property agreements between State agencies and commercial landlords (Joint Chairmen's Report).</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Retention and Availability of Reports.</heading>
    <text>The reports required under this subtitle shall be retained for a period of at least 3 years and shall be made available to the general public only as provided by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 10, Subtitle 6, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Reporting of Protests and Contract Disputes.</heading>
    <text>Each procurement officer shall prepare and submit a written report to the procurement officer’s respective agency head concerning all protests and contract disputes. The frequency of this report shall be determined by the procurement agency. The report shall, at a minimum:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Name each bidder/contractor;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>State the amount/estimate and type of each contract; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Indicate the reasons for any time extensions in resolving a protest or contract dispute.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Report of Contracts Performed Outside of the State.</heading>
    <text>Each department shall prepare and submit an annual report within 90 days following the close of the fiscal year to the Governor and, subject to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|2-1257">State Government Article, §2-1257, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, to the General Assembly of each procurement contract within its jurisdiction awarded during the preceding fiscal year that was exempt from the notice requirements of State Finance and Procurement Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|13-103">13-103</cite>(c) and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|13-104">13-104</cite>(c), Annotated Code of Maryland, because the procurement contract reasonably was expected to be performed entirely outside the State or the District of Columbia. The report shall, at a minimum, include:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The name of each contractor;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The amount and type of each contract;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A description of the procurement; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The basis of the award and reasons why the contract required performance outside the State or the District of Columbia.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Report of Noncompetitive Negotiated Procurements.</heading>
    <text>The Department of General Services shall prepare and submit an annual report within 90 days following the close of the fiscal year to the Board and, subject to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|2-1257">State Government Article, §2-1257, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, to the General Assembly, of each class of procurement for which the noncompetitive negotiated procurement method has been approved. The report shall describe the reason for approving the use of that methodology for each class.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Procurement Policies and Procedures.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each State agency not governed by its own board, commission, council or authority that is required to report to the Board under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|12-401">State Finance and Procurement Article, §12-401, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, shall submit written procurement policies and procedures to the Board annually within 60 days following the close of the fiscal year. State agencies governed by their own board, commission, council, or authority shall submit the policies and procedures to the board, commission, council, or authority for approval. In fiscal years following the initial submission of the procurement policies and procedures, State agencies shall report only changes to the policies and procedures annually, unless the Board directs otherwise.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This regulation does not apply to agreements that are excluded from the definition of procurement contract in <cite path="21.01.02.01|B.">COMAR 21.01.02.01B</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Individual Surety Report — Repealed</heading>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Report on Unsolicited Proposal Outreach — Repealed</heading>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Report on Project Delivery Methods.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>On or before December 1 of each year, each agency procuring construction shall report to the Board of Public Works on the use of the design-build and construction management at risk project delivery methods for the prior fiscal year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The report format shall be determined by the Board of Public Works.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Report on Green Purchasing.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>On or before September 1 of each year, each procurement agency shall report to the Department of General Services on the agency’s procurement of environmentally preferable products and services during the preceding fiscal year, including the types and quantities of products and services procured. The report format shall be determined by the Department of General Services.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Green Purchasing Committee. On or before October 1 of each year, the Maryland Green Purchasing Committee, as established in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|14-410">State Finance and Procurement Article, §14-410, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, shall report to the General Assembly on the Committee’s activities and the progress made on the implementation of the Green Maryland Act of 2010. The report is subject to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|2-1257">State Government Article,  §2-1257, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Report on Veteran-Owned Small Business Participation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>On or before October 1 of each year, each procurement unit shall report to the Governor's Office of Small, Minority &amp; Women Business Affairs on the number and amount of contracts awarded to VSBEs and the effectiveness of the VSBE program, in accordance with <cite path="21.11.14.06">COMAR 21.11.14.06</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The report format shall be determined by the Governor's Office of Small, Minority &amp; Women Business Affairs.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Preferred Provider Reports.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Within 60 days after enactment of the State budget bill by the General Assembly, each unit and State aided or controlled entity shall report to the Department of General Services on the forecasted expenditures and contracts for the upcoming fiscal year. The report format shall be determined by the Department of General Services.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Within 90 days after the end of each fiscal year, a unit or State aided or controlled entity shall submit a report to the Department of General Services on the contracts awarded and payments made to preferred providers. The report format shall be determined by the Department of General Services.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Within 60 days after receipt of the reports required under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|14-110">State Finance and Procurement Article, §14-110(c)</cite>—(d), Annotated Code of Maryland, the Department of General Services shall provide a summary report to the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Board of Public Works;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Senate Education, Health, and Environmental Affairs Committee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>House Health and Government Operations Committee; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Legislative Policy Committee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.17</num>
    <heading>State Board of Elections Report.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definition.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In this regulation, the following term has the meaning indicated.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Defined Term — Doing Public Business.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Doing public business” means making or having a single contract with a single governmental entity involving cumulative consideration of at least $200,000.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Doing public business” does not include receiving a salary from a governmental entity.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Each governmental entity shall prepare and submit a quarterly report to the State Board of Elections within 10 Business Days following the close of each calendar quarter on a form provided by the State Board of Elections, pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|14-107">Election Law Article §14-107, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>. The report shall include the required information for any person that was awarded a contract that caused the person to be doing public business with the governmental entity during the preceding calendar quarter.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.18</num>
    <heading>Report on Cybersecurity Infrastructure Procurements.</heading>
    <text>On or before December 1 of each year, the Department of General Services shall submit a report to the Board of Public Works on procurements made under <cite path="21.02.01.04|B.|(10)">COMAR 21.02.01.04B(10)</cite> that shall include for each procurement:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The purposes of the procurement;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The name of the contractor;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The contract amount;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The method of procurement utilized;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The number of bidders who bid on the procurement; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The contract term.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">:Election Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|14-101">14-101</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|14-107">14-107</cite>; State Finance and Procurement Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|12-101">12-101</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|13-207">13-207</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|14-305">14-305</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|14-505">14-505</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|15-110">15-110</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|15-111">15-111</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsf|17-104">17-104</cite>; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1981-07-01">Effective date: July 1, 1981 (8:13 Md. R. II-5)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1982-10-12">Regulations .01B, .02, .03 and .04A amended as an emergency provision effective July 1, 1982 (9:15 Md. R. 1508); emergency status extended at 9:16 Md. R. 1601, 9:17 Md. R. 1698, 9:20 Md. R. 1979; adopted permanently effective October 12, 1982 (9:20 Md. R. 1982)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-05-06">Regulations .01B, .02, and .04 amended effective May 6, 1985 (12:9 Md. R. 817)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-04-07"><cite path="|21|13|01|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite>, C amended effective April 7, 2008 (35:7 Md. R. 751)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-01-09">Regulations <cite path="|21|13|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|21|13|01|.03">.03</cite>, .06 amended effective January 9, 1989 (15:27 Md. R. 3138)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-09-05"><cite path="|21|13|01|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective June 29, 2020 (47:13 Md. R. 643); September 5, 2022 (49:18 Md. R. 819)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-09-05"><cite path="|21|13|01|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective April 7, 2008 (35:7 Md. R. 751); September 5, 2022 (49:18 Md. R. 819)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-09-05"><cite path="|21|13|01|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective October 18, 1999 (26:21 Md. R. 1631); July 4, 2005 (32:13 Md. R. 1117); March 12, 2007 (34:5 Md. R. 562); June 29, 2020 (47:13 Md. R. 643); September 5, 2022 (49:18 Md. R. 819)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-07-15"><cite path="|21|13|01|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite> amended effective July 15, 2019 (46:14 Md. R. 623)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-04-29"><cite path="|21|13|01|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite>, B amended effective April 29, 2024 (51:8 Md. R. 369)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-03-03"><cite path="|21|13|01|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite> amended effective March 3, 2025 (52:4 Md. R. 221)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-03-03"><cite path="|21|13|01|.03|D.">Regulation .03D</cite> adopted effective March 3, 2025 (52:4 Md. R. 221)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-02-23"><cite path="|21|13|01|.04">Regulation .04</cite> repealed effective February 23, 2009 (36:4 Md. R. 355)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-06-29"><cite path="|21|13|01|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective June 29, 2020 (47:13 Md. R. 643)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-01-09">Regulations .08 and .09 adopted effective January 9, 1989 (15:27 Md. R. 3138)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-09-18"><cite path="|21|13|01|.08">Regulation .08</cite> amended effective April 7, 2008 (35:7 Md. R. 751); September 5, 2022 (49:18 Md. R. 819); September 18, 2023 (50:18 Md. R. 800)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-06-29"><cite path="|21|13|01|.09">Regulation .09</cite> amended effective April 7, 2008 (35:7 Md. R. 751); June 29, 2020 (47:13 Md. R. 643)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-03-13"><cite path="|21|13|01|.10">Regulation .10</cite> adopted effective March 13, 2006 (33:5 Md. R. 523)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-04-28"><cite path="|21|13|01|.10">Regulation .10</cite> amended effective April 28, 2014 (41:8 Md. R. 473)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-07-16"><cite path="|21|13|01|.11">Regulation .11</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective March 31, 2007 (34:9 Md. R. 824); adopted permanently effective July 16, 2007 (Md. R. 1246)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-03-16"><cite path="|21|13|01|.11">Regulation .11</cite> repealed effective March 16, 2015 (42:5 Md. R. 488)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-02-23"><cite path="|21|13|01|.11|A.">Regulation .11A</cite> amended effective February 23, 2009 (36:4 Md. R. 355)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-02-23"><cite path="|21|13|01|.12">Regulation .12</cite> adopted effective February 23, 2009 (36:4 Md. R. 355)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-03-16"><cite path="|21|13|01|.12">Regulation .12</cite> repealed effective March 16, 2015 (42:5 Md. R. 488)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-08-23"><cite path="|21|13|01|.13">Regulation .13</cite> adopted effective August 23, 2010 (37:17 Md. R. 1186)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-03-05"><cite path="|21|13|01|.14">Regulation .14</cite> adopted effective March 5, 2012 (39:4 Md. R. 338)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-03-16"><cite path="|21|13|01|.14|A.">Regulation .14A</cite> amended effective March 16, 2015 (42:5 Md. R. 488)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-09-18"><cite path="|21|13|01|.14|B.">Regulation .14B</cite> amended effective September 18, 2023 (50:18 Md. R. 800)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-07-23"><cite path="|21|13|01|.15">Regulation .15</cite> adopted effective July 23, 2012 (39:14 Md. R. 839)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-04-29"><cite path="|21|13|01|.15">Regulation .15</cite> amended effective April 29, 2024 (51:8 Md. R. 369)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-04-28"><cite path="|21|13|01|.16">Regulation .16</cite> adopted effective April 28, 2014 (41:8 Md. R. 473)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-03-11"><cite path="|21|13|01|.17">Regulation .17</cite> adopted effective March 11, 2019 (46:5 Md. R. 310)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-09-18"><cite path="|21|13|01|.18">Regulation .18</cite> adopted effective September 18, 2023 (50:18 Md. R. 800)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
