<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>08</num>
  <heading>Licensing and Certification of Veterinarians from Another State or Foreign Jurisdiction</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="15|14|08|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Requirements for Licensing and Certification.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General Requirements. Subject to the provisions of this chapter, the Board may license and certify an applying veterinarian who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is licensed:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In another state; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>In a foreign jurisdiction and is a graduate of a school accredited by the American Veterinary Medical Association;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Has satisfied one of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Engaged in the clinical practice of veterinary medicine continuously for the preceding 5 years from application;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Taught clinical veterinary medicine for the preceding 5 years from application at an institution accredited by the American Veterinary Medical Association; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Meets the requirements set forth in <cite path="15|14|08|.01|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Has paid all appropriate fees; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Has passed the Board Examination, consisting of a notarized statement submitted to the Board, attesting to the fact that the applicant has read and comprehends the laws and regulations governing the practice of veterinary medicine in this State.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Alternative Requirements to Requisite Clinical Experience. Subject to §§C and D of this regulation, in addition to meeting the requirements set forth in §A(1), (3), and (4) of this regulation, an applying veterinarian who fails to meet either §A(2)(a) or (b) of this regulation shall meet the following requirements before being considered for licensure by the Board:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The applicant has not been absent from the practice of clinical veterinary medicine for longer than 5 consecutive years prior to application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>During the preceding 5-year period, the applicant has practiced clinical veterinary medicine for the equivalent of 3 full years, at a minimum;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The applicant submits licensure verification, or letters of good standing, from all licensing boards with which the applicant is currently licensed, or has ever been licensed; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The applicant submits proof that during the 5-year period preceding application, the applicant maintained:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The type of continuing education accredited by the Board, as provided in <cite path="15.14.10.04">COMAR 15.14.10.04</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The minimum number of hours required of Maryland licensed veterinarians during the same time period.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Relocation Due to Government Service. If the applicant has not practiced clinical veterinary medicine for the equivalent of 3 full years during the 5-year period immediately preceding application to the Board in accordance with <cite path="15|14|08|.01|B.|(2)">§B(2) of this regulation</cite>, the applicant shall submit proof to the Board of the following, as a substitute for the required years of clinical practice under <cite path="15|14|08|.01|B.|(2)">§B(2) of this regulation</cite>:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>That either the applicant or the applicant's spouse served the government, and that this service resulted in relocation outside the United States; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>One of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>That the applicant has practiced clinical veterinary medicine for the equivalent of 10 full years over the applicant's veterinary career; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>That during the preceding 5-year period, the applicant has practiced clinical veterinary medicine for the equivalent 1 full year, at a minimum.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Acquiring Additional Continuing Education Credits. If the applicant has not taken the requisite type and number of continuing education credits during the 5-year period preceding application in accordance with §B(4)(a) and (b) of this regulation, the applicant shall take, and submit proof of having completed, a sufficient number of continuing education hours that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Meet the requirements set forth in §B(4)(a) and (b) of this regulation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Are clinically oriented or practical in nature.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An applicant shall submit proof of good moral character to the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-304">Agriculture Article, §2-304, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1979-06-15">Effective date: June 15, 1979 (6:12 Md. R. 1053)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1982-01-18"><cite path="|15|14|08|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective January 18, 1982 (9:1 Md. R. 23)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1987-05-18"><cite path="|15|14|08|.01">Regulation .01</cite> repealed and new Regulation .01 adopted effective May 18, 1987 (14:10 Md. R. 1172)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-06-25"><cite path="|15|14|08|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective June 25, 2001 (28:12 Md. R. 1112)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-03-10"><cite path="|15|14|08|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective September 17, 2007 (34:21 Md. R. 1911); amended permanently effective March 10, 2008 (35:5 Md. R. 642)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
