<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>13</num>
  <heading>Qualifications for Examination and Registration of a Veterinary Technician</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter applies to any person who makes application to the State Board of Veterinary Medical Examiners to be registered as a veterinary technician.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“AAVSB” means the American Association of Veterinary State Boards.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“AVMA” means the American Veterinary Medical Association.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Board" means the State Board of Veterinary Medical Examiners.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Candidate for graduation” means a student who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is within approximately 3 months of graduating college with a degree in veterinary technology; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has a letter sent from the college to the Board’s office, indicating the student’s expected date of graduation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Committee" means the Veterinary Technician Committee of the State Board of Veterinary Medical Examiners.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Maryland State Veterinary Technician Examination" means both the Veterinary Technician National Examination, and the State Board Examination for becoming a registered veterinary technician.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“PES” means the Professional Examination Service.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Registered veterinary technician" means a person who is registered with the Board as a veterinary technician.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“VTNE” means the Veterinary Technician National Examination.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="15|14|13|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Qualifications for Examination.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Eligibility Requirements for Graduates or Candidates for Graduation From Veterinary Technology Programs.   To be eligible to take the State Board Examination, an examination applicant shall provide a final transcript from a school showing that the applicant is a graduate or candidate for graduation from a veterinary technology program approved by the AVMA.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Eligibility Requirements for Applicants Who do not Meet the Educational Criteria Set Forth in <cite path="15|14|13|.03|A.">§A of this Regulation</cite>. To be eligible to take the State Board Examination, an examination applicant shall provide:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A school-authenticated transcript showing the applicant to be a holder of an associate’s degree or above, which includes a minimum of three credits with a passing grade of C or above in each of the following college level courses:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Biology I;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Biology II;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Microbiology;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Chemistry;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Anatomy and Physiology I; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Anatomy and Physiology II.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Proof of completion of 10,000 hours of work experience as a technician, with a signed affidavit from a supervising veterinarian specifying the number of hours worked and the dates worked;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A Maryland Technician Skill Assessment completed by a licensed veterinarian;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Proof of having completed a minimum of 24 hours of veterinary technician continuing education; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Proof of having completed a minimum of 24 hours of work as a veterinary technician in a veterinary emergency facility.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Board Examination. To take the State Board Examination, an applicant shall submit the following to the State Board within 1 year from the date the Board has received the application:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A complete and notarized examination application on a form provided by the Board or an online examination application developed by the Board and submitted online with a signature that may be electronic;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The application fee, as provided in <cite path="15.14.12.02">COMAR 15.14.12.02</cite>, in the form of a check or money order, payable to the State Board of Veterinary Medical Examiners or in the form of an online credit card payment or other electronic means deemed practical by the Board and submitted in conjunction with an online application developed by the Board;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A 2-inch by 3-inch headshot photograph of the applicant taken within 6 months of the application date, with the applicant's complete signature on the photograph or an electronic headshot photograph of the applicant taken within 6 months of the application date that is uploaded with an online application developed by the Board and attested to as true and accurate with a signature that may be electronic; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>One of the following documents:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A final transcript from a school, as set forth in <cite path="15|14|13|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Proof of completion of certain coursework, as set forth in <cite path="15|14|13|.03|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Unless timely filed and complete, an examination application shall be denied.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>VTNE.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Graduate of an AVMA-Accredited Program.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>To sit for a scheduled VTNE, an examination applicant who has graduated from an AVMA-accredited program shall submit to the AAVSB, by a date specified by the AAVSB, the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The information specified under <cite path="15|14|13|.03|A.|(1)|(a)">§A(1)(a) of this regulation</cite> pertaining to the applicant’s schooling, so that the AAVSB may determine whether the applicant is eligible to take this examination;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A completed AAVSB application to take the VTNE; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The requisite fees associated with taking the VTNE.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the AAVSB determines that the applicant is eligible to take the VTNE, it shall notify the applicant.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Other Type Graduate.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>To sit for a scheduled VTNE, an examination applicant who meets the eligibility requirements set forth in <cite path="15|14|13|.03|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> shall have the school from which the applicant graduated submit to the Board a school authenticated copy of the applicant’s final transcript and, if applicable, an English translation, for its review. The applicant shall also provide the following information in writing to the Board:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Name of applicant; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Telephone number or email address of applicant.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the Board determines that the applicant is eligible to take the VTNE, it shall notify the applicant and the AAVSB.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Upon notification of eligibility to take the VTNE, the applicant shall submit the following to the AAVSB:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A completed AAVSB application to take the VTNE; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The requisite fees associated with taking the VTNE.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Maryland Examination — Time and Place.</heading>
    <text>The AAVSB shall specify the times and locations for taking the VTNE.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Maryland State Examination — Subject Matter.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Exam Format. The Maryland State Veterinary Technician Examination is divided into two parts:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The VTNE; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The State Board Examination.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The VTNE, written by veterinarians and veterinary technicians affiliated with the AAVSB, AVMA, the National Association of Veterinary Technicians of America and the Canadian Association of Animal Health Technologists and Technicians, tests a candidate's general knowledge on subjects relating to veterinary technology.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>To pass the State Board Examination, an applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Read and comprehend the laws and regulations governing registered veterinary technicians in this State; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Sign a statement before a notary public or provide an electronic signature in conjunction with an online application developed by the Board attesting to this fact.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Examination — Passing Grade.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A candidate shall pass the VTNE. The VTNE shall be administered for those candidates who have not previously taken and passed the VTNE. Candidates who have previously taken and passed the VTNE shall provide the Committee with a report from the AAVSB’s Veterinary Information Verifying Agency showing that the candidate has passed the VTNE.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Passing Score for the VTNE. The PES shall establish the passing score for the VTNE.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>State Board's Acceptance of Passing Scores on Previously Taken Tests. If an applicant has previously taken and passed the Maryland State Veterinary Technician Examination, the State Board shall accept the applicant's score if the score is not more than 5 years old. After this 5-year period, the applicant shall take and pass this examination to be a registered veterinary technician if the applicant does not meet the qualifications set forth in <cite path="|15|14|13|.11">Regulation .11 of this chapter</cite> for veterinary technicians who have practiced in another state or foreign jurisdiction.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Notice of Pass or Fail of VTNE.</heading>
    <text>The AAVSB shall notify each candidate if the candidate passes or fails. Upon request, a candidate may be given the candidate's grade.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Taking Examination After Failure.</heading>
    <text>After a failure on the VTNE, a candidate may take another examination by:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Making application directly to the AAVSB; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Meeting all other conditions as specified by the AAVSB or its authorized representative.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Fee Refunds.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The fee associated with the State Board Examination is non-refundable.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The fee associated with the VTNE shall be refunded in accordance with AAVSB’s policy on refunds.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Registration.</heading>
    <text>The Board shall register an applicant as a registered veterinary technician who:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Meets the requirements of this chapter;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Meets the Committee's educational requirements;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Passes the Committee's examination;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Is of good moral character; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Is at least 18 years old.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Requirements of Veterinary Technicians from Another State or Foreign Jurisdiction.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Subject to the provisions of this regulation, the Board may register an applying veterinary technician who submits proof of meeting the following requirements:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is registered in another state or a foreign jurisdiction and is a graduate of a school accredited by the American Veterinary Medical Association;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Has been employed in a clinical practice as a veterinary technician continuously for the 5 years preceding application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Has paid all appropriate fees, as provided in <cite path="15.14.12.02">COMAR 15.14.12.02</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Has passed the Maryland State Veterinary Technician Examination, as defined in <cite path="|15|14|13|.02|B.|(6)">Regulation .02B(6) of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An applicant shall submit proof of good moral character to the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Registration Renewal.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A registration is issued for 3 years and expires on June 30 on the third year after the date issued, unless the applicant renews the applicant's registration by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Submitting a renewal application on the form that the Committee requires;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Paying to the Board a renewal fee, as provided in <cite path="15.14.12.02">COMAR 15.14.12.02</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Satisfactorily completing Committee-approved continuing education requirements, as provided in <cite path="|15.14.16">COMAR 15.14.16</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board shall renew a lapsed registration of less than 5 years, if the applicant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Submits a renewal application in a manner the Board requires;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Submits proof of satisfactorily completing at least 8 hours of Committee-approved continuing educational requirements, as provided in <cite path="|15.14.16">COMAR 15.14.16</cite>, for each year the registration is considered to be lapsed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Pays to the Board a renewal fee; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Is otherwise entitled to be registered.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Board shall reinstate a lapsed registration of 5 years or more if the applicant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Submits a reinstatement application in a manner the Board requires;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Submits proof of satisfactorily completing at least 8 hours of Committee-approved continuing educational requirements, as provided in <cite path="|15.14.16">COMAR 15.14.16</cite>, for each year the registration is considered to be lapsed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Pays to the Board a reinstatement fee; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Submits letters of good standing, as applicable, from any other state veterinary boards under which the applicant is, or has been, registered.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="15|14|13|.13">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Duties and Restrictions on Registered Veterinary Technicians.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A registered veterinary technician may not:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Diagnose;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Offer prognosis;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Prescribe:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Drugs;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Medication;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Appliances;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Perform surgery; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Initiate treatment without prior instruction by a veterinarian.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A registered veterinary technician may perform the following procedures under the responsible direct supervision of a veterinarian:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Inducing anesthesia by intramuscular injection;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Applying casts and splints;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Simple dental extractions of loose teeth that do not involve flaps or tooth sectioning;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Suturing of existing surgical skin or gingival incisions; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Accessing a small working stock of Schedule II drugs under separate lock.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A registered veterinary technician may perform anesthetic induction by inhalation or intravenous injection if the veterinarian is able to maintain direct visual supervision of the technician’s performance.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A registered veterinary technician may administer medication and render other auxiliary or supporting assistance not referenced in <cite path="15|14|13|.13|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> under the responsible direct supervision of a licensed veterinarian.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Emergency Conditions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Under emergency conditions only, the following activities may be performed by a registered veterinary technician before a veterinarian’s initial examination of an animal:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Provide supportive care and first aid; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Follow written protocols for specific conditions, as established by the veterinarian.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a veterinarian is not available to perform an initial examination of an animal that is presented as an emergency, a registered veterinary technician shall notify the animal’s owner of the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Veterinarian’s unavailability;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Estimated time of arrival of the veterinarian; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Estimated distance to another veterinary hospital.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If employed at a veterinary hospital, a veterinary technician shall display at that facility the registration that the Board issued to the veterinary technician.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Sanctions.</heading>
    <text>The Board may refuse to register an applicant, suspend or revoke the registration, reprimand and censure, or place on probation any registered veterinary technician, if the registered veterinary technician:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Practices veterinary medicine;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Fraudulently or deceptively obtains a registration;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Is professionally, physically, or mentally incompetent;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Acts in an unprofessional or immoral manner;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Is convicted of a felony or a crime involving moral turpitude;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Is convicted of a violation of any federal or State law relating to narcotic drugs;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Is grossly negligent or deliberately cruel to an animal;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Violates any provision of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-309">Agriculture Article, §2-309, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>This chapter; or</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Is determined by the Board to be incompetent as a registered veterinary technician.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-309">Agriculture Article, §2-309, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-10-07">Regulations <cite path="|15|14|13|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|15|14|13|.13">.13</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective March 13, 1985 (12:7 Md. R. 696); emergency status expired June 1, 1985; adopted permanently effective October 7, 1985 (12:20 Md. R. 1930)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-12-12"><cite path="|15|14|13|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective July 27, 1998 (25:15 Md. R. 1194); December 12, 2002 (29:24 Md. R. 1920)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-12-12"><cite path="|15|14|13|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite> amended effective October 11, 1993 (20:20 Md. R. 1573); December 12, 2002 (29:24 Md. R. 1920)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-09-13"><cite path="|15|14|13|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective May 24, 2004 (31:12 Md. R. 908); amended permanently effective September 13, 2004 (31:18 Md. R. 1351)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-12-12"><cite path="|15|14|13|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective December 12, 2002 (29:24 Md. R. 1920)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-12-12"><cite path="|15|14|13|.05|A.">Regulation .05A</cite>, B amended effective December 12, 2002 (29:24 Md. R. 1920)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-07-27"><cite path="|15|14|13|.05|C.">Regulation .05C</cite> amended effective July 27, 1998 (25:15 Md. R. 1194)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-12-12"><cite path="|15|14|13|.06|A.">Regulation .06A</cite> amended effective December 12, 2002 (29:24 Md. R. 1920)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-12-12"><cite path="|15|14|13|.06|B.">Regulation .06B</cite> amended effective March 20, 1989 (16:5 Md. R. 630); March 9, 1998 (25:5 Md. R. 370); December 12, 2002 (29:24 Md. R. 1920)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-12-12"><cite path="|15|14|13|.06|C.">Regulation .06C</cite> adopted effective December 12, 2002 (29:24 Md. R. 1920)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-12-12"><cite path="|15|14|13|.08">Regulation .08</cite> amended effective December 12, 2002 (29:24 Md. R. 1920)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-07-27"><cite path="|15|14|13|.10">Regulation .10</cite> amended effective July 27, 1998 (25:15 Md. R. 1194)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-10-11"><cite path="|15|14|13|.11|A.">Regulation .11A</cite> amended effective October 11, 1993 (20:20 Md. R. 1573)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-09-13"><cite path="|15|14|13|.11|A.">Regulation .11A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective May 24, 2004 (31:12 Md. R. 908); amended permanently effective September 13, 2004 (31:18 Md. R. 1351)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-07-27"><cite path="|15|14|13|.12">Regulation .12</cite> amended effective July 27, 1998 (25:15 Md. R. 1194)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1996-12-02"><cite path="|15|14|13|.12|B.">Regulation .12B</cite> amended and C adopted effective December 2, 1996 (23:24 Md. R. 1684)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-03-09"><cite path="|15|14|13|.12|D.">Regulation .12D</cite> adopted effective March 9, 1998 (25:5 Md. R. 370)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-07-27"><cite path="|15|14|13|.13">Regulation .13</cite> amended effective July 27, 1998 (25:15 Md. R. 1194)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-02-27" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised as an emergency provision effective December 1, 2005 (32:26 Md. R. 1994); revised permanently effective February 27, 2006 (33:4 Md. R. 353)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-10-15"><cite path="|15|14|13|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective April 4, 2011 (38:7 Md. R. 433); October 15, 2012 (39:20 Md. R. 1308)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-10-15"><cite path="|15|14|13|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective April 4, 2011 (38:7 Md. R. 433); October 15, 2012 (39:20 Md. R. 1308)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-03-16"><cite path="|15|14|13|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite> amended effective March 16, 2015 (42:5 Md. R. 487)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-12-17"><cite path="|15|14|13|.03|C.">Regulation .03C</cite> amended effective December 17, 2018 (45:25 Md. R. 1206)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-04-04"><cite path="|15|14|13|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective January 1, 2007 (33:26 Md. R. 1997); April 4, 2011 (38:7 Md. R. 433)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-04-04"><cite path="|15|14|13|.05|B.">Regulation .05B</cite> amended effective April 4, 2011 (38:7 Md. R. 433)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-12-17"><cite path="|15|14|13|.05|C.">Regulation .05C</cite> amended effective December 17, 2018 (45:25 Md. R. 1206)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-04-04"><cite path="|15|14|13|.06|A.">Regulation .06A</cite>, B amended effective April 4, 2011 (38:7 Md. R. 433)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-01-01"><cite path="|15|14|13|.06|B.">Regulation .06B</cite> amended effective January 1, 2007 (33:26 Md. R. 1997)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-04-04"><cite path="|15|14|13|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective April 4, 2011 (38:7 Md. R. 433)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-04-04"><cite path="|15|14|13|.08">Regulation .08</cite> amended effective April 4, 2011 (38:7 Md. R. 433)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-04-04"><cite path="|15|14|13|.09">Regulation .09</cite> amended effective April 4, 2011 (38:7 Md. R. 433)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-03-16"><cite path="|15|14|13|.11|A.">Regulation .11A</cite> amended effective October 15, 2012 (39:20 Md. R. 1308); March 16, 2015 (42:5 Md. R. 487)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-08-13"><cite path="|15|14|13|.12">Regulation .12</cite> amended effective August 13, 2007 (34:16 Md. R. 1433)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-12-17"><cite path="|15|14|13|.12|B.">Regulation .12B</cite>, C amended effective December 17, 2018 (45:25 Md. R. 1206)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-10-15"><cite path="|15|14|13|.13">Regulation .13</cite> amended effective October 15, 2012 (39:20 Md. R. 1308)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
