<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>16</num>
  <heading>Continuing Education Requirements for Registered Veterinary Technicians</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter applies to any person registered to practice veterinary technology in the State.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>"AVMA" means the American Veterinary Medical Association.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>"Board" means the Maryland State Board of Veterinary Medical Examiners.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>"Committee" means the Veterinary Technician Committee of the State Board of Veterinary Medical Examiners.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>“Continuing education courses” means courses that offer credit hours and includes seminars, lectures, conferences, workshops, and other programs that offer credit hours.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>"Credit hour" means 1 program hour.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>"Unused credit hour" means a credit hour which a practitioner earned in a given licensing year but did not use toward fulfilling the continuing education requirement for that year.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="15|14|16|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Registration Renewal.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="15|14|16|.03|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, the Board may not renew a veterinary technician's registration unless that veterinary technician has earned 24 credit hours of continuing education during the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>36 months preceding the beginning of the new registration period; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>72 months preceding the beginning of the new registration period provided, however, that any credit hours earned before the 36 months preceding the beginning of the new registration period are unused credit hours.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board may conditionally renew a veterinary technician's registration even if the requirements of <cite path="15|14|16|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> have not been met if the veterinary technician submits to the Board:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Satisfactory proof that these requirements reasonably cannot be met because of exigent circumstances, such as meeting or recently completing an armed services commitment; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A plan showing that the veterinary technician will, within a reasonable period of time, complete the requirements of <cite path="15|14|16|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Accreditation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Accreditation of continuing education courses by the Committee shall be based upon content. Continuing education courses shall be directed towards improvement, advancement, enhancement, and extension of professional skills and knowledge relating to the practice of veterinary technology.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Credit hours may be approved for the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Continuing veterinary technician education programs given by colleges of veterinary medicine or veterinary technology approved by the AVMA;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Lectures and scheduled courses at national and regional meetings of the AVMA;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Continuing education courses given or arranged by the AVMA;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Local, state, regional, or national continuing professional education courses, including graduate and postgraduate studies, institutes, seminars, lectures, conferences, workshops, and extension studies; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Continuing education courses available online.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>After review of course content, the Committee may withdraw its approval of a previously accredited continuing education course.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Credit Substantiation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A veterinary technician shall keep an accurate attendance record of approved continuing education courses.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board may request verification from a veterinary technician concerning the technician's attendance at any continuing education course.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If a veterinary technician reports false or misleading information to the Board, the veterinary technician may be subject to Board discipline following a hearing.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Failure to Meet Requirements.</heading>
    <text>The Board may refuse to reregister a registered veterinary technician who fails to meet the continuing education requirements of this chapter. However, if a veterinary technician intends to practice veterinary technology over the next registration period, the veterinary technician shall renew the technician's registration not later than June 30 of each 3-year period by submitting to the Board proof of compliance with the requirements of this chapter.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|2-309">Agriculture Article, §2-309, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-08-13">Effective date: August 13, 2007 (34:16 Md. R. 1433)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-03-06"><cite path="|15|14|16|.02|D.">Regulation .02D</cite>—F adopted effective March 6, 2023 (50:4 Md. R. 123)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-03-06"><cite path="|15|14|16|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite> amended effective June 29, 2009 (36:13 Md. R. 900); March 6, 2023 (50:4 Md. R. 123)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-03-06"><cite path="|15|14|16|.04|B.">Regulation .04B</cite> amended effective March 6, 2023 (50:4 Md. R. 123)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
