<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>11</num>
  <heading>Annual Financial Reporting</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|05|11|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose and Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Purpose. The purpose of this chapter is to improve the Maryland Insurance Administration's surveillance of the financial condition of insurers by requiring:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An annual audit of financial statements reporting the financial position and the results of operations of insurers by independent certified public accountants;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Communication of Internal Control Related Matters Noted in an Audit; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Management's Report on Internal Control over Financial Reporting.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Scope. Except as provided in <cite path="31|05|11|.01|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, an insurer is subject to this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Exemptions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Insurers having direct premiums written in this State of less than $1,000,000 in any calendar year and less than 1,000 policyholders or certificate holders of direct written policies nationwide at the end of the calendar year are exempt from this chapter for the year, unless the Commissioner makes a specific finding that compliance is necessary for the Commissioner to carry out statutory responsibilities. Insurers having assumed premiums pursuant to contracts or treaties of reinsurance of $1,000,000 or more are not exempt.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Foreign or alien insurers filing the audited financial report in another state, pursuant to that state's requirement for filing of audited financial reports, which has been found by the Commissioner to be substantially similar to the requirements herein, are exempt from Regulations <cite path="|31|05|11|.03">.03</cite>—<cite path="|31|05|11|.12">.12</cite> of this chapter if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A copy of the audited financial report, Communication of Internal Control Related Matters Noted in an Audit, and the Accountant's Letter of Qualifications that are filed with the other state are filed with the Commissioner in accordance with the filing dates specified in Regulations .03, .10, and .11 of this chapter, or Canadian insurers may submit copies of the accountants' reports as filed with the Office of the Superintendent of Financial Institutions, Canada; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A copy of any Notification of Adverse Financial Condition Report filed with the other state is filed with the Commissioner within the time specified in <cite path="|31|05|11|.09">Regulation .09 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Foreign or alien insurers required to file Management's Report on Internal Control over Financial Reporting in another state are exempt from filing the report in Maryland, provided the other state has substantially similar reporting requirements, and the report is filed with the Commissioner of the other state within the time specified.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>This chapter does not prohibit, preclude, or in any way limit the Maryland Insurance Commissioner from ordering or conducting or performing examinations of insurers under the rules and regulations of the Maryland Insurance Administration, and the practices and procedures of the Maryland Insurance Administration.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|05|11|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Accountant" or "independent certified public accountant" means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An independent certified public accountant or accounting firm in good standing with the American Institute of Certified Public Accountants (AICPA) and in all states in which the accountant is licensed to practice; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For a Canadian or a British company, a Canadian-chartered or British-chartered accountant.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Affiliate of", or person "affiliated with", a specific person, means a person that directly, or indirectly through one or more intermediaries, controls, or is controlled by, or is under common control with, the person specified.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Audit Committee.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Audit committee” means a committee, or equivalent body, established by the board of directors of an entity for the purpose of overseeing the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Accounting and financial reporting processes of an insurer or group of insurers;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Internal audit function of an insurer or group of insurers; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>External audits of financial statements of the insurer or group of insurers.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Audit committee" at the election of the controlling person pursuant to Regulation .13H—J of this chapter, may, for one or more controlled insurers, be deemed to be the audit committee of any entity that controls a group of insurers.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>"Audit committee" means the insurer's entire board of directors, if an audit committee is not designated by the insurer.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Audited financial report" means and includes those items specified in <cite path="|31|05|11|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Group of insurers" means those insurers included in the reporting requirements of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|7-601">Insurance Article, §7-601, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or a set of insurers as identified by management, for the purpose of assessing the effectiveness of internal control over financial reporting.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Indemnification" means an agreement of indemnity or a release from liability where the intent or effect is to shift or limit in any manner the potential liability of the person or firm for failure to adhere to applicable auditing or professional standards, whether or not resulting in part from knowing of other misrepresentations made by the insurer or its representatives.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Independent board member" has the same meaning as described in Regulation .13E and F of this chapter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Insurer.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Insurer" means an insurer holding a certificate of authority issued by the Commissioner, or authorized to engage in the insurance business in this State, as defined in Insurance Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|1-101">1-101</cite>(v) and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|4-101">4-101</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Insurer" includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The Maryland Automobile Insurance Fund;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The Medical Mutual Liability Insurance Society of Maryland;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Nonprofit health service plans;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Dental plan organizations;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Health maintenance organizations;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Managed care organizations; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Provider-sponsored organizations.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“Internal audit function” means a person or persons that provide independent, objective, and reasonable assurance designed to add value and improve an organization’s operations and accomplish its objectives by bringing a systematic, disciplined approach to evaluate and improve the effectiveness of risk management and control and governance processes.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Internal control over financial reporting" means a process effected by an entity's board of directors, management, and other personnel designed to provide reasonable assurance regarding the reliability of the financial statements, that is, those items specified in Regulation .04B(2)—(6) of this chapter, and includes those policies and procedures that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Pertain to the maintenance of records that, in reasonable detail, accurately and fairly reflect the transactions and dispositions of assets;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Provide reasonable assurance that:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Transactions are recorded as necessary to permit preparation of the financial statements, that is, those items specified in Regulation .04B(2)—(6) of this chapter; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Receipts and expenditures are being made only in accordance with authorizations of management and directors; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Provide reasonable assurance regarding prevention or timely detection of unauthorized acquisition, use, or disposition of assets that could have a material effect on the financial statements, that is, those items specified in Regulation .04B(2)—(6) of this chapter.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"NAIC" means the National Association of Insurance Commissioners.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>"SEC" means the United States Securities and Exchange Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>"Section 404" means Section 404 of the Sarbanes-Oxley Act of 2002, and the SEC's rules and regulations promulgated under it.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>"Section 404 report" means Management's Report on Internal Control over Financial Reporting as defined by the SEC, and the related attestation report of the independent certified public accountant as described in <cite path="31|05|11|.02|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>"SOX compliant entity" means an entity that either is required to be compliant with, or voluntarily is compliant with, all of the following provisions of the Sarbanes-Oxley Act of 2002:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The preapproval requirements of §201 (§10A(i) of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The audit committee independence requirements of §301 (§10A(m)(3) of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934); and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The internal control over financial reporting requirements of §404 (Item 308 of SEC Regulation S—K).</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>Workpapers.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Workpapers" means the records kept by the independent certified public accountant of the procedures followed, the tests performed, the information obtained, and the conclusions reached pertinent to the accountant's audit of the financial statements of an insurer.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Workpapers" may include the following documents prepared or obtained by the independent certified public accountant in the course of an audit of the financial statements of an insurer and which support the accountant's opinion:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Audit planning documentation;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Work programs;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Analyses;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Memoranda;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Letters of confirmation and representation;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Abstracts of company documents; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Schedules or commentaries.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Filing and Extensions for Filing Audited Financial Reports; Audit Committee Appointment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Insurers shall have an annual audit by an independent certified public accountant, and shall file an audited financial report with the Commissioner for the year ended December 31 immediately preceding, for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Nonprofit health service plans, on or before March 1 of each year;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Dental plan organizations, on or before April 1 of each year;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Health maintenance organizations, on or before June 1 of each year, or if approved by the Commissioner, within 150 days after the date their fiscal year ends; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>All other insurers, on or before June 1 of each year.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Extensions of the filing date may be granted by the Commissioner for up to 30-day periods upon a showing by the insurer and its independent certified public accountant of the reasons for requesting an extension and determination by the Commissioner of good cause for an extension.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The request for extension shall be submitted in writing not less than 10 days prior to the due date in sufficient detail to permit the Commissioner to make an informed decision with respect to the requested extension.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If an extension is granted in accordance with the provisions in §§B and C of this regulation, a similar extension of 30 days is granted to the filing of Management's Report on Internal Control over Financial Reporting.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An insurer required to file an annual audited financial report pursuant to this chapter shall designate a group of individuals as constituting its audit committee, as defined in <cite path="|31|05|11|.02|B.|(3)">Regulation .02B(3) of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The audit committee of an entity that controls an insurer may be deemed to be the insurer's audit committee for purposes of this chapter at the election of the controlling person.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|05|11|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Contents of Annual Audited Financial Report.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The annual audited financial report shall report the financial position of the insurer as of the end of the most recently ended calendar year and the results of its operations, cash flows, and changes in capital and surplus for the year then ended in conformity with statutory accounting practices prescribed, or otherwise permitted, by the department of insurance of the state of domicile.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The annual audited financial report shall include the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Report of independent certified public accountant;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Balance sheet reporting admitted assets, liabilities, capital, and surplus;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Statement of operations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Statement of cash flow;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Statement of changes in capital and surplus; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Notes to financial statements, which shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be those required by the appropriate NAIC Annual Statement Instructions and the NAIC Accounting Practices and Procedures Manual; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Include a reconciliation of differences, if any, between the audited statutory financial statements and the annual statement filed with the Commissioner, with a written description of the nature of these differences.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Form.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="31|05|11|.04|C.|(2)">§C(2) of this regulation</cite>, the financial statements included in the audited financial report shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be prepared in a form and using language and groupings substantially the same as the relevant sections of the annual statement of the insurer filed with the Commissioner; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Be comparative, presenting the amounts as of December 31 of the most recently ended year, and the amounts as of the immediately preceding December 31.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In the first year in which an insurer is required to file an audited financial report, the comparative data may be omitted.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|05|11|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Designation of Independent Certified Public Accountant.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An insurer required by this chapter to file an annual audited financial report shall, within 60 days after becoming subject to the requirement:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Register with the Commissioner in writing the name and address of the independent certified public accountant or accounting firm retained to conduct the annual audit set forth in this regulation; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Register the name and address of their retained independent certified public accountant not less than 6 months before the date when the first audited financial report is to be filed if the insurer has not retained an independent certified public accountant on the effective date of this chapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The insurer shall obtain a letter from the accountant, and file a copy with the Commissioner:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Stating that the accountant is aware of the provisions of the insurance code and the regulations of the insurance department of the state of domicile that relate to accounting and financial matters; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Affirming that the accountant will express an opinion on the financial statements in terms of their conformity to the statutory accounting practices prescribed or otherwise permitted by that insurance department, specifying such exceptions as the accountant may believe appropriate.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If an accountant who was the accountant for the immediately preceding filed audited financial report is dismissed or resigns, the insurer shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within 5 business days notify the Commissioner of this event;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Furnish the Commissioner with a separate letter within 10 business days of the above notification stating whether in the 24 months preceding the event there were any disagreements with the former accountant on any matter of accounting principles or practices, financial statement disclosure, or auditing scope or procedure, which disagreements, if not resolved to the satisfaction of the former accountant, would have caused him to make reference to the subject matter of the disagreement in connection with his opinion;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>In writing, request the former accountant to furnish a letter addressed to the insurer stating whether the accountant agrees with the statements contained in the insurer's letter and, if not, stating the reasons for which the accountant does not agree; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Furnish the responsive letter from the former accountant to the Commissioner together with its own letter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Disagreements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The disagreements required to be reported under <cite path="31|05|11|.05|C.|(2)">§C(2) of this regulation</cite> include both those resolved to the former accountant's satisfaction and those not resolved to the former accountant's satisfaction.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Disagreements contemplated by <cite path="31|05|11|.05|C.|(2)">§C(2) of this regulation</cite> are those that occur at the decision-making level, that is, between personnel of the insurer responsible for presentation of its financial statements and personnel of the accounting firm responsible for rendering its report.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|05|11|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Qualifications of Independent Certified Public Accountant.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner may not recognize a person or firm as a qualified independent certified public accountant if the person or firm:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is not in good standing with the American Institute of Certified Public Accountants (AICPA) and in all states in which the accountant is licensed to practice, or, for a Canadian or British company, that is not a chartered accountant; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Has either directly or indirectly entered into an agreement of indemnity or release from liability, collectively referred to as indemnification, with respect to the audit of the insurer.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Except as otherwise provided in this chapter, the Commissioner shall recognize an independent certified public accountant as qualified as long as the accountant conforms to the standards of the profession, as contained in:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Code of Professional Ethics of the AICPA; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Either:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The rules and regulations, code of ethics, and rules of professional conduct of the Maryland Board of Public Accountancy; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A similar code.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A qualified independent certified public accountant may enter into an agreement with an insurer to have disputes relating to an audit resolved by mediation or arbitration. However, in the event of a delinquency proceeding commenced against the insurer under the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin">Insurance Article, Title 9, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, the mediation or arbitration provisions shall operate at the option of the statutory successor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Lead or Coordinating Audit Partner.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The lead or coordinating audit partner having primary responsibility for the audit may not act in that capacity for more than 5 consecutive years. The person shall be disqualified from acting in that or a similar capacity for the same company or its insurance subsidiaries or affiliates for a period of 5 consecutive years.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An insurer may make application to the Commissioner for relief from the rotation requirement in <cite path="31|05|11|.06|D.|(1)">§D(1) of this regulation</cite> on the basis of unusual circumstances.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The application for relief from the rotation requirement in <cite path="31|05|11|.06|D.|(1)">§D(1) of this regulation</cite> shall be made at least 30 days before the end of the calendar year. The Commissioner may consider the following factors in determining if the relief should be granted:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Number of partners, expertise of the partners, or the number of insurance clients in the currently registered firm;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Premium volume of the insurer; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Number of jurisdictions in which the insurer transacts business.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The insurer shall file, with its annual statement filing, the approval for relief from <cite path="31|05|11|.06|D.|(1)">§D(1) of this regulation</cite> with the states that it is licensed in or doing business in, and with the NAIC. If the nondomestic state accepts electronic filing with the NAIC, the insurer shall file the approval in an electronic format acceptable to the NAIC.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner may not recognize as a qualified independent certified public accountant, or accept an annual audited financial report, prepared in whole or in part by, a natural person who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Has been convicted of fraud, bribery, a violation of the Racketeer Influenced and Corrupt Organizations Act, 18 U.S.C. §§1961—1968, or any dishonest conduct or practices under federal or state law;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Has been found to have violated the insurance laws of Maryland with respect to any previous reports submitted under this regulation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Has demonstrated a pattern or practice of failing to detect or disclose material information in previous reports filed under the provisions of this chapter; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Has violated any provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbo">Business Occupations and Professions Article, Title 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or any rule of professional conduct established by the State Board of Public Accountancy.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Hearing to Determine Qualifications.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Commissioner may, as provided in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|4-118">Insurance Article, §4-118, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, hold a hearing to determine whether an independent certified public accountant is qualified.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>After considering the evidence presented, the Commissioner may:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Rule that the accountant is not qualified for purposes of expressing an opinion on the financial statements in the annual audited financial report made pursuant to this chapter; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Require the insurer to replace the accountant with another whose relationship with the insurer is qualified within the meaning of this chapter.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Accountants That Provide Non-Audit Services.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Commissioner may not recognize as a qualified independent certified public accountant, or accept an annual audited financial report, prepared in whole or in part, by an accountant who provides to an insurer, contemporaneously with the audit, the following non-audit services:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Bookkeeping or other services related to the accounting records or financial statements of the insurer;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Financial information systems design and implementation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Appraisal or valuation services, fairness opinions, or contribution-in-kind reports;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Actuarially oriented advisory services involving the determination of amounts recorded in the financial statements;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Internal audit outsourcing services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Management functions or human resources;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Broker or dealer, investment adviser, or investment banking services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Legal services or expert services unrelated to the audit; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Any other services that the Commissioner determines, by regulation, are impermissible.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The actuarially oriented advisory services under <cite path="31|05|11|.06|G.|(1)|(d)">§G(1)(d) of this regulation</cite> do not include an accountant assisting an insurer in understanding the methods, assumptions, and inputs used in the determination of amounts recorded in the financial statement only if it is reasonable to conclude that the services provided will not be subject to audit procedures during an audit of the insurer's financial statements.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The actuarially oriented advisory services under <cite path="31|05|11|.06|G.|(1)|(d)">§G(1)(d) of this regulation</cite> do not include an accountant's actuary issuing an actuarial opinion or certification opinion on an insurer's reserves if the following conditions are met:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Neither the accountant nor the accountant's actuary has performed any management functions or made any management decisions;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The insurer has competent personnel, or engages a third-party actuary, to estimate the reserves for which management takes responsibility; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The accountant's actuary tests the reasonableness of the reserves after the insurer's management has determined the amount of the reserves.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>In general, the principles of independence with respect to services provided by the qualified independent certified public accountant are largely predicated on three basic principles, violations of which would impair the accountant's independence. The principles are that accountants cannot function in the role of management, cannot audit their own work, and cannot serve in an advocacy role for the insurer.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Exemptions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Insurers having direct written and assumed premiums of less than $100,000,000 in any calendar year may request an exemption from <cite path="31|05|11|.06|G.|(1)">§G(1) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The insurer shall file with the Commissioner a written statement discussing the reasons why the insurer should be exempt from these provisions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the Commissioner finds, upon review of this statement, that compliance with this chapter would constitute a financial or organizational hardship upon the insurer, an exemption may be granted.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>A qualified independent certified public accountant who performs the audit may engage in other non-audit services, including tax services, that are not described in <cite path="31|05|11|.06|G.|(1)">§G(1) of this regulation</cite> or that do not conflict with <cite path="31|05|11|.06|G.|(2)">§G(2) of this regulation</cite>, only if the activity is approved in advance by the audit committee, in accordance with §§J and K of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>All auditing services and non-audit services provided to an insurer by the qualified independent certified public accountant of the insurer shall be preapproved by the audit committee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>The preapproval requirement is waived with respect to non-audit services if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The insurer is a SOX compliant entity, or a direct or indirect wholly owned subsidiary of a SOX compliant entity; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All of the following conditions are met:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The aggregate amount of all such non-audit services provided to the insurer constitutes not more than 5 percent of the total amount of fees paid by the insurer to its qualified independent certified public accountant during the fiscal year in which the non-audit services are provided;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The services were not recognized by the insurer at the time of the engagement to be non-audit services; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The services are promptly brought to the attention of the audit committee and approved prior to the completion of the audit by the audit committee or by one or more members of the audit committee who are the members of the board of directors to whom authority to grant such approvals has been delegated by the audit committee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Preapproval.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The audit committee may delegate to one or more designated members of the audit committee the authority to grant the preapprovals required by §§J and K of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The decisions of any member to whom this authority is delegated shall be presented to the full audit committee at each of its scheduled meetings.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>Independent Certified Public Accountant Conflicts.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Section M(2) of this regulation applies only to partners and senior managers involved in the audit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Commissioner may not recognize an independent certified public accountant as qualified for a particular insurer if a member of the board, president, chief executive officer, controller, chief financial officer, chief accounting officer, or any person serving in an equivalent position for that insurer, was employed by the independent certified public accountant and participated in the audit of that insurer during the 1-year period preceding the date that the most current statutory opinion is due.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An insurer may make application to the Commissioner for relief from the requirement in <cite path="31|05|11|.06|M.|(2)">§M(2) of this regulation</cite>, on the basis of unusual circumstances.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The insurer shall file, with its annual statement filing, the approval for relief from <cite path="31|05|11|.06|M.|(2)">§M(2) of this regulation</cite>, with the states that it is licensed in, or doing business in, and the NAIC. If the nondomestic state accepts electronic filing with the NAIC, the insurer shall file the approval in an electronic format acceptable to the NAIC.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|05|11|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Consolidated or Combined Audits.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An insurer may make written application to the Commissioner for approval to file audited consolidated or combined financial statements in lieu of separate annual audited financial statements if the insurer is part of a group of insurance companies that utilizes a pooling or 100 percent reinsurance agreement that affects the solvency and integrity of the insurer's reserves, and the insurer cedes all of its direct and assumed business to the pool.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>When an insurer makes a written application as allowed by <cite path="31|05|11|.07|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, a columnar consolidating or combining worksheet shall be filed with the report, as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Amounts shown on the consolidated or combined audited financial report shall be shown on the worksheet;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Amounts for each insurer subject to this section shall be stated separately;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Noninsurance operations may be shown on the worksheet on a combined or individual basis;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Explanations of consolidating and eliminating entries shall be included; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A reconciliation shall be included of any differences between the amounts shown in the individual insurer columns of the worksheet and comparable amounts shown on the annual statements of the insurers.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Scope of Audit and Report of Independent Certified Public Accountant.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Financial statements furnished pursuant to <cite path="|31|05|11|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite> shall be examined by the independent certified public accountant. The audit of the insurer's financial statements shall be conducted in accordance with generally accepted auditing standards.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The independent certified public accountant shall obtain an understanding of internal control sufficient to plan the audit in accordance with AU Section 319 of the Professional Standards of the AICPA, Consideration of Internal Control in a Financial Statement Audit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>To the extent required by AU 319, for those insurers required to file a Management’s Report of Internal Control over Financial Reporting pursuant to <cite path="|31|05|11|.16">Regulation .16 of this chapter</cite>, the independent certified public accountant should consider, as that term is defined in Statement on Auditing Standards (SAS) No. 102, Defining Professional Requirements in Statements on Auditing Standards or its replacement, the most recently available report in planning and performing the audit of the statutory financial statements.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The independent certified public accountant shall give consideration as he deems necessary to the procedures illustrated in the Financial Condition Examiners Handbook promulgated by the NAIC.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|05|11|.09">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Notification of Adverse Financial Condition.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The insurer required to furnish the annual audited financial report shall require the independent certified public accountant to report, in writing, within 5 business days to the board of directors or its audit committee any determination by the independent certified public accountant that the insurer has materially misstated its financial condition as reported to the Commissioner as of the balance sheet date currently under audit, or that the insurer does not meet the minimum capital and surplus requirement of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin">Insurance Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, as of that date.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An insurer that has received a report pursuant to <cite path="31|05|11|.09|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall forward a copy of the report to the Commissioner within 5 business days of receipt of the report and shall provide the independent certified public accountant making the report with evidence of the report being furnished to the Commissioner.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the independent certified public accountant fails to receive the evidence within the required 5 business day period, the independent certified public accountant shall furnish to the Commissioner a copy of its report within the next 5 business days.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An independent certified public accountant is not liable in any manner to any person for any statement made in connection with §A, B, or C of this regulation, if the statement is made in good faith in compliance with those sections.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If an accountant, subsequent to the date of the audited financial report filed pursuant to this chapter, becomes aware of facts that might have affected the accountant's report, the Commissioner notes the obligation of the accountant to take such action as prescribed in Volume 1, Section AU 561 of the Professional Standards of the AICPA.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|05|11|.10">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Communication of Internal Control Related Matters Noted in an Audit.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In addition to the annual audited financial report, each insurer shall furnish the Commissioner with a written communication as to any unremediated material weaknesses in its internal control over financial reporting noted during the audit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The communication in <cite path="31|05|11|.10|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, shall be prepared by the accountant within 60 days after the filing of the annual audited financial report, and shall contain a description of any unremediated material weakness, as the term material weakness is defined by Statement on Auditing Standard 60, Communication of Internal Control Related Matters Noted in an Audit, or its replacement, as of the immediately preceding December 31, so as to coincide with the audited financial report discussed in <cite path="|31|05|11|.03|A.">Regulation .03A of this chapter</cite> in the insurer's internal control over financial reporting noted by the accountant during the course of their audit of the financial statements.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If no unremediated material weaknesses were noted, the communication from §A shall so state.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The insurer shall provide a description of remedial actions taken or proposed to correct unremediated material weaknesses, if the actions are not described in the accountant's communication.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|05|11|.11">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Accountant's Letter of Qualifications.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The accountant shall furnish the insurer in connection with, and for inclusion in, the filing of the annual audited financial report, a letter as provided in <cite path="31|05|11|.11|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The letter shall state:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>That the accountant is independent with respect to the insurer, and conforms to the standards of the accountant's profession as contained in:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Code of Professional Ethics and pronouncements of the AICPA; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The rules of professional conduct of the Maryland Board of Public Accountancy or similar code;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The background and experience in general, and the experience in audits of insurers of the staff assigned to the engagement and whether each is an independent certified public accountant;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>That the accountant understands the annual audited financial report, and the opinion thereon will be filed in compliance with this regulation, and that the Commissioner will be relying on this information in the monitoring and regulation of the financial position of insurers;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>That the accountant consents to the requirements of <cite path="|31|05|11|.12">Regulation .12 of this chapter</cite>, and that the accountant consents and agrees to make available for review by the Commissioner, or the Commissioner's designee or appointed agent, the workpapers, as defined in <cite path="|31|05|11|.12">Regulation .12 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>That the accountant is properly licensed by an appropriate state licensing authority and is a member in good standing in the AICPA; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A representation that the accountant is in compliance with the requirements of <cite path="|31|05|11|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Nothing within this chapter may be construed as prohibiting the accountant from utilizing such staff as the accountant deems appropriate where use is consistent with the standards prescribed by generally accepted auditing standards.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|05|11|.12">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Definition, Availability, and Maintenance of Independent Certified Public Accountant's Workpapers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An insurer required to file an audited financial report pursuant to this chapter shall require the accountant to make available for review by the Maryland Insurance Administration examiners, all workpapers prepared in the conduct of the accountant's audit, and any communications related to the audit between the accountant and the insurer, at the offices of the insurer, at the Maryland Insurance Administration, or at any other reasonable place designated by the Commissioner.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The insurer shall require that the accountant retain the audit workpapers and communications until the Maryland Insurance Administration has filed a report on examination covering the period of the audit but not longer than 7 years from the date of the audit report.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In the conduct of the periodic review described in <cite path="31|05|11|.12|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, the Maryland Insurance Administration may make and retain photocopies of pertinent audit workpapers.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The reviews described in <cite path="31|05|11|.12|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, shall be considered investigations and all working papers and communications obtained during the course of the investigations shall be afforded the same confidentiality as other examination workpapers generated by the Maryland Insurance Administration.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|05|11|.13">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Requirements for Audit Committees.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This regulation does not apply to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Foreign or alien insurers licensed in Maryland;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An insurer that is a SOX compliant entity; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A direct or indirect wholly owned subsidiary of a SOX compliant entity.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The audit committee shall be directly responsible for the appointment, compensation, and oversight of the work of any accountant, including resolution of disagreements between management and the accountant regarding financial reporting, for the purpose of preparing or issuing the audited financial report or related work pursuant to this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The audit committee of an insurer or group of insurers shall be responsible for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Overseeing the insurer’s internal audit function; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Granting the person or persons performing the function suitable authority and resources to fulfill their responsibilities if required by <cite path="|31|05|11|.14">Regulation .14 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The accountant shall report directly to the audit committee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A member of the audit committee shall be a member of the board of directors of the insurer or a member of the board of directors of an entity elected pursuant to <cite path="31|05|11|.13|I.">§I of this regulation</cite> and <cite path="|31|05|11|.02|B.|(3)">Regulation .02B(3) of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>In order to be considered independent for purposes of this regulation, a member of the audit committee may not, other than in the member's capacity as a member of the audit committee, the board of directors, or any other board committee, accept any consulting, advisory, or other compensatory fee from the entity, or be an affiliated person of the entity, or any subsidiary of the entity.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>If law requires board participation by an otherwise non-independent member, that law shall prevail and the member may participate in the audit committee and be designated as independent for audit committee purposes, unless the member is an officer or employee of the insurer or one of its affiliates.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>If a member of the audit committee ceases to be independent for reasons outside the member's reasonable control, that person, with notice by the responsible entity to the Commissioner, may remain an audit committee member of the responsible entity until the earlier of the next annual meeting of the responsible entity or 1 year from the occurrence of the event that caused the member to be no longer independent.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>To exercise the election of the controlling person to designate the audit committee for purposes of this regulation, the ultimate controlling person shall provide written notice to the commissioners of the affected insurers.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Notification of the election of the controlling person shall be made timely prior to the issuance of the statutory audit report and include a description of the basis for the election. The election may be changed through notice to the Commissioner by the insurer, which shall include a description of the basis for the change.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>The election of the controlling person to designate the audit committee for purposes of this regulation shall remain in effect for perpetuity, until rescinded.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Audit Committee Reports.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The audit committee shall require the accountant that performs for an insurer any audit required by this chapter to timely report to the audit committee in accordance with the requirements of SAS 61, Communication with Audit Committees, or its replacement, including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All significant accounting policies and material permitted practices;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>All material alternative treatments of financial information within statutory accounting principles that have been discussed with management officials of the insurer, ramifications of the use of the alternative disclosures and treatments, and the treatment preferred by the accountant; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Other material written communications between the accountant and the management of the insurer, such as any management letter or schedule of unadjusted differences.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If an insurer is a member of an insurance holding company system, the reports required by <cite path="31|05|11|.13|L.|(1)">§L(1) of this regulation</cite> may be provided to the audit committee on an aggregate basis for insurers in the holding company system, provided that any substantial differences among insurers in the system are identified to the audit committee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>The proportion of independent audit committee members shall meet or exceed the following criteria:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Table.</text>
        <text>
          <table class="layout-table">
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="3" data-vertical-align="middle">Prior Calendar Year Direct Written and Assumed Premiums</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>$0—$300,000,000</td>
                <td>Over $300,000,000 —500,000,000</td>
                <td>Over $500,000,000</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>No minimum requirements. See also Note A and B.</td>
                <td>Majority (50% or more) of members shall be independent. See also Note A and B.</td>
                <td>Supermajority of members (75% or more) shall be independent. See also Note A.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Note A. The Commissioner has authority afforded by State law to require the entity's board to enact improvements to the independence of the audit committee membership if the insurer is in a RBC action level event, meets one or more of the standards of an insurer considered to be in hazardous financial condition, or otherwise exhibits qualities of a troubled insurer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Note B. All insurers with less than $500,000,000 in prior year direct written and assumed premiums are encouraged to structure their audit committees with at least a supermajority of independent audit committee members.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Note C. Prior calendar year direct written and assumed premiums shall be the combined total of direct premiums and assumed premiums from non-affiliates for the reporting entities.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>An insurer with direct written and assumed premium, excluding premiums reinsured with the Federal Crop Insurance Corporation and Federal Flood Program, less than $500,000,000 may make application to the Commissioner for a waiver from the requirements of <cite path="|31|05|11|.13">Regulation .13 of this chapter</cite> based upon hardship.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>The insurer shall file, with its annual statement filing, the approval for relief from <cite path="|31|05|11|.13">Regulation .13 of this chapter</cite> with the states that it is licensed in or doing business in and the NAIC. If the nondomestic state accepts electronic filing with the NAIC, the insurer shall file the approval in an electronic format acceptable to the NAIC.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Internal Audit Function Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An insurer is exempt from the requirements of this section if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The insurer has annual direct written and unaffiliated assumed premium, including international direct and assumed premium but excluding premiums reinsured with the Federal Crop Insurance Corporation and Federal Flood Program, less than $500,000,000; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The insurer is a member of a group of insurers and the group has annual direct written and unaffiliated assumed premium, including international direct and assumed premium but excluding premiums reinsured with the Federal Crop Insurance Corporation and Federal Flood Program, less than $1,000,000,000.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Function.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The insurer or group of insurers shall establish an internal audit function providing independent, objective, and reasonable assurance to the audit committee and insurer management regarding the insurers’:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Governance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Risk management; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Internal controls.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The reasonable assurance shall be provided by performing general and specific audits, reviews, and tests and by employing other techniques deemed necessary to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Protect assets;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Evaluate control effectiveness and efficiency; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Evaluate compliance with policies and regulations.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Independence.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In order to ensure that internal auditors remain objective, the internal audit function shall be organizationally independent.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The internal audit function may not defer ultimate judgement on audit matters to others and shall appoint an individual to head the internal audit function who will have direct and unrestricted access to the board of directors.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Organizational independence does not preclude dual-reporting relationships.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Reporting.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The head of the internal audit function shall report to the audit committee on:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The periodic audit plan;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Factors that may adversely impact the internal audit function’s independence or effectiveness;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Material findings from completed audits; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The appropriateness of corrective actions implemented by management as a result of audit findings.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The reporting shall be done regularly, but on no less than an annual basis.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Additional Requirements. If an insurer is a member of an insurance holding company system or included in a group of insurers, the insurer may satisfy the internal audit function requirements set forth in this regulation at the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Ultimate controlling parent level;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Intermediate holding company level; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Individual legal entity level.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|05|11|.15">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Conduct of Insurer in Connection with the Preparation of Required Reports and Documents.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A director or officer of an insurer may not, directly or indirectly:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Make or cause to be made a materially false or misleading statement to an accountant in connection with any audit, review, or communication required under this chapter; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Omit to state, or cause another person to omit to state, any material fact necessary in order to make statements made, in light of the circumstances under which the statements were made, not misleading to an accountant in connection with any audit, review, or communication required under this chapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An officer or director of an insurer, or any other person acting under the direction thereof, may not directly or indirectly take any action to coerce, manipulate, mislead, or fraudulently influence any accountant engaged in the performance of an audit pursuant to this regulation if that person knew or should have known that the action, if successful, could result in rendering the insurer's financial statements materially misleading.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>For purposes of <cite path="31|05|11|.15|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, actions that, "if successful, could result in rendering the insurer's financial statements materially misleading" include, but are not limited to, actions taken at any time with respect to the professional engagement period to coerce, manipulate, mislead, or fraudulently influence an accountant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To issue or reissue a report on an insurer's financial statements that is not warranted in the circumstances, due to material violations of statutory accounting principles prescribed by the Commissioner, generally accepted auditing standards, or other professional or regulatory standards;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Not to perform audit, review, or other procedures required by generally accepted auditing standards or other professional standards;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Not to withdraw an issued report; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Not to communicate matters to an insurer's audit committee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|05|11|.16">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Management's Report on Internal Control over Financial Reporting.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An insurer required to file an audited financial report pursuant to this chapter that has annual direct written and assumed premiums, excluding premiums reinsured with the Federal Crop Insurance Corporation and Federal Flood Program, of $500,000,000 or more shall prepare a report (Management's Report on Internal Control over Financial Reporting) of the insurer's or group of insurers' internal control over financial reporting, as these terms are defined in <cite path="|31|05|11|.02">Regulation .02 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The report shall be filed with the Commissioner along with the Communication of Internal Control Related Matters Noted in an Audit described under <cite path="|31|05|11|.10">Regulation .10 of this chapter</cite>. Management's Report on Internal Control over Financial Reporting shall be as of the immediately preceding December 31.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Notwithstanding the premium threshold in <cite path="31|05|11|.16|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, the Commissioner may require an insurer to file Management's Report on Internal Control over Financial Reporting if the insurer is in any risk-based capital (RBC) level event, or meets any one or more of the standards of an insurer deemed to be in hazardous financial condition as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin">Insurance Article, Title 9, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Alternative Filing.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An insurer or a group of insurers that is directly subject to Section 404, part of a holding company system whose parent is directly subject to Section 404, not directly subject to Section 404 but is a SOX compliant entity, or a member of a holding company system whose parent is not directly subject to Section 404 but is a SOX compliant entity, may file its or its parent's Section 404 report and an addendum in satisfaction of this regulation if the internal controls of the insurer or group of insurers having a material impact on the preparation of the insurer's or group of insurers' audited statutory financial statements (those items included in Regulation .04B(2)—(6) of this chapter) were included in the scope of the Section 404 report.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The addendum shall be a positive statement by management that there are no material processes with respect to the preparation of the insurer's or group of insurers' audited statutory financial statements (those items included in Regulation .04B(2)—(6) of this chapter) excluded from the Section 404 report.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If there are internal controls of the insurer or group of insurers that have a material impact on the preparation of the insurer's or group of insurers' audited statutory financial statements and those internal controls were not included in the scope of the Section 404 report, the insurer or group of insurers may either file:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A Management's Report on Internal Control over Financial Reporting; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Section 404 report and a Management's Report on Internal Control over Financial Reporting for those internal controls that have a material impact on the preparation of the insurer's or group of insurers' audited statutory financial statements not covered by the Section 404 report.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Management's Report on Internal Control over Financial Reporting shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A statement that management is responsible for establishing and maintaining adequate internal control over financial reporting;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A statement that management has established internal control over financial reporting and an assertion, to the best of management's knowledge and belief, after diligent inquiry, as to whether its internal control over financial reporting is effective to provide reasonable assurance regarding the reliability of financial statements in accordance with statutory accounting principles;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A statement that briefly describes the approach or processes by which management evaluated the effectiveness of its internal control over financial reporting;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A statement that briefly describes the scope of work that is included and whether any internal controls were excluded;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Disclosure of any unremediated material weaknesses in the internal control over financial reporting identified by management as of the immediately preceding December 31;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A statement regarding the inherent limitations of internal control systems; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Signatures of the chief executive officer and the chief financial officer, or individuals with equivalent position and title.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>With regard to <cite path="31|05|11|.16|E.|(5)">§E(5) of this regulation</cite>, management is not permitted to conclude that the internal control over financial reporting is effective to provide reasonable assurance regarding the reliability of financial statements in accordance with statutory accounting principles if there is one or more unremediated material weaknesses in its internal control over financial reporting.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Management shall document and make available upon financial condition examination the basis upon which its assertions, required in <cite path="31|05|11|.16|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>, are made.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Management may base its assertions, in part, upon its review, monitoring, and testing of internal controls undertaken in the normal course of its activities.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Management shall have discretion as to the nature of the internal control framework used, and the nature and extent of documentation, in order to make its assertion in a cost effective manner and, as such, may include assembly of or reference to existing documentation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Management's Report on Internal Control over Financial Reporting, required by §§A and B of this regulation, and any documentation provided in support thereof during the course of a financial condition examination, shall be kept confidential by the Maryland Insurance Administration.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="31|05|11|.17">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.17</num>
    <heading>Exemptions and Effective Dates.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Upon written application of any insurer, the Commissioner may grant an exemption from compliance with provisions of this chapter if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The exemption is not prohibited by statute; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Commissioner finds, upon review of the application, that compliance with this chapter would constitute a financial or organizational hardship upon the insurer.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner may grant exemption at any time and from time to time for a specified period or periods.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The insurer may request in writing a hearing on its application for an exemption within 10 days from a denial of an insurer's written request for an exemption from this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The hearing requested in <cite path="31|05|11|.17|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, shall be held in accordance with <cite path="|31.02.01">COMAR 31.02.01</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Domestic insurers retaining a certified public accountant on the effective date of this chapter who qualify as independent shall comply with this chapter for the year ending December 31, 2010, and each year thereafter, unless the Commissioner permits otherwise:</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Domestic insurers not retaining a certified public accountant on the effective date of this chapter who qualifies as independent shall meet the following schedule for compliance unless the Commissioner permits otherwise.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>As of December 31, 2010, file with the Commissioner an audited financial report; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For the year ending December 31, 2010, and each year thereafter, file with the Commissioner all reports and communication required by this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Foreign insurers shall comply with this regulation for the year ending December 31, 2010, and each year thereafter, unless the Commissioner permits otherwise.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The requirements of <cite path="|31|05|11|.06|D.">Regulation .06D of this chapter</cite> shall become effective July 1, 2010, and shall be in effect for audits of the year beginning January 1, 2010, and thereafter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>The requirements of <cite path="|31|05|11|.13">Regulation .13 of this chapter</cite> are to be in effect January 1, 2010.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>An insurer or group of insurers that is not required pursuant to <cite path="|31|05|11|.13">Regulation .13 of this chapter</cite> to have independent audit committee members or only a majority of independent audit committee members, as opposed to a supermajority, because the total written and assumed premium is below the threshold and subsequently becomes subject to one of the independence requirements due to changes in premium, shall have 1 year following the year the threshold is exceeded, but not earlier than January 1, 2010, to comply with the independence requirements.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>An insurer that becomes subject to one of the independence requirements of <cite path="|31|05|11|.13">Regulation .13 of this chapter</cite> as a result of a business combination shall have 1 calendar year following the date of acquisition or combination to comply with the independence requirements.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Reporting Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The requirements of <cite path="|31|05|11|.16">Regulation .16 of this chapter</cite> are effective beginning with the reporting period ending December 31, 2010, and each year thereafter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An insurer or group of insurers that is not required to file a report because the total written premium is below the threshold and subsequently becomes subject to the reporting requirements, shall have 2 years following the year the threshold is exceeded (but not earlier than December 31, 2010) to file a report.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An insurer acquired in a business combination shall have 2 calendar years following the date of acquisition or combination to comply with the reporting requirements.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>The requirements of <cite path="|31|05|11|.14">Regulation .14 of this chapter</cite> are effective as of January 1, 2019. If an insurer or group of insurers that are exempt from <cite path="|31|05|11|.14">Regulation .14 of this chapter</cite> no longer qualifies for that exemption, it shall have one year after the year the threshold is exceeded to comply with the requirements of this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.18</num>
    <heading>Canadian and British Companies.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In the case of Canadian and British insurers, the annual audited financial report shall be defined as the annual statement of total business on the form filed by such companies with their supervision authority duly audited by an independent chartered accountant.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>For such insurers, the letter required in <cite path="|31|05|11|.05|B.">Regulation .05B of this chapter</cite> shall state that the accountant is aware of the requirements relating to the annual audited financial report filed with the Commissioner pursuant to <cite path="|31|05|11|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>, and shall affirm that the opinion expressed is in conformity with those requirements.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Insurance Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|2-109">2-109</cite>(a)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|1">1</cite>), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|2-205">2-205</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|4-116">4-116</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|14-118">14-118</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|14-121">14-121</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|14-413">14-413</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-605">15-605</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|24-211">24-211</cite>, and  24-304, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-08-10">Effective date: August 10, 2009 (36:16 Md. R. 1252)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-02-27"><cite path="|31|05|11|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective February 27, 2017 (44:4 Md. R. 255)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-12-06" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective December 6, 2018 (45:24 Md. R. 1163)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
