<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>General</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This subtitle is applicable to electric utilities and suppliers only in service territories where customers have customer choice.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this subtitle, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Agent.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Agent” means a person who conducts marketing or sales activities, or both, on behalf of a licensed supplier or broker.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Agent” includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>An employee;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A representative;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>An independent contractor;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>A vendor;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Subcontractors;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Employees;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Vendors; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Representatives not directly contracted by the supplier who conduct marketing or sales activities on behalf of the supplier.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“CAD” means the Consumer Affairs Division within the Commission pursuant to <cite path="20.32.01.02|B.|(2)">COMAR 20.32.01.02B(2)</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Commission” means the Public Service Commission of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Consent” means an agreement with an action communicated by the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A written document with customer signature;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An electronic document with electronic signature; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A voice recording only if the agreement is exempt under the Maryland Telephone Solicitations Act.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Consumer” or “customer” means the regulated utility retail electric customer account holder.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Contract for energy assistance households” means a residential retail energy supply contract that meets the legal requirements of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|4-308">Public Utilities Article, §4-308, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and any other applicable requirements in the Public Utilities Article in connection with a supplier’s<em> supply service for customers who are part of an energy assistance household.</em></text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Contract Summary” means a summary of the material terms and conditions of a retail energy supply contract, on a form provided by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Customer choice” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-501">Public Utilities Article, §7-501, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“Drop” means the removal of a customer from a supplier's service.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>“Electric company” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|1-101">Public Utilities Article, §1-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>“Electricity supplier” or “supplier” means a person licensed under <cite path="|20.51">COMAR 20.51</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>“Electronic transaction” means a standardized data protocol or electronic transmission medium that has been accepted by the Commission for use in Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>“Energy assistance household” means that the Office of Home Energy Programs found that the service address or household associated with the utility account qualified for an electric assistance program during the current or previous fiscal year. For a utility that provides both gas and electric service, an energy assistance household means that the Office of Home Energy Programs found that the service address or household associated with the utility account qualified for an electric or gas assistance program during the current or previous fiscal year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>“Energy assistance program” means the following programs administered by the Maryland Office of Home Energy Programs by which a customer receives financial assistance paying their electricity utility bills, which includes but is not necessarily limited to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Maryland Energy Assistance Program;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Electric Universal Service Program; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Arrearage Retirement Assistance Program.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>“Enrollment” means the addition of a customer to a supplier's service.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>“Evergreen contract” means an existing contract that automatically renews without any action by the customer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>“Fiscal year” means the 12-month period that begins on July 1 of a calendar year and ends June 30 of the next calendar year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>“Overcharge” means the difference between the price the customer would have paid the customer's authorized supplier and what the customer paid to the unauthorized supplier.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>“Public event” means an event open to the public, which may facilitate retail electricity sales and marketing activities or may result in an electricity customer enrollment transaction.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>“Scheduling coordinator” means an entity or entities:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Recognized by the regional transmission organization designated for Maryland by the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Qualified to act on behalf of the supplier in taking those actions with the regional transmission organization as are necessary to fulfill the supplier's coordination service obligations as defined in the utility tariff, including the submission of energy schedules to the regional transmission organization; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>That is:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A member of the regional transmission organization; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The agent for scheduling purposes of one or more suppliers that are members of the regional transmission organization.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>“Standard offer service (SOS)” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-501">Public Utilities Article, §7-501, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>“Standard offer service rate” is the utility rate as approved in the utility’s applicable SOS tariff that would be charged to an SOS customer, excluding any charges, adjustments, riders, or taxes related to distribution rate. The utility shall post and maintain this rate in an easily accessible location on its website.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>“Supplier-consolidated billing (SCB)” means a form of competitive billing services in which a gas or an electricity supplier is authorized by the Commission to render a bill to a retail gas or electric customer that includes both the supplier charges and the gas or electric company’s regulated charges.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(24)</num>
        <text>“Supply price comparison information” means the rate and language that the Commission may require to be printed on a customer’s bill to permit the customer to make meaningful comparisons between competitive supplier prices and the price for standard offer service or sales service provided by the customer’s utility.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(25)</num>
        <text>“Third party verification (TPV)” means consent from the customer agreeing to each of the below-listed material contract terms that is recorded by an independent person not party to the agreement or that may be performed by an automated, computerized system. To be valid, the TPV must occur without the presence of the sales agent, and at the outset must describe how the customer can cancel the TPV at any time prior to completion. The consent from the customer must include an acknowledgement:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>That he or she is voluntarily choosing to enroll with a supplier;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Of the type of product offered (variable, fixed, a combination of both);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Of the price and duration of the contract;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Of the amount of an early termination fee (if applicable);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>That the customer is authorized to make the switch;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Of the contract renewal procedures;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>That the customer may access future pricing information;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>That the customer has received the supplier’s customer support contact information; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>If the customer is entering into a supplier-consolidated billing contract:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>That the customer is voluntarily choosing to be billed by the supplier for both supplier charges and utility charges; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>That the customer understands that the customer’s previous bill provider may bill the customer for prior unpaid charges.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(26)</num>
        <text>“Utility” means an electric company as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|1-101">Public Utilities Article, §1-101, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(27)</num>
        <text>“Utility consolidated billing” means a customer bill produced by a utility that contains both supplier and utility charges.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Uniform Electronic Transactions.</heading>
    <text>All suppliers and utilities shall use the uniform electronic transaction processes approved by the Commission.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Utility Compliance Plan.</heading>
    <text>Utilities shall file a plan and relevant tariffs for compliance with this subtitle within 45 days after this regulation becomes effective.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Waiver.</heading>
    <text>The Commission may waive a regulation in this subtitle for good cause shown.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Public Utilities Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-113">2-113</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-121">2-121</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|4-308">4-308</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|5-101">5-101</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-505">7-505</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-507">7-507</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-511">7-511</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-603">7-603</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-07-01">Effective date: July 1, 2005 (31:26 Md. R. 1865)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-06-20" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|20|53|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|20|53|01|.08">.08</cite> repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|20|53|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|20|53|01|.05">.05</cite> adopted effective June 20, 2008 (35:11 Md. R. 1043)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-07-10"><cite path="|20|53|01|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective March 14, 2016 (43:5 Md. R. 386); March 7, 2022 (49:5 Md. R. 367); July 10, 2023 (50:13 Md R. 513)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
