<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>Examination and Post-Graduate Training</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Board" means the Maryland State Board of Podiatric Medical Examiners.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Maryland Board Examination" means the test administered by the Maryland State Board of Podiatric Medical Examiners.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Maryland Licensing Examination" means the test the Maryland State Board of Podiatric Medical Examiners administers to applicants for licensure.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"National Board Examination" means the American Podiatric Medical Licensure Examinations administered by the National Board of Podiatric Medical Examiners.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Practiced podiatry actively” means for the immediately preceding 5 years has been actively engaged in the practice of podiatric medicine for at least 400 hours on average per year.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|40|01|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Examinations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Only graduates of podiatric medical colleges which at the time of the applicant's graduation had standards equivalent to the standards for colleges approved by the Council on Education of the American Podiatric Medical Association are eligible for examination.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board requires the following examinations for licensure:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The National Board Examinations, parts I, II, and III;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Maryland Board Examination.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The examinations specified in <cite path="10|40|01|.02|B.|(2)">§B(2) of this regulation</cite> may be prepared by the Board or by a recognized national or state testing or licensing agency, with the approval of the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>On each of the National Board Examinations, an applicant shall obtain a passing score as set by the National Board of Podiatric Medical Examiners. This result is required in order to be eligible to take the Maryland Board Examination and, after that, to be licensed by the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>On the Maryland Board Examination, an applicant shall obtain a passing score, as set by the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The examination shall be taken within 1 year of the date of the application.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The Maryland Board Examination may include, but is not limited to, the following subject areas:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Physiology;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Pharmacology;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Diagnostic techniques;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Pathology;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Patient management;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Surgical procedures;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Biomechanics;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Dermatology;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Orthopedics;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Podopediatrics.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>An individual found by the Board to have engaged in conduct which subverts or attempts to subvert the licensing examination may, at the discretion of the Board, have the results of his licensing examination withheld, or declared invalid, or both. In addition, an individual who has subverted or attempted to subvert the licensing examination may be found ineligible for future licensure following a determination that the individual lacks good moral character as required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|16-302">Health Occupations Article, §16-302(b), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or is guilty of a violation of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|16-311">Health Occupations Article, §16-311(a)(1), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>. Conduct which subverts or attempts to subvert the licensing examination includes, but is not limited to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Conduct which violates the security of the examination materials, including but not limited to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Removing from the examination room any of the examination materials;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Reproducing a portion of any past or future licensing examination;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Aiding by any means in the reproduction of any portions of a past or future licensing examination; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Selling, distributing, buying, receiving, or having unauthorized possession of any portion of a future or current licensing examination;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Conduct which violates the standard of test administration, including, but not limited to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Communicating with any other examinee during the administration of the licensing examination;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Copying answers from another examinee or permitting one's answers to be copied by another examinee during the administration of the licensing examination; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Having in one's possession during the administration of the licensing examination any books, notes, written or printed materials or data of any kind, other than the examination materials distributed;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Conduct which violates the credentialing process, including but not limited to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Falsifying or misrepresenting education credentials or other information required for admission to the licensing examination;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Impersonating an examinee; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Having an impersonator take the licensing examination on one's behalf.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Applications.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Applications should be filed not later than 30 days before the date of the examination.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Application fees are not refundable or transferrable.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Location of Exams.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Board examinations may be given in any locality in the State as determined by the Board of Podiatric Medical Examiners.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The applicant will be notified of the location of the examination when his application is approved.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Post-Graduate Clinical Training.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as otherwise provided in this regulation, an applicant who submits an application for a license after January 1, 1990 shall demonstrate satisfactory completion of 2 years in a post-graduate medical education program in podiatric medicine and surgery approved by the Council on Education of the American Podiatric Medical Association, or its successor, and approved by the Board, in order to be eligible for the examination.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This regulation does not apply to applicants who apply for a limited license.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Board may waive the requirement of this regulation at the request of an applicant who has practiced podiatry actively in another state for at least 5 years immediately before applying for a license in Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Speech Impairment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant who claims a speech impairment shall submit a written request to the Board:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>With the applicant's initial licensure application; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Within 1 year of development of the impairment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board retains the right to waive the 1-year time limit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An applicant may claim a speech impairment only if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A speech impairment exists; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Board:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Was properly notified of the impairment at the time of initial licensure; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Determines that a medical or surgical event created the impairment after licensure.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If an applicant has a properly claimed and documented speech impairment, the Board may grant or renew a license only if the applicant is able to effectively communicate with health care providers and patients.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Board recognizes the following as proof of the applicant's ability to communicate effectively:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Documentation from:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A speech-language pathologist who is currently licensed to practice speech pathology in the United States indicating that the applicant can communicate in a professionally competent manner with patients and other health care providers; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Three Maryland licensed podiatrists that attest to the fact that the applicant can communicate in a professionally competent manner with patients and other health care providers; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A personal hearing before the Board during which the applicant relays the manner in which the applicant would:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Obtain a history;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Conduct a physical examination;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Order additional tests;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Obtain consultations; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Relay the results of the examination and treatment plan to a patient.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|16-205">16-205</cite>(a)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|1">1</cite>), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|16-302">16-302</cite>(f), and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|16-304">16-304</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1973-12-22">Effective date: December 22, 1973</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1983-10-24"><cite path="|10|40|01|.01|C.">Regulation .01C</cite> amended effective October 24, 1983 (10:21 Md. R. 1902)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1983-10-24"><cite path="|10|40|01|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective February 4, 1976 (3:3 Md. R. 150); October 24, 1983 (10:21 Md. R. 1902)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-07-29" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective July 29, 1985 (12:15 Md. R. 1520)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-12-05"><cite path="|10|40|01|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective March 5, 1990 (17:4 Md. R. 496); December 5, 1994 (21:24 Md. R. 1989)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-12-05"><cite path="|10|40|01|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective December 5, 1994 (21:24 Md. R. 1989)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-03-05"><cite path="|10|40|01|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite>—D, G amended effective March 5, 1990 (17:4 Md. R. 496)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-03-05"><cite path="|10|40|01|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite> amended effective March 5, 1990 (17:4 Md. R. 496)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-05-01"><cite path="|10|40|01|.06">Regulation .06</cite> adopted effective May 1, 1989 (16:8 Md. R. 910)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-10-18"><cite path="|10|40|01|.07">Regulation .07</cite> adopted effective October 18, 1999 (26:21 Md. R. 1630)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-12-22" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective December 22, 2003 (30:25 Md. R. 1848)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-07-02"><cite path="|10|40|01|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective July 2, 2018 (45:13 Md. R. 668)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-07-03"><cite path="|10|40|01|.05|A.">Regulation .05A</cite> amended effective July 3, 2017 (44:13 Md. R. 621)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-07-02"><cite path="|10|40|01|.05|C.">Regulation .05C</cite> amended effective July 2, 2018 (45:13 Md. R. 668)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
