<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>06</num>
  <heading>Advertising</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>These regulations govern advertising by all podiatrists in Maryland.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following words have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Advertising" means calling to the attention of the public the services one has to offer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Board" means the State Board of Podiatric Medical Examiners.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Podiatrist" means an individual who holds, or is required to hold, a current license to practice podiatry in Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Advertising.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A podiatrist may advertise the services offered by the podiatrist subject to the provisions of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Advertisements. Subject to <cite path="|10|40|06|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>, a podiatrist may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Place advertisements in any form of print or electronic media; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Refer to himself or herself as a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Podiatrist”;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Foot and ankle specialist”; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>“Foot and ankle surgeon”.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An advertisement may not include statements:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Containing misrepresentation of facts;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Likely to mislead or deceive because in context the statement makes only a partial disclosure of relevant facts;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Likely to create false or unjustified expectations of favorable results;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Relating to fees without reasonable disclosure of all relevant variables so that the statement would not be misunderstood or be deceptive to a layman;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Conveying the impression that the podiatrist could influence improperly a public body, official, corporation, or a person on behalf of a patient;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Containing representations or implications that in reasonable probability can be expected to cause an ordinarily prudent person to misunderstand or be deceived; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Containing representations that the podiatrist is willing to perform any procedure which is illegal under the laws or regulations of Maryland or the United States.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A podiatrist shall be accountable under this regulation if the podiatrist uses an agent, partnership, professional association, or health maintenance organization to implement actions prohibited by this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Solicitation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A podiatrist may not engage in solicitation, including but not limited to, in person, telephone, or direct mail solicitation which:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Amounts to fraud, undue influence, intimidation or over reaching; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Contains statements which would be improper under <cite path="|10|40|06|.03|C.">Regulation .03C of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A podiatrist shall be accountable under this regulation if the podiatrist uses an agent, partnership, professional association, or health maintenance organization to implement actions prohibited by this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|40|06|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Advertisement of Free, Discounted, or Reduced Fee Podiatric Goods or Services.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>It is false and misleading advertising for a podiatrist to advertise or otherwise represent that any goods or services (for example, examination or X-rays) shall be offered or performed for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Free when the podiatrist in fact requests or receives a fee for reimbursement, directly or indirectly, for providing those goods or services; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A discounted or reduced fee when the podiatrist in fact requests or receives, directly or indirectly, a higher fee or reimbursement for providing those goods or services.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In addition to the free, discounted, or reduced price goods or services, a podiatrist, who has not obtained the written informed consent of the patient in the form as shown in <cite path="10|40|06|.05|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, may not for a fee offer or provide any podiatric goods or services to a patient within 72 hours of the date the patient presents a coupon, voucher, similar document, or advertisement offering:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Free" podiatric goods or services; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Podiatric goods or services for a discounted or reduced fee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The podiatrist shall use the following Consent to Treatment Form and shall retain the form in the patient's file:</text>
      <text class="center">PLEASE READ WITH CARE</text>
      <text class="center">CONSENT TO TREATMENT</text>
      <text class="center">IMMEDIATELY AFTER RECEIPT OF</text>
      <text class="center">FREE/DISCOUNTED/REDUCED PRICE GOODS OR SERVICES</text>
      <text class="center">INTRODUCTION</text>
      <text>The Board of Podiatric Medical Examiners wishes to inform you that, under the law of Maryland, you may not be charged a fee for podiatric goods or services which have been advertised as "free". Nor may you be charged more than the "reduced or discounted" fee advertised for particular podiatric goods or services. In addition, before a podiatrist may charge you a fee to treat immediately or within 72 hours a problem diagnosed at the time you received free, reduced, or discounted podiatric goods or services, you shall consent in writing to accept that treatment. The podiatrist shall explain to you whether he or she thinks that you need the treatment immediately or within 72 hours, or whether your condition does not require immediate treatment. The decision to accept treatment immediately or at a later date is always your decision. If you desire to accept treatment immediately or within 72 hours of today, please sign this document as required by law. Please be aware that you may be financially responsible for payment for the goods or services you receive.</text>
      <text>INFORMATION PROVIDED</text>
      <text>/ /  This podiatrist has explained to me the diagnosis of my condition and I understand it.</text>
      <text>/ /  This podiatrist has explained the treatment alternatives and their risks to me and I understand them.</text>
      <text>/ /  This podiatrist has explained the likely cost of each of the treatment alternatives and I understand it.</text>
      <text>/ /  This podiatrist has explained to me the treatment he or she believes I need and I understand it.</text>
      <text>/ /  This podiatrist has explained to me why I need the treatment immediately (within 72 hours of today) and I understand it.</text>
      <text>CONSENT TO TREATMENT</text>
      <text>I have received my free, reduced, or discounted goods or services.</text>
      <text>I am accepting treatment today or within 72 hours of today's date and</text>
      <text>I fully understand that I may be charged for the treatment rendered.</text>
      <text>_____________________       __________________________________________</text>
      <text>Date                       			 Patient's Signature</text>
      <text>__________________________________________</text>
      <text>Witness' Signature</text>
      <text>__________________________________________</text>
      <text>Podiatrist's Signature</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Penalties for Violation.</heading>
    <text>The Board may enforce this chapter against the podiatrist by any appropriate ground for disciplinary action, under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|16-311">Health Occupations Article, §16-311, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|16-205">16-205</cite>(a)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|1">1</cite>) and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|16-311">16-311</cite>(a)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|20">20</cite>), Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1988-04-04">Effective date: April 4, 1988 (15:7 Md. R. 849)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-03-05"><cite path="|10|40|06|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective March 5, 1990 (17:4 Md. R. 497)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-07-02"><cite path="|10|40|06|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite>, C amended effective July 2, 2018 (45:13 Md. R. 668)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-03-05"><cite path="|10|40|06|.03|C.">Regulation .03C</cite> amended effective March 5, 1990 (17:4 Md. R. 497)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-10-12"><cite path="|10|40|06|.05">Regulation .05</cite> recodified to .06 and new Regulation .05 adopted effective October 12, 1992 (19:20 Md. R. 1815)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
