<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>12</num>
  <heading>Telehealth</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter governs the practice of podiatry using telehealth as an adjunct to, or replacement for, in-person patient visits.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Nothing in this chapter restricts or limits reimbursement requirements pursuant to Health-General Article and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin">Insurance Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Asynchronous” means not occurring in real time.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“In-person” means within the physical presence of the patient.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Interpretive services” means reading and analyzing images, tracings, or specimens through telehealth or giving interpretations based on visual, auditory, thermal, or ultrasonic patterns or other patterns as may evolve with technology.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Remote patient monitoring” means the use of telehealth devices to collect medical and other forms of health data from patients that are securely provided to a telehealth practitioner in a different location for assessment, recommendation, and diagnosis.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Store and forward technology” means the asynchronous transmission of digital images, documents, and videos electronically through secure means.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Synchronous” means occurring in real time.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Telehealth” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|1-1001">Health Occupations Article, §1-1001, of the Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Telehealth devices” means devices that gather visual or other data and remotely send the images or data to a telehealth practitioner in a different location from the patient.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“Telehealth practitioner” means a Maryland-licensed podiatrist performing telehealth services within the scope of practice.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Licensure.</heading>
    <text>Subject to the provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 16, Subtitle 3, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, a telehealth practitioner shall be licensed in Maryland when providing telehealth services to a patient located in the State.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Standards of Practice for Telehealth.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Before providing telehealth services, a telehealth practitioner shall develop and follow a procedure to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Verify the identification of the patient receiving telehealth services through use of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A government-issued photograph identification;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An insurance, Medicaid, or Medicare card; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Documentation of the patient’s:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Date of birth; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Home address;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For an initial patient-telehealth practitioner encounter, disclose the telehealth practitioner’s:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Name;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Contact information; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Maryland license number;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Except for interpretive services, obtain oral or written acknowledgement from a patient or a patient’s parent or guardian if State law requires the consent of a parent or guardian, including informing patients of the risks, benefits, and side effects of prescribed treatments;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Securely collect and transmit a patient’s medical health information, clinical data, clinical images, laboratory results, and self-reported medical health and clinical history, as necessary, and prevent access to data by unauthorized persons through encryption or other means;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Notify patients in the event of a data breach;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Ensure that the telehealth practitioner provides a secure and private communication modality that complies with federal and state privacy laws; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Establish safety protocols to be used in the case of an emergency, including contact information for emergency services at the patient’s location.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Except when utilizing store and forward technology to provide telehealth services or remote patient monitoring, a telehealth practitioner shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Obtain or confirm an alternative method of contacting the patient in case of a technological failure;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Confirm whether the patient is in Maryland and identify the specific practice setting in which the patient is located; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Identify all individuals present at each location and confirm they are allowed to hear the patient’s health information.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A telehealth practitioner shall be held to the same standards of practice and documentation as those applicable for in-person health care settings.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A telehealth practitioner may not prescribe opioids for the treatment of pain through telehealth except if the patient is in a health care facility as defined in Health-General Article, §19-114, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="10|40|12|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Patient Evaluation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except when providing asynchronous telehealth services or remote patient monitoring, a telehealth practitioner shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Perform a clinical patient evaluation adequate to establish a diagnosis and identify underlying conditions or contraindications to recommended treatment options before providing treatment or prescribing medication through telehealth; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If clinically appropriate for the patient, provide or refer a patient to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In-person health care services; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Another type of telehealth service.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the evaluation is adequate to comply with <cite path="10|40|12|.05|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, a telehealth practitioner may use:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Telehealth devices;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Live synchronous audio-visual communication;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Other methods of performing a medical examination remotely; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A patient evaluation performed by another licensed health care practitioner providing coverage.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A telehealth practitioner may not treat a patient or issue a prescription based solely on an online questionnaire.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Telehealth Practitioner Discipline.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board shall use the same standards of evaluating and investigating a complaint about and in disciplining a licensee who practices telehealth as it would use for a licensee who does not use telehealth technology in the licensee’s practice.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The failure of a telehealth practitioner to comply with Regulations .04 and .05 of this chapter shall constitute unprofessional conduct and may be subject to disciplinary action by the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|1-1001">1-1001</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|1-1006">1-1006</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-09-18">Effective date: September 18, 2023 (50:18 Md. R. 795)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
