<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>06</num>
  <heading>Procedures for Quasi-Legislative Hearings</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter applies to quasi-legislative hearings that the Insurance Commissioner conducts to gather information before making a decision or taking an action.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This chapter does not apply to contested case hearings.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Relation to Other Laws.</heading>
    <text>The procedural requirements of this chapter are in addition to the procedural requirements of any other applicable provision of law.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Notice of Hearing.</heading>
    <text>A notice of a hearing held under this chapter shall include:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The time and location of the hearing;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The purpose of the hearing; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Any other information required by applicable law.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Conduct and Control of Hearing.</heading>
    <text>The Insurance Commissioner or a designee of the Insurance Commissioner shall determine the conduct of a hearing held under this chapter, including:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The order of presentation; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Time limits for questions and testimony.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Testimony.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Insurance Commissioner or a designee of the Insurance Commissioner may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Request the attendance of persons to testify or the production of documents;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Issue a subpoena requiring the attendance of persons to testify or the production of documents; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Require testimony to be given under oath.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Insurance Commissioner or a designee of the Insurance Commissioner shall give all persons present who wish to testify an opportunity to do so, but may limit repetitious testimony.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Insurance Commissioner or a designee of the Insurance Commissioner may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Ask questions of anyone present at a hearing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Take questions from the audience and redirect the questions to others present at the hearing; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Refer questions to employees of the Maryland Insurance Administration who may respond after the hearing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The rules of evidence do not apply to a hearing held under this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Insurance Commissioner or designee of the Insurance Commissioner shall receive and mark all exhibits offered in testimony if they are relevant to the hearing.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Transcript.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>At the discretion of the Maryland Insurance Administration and unless otherwise required by law, the Administration or a court reporter service shall stenographically record verbatim or tape record a hearing held under this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If a court reporter service records the hearing, a person who desires a copy of a transcript of the recording may purchase a copy from the court reporter service.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If an employee of the Maryland Insurance Administration records the hearing:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Maryland Insurance Administration shall keep the tape recording or stenographic recording with the original record of the hearing; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person who desires a copy of the transcript of the recording, if one is made, may purchase a copy from the Maryland Insurance Administration for a reasonable cost in accordance with <cite path="31.02.05.09">COMAR 31.02.05.09</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Record.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Insurance Commissioner or a designee of the Insurance Commissioner controls the record of a hearing held under this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Insurance Commissioner or a designee of the Insurance Commissioner shall assemble a record that consists of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The notice of the hearing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Exhibits and documents entered into the record;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The register of all persons who attended the hearing including their names, addresses, and any affiliations relevant to the hearing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>In accordance with <cite path="|31|02|06|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>, any:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Full or partial transcript of the hearing made or purchased by the Maryland Insurance Administration; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Tape or stenographic recording of the hearing made by the Maryland Insurance Administration; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If applicable, the final decision of the Insurance Commissioner or a designee of the Insurance Commissioner.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Postponement and Continuance.</heading>
    <text>The Insurance Commissioner or a designee of the Insurance Commissioner has sole discretion to:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Postpone or continue a hearing; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Keep the record open beyond the date of the hearing.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Judicial Review.</heading>
    <text>Unless otherwise required by law, a party who is aggrieved by a final decision issued by the Insurance Commissioner, or a designee of the Insurance Commissioner, at the conclusion of a hearing held under this chapter, may file a petition for judicial review in the Circuit Court for Baltimore City within 30 days after the date of the final decision.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health-General Article, §19-713; Insurance Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|2-109">2-109</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|2-203">2-203</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|4-309">4-309</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|11-502">11-502</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|12-203">12-203</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|12-204">12-204</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|12-205">12-205</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|13-110">13-110</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|13-111">13-111</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|4-126">4-126</cite>; State Government Article, §§6.5-103 and 6.5-203; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-10-15">Effective date: October 15, 2001 (28:20 Md. R. 1785)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
