<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>Plan Administrator Criteria</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter establishes criteria the Board of Directors of the Maryland Health Insurance Plan shall apply to select the Plan Administrator.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Administrator" means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A person that is registered as an Administrator under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin">Insurance Article, Title 8, Subtitle 3, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A carrier.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Board" means the Board of Directors for the Maryland Health Insurance Plan.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Carrier" means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An authorized insurer that provides health insurance in the State;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A nonprofit health service plan that is licensed to operate in the State; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A health maintenance organization that is licensed to operate in the State.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Health Plan.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Health plan" means any:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Contract providing hospital, medical, or surgical benefits on an expense incurred basis issued by an insurer;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Contract issued by a nonprofit health service plan;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Contract issued by a health maintenance organization; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Employer-sponsored plan that provides health benefits to the employees of the employer.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Health plan" does not include one or more, or any combination of the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Coverage only for accident or disability insurance;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Coverage issued as a supplement to liability insurance;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Coverage only for travel insurance;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Liability insurance, including general liability insurance and automobile liability insurance;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Workers' compensation or similar insurance;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Automobile medical payment insurance;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Credit-only insurance; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Coverage for on-site medical clinics.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>"Health plan" does not include the following benefits if they are provided under a separate policy, certificate, or contract of insurance or are otherwise not an integral part of a plan:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Limited scope dental or vision benefits;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Benefits for long-term care, nursing home care, home health care, community based care, or any combination of these benefits;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Coverage only for a specified disease or illness; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Hospital indemnity or other fixed indemnity insurance.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>"Health plan" does not include the following benefits if offered as a separate insurance policy:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Medicare supplemental health insurance, as defined under §1882(g)(1) of the Social Security Act;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Coverage supplemental to the coverage provided under 10 U.S.C. Chapter 55; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Coverage that is similar to the supplemental coverage described in §B(4)(d)(i) and (ii) of this regulation, which is provided as supplemental coverage under an employer sponsored plan.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Managed care organization" has the meaning stated in Health-General Article, §15-101, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Member" means an individual covered under the Plan.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Plan" means the Maryland Health Insurance Plan.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Plan Administrator" means the Administrator selected by the Board to administer the Plan.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Private review agent" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-10">Insurance Article, §15-10</cite>B-01(k), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Utilization review" means a system for reviewing the appropriate and efficient allocation of health care resources and services given or proposed to be given to a patient or group of patients.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Selection Criteria for Plan Administrator.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board may select an administrator to be the Plan Administrator only if the administrator:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Satisfies the requirements listed in §§C—I of this regulation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Meets all other terms that are established in any contract between the administrator and the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board may select more than one Plan Administrator to administer different benefits or administrative functions of the Plan.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Proven Ability to Provide Health Insurance Coverage to Individuals. An administrator shall provide evidence to the Board that it has at least 3 years experience of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Providing health plan benefits under insured contracts that cover at least 15,000 lives per year;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Administering health plans for self-funded employer health plans that cover at least 15,000 lives per year;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Enrolling at least 15,000 lives per year in the administrator's capacity as a managed care organization; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Insuring, administering, or enrolling at least 15,000 lives per year through a combination of any of the health plans or programs listed in §C(1)—(3) of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Efficiency and Timeliness of Administrator's Claim Processing Procedures.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A carrier shall provide evidence to the Board that it has procedures in place to comply with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The claim processing procedures required under Insurance Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-1004">15-1004</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-1006">15-1006</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-1008">15-1008</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-1009">15-1009</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland, for members covered under the Plan; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Any notice requirements specified by the Board in the request for proposals for the Plan Administrator.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An administrator that is not a carrier shall provide the following to the Board:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A detailed description of the claim procedures and processes that the administrator uses;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An assurance that the administrator shall accept the uniform claims form as adopted by the Commissioner under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-1003">Insurance Article, §15-1003, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, for claims submitted on behalf of members of the Plan;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>An assurance that the administrator shall comply with the uniform claims forms regulations in <cite path="|31.10.11">COMAR 31.10.11</cite> for claims submitted on behalf of members of the Plan;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>An assurance that the administrator shall pay claims for members of the Plan within the time required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-1005">Insurance Article, §15-1005, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>An assurance that if the administrator denies a member's claim, the administrator, upon request of the member, shall give written notice to the member that states fully the reason for the denial;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>An assurance that the administrator shall comply with the requirements regarding retroactive denial of reimbursement as found in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-1008">Insurance Article, §15-1008, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, for claims for members of the Plan;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>An assurance that the administrator shall comply with the requirements regarding reimbursement for preauthorized care as found in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-1009">Insurance Article, §15-1009, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, for claims for members of the Plan; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>An assurance that the administrator shall comply with any notice requirements specified by the Board in the request for proposals for the Plan Administrator.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Estimate of Total Charges for Administering the Plan. Each administrator that responds to a request for proposals to be the Plan Administrator shall provide, in the manner requested by the Board, an estimate of the total charges for administering the Plan.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Proven Ability to Apply Effective Cost Containment Programs.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each administrator that responds to a request for proposals to be the Plan Administrator shall provide to the Board:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A description of each cost containment program that the administrator has available to use in the State; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An estimate of the savings that each cost containment program will provide to the Plan.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Use of Private Review Agents. The Administrator shall provide to the Board an assurance that any utilization review performed for a member of the Plan shall be performed by a private review agent that has a certificate from the Commissioner to perform utilization review in the State.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Financial Condition and Stability of the Plan Administrator.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A carrier shall be deemed to meet the financial condition and stability requirements for the Plan Administrator if the carrier is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An insurer with a certificate of authority in good standing to write health insurance in the State;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A nonprofit health service plan with a certificate of authority in good standing to operate in the State; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A health maintenance organization with a certificate of authority in good standing to operate in the State.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An administrator who is not a carrier shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be registered in the State as an administrator under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin">Insurance Article, Title 8, Subtitle 3, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>File with the Board the administrator's financial statements audited by an independent certified public accountant from the preceding two calendar years.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Provider Panel Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A carrier shall provide evidence to the Board that it has procedures in place to comply with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The provider panel requirements of Insurance Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-112">15-112</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-115">15-115</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland, for any provider panels used to provide health care services to Plan members;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The compensation of health care practitioners requirements of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-113">Insurance Article, §15-113, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, for services rendered to Plan members; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The uniform credentialing form requirements of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-112">Insurance Article, §15-112</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland, when credentialing providers for the Plan.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An administrator that is not a carrier shall provide assurances to the Board that the administrator shall comply with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The provider panel requirements of Insurance Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-112">15-112</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-115">15-115</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland, for any provider panels used to provide health care services to Plan members;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The compensation of health care practitioners requirements of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-113">Insurance Article, §15-113, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, for services rendered to Plan members; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The uniform credentialing form requirements of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-112">Insurance Article, §15-112</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland, when credentialing providers for the Plan.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Use of Standardized Forms.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A carrier shall provide evidence to the Board that it has procedures in place to comply with the uniform consultation referral form requirements of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-119">Insurance Article, §15-119, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite> and <cite path="|31.10.12">COMAR 31.10.12</cite> for Plan member referrals.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An administrator that is not a carrier shall provide written assurance to the Board that it will comply with the uniform consultation referral form requirements of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|15-119">Insurance Article, §15-119, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite> and <cite path="|31.10.12">COMAR 31.10.12</cite> for Plan member referrals.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gin|14-506">Insurance Article, §14-506(a), </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-08-04">Regulations <cite path="|31|17|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|31|17|01|.03">.03</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective February 6, 2003 (30:5 Md. R. 365); adopted permanently effective August 4, 2003 (30:15 Md. R. 993)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
