<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>04</num>
  <heading>Forest Wildlife</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Junior Hunting Day.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Only an individual 16 years old or younger may participate on Junior Hunting Days as described in <cite path="08.03.03.03">COMAR 08.03.03.03</cite>, .07, and .08.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A junior hunter shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Possess a valid hunting license;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Possess a nonresident hunting license; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Be exempt from the hunting license requirement by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|10-301">Natural Resources Article, §10-301, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A junior hunter shall be accompanied by an unarmed individual who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is 21 years old or older; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Either:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Possesses a valid hunting license; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is exempt from the hunting license requirement by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|10-301">Natural Resources Article, §10-301, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|03|04|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Deer Management Permit Procedures.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Form of Request. Pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|10-415">Natural Resources Article, §10-415, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, a person may request that the Service investigate severe damage caused by deer for the purpose of having the Service reduce the deer population in the area.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Investigation. Upon receipt of a request for investigation, an investigator shall be assigned by the Service to investigate the area of alleged deer damage. The investigator shall furnish written findings to the Service on a form prescribed by the Service. The report shall contain a recommendation of action to be taken, if any, to reduce deer in the area.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>For the purposes of this regulation, “State agricultural crop land” means State properties which are listed and mapped on the Department’s website as being leased for the purpose of cultivating crops.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Service Action.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A deer management permit may be issued to a landowner, or the agricultural lessee of a landowner, for economic loss or significant ecological damage to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Commercial agricultural crops, including row crops, truck crops, and pasture;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Orchard or nursery stock;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Christmas trees;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Ornamental vegetation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Woodland areas that have forest management plans or tree planting plans that are written by a Department forester or a licensed private forester; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Native plant communities of ecological significance managed under the direction of a professional botanist or ecologist.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>At the earliest practicable time, but within 15 days from receipt of the formal request, the request and investigation report shall be reviewed by the Director or his representative, who shall decide what action shall be taken, if any, to reduce the deer population. The Director shall notify the complainant in writing of his decision.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Factors to be considered include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Nature, extent, and severity of damage as shown by investigation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Type of damage;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Time of year;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Deer population surveys and estimates.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An individual is ineligible to receive a deer management permit, or to act as an agent under the authority of a deer management permit, if the individual:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Cannot legally possess a firearm;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is ineligible to receive a Maryland hunting license;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Is within a period of license revocation or cancellation; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Has been convicted of a violation of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr">Natural Resources Article, Title 10, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, within a 2-year period before the date of the application for the deer management permit.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Deer Reduction Procedure.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If the Service determines that deer population reduction is necessary to prevent severe damage by deer in an area, the reduction shall be accomplished according to the procedures in this section.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Service shall issue a deer management permit to the landowner or lessee, who is a permittee under this regulation. A lessee shall secure permission of the landowner before using a deer management permit. The permit shall be valid for a period to be determined by the Service.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The permit in <cite path="08|03|04|.02|E.|(1)">§E(1) of this regulation</cite> shall describe:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The hunting device to be used;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The number of deer to be shot; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The type of deer to be taken as antlered, antlerless, or both.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>While attempting to take deer under the terms of the permit, the permittee and all designated shooters shall possess a copy of the deer management permit signed by both the permittee and the designated shooter, and present the permit to Department personnel upon request.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>In accordance with <cite path="|08|03|04|.24">Regulation .24 of this chapter</cite>, wanton waste is prohibited and an individual who intentionally wounds or kills a deer under the authority of a deer management permit shall make a reasonable effort to take possession of the wounded or dead deer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Tagging and Confirmation Procedures.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A confirmation number shall be generated or a game field tag shall be attached to the deer before removing it from the place of kill that includes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The deer management permit number;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Name and DNRid number of the permittee or designated shooter that killed the deer; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>County and date of harvest.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An individual shall report each deer killed to the Department through the Service’s telephone or Internet-based checking system not later than 24 hours after the deer was taken into the permittee’s or designated shooter’s possession.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Once a confirmation number has been generated by reporting the deer though the Service's telephone or Internet-based checking system, attaching a game field tag is not required while the deer remains in the hunter’s possession.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>When leaving a deer unattended or in the possession of another person, the deer shall be tagged with:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A game field tag as described in <cite path="08|03|04|.02|F.|(6)|(a)">§F(6)(a) of this regulation</cite>, if the deer has not been reported to the Department; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A tag that includes the permittee’s or designated shooter’s name and the confirmation number provided by the Department, if the deer has already been reported to the Department.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The tag required under <cite path="08|03|04|.02|F.|(6)">§F(6) of this regulation</cite> shall remain attached to the deer until the carcass is either:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Processed for consumption; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Disposed of by a processing facility.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Upon request, permittees and designated shooters shall provide a completed log sheet or an electronic record stored on a mobile device as proof that deer taken under the authority of the deer management permit were reported to the Department’s checking system.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>On the master copy of the confirmation number log sheet supplied with the deer management permit, a permittee shall record all the confirmation numbers with the date of kill, designated shooter number, and species and sex of any deer taken under the authority of the permit.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>The master copy of the confirmation number log sheet shall be returned with the deer management permit to the Service in accordance with the date set forth on the deer management permit.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Agents.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A permittee may designate individuals to serve as his agents for the purpose of shooting the deer during the period for which the permit is issued. All agents shall be approved by the Director or his representative, and their names shall be noted on the permit by the Director or his representative.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Agents shall possess a current, valid Maryland hunting license when shooting deer during the bow, firearms, or muzzleloader season. Exempt from this requirement to possess a hunting license are those individuals so exempted pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|10-301">Natural Resources Article, §10-301(b), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Permittees and agents shooting under the authority of a deer management permit shall wear fluorescent orange clothing in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|10-418">Natural Resources Article, §10-418(b), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite> when:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Using a firearm anytime;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Using any weapon during the deer firearms or muzzleloader season; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Using any weapon during the black bear season in a county or zone where the black bear season is open.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Deer or parts of a deer shot under a deer management permit shall be disposed of in the manner provided for in the permit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Using a Deer Management Permit.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Except as provided for in <cite path="08|03|04|.02|F.|(8)|(b)">§F(8)(b) of this regulation</cite>, all permittees and their agents shooting deer under the authority of a deer management permit may use any hunting device legal for hunting deer during the deer firearms season in that county or zone.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>In Baltimore, Calvert, Charles, Harford, and St. Mary’s counties, all persons shooting deer under the authority of a valid deer management permit may shoot deer using a breech loading center fired rifle or any hunting device legal for hunting deer during the deer firearms season.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>An individual authorized as a permittee on a deer management permit for property in Calvert, Charles, or St. Mary’s county who leases State agricultural crop land may shoot deer on the leased State agricultural land in Calvert, Charles, and St. Mary’s counties to the same extent, and subject to the same conditions, that the individual is authorized to shoot deer under the deer management permit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The deer management permit may contain other terms and conditions considered appropriate by the Department.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Appeal Procedure. If an application for a deer management permit is denied, the Service shall notify the applicant of the grounds upon which the denial is based. An individual who has received a notice that the Service has denied or refused an individual's application may file, within 21 days after the notice was mailed, a letter to the Director of the Service requesting a formal hearing. Upon receipt of the letter, the Service shall schedule a hearing before the Office of Administrative Hearings in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 10, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and <cite path="|08.01.04">COMAR 08.01.04</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Violations of any provision or restriction of the deer management permit constitute a violation of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>The Department shall provide an opportunity for a contested case hearing conducted in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 10, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and <cite path="|08.01.04">COMAR 08.01.04</cite> when suspending or revoking a deer management permit.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|03|04|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Tagging and Reporting Deer and Wild Turkey.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Tagging.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A game field tag, including the hunter’s name, DNR ID number, and the deer or turkey’s date and county of harvest, serves to identify the hunter who has killed a deer or turkey.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A big game harvest record of deer and turkey harvested by a hunter serves to record a hunter’s kill. The big game harvest record shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Include, for each deer or turkey killed, the species, sex, date and county of harvest, weapon class and confirmation number attained from the Department at the time of reporting in accordance with <cite path="08|03|04|.03|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Be in the hunter’s possession while deer or turkey hunting.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Game field tags and big game harvest records may be provided by the Department when purchasing a Maryland hunting license, may be obtained from any DNR sport license agent, or created by the hunter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A hunter’s possession of an electronic record of the confirmation number acquired in accordance with <cite path="08|03|04|.03|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> may substitute for the game field tag or big game harvest record. An electronic record may be presented:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>By accessing the hunter’s DNR license system account by a cell phone, tablet, or other electronic device; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>As a digital copy of a completed big game harvest record.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A game field tag shall be attached to the deer or turkey before removing it from the place of kill.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>If a confirmation number has been generated, attaching a game field tag is not required while the deer or turkey remains in the hunter’s possession.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>When leaving a deer or turkey unattended or in the possession of another person, the deer or turkey shall be tagged with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A game field tag as described in <cite path="08|03|04|.03|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite>, if the deer or turkey has not been reported to the Department; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A tag that includes the hunter’s name and the confirmation number provided by the Department if the deer or turkey has already been reported to the Department.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The tag required under <cite path="08|03|04|.03|A.|(7)">§A(7) of this regulation</cite> shall remain attached to the deer or turkey until the carcass is either:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Processed for consumption;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Disposed of by a processing facility; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Left with a taxidermist.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Harvest Reporting.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An individual killing a deer or turkey shall report the kill to the Department by calling a designated toll-free number, by registering the kill on the Department’s internet-based checking system accessible through the Department’s website, or as otherwise designated on the Department’s website.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The harvest of a deer or turkey shall be reported not later than 24 hours after the deer or turkey was taken into possession by the hunter. Deer must be reported before the head or hide is removed. Turkeys must be reported before being processed for consumption.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>After reporting the kill, the hunter will receive a confirmation number from the Department that shall be recorded in ink on the big game harvest record or shall be in the hunter’s possession as an electronic record in accordance with <cite path="08|03|04|.03|A.|(4)">§A(4) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The requirements of this regulation apply to all hunters including those hunters who are exempt from the hunting license requirements of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|10-301">Natural Resources Article, §10-301, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Reporting Deer or Turkey Killed by Means Other than Hunting.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may take possession of a deer or turkey that has been killed by means other than hunting by obtaining a confirmation number from the Department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An individual taking possession of a deer or turkey killed by means other than hunting shall report the deer or turkey to the Department by registering the kill on the Department’s internet-based checking system accessible through the Department’s website, or as otherwise designated on the Department’s website.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Prior to taking possession and transporting the deer or turkey, a field tag, including the person’s name, address, county location of the deer or turkey, and method of kill, shall be attached until a confirmation number has been obtained.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If a confirmation number has been obtained, a field tag is not required if the deer or turkey remains in the person’s possession.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The deer or turkey shall be reported not later than 24 hours after the deer or turkey is taken into possession. Deer shall be reported before the head or hide is removed. Turkeys shall be reported before being processed for consumption.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>After registering the deer or turkey, the person shall receive a confirmation number.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The individual shall maintain a record of the confirmation number. The confirmation number shall be made available to the Department on request.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A deer or turkey not tagged as required by this regulation and found in the possession of any person may be confiscated by any authorized representative of the Department and shall be disposed of as the Director may deem advisable for the best interest of the State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A person may not knowingly make any false statements or record false information when tagging or reporting the harvest of any deer or turkey.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Devices for Hunting Forest Game.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A person may hunt forest game with a bow, a rifle, or any other means not prohibited by these regulations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A person may not hunt forest game, except deer or black bear, with any automatic loading or hand-operated repeating shotgun capable of holding more than three shells, unless the magazine is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Cut off; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Plugged with a solid, one-piece filler which cannot be removed from the loading end.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The gun cannot hold more than three shells in the magazine and chamber combined.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|03|04|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Devices for Hunting Deer and Black Bear.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="08|03|04|.05|I.">§I of this regulation</cite>, only the weapons described in §§B and C of this regulation may be used to hunt deer and black bear. All other weapon types are prohibited for hunting deer or black bear.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Bow.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An individual may use a bow to hunt deer and black bear during all legal deer and black bear hunting seasons.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A deer or black bear taken with a bow shall count towards the respective season's bag limits.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An individual may not:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Possess an airgun or firearm while hunting with a bow during the deer bow hunting season, except in Deer Management Region A as described in <cite path="08.03.03.06|A.|(2)|(a)">COMAR 08.03.03.06A(2)(a)</cite>, a person 21 years old or older may carry a handgun for personal protection while hunting deer in the bow season if that handgun:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Has a barrel length not exceeding 6 inches;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Does not have a telescopic sight or electronic aiming device attached; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Is not used to kill wildlife wounded by a vertical bow or crossbow.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Hunt with a bow from or on any vehicle except as provided for in <cite path="08.03.10.09">COMAR 08.03.10.09</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Use a poisoned arrow; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Use an arrow with an explosive tip.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>An individual may use a telescopic sight or electronic aiming device on a bow.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Vertical Bow.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A vertical bow used for deer and black bear hunting shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Use an arrow with a sharpened broadhead with metal points and a minimum width of 7/8 inch; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Have a full draw and pull of not less than 30 pounds</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An individual may use a release aid with a vertical bow.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>An individual may use a vertical bow equipped with a draw-lock device.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Crossbow.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A crossbow used for deer or black bear hunting shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Use an arrow with a sharpened broadhead with metal points and a minimum width of 7/8 inch;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Have a draw weight of not less than 75 pounds; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Have a working safety.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A crossbow may be cocked with the aid of a mechanical device.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>An individual may not possess a crossbow loaded with an arrow while in or on a vehicle except as provided for in <cite path="08.03.10.09">COMAR 08.03.10.09</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Firearms.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An individual may hunt deer and black bear only with the firearms in §C(2)—(6) of this regulation, subject to the restrictions provided in §§D and E of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A rifle or shotgun propelling one soft-nosed or expanding bullet or ball at a single discharge which generates at least 1,200 foot-pounds of muzzle energy is allowed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A handgun having a barrel length of 6 inches or longer and ammunition which produces a muzzle energy of 700 foot-pounds or more is allowed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A muzzle loading rifle or muzzle loading shotgun, not less than .40 caliber and using not less than the equivalent of 60 grains of black powder or a single shot muzzle loading handgun or muzzle loading revolver of not less than .40 caliber with a minimum barrel length of 6 inches and using not less than the equivalent of 40 grains of black powder propelling one soft-nosed or expanding bullet or ball at a single discharge, is allowed. Sabot loads are allowed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>An air gun that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Propels one .40 caliber or greater bullet or ball at a single discharge which generates at least 400 foot-pounds of muzzle energy; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Propels an arrow at least 18" in length with a minimum speed of 300 feet per second at release, uses an arrow with a sharpened broadhead with metal points and a minimum width of 7/8 inch, and has a working safety if the device is fired by a trigger.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>In Dorchester County only, a shotgun propelling Number 1 size buckshot or larger is allowed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>An individual may use a telescopic sight or electronic aiming device on a firearm.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Firearms — Restrictions. In the counties listed below, an individual may hunt deer with a rifle or handgun, employing a straight-walled cartridge, a shotgun, an air gun, a muzzle loading rifle, a muzzle loading shotgun, a muzzle loading handgun, or a muzzle loading revolver:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Anne Arundel;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Baltimore;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Calvert;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Charles;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Harford;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Howard;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Kent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Montgomery;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Prince George's;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Queen Anne's;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>St. Mary's;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Talbot; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>In Worcester:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Within 1 mile of any school;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>That portion of South Point lying south of a line beginning at the west end of the Sinepuxent Bay bridge on State Route 611, then by and with the south side of Route 611 to the junction of the South Point road going south for a distance of 0.6 miles to a point opposite the southern boundary of the Ocean City Golf and Yacht Club property on the west side of the road, then by the southern boundary of the Ocean City Golf and Yacht Club to Trappe Creek; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>That portion of the lands lying south of a line beginning at the mouth of the St. Martin River northwest to the junction with Shingle Landing Road, then by and with the south side of Shingle Landing Road to the junction with Route 113, then by and with the east side of Route 113 to the junction with Route 589, then by and with the east side of Route 589 to the junction with Route 50, then by and with the north side of Route 50 to the junction with Isle of Wight Bay, then by and with the west boundary of Isle of Wight Bay to the junction with St. Martin River.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>In that portion of Frederick County located west of the Monocacy River beginning where Fingerboard Road crosses the river, then by and with the west side of the Monocacy River to the crossing by Biggs Ford Road, then by and with the south side of Biggs Ford Road to the junction with Route 15, then by and with the west side of Route 15 to the junction with Sundays Lane, then by and with the south side of Sundays Lane to the junction with Bloomfield Road, then by and with the east side of Bloomfield Road to the junction with Opossumtown Pike, then by and with the south side of Opossumtown Pike to the junction with Walter Martz Road, then by and with the east side of Walter Martz Road to the junction with Christopher’s Crossing, then by and with the south side of Christopher’s Crossing to the junction with Walter Martz Road, then by and with the south side of Walter Martz Road to the junction with Rocky Springs Road, then by and with the south and east side of Rocky Springs Road to the junction with Kemp Lane, then by and with the east side of Kemp Lane to the junction with Shookstown Road, then by and with the north side of Shookstown Road to the junction with Bowers Road, then by and with the east side of Bowers Road to the junction West Patrick Street, then by and with the north side of West Patrick Street to the junction with Blentlinger Road, then by and with the east side of Blentlinger Road to the junction with Old National Pike, then by and with the south side of Old National Pike to the junction with Maryland Interstate 70, then by and with the north side of Maryland Interstate 70 to the junction with Route 15, then by and with the east side of Route 15 to the junction with Mt. Zion Road, then by and with the north side of Mt. Zion Road to the junction with Elmer Derr Road, and then by and with the north side of Elmer Derr Road to the junction with New Design Road, then by and with the east side of New Design Road to the junction with Manor Woods Road, then by and with the north side of Manor Woods Road to the junction with Buckystown Pike, then by and with the east side of Buckystown Pike to the junction with Fingerboard Road, and then by and with the north side of Fingerboard Road to the crossing over the Monocacy River, an individual may hunt deer with a rifle, employing a straight-walled cartridge, a handgun, a shotgun, a muzzle loading rifle, a muzzle loading shotgun, a muzzle loading handgun, or a muzzle loading revolver.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>An individual may hunt deer with firearms, bow, or both, during the firearms season.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Except as prohibited by <cite path="08|03|04|.05|H.">§H of this regulation</cite>, an individual may hunt deer with muzzle loading firearms, bow, or both, during the muzzle loader firearms season.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>An individual may not possess both a muzzle loading firearm and a bow while hunting when muzzle loading season and bow season overlap or during the February deer hunting season dates.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Primitive Weapon.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An individual may only use a primitive weapon to hunt deer during the February deer hunting season dates.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An individual may not use a primitive weapon equipped with a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Telescopic or electronic aiming device;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Release aid; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Draw lock device.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The use of a crossbow is prohibited during the February deer hunting season dates.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A muzzle loading firearm used for deer hunting during the February deer hunting season dates shall be of a flintlock or percussion cap sidelock design. Modern inline muzzle loading firearms are prohibited.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Wild Turkey Hunting.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Shooting hours during the spring turkey season are from 1/2 hour before sunrise to 12 noon except during the last 2 weeks of the season and on the Junior Hunting Day when the shooting hours are 1/2 hour before sunrise to sunset.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A person may not use dogs or organized drives for the purpose of hunting turkeys during the spring season.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>During the spring and winter turkey seasons a person may only hunt turkeys with an air gun propelling an arrow, a bow, or shotgun with shotgun shells loaded with shot size number 4 or smaller.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>During the fall turkey season a person may only hunt turkeys with a rifle, handgun, bow, air gun, or shotgun with shotgun shells loaded with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shot size number 4 or smaller; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A solid single projectile, such as a pumpkin ball, sabot, or slug.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>To hunt wild turkeys, a person may not use:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Recorded or electronically amplified calls; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Motorized decoys operated by batteries or any source of electricity.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Repealed.</heading>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Permit Requirements for Aberdeen Proving Ground.</heading>
    <text>An individual shall obtain a special Aberdeen Proving Ground Hunting Permit before hunting is authorized on this military installation.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Eastern Neck National Wildlife Refuge Deer Hunting Seasons.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Seasons. At Eastern Neck National Wildlife Refuge, the deer hunting season or seasons will be set by the Refuge Manager between the dates of September 1 and December 31. The actual opening and closing dates shall be proposed by the Refuge Manager and approved by the Director, on or before September 1, annually.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Bag limits shall conform to Statewide bag limits.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A person shall obtain a special Eastern Neck National Wildlife Refuge hunting permit before hunting is authorized on the Refuge.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Daily Deer Bag Limit.</heading>
    <text>There is no limit to the number of deer that an individual may bag in 1 day, within the confines of the bag limit for that season and deer management region.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Hunting Wild Turkeys and Black Bear Over Bait.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definitions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Baited area” means any area where shelled, shucked, or unshucked corn, wheat, other grain, or other feed capable of luring, attracting, or enticing wild turkeys or black bears is directly or indirectly placed, exposed, deposited, distributed, or scattered. An area is considered a baited area for 10 days following complete removal of all corn, wheat, other grain, or other feed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Baiting” means the placing, exposing, depositing, distributing, or scattering of shelled, shucked, or unshucked corn, wheat, other grain, or other feed so as to constitute for wild turkeys or black bears a lure, attraction, or enticement to, on, or over any areas where hunters are attempting to take wild turkeys or black bears.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A person may not take or attempt to take wild turkeys or black bears by the aid of baiting, or on or over any baited area if the person knows or reasonably should know that the area is a baited area.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>This regulation does not prohibit the taking of wild turkeys or black bears on or over:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Standing crops, grain crops properly shucked on the field where grown, or grains found scattered solely as the result of normal agricultural planting or harvesting.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Lands where shelled, shucked, or unshucked corn, wheat, other grain, or other feed has been distributed or scattered as the result of bona fide agricultural operations or procedures, or as a result of manipulation of a crop or other feed on the land where grown for wildlife management purposes. Manipulation of crops or other feed for wildlife management purposes does not include the distributing or scattering of grain or other feed once it has been removed from or stored on the field where grown.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Lands where a person is hunting black bear during the black bear season provided that the person and any black bear that the person shoots at is 150 yards or more from an area where grain or other feed has been legally placed for the purpose of attracting wildlife other than black bears.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Lands where a person is hunting wild turkeys during the fall season provided that the person and any wild turkey that the person shoots at is 150 yards or more from an area where grain or other feed has been legally placed for the purpose of attracting wildlife other than wild turkeys.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Patuxent River Naval Air Station Deer Hunting Seasons.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Seasons. Season dates will conform to Statewide season dates. However, the commanding officer of the station may extend the length of the firearm season 1 week if necessary to meet the harvest quota for that season.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Bag Limits. The bag limits for the Station will be two deer of either sex for each of the three seasons to hunt deer.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Repealed.</heading>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Deer Hunting Season on Military Bases, National Wildlife Refuges, and Units of the National Park System.</heading>
    <text>Deer hunting seasons and bag limits at all military bases, National Wildlife Refuges, and units of the National Park System shall conform to Statewide seasons and bag limits. However, the commanding officer of the base, manager of the National Wildlife Refuge, or superintendent of the National Park unit may submit a written request for an extension of the season, or to increase the bag limit, to the Director by August 1, annually. The Director shall review the request and advise the commanding officer of the base, manager of the National Wildlife Refuge, or superintendent of the National Park unit, of the Director's decision, in writing, within 30 days of the receipt of the formal request.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Bow Hunting on Junior Hunting Day.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>On the Junior Hunting Day described in <cite path="08.03.03.07">COMAR 08.03.03.07</cite>—.08 an individual:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>17 years old or older may hunt deer with a bow provided that any deer taken shall count toward the bow season bag limit;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>16 years old or younger may hunt deer with a bow provided that any deer taken shall count toward the Junior Hunting Day bag limit.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>All bowhunters hunting on the Junior Hunting Day described in <cite path="08.03.03.07">COMAR 08.03.03.07</cite>—.08 shall wear fluorescent orange or daylight fluorescent pink clothing in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|10-418">Natural Resources Article, §10-418, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Attracting Bears.</heading>
    <text>A person may not place any harvested agricultural crop, animal carcass, or food products on any area that may cause bears to congregate or become habituated to an area. A law enforcement officer may issue a citation to a person if the person does not remove the attractant following a request from a law enforcement officer.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.17</num>
    <heading>Special Deer Hunting Seasons in State Parks.</heading>
    <text>Hunting seasons and bag limits at all State parks shall conform to Statewide seasons and bag limits unless otherwise limited by <cite path="08.07.06.03">COMAR 08.07.06.03</cite>. However, if necessary to reduce the white-tailed deer population in the area, the Director may request special white-tailed deer hunting seasons in State parks where it is necessary. The Director shall review the request and either approve it, deny it, or approve it with conditions.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.18</num>
    <heading>Managed Deer Hunts.</heading>
    <text>The Department may authorize a managed deer hunt to occur on private or public land, that is not subject to the season dates or bag limits in <cite path="08.03.03.07">COMAR 08.03.03.07</cite>. A person, or persons, may apply to the Director of the Service to request permission to hold a managed deer hunt. The Director of the Service shall review the request and either approve it, describing the conditions under which the hunt may be held, or deny the request.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.19</num>
    <heading>Use of Dogs for Tracking Deer and Black Bear.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>It is unlawful to use dogs for locating dead, wounded, or injured deer or black bear except, if an individual legally hunting deer or black bear has killed, wounded, or injured a deer or black bear, or reasonably believes the individual has killed, wounded, or injured a deer or black bear, the individual may either personally, or by engaging a dog handler, use a dog to track and recover the killed, wounded, or injured deer or black bear.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The act of tracking a dead, wounded, or injured deer or black bear, with a dog, is considered to be hunting as defined by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|10-101">Natural Resources Article, §10-101(j), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and is subject to all applicable laws, regulations, and conditions.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>No person other than the hunter or the dog handler may carry a firearm or bow of any description while tracking dead, wounded, or injured deer or black bear under this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The hunter or the dog handler may kill a wounded or injured deer or black bear only if done in accordance with the laws, regulations, or other conditions for deer or black bear hunting at that time. The deer or black bear shall count toward the bag limit or quota of the hunter who first killed, wounded, or injured the deer or black bear.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Before tracking a dead, wounded, or injured deer or black bear, the hunter shall notify, by telephone or in person, the Natural Resources Police regional office. If the nearest regional office of the Natural Resources Police is unavailable, the hunter may notify the Department of Natural Resources Communication Center. The hunter shall provide information as to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Where the deer or black bear was killed, wounded, or injured;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The name, address, telephone number, and hunting license number of the hunter and dog handler;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The general location of the dead, wounded, or injured deer or black bear; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The name of the landowner where the search will be conducted.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The dog handler shall maintain physical control of the leashed tracking dog at all times while conducting the search.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The hunter shall obtain permission of the landowner or land manager before tracking deer or black bear with dogs as provided in this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|03|04|.20">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.20</num>
    <heading>Black Bear Hunting.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this regulation, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Annual mortality rate” means the estimated percent of the black bear population in the hunted area that is known to have died as a result of natural death, accidents, hunting, or other causes.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Hunted area” means Allegany County, Frederick County, Garrett County, and Washington County.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Known mortality rate” means the estimated percent of the black bear population in the hunted area that is known to have died as a result of natural death, accidents, or other nonhunting related causes.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Permittee” means a person who has been issued a permit to hunt black bears by the Service.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Subpermittee” means a person designated by the permittee to participate with the permittee in hunting black bears.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Targeted harvest rate” means the difference between the Department's goal for the annual mortality rate and the known mortality rate.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A person may hunt black bears in accordance with <cite path="08.03.03.03|F.">COMAR 08.03.03.03F</cite> after meeting the conditions listed in §§D—N of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Permit Required.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may not hunt or participate in a hunt for black bears in Maryland without having first obtained a black bear hunting permit from the Service.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person that assists with the removal of a dead bear or escorts hunters into or out of a bear hunting area:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is not required to possess a bear hunting permit; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Shall be unarmed.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A subpermittee may continue to hunt black bears when the permittee is not hunting black bears.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Targeted Harvest Rate.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Prior to the beginning of a hunting season, the Service will determine the targeted harvest rate for the season.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Service will issue the number of permits estimated to be required to meet the targeted harvest rate for the season.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>At the discretion of the Director, the Service shall either close the season upon a determination that the targeted harvest rate has been reached or establish an appropriate season length estimated to achieve the targeted harvest rate.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The use of dogs to hunt black bears is prohibited, except as provided in <cite path="|08|03|04|.19">Regulation .19 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The use of scent attractants or electronic calls is prohibited for black bear hunting.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Any person killing a black bear shall attach the black bear field tag to the carcass of the black bear before removing the carcass from the place of the kill.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Proof of sex shall remain attached to all field-dressed bear carcasses.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>A black bear may be quartered or separated into pieces to facilitate retrieval. However, the head and hide shall remain attached to each other and proof of sex shall remain attached to one hindquarter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="08|03|04|.20|M.">§M of this regulation</cite>, a person killing a black bear shall report to an official designated black bear checking station with the entire carcass of the black bear by 8 p.m. of the day of kill. At this time, the tag previously attached on the carcass shall be exchanged for an official black bear possession tag provided by the Service and securely attached to the carcass.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>If a person kills a bear and cannot reach a designated black bear checking station by 8 p.m. of the day of kill, the person shall contact the appropriate Service office by 8 p.m. on the day of the kill to report the kill. The person shall then have 24 hours to report with the black bear carcass to a designated black bear checking station.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>All successful black bear hunters shall forfeit any biological data or specimens that the Service considers necessary to properly manage this species.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>Any violation of the terms and conditions of the black bear hunting permit is a violation of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.21</num>
    <heading>Reporting the Wounding or Killing of a Black Bear</heading>
    <text>Unless authorized by a black bear hunting permit issued pursuant to <cite path="|08|03|04|.20">Regulation .20 of this chapter</cite>, any person that kills or wounds a black bear shall report the killing or wounding within 24 hours to the Department by contacting the Department of Natural Resources (DNR) Communications Center at 410-260-8888.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|03|04|.22">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.22</num>
    <heading>Cervid Carcass and Part Importation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this regulation, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Authorized commercial deer processor” means an establishment that is open to the public and processes cervid carcasses or parts into food products for compensation and that possesses a letter from the Director granting permission to possess and process deer taken from within a CWD management area.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Authorized licensed taxidermist” means a taxidermist licensed with the Service in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|10-512">Natural Resources article, §10-512, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, who is permitted to possess and preserve, mount or tan cervid carcasses or cervid parts taken from within a CWD management area in accordance with <cite path="08|03|04|.22|C.|(2)">§C(2) of this regulation</cite>..</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Cervid.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Cervid” means a hoofed animal that is a member of the family Cervidae.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Cervid” includes, but is not limited to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Black-tailed deer;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Caribou (reindeer);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Elk;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Fallow deer;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Moose;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Mule deer;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Musk deer;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Pampas deer;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ix)</num>
            <text>Red deer;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(x)</num>
            <text>Roe deer;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xi)</num>
            <text>Sika deer;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xii)</num>
            <text>Swamp deer;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xiii)</num>
            <text>Tufted deer; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xiv)</num>
            <text>White-tailed deer.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“CWD” means chronic wasting disease.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“CWD management area” means a geographical region in Maryland where the Department has determined there is a need to minimize the spread of CWD by restricting certain practices.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“CWD positive area” means a geographical region outside of Maryland where the Department has determined that chronic wasting disease has been detected in free-ranging or captive cervids.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>CWD Positive Areas and CWD Management Areas.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Department shall maintain a list of CWD positive areas, CWD management areas, authorized commercial deer processors and authorized licensed taxidermists and make this list available to the public and post it on the Department's website. The Department shall disseminate a notice of modification to the list through various media and post it on the Department’s website so that an affected person has a reasonable opportunity to be informed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>CWD Authorized Taxidermist.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A licensed taxidermist may be authorized to possess and preserve, mount or tan cervid carcasses or cervid parts taken from within a CWD management area by signing an agreement to comply with disposal methods prescribed by the Service.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Service shall list a CWD authorization on a taxidermy license.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Importation, Transportation, and Possession Prohibited. Except as provided in §§E, G, and H of this regulation, a person may not import, transport, or possess a part of a dead cervid from a CWD positive area or a CWD management area.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Importation, Transportation, and Possession of Certain Cervid Parts Allowed. A person may import, transport, and possess the following parts of a dead cervid from a CWD positive area or a CWD management area:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Antlers with no meat or soft tissue attached;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Finished taxidermy mount;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Hide, clean with no head attached;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Boneless meat;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Skull plate cleaned of all meat and brain tissue;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Upper canine teeth, also known as buglers, whistlers, or ivories, cleaned of all soft tissue; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Leg quarters, to include the bones, meat or hide of the front or hind legs, of a cervid with no portion of the spinal column attached.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Notification Required.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a person imports a part of a dead cervid from a CWD positive area and receives notice after the importation that the cervid has tested positive for CWD, the person shall contact the Department within 24 hours after receiving the notice of a positive CWD test.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a person imports a part of a dead cervid from a CWD positive area and knows at the time of importation the cervid has tested positive for CWD, the person shall contact the Department within 24 hours of importation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The contact of the Department as required by §F(1) and (2) of this regulation shall be made by phone, fax, or email as prescribed on the Department's website or in the annual Guide to Hunting and Trapping in Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Department may assist with disposal of cervid parts from animals that have tested positive for CWD.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Department shall maintain a record of notifications received pursuant to this section for tracking purposes.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Temporary Possession Allowed.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may import and possess any part of a dead cervid from a CWD positive area or a CWD management area if the dead cervid carcass or part does not remain in the State for longer than 24 hours.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If any part of a cervid imported and possessed in the State as authorized by <cite path="08|03|04|.22|G.|(1)">§G(1) of this regulation</cite> remains in the State for more than 24 hours, the person in possession shall notify the Department by phone, fax, or email as prescribed on the Department's website or in the annual Guide to Hunting and Trapping in Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person may transport a cervid carcass or part from a CWD management area to an authorized commercial deer processor within the same county within 24 hours of taking the cervid into possession.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A person may transport a cervid carcass or part taken from a CWD management area to an authorized licensed taxidermist.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>An authorized commercial deer processor or authorized licensed taxidermist in Maryland may possess a cervid carcass or part originating from a CWD management area within Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>A person may import and possess any part of a dead cervid from a CWD positive area or CWD management area out of the State, if within 24 hours of entering the State the dead cervid’s final disposition is within a Maryland CWD management area or to a Department-approved CWD processor or taxidermist.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.23</num>
    <heading>Hunting Deer When the Black Bear Season is Open.</heading>
    <text>A person may not bow hunt or assist with bow hunting deer in the hunted area for black bears as defined by <cite path="08.03.04.20|B.">COMAR 08.03.04.20B</cite> when the black bear hunting season is open unless the person wears:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A cap of solid daylight fluorescent orange or daylight fluorescent pink color;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A vest, jacket, or jacket containing back and front panels of at least 250 square inches of a solid daylight fluorescent orange or daylight fluorescent pink color; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An outer garment of camouflage fluorescent orange or daylight fluorescent pink worn above the waist which contains at least 50 percent daylight fluorescent orange or daylight fluorescent pink color.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|03|04|.24">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.24</num>
    <heading>Wanton Waste of Deer Prohibited.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="08|03|04|.24|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, an individual who intentionally wounds or kills a deer with a firearm, bow, or crossbow shall make a reasonable effort to take possession of the wounded or dead deer. If recovered, the deer shall be tagged and reported in accordance with <cite path="|08|03|04|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite> and retained in the individual's possession until any of the following occurs:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The deer is processed for consumption;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The deer is transported to the individual's residence, to the individual’s temporary place of lodging, to a taxidermist, or to a place for commercial or noncommercial processing or is donated to another individual or organization;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The deer is utilized for scientific, educational, or research purposes; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The deer is properly disposed of according to conditions included in a permit issued by the Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Nothing in this regulation shall be construed to supersede any provision of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|10-411">Natural Resources Article, §10-411, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, requiring written permission before entering the lands owned by another person.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An individual who humanely euthanizes an injured deer they did not intentionally wound is exempt from this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Failure to make a reasonable attempt to recover a wounded or killed deer, or failure to use a deer in a manner described in <cite path="08|03|04|.24|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, will be deemed wanton waste.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.25</num>
    <heading>Killing Wounded Deer After Legal Shooting Hours.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A hunter who wounds a deer during legal shooting hours may pursue and kill the deer after legal shooting hours subject to the following restrictions:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The pursuit and killing of the deer must occur within 24 hours of the end of legal shooting hours on the day the deer was wounded;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>No person other than the hunter or a tracking dog handler may carry a firearm or bow of any description while pursuing a wounded deer after legal shooting hours;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>No person other than the hunter or a tracking dog handler may kill a wounded deer that is pursued after legal shooting hours;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The hunter or tracking dog handler shall use only the means authorized for the applicable hunting season or permit to pursue and kill the deer; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>No additional hunting or pursuit of unwounded game is permitted after legal shooting hours.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Except as provided for in this subtitle, the act of pursuing and killing a wounded deer constitutes hunting as defined by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|10-101">Natural Resources Article, §10-101(k)(1), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and is subject to all applicable laws, regulations, and conditions.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A hunter who pursues a wounded deer after legal shooting hours may use an artificial light including a spotlight, flashlight, headlamp, or other lighting device to cast a ray on the deer while in pursuit or while killing the animal.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Motorized vehicles may not be used to pursue a wounded deer during or after legal shooting hours.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If a hunter believes a deer will need to be killed after legal shooting hours, the hunter shall notify the Natural Resources Police by calling the Department of Natural Resources (DNR) Communication Center 24-Hour Emergency telephone number prior to initiating or continuing the pursuit after legal shooting hours and once the pursuit has concluded. The hunter shall provide the following information:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The address and general location of where the deer was wounded;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The name, address, telephone number, and DNRid number of the hunter;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The name and, if known, the telephone number of the landowner where the deer was wounded;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The direction in which the wounded deer was traveling; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The status of the pursuit when it concluded.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>This subtitle does not authorize a hunter to trespass onto the property of another in pursuit of a wounded deer.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Recovered deer must be tagged and reported in accordance with <cite path="08.03.04.03">COMAR 08.03.04.03</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation app="2025-10-13" doc="Maryland Register, Volume 52, Issue 20" eff="2025-10-13" path="regulations|final|25-158-F" type="History" display="false"/>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Natural Resources Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|1-104">1-104</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|10-205">10-205</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|10-206">10-206</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|10-301">10-301</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|10-308">10-308</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|10-309">10-309</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|10-404">10-404</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|10-409">10-409</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|10-415">10-415</cite>,<br/>10-416, 10-418, 10-902, and 10-903; <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-206">State Government Article, §10-206</cite>; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-06-03">Regulations <cite path="|08|03|04|.02">.02</cite>—<cite path="|08|03|04|.05">.05</cite> were previously codified as Regulations .14, .21, .26, and Regulations <cite path="|08|03|04|.06">.06</cite>—<cite path="|08|03|04|.10">.10</cite> were previously codified as Regulations .30, .51, .52, .55, and .67, respectively, under <cite path="|08.03.01">COMAR 08.03.01</cite> Wildlife Conservation. This recodification was effective June 3, 1985 (12:11 Md. R. 1047)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-06-03">For the history of these regulations before June 3, 1985, see the Administrative History which follows <cite path="|08.03.01">COMAR 08.03.01</cite>.</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-06-03" discontinuity="true"><cite path="|08|03|04|.01">Regulation .01</cite> adopted effective June 3, 1985 (12:11 Md. R. 1047)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1997-01-13"><cite path="|08|03|04|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 19, 1996 (23:16 Md. R. 1166); amended permanently effective January 13, 1997 (24:1 Md. R. 29)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-08-15"><cite path="|08|03|04|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective July 29, 1985 (12:15 Md. R. 1514); June 30, 1986 (13:13 Md. R. 1489); July 25, 1988 (15:15 Md. R. 1808); June 26, 1989 (16:12 Md. R. 1334); September 2, 1991 (18:17 Md. R. 1917); August 31, 1992 (19:17 Md. R. 1606); August 15, 1994 (21:16 Md. R. 1381)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1988-07-25"><cite path="|08|03|04|.01|C.">Regulation .01C</cite> amended effective June 30, 1986 (13:13 Md. R. 1489); October 19, 1987 (14:21 Md. R. 2222); July 25, 1988 (15:15 Md. R. 1808)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1988-07-25"><cite path="|08|03|04|.01|D.">Regulation .01D</cite> amended effective July 29, 1985 (12:15 Md. R. 1514); July 25, 1988 (15:15 Md. R. 1808)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-08-31"><cite path="|08|03|04|.01|E.">Regulation .01E</cite> amended effective August 31, 1992 (19:17 Md. R. 1606)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-12-28"><cite path="|08|03|04|.01">Regulation .01</cite> repealed and new Regulation .01 adopted as an emergency provision effective September 15, 1998 (25:21 Md. R. 1571); adopted permanently effective December 28, 1998 (25:26 Md. R. 1920)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-08-07"><cite path="|08|03|04|.01|A.">Regulation .01A</cite> amended effective August 7, 2000 (27:15 Md. R. 1400)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-08-19"><cite path="|08|03|04|.01">Regulation .01</cite> repealed and new Regulation .01 adopted effective August 19, 2002 (29:16 Md. R. 1287)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-10-12"><cite path="|08|03|04|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective September 2, 1991 (18:17 Md. R. 1917); September 3, 2001 (28:17 Md. R. 1555); March 3, 2003 (30:4 Md. R. 315); December 22, 2014 (41:25 Md. R. 1478); October 12, 2015 (42:20 Md. R. 1263)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-10-19"><cite path="|08|03|04|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended effective October 19, 2020 (47:21 Md. R. 903)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-08-31"><cite path="|08|03|04|.02|D.">Regulation .02D</cite> amended effective June 30, 1986 (13:13 Md. R. 1489); July 25, 1988 (15:15 Md. R. 1808); July 23, 1990 (17:14 Md. R. 1756); August 31, 1992 (19:17 Md. R. 1606)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-08-23"><cite path="|08|03|04|.02|E.">Regulation .02E</cite> amended effective August 15, 2005 (32:16 Md. R. 1391); September 25, 2006 (33:19 Md. R. 1558); November 30, 2009 (36:24 Md. R. 1857); August 23, 2010 (37:17 Md. R. 1184)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-06-30"><cite path="|08|03|04|.02|F.">Regulation .02F</cite> adopted effective June 30, 1986 (13:13 Md. R. 1489)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-10-19"><cite path="|08|03|04|.02|F.">Regulation .02F</cite> amended effective August 15, 2016 (43:16 Md. R. 899); September 11, 2017 (44:18 Md. R. 864); October 8, 2018 (45:20 Md. R. 917); October 19, 2020 (47:21 Md. R. 903)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-10-08"><cite path="|08|03|04|.02|G.">Regulation .02G</cite> amended effective September 25, 2006 (33:19 Md. R. 1558); April 5, 2010 (37:7 Md. R. 569); October 8, 2018 (45:20 Md. R. 917)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-04-05"><cite path="|08|03|04|.02|I.">Regulation .02I</cite> adopted effective April 5, 2010 (37:7 Md. R. 569)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-10-05"><cite path="|08|03|04|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective August 15, 2005 (32:16 Md. R. 1391); October 8, 2018 (45:20 Md. R. 917); October 5, 2020 (47:20 Md. R. 874)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-09-11"><cite path="|08|03|04|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite> amended effective August 15, 1994 (21:16 Md. R. 1381); August 14, 2006 (33:16 Md. R. 1365); September 11, 2017 (44:18 Md. R. 864)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-12-28"><cite path="|08|03|04|.03|C.">Regulation .03C</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective September 15, 1998 (25:21 Md. R. 1571); amended permanently effective December 28, 1998 (25:26 Md. R. 1920)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-08-15"><cite path="|08|03|04|.03|E.">Regulation .03E</cite> adopted effective August 15, 2016 (43:16 Md. R. 899)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-08-23"><cite path="|08|03|04|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective June 3, 1985 (12:11 Md. R. 1047); September 27, 2004 (31:19 Md. R. 1430); August 23, 2010 (37:17 Md. R. 1184)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-06-03"><cite path="|08|03|04|.05">Regulation .05</cite> adopted effective June 3, 1985 (12:11 Md. R. 1047)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1997-01-13"><cite path="|08|03|04|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 19, 1996 (23:16 Md. R. 1166); amended permanently effective January 13, 1997 (24:1 Md. R. 29)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-08-10"><cite path="|08|03|04|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective August 23, 2010 (37:17 Md. R. 1184); November 24, 2016 (43:23 Md. R. 1279); August 10, 2020 (47:16 Md. R. 737)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-08-06"><cite path="|08|03|04|.05|A.">Regulation .05A</cite> amended effective June 30, 1986 (13:13 Md. R. 1489); September 2, 1991 (18:17 Md. R. 1917); August 18, 2003 (30:16 Md. R. 1704); August 30, 2004 (31:17 Md. R. 1311); September 27, 2004 (31:19 Md. R. 1430); July 17, 2008 (35:14 Md. R. 1245); August 6, 2012 (39:15 Md. R. 963)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-10-01"><cite path="|08|03|04|.05|A.">Regulation .05A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective October 1, 2014 (41:21 Md. R. 1258); emergency status expired February 28, 2015</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-08-31"><cite path="|08|03|04|.05|A.">Regulation .05A</cite> amended effective August 31, 2015 (42:17 Md. R. 1110)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-10-04"><cite path="|08|03|04|.05|B.">Regulation .05B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective October 4, 1985 (12:22 Md. R. 2099); emergency status expired January 24, 1986</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-09-27"><cite path="|08|03|04|.05|B.">Regulation .05B</cite> amended effective July 29, 1985 (12:15 Md. R. 1514); June 30, 1986 (13:13 Md. R. 1489); June 26, 1989 (16:12 Md. R. 1334); September 2, 1991 (18:17 Md. R. 1917); August 15, 1994 (21:16 Md. R. 1381); October 6, 1997 (24:20 Md. R. 1402); August 7, 2000 (27:15 Md. R. 1400); August 19, 2002 (29:16 Md. R. 1287); August 30, 2004 (31:17 Md. R. 1311): September 27, 2004 (31:19 Md. R. 1430)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-12-28"><cite path="|08|03|04|.05|B.">Regulation .05B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective September 15, 1998 (25:21 Md. R. 1571); amended permanently effective December 28, 1998 (25:26 Md. R. 1920)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-09-11"><cite path="|08|03|04|.05|B.">Regulation .05B</cite> amended effective September 11, 2017 (44:18 Md. R. 864)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-08-15"><cite path="|08|03|04|.05|C.">Regulation .05C</cite> amended effective July 29, 1985 (12:15 Md. R. 1514); May 18, 1987 (14:10 Md. R. 1170); July 25, 1988 (15:15 Md. R. 1808); September 2, 1991 (18:17 Md. R. 1917); August 15, 2016 (43:16 Md. R. 899)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-06-30"><cite path="|08|03|04|.05|D.">Regulation .05D</cite> adopted effective June 30, 1986 (13:13 Md. R. 1489)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-12-28"><cite path="|08|03|04|.05|D.">Regulation .05D</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective September 15, 1998 (25:21 Md. R. 1571); amended permanently effective December 28, 1998 (25:26 Md. R. 1920)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-08-08"><cite path="|08|03|04|.05|D.">Regulation .05D</cite> amended effective October 12, 2015 (42:20 Md. R. 1264); August 8, 2022 (49:16 Md. R. 758)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-06-26"><cite path="|08|03|04|.05|E.">Regulation .05E</cite> adopted effective June 26, 1989 (16:12 Md. R. 1334)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-08-23"><cite path="|08|03|04|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective July 17, 2006 (33:14 Md. R. 1162); August 23, 2010 (37:17 Md. R. 1184)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1997-10-06"><cite path="|08|03|04|.06|B.">Regulation .06B</cite> amended effective July 25, 1988 (15:15 Md. R. 1808); October 6, 1997 (24:20 Md. R. 1402)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-07-23"><cite path="|08|03|04|.06|C.">Regulation .06C</cite> adopted effective July 23, 1990 (17:14 Md. R. 1756)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-08-04"><cite path="|08|03|04|.06|C.">Regulation .06C</cite> amended effective August 4, 2014 (41:15 Md. R. 889)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-11-24"><cite path="|08|03|04|.06|C.">Regulation .06C</cite>, D amended effective July 17, 2008 (35:14 Md. R. 1245); November 24, 2016 (43:23 Md. R. 1279)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-08-15"><cite path="|08|03|04|.07">Regulation .07</cite> repealed effective August 15, 2005 (32:16 Md. R. 1391)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1991-09-02"><cite path="|08|03|04|.07|F.">Regulation .07F</cite> amended effective September 2, 1991 (18:17 Md. R. 1917)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1991-09-02"><cite path="|08|03|04|.07|G.">Regulation .07G</cite> adopted effective September 2, 1991 (18:17 Md. R. 1917)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-06-30"><cite path="|08|03|04|.08|A.">Regulation .08A</cite> amended effective June 30, 1986 (13:13 Md. R. 1489)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-06-30"><cite path="|08|03|04|.08|B.">Regulation .08B</cite> amended effective July 29, 1985 (12:15 Md. R. 1514); June 30, 1986 (13:13 Md. R. 1489)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-06-30"><cite path="|08|03|04|.08|C.">Regulation .08C</cite> amended effective June 30, 1986 (13:13 Md. R. 1489)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-02-14"><cite path="|08|03|04|.08">Regulation .08</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective September 15, 1993 (20:20 Md. R. 1556); amended permanently effective February 14, 1994 (21:3 Md. R. 184)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1997-01-13"><cite path="|08|03|04|.08">Regulation .08</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 19, 1996 (23:16 Md. R. 1166); amended permanently effective January 13, 1997 (24:1 Md. R. 29)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-06-03"><cite path="|08|03|04|.10">Regulation .10</cite> amended effective June 3, 1985 (12:11 Md. R. 1047)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-07-29"><cite path="|08|03|04|.10|C.">Regulation .10C</cite> amended effective July 29, 1985 (12:15 Md. R. 1514)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-12-28"><cite path="|08|03|04|.10">Regulation .10</cite> repealed and new Regulation .10 adopted as an emergency provision effective September 15, 1998 (25:21 Md. R. 1571); adopted permanently effective December 28, 1998 (25:26 Md. R. 1920)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-08-30"><cite path="|08|03|04|.10">Regulation .10</cite> amended effective August 7, 2000 (27:15 Md. R. 1400); August 30, 2004 (31:17 Md. R. 1311)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-06-30"><cite path="|08|03|04|.11">Regulation .11</cite> adopted effective June 30, 1986 (13:13 Md. R. 1489)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-08-15"><cite path="|08|03|04|.11">Regulation .11</cite> amended effective September 27, 2004 (31:19 Md. R. 1430); August 15, 2016 (43:16 Md. R. 899)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1987-05-18"><cite path="|08|03|04|.12">Regulation .12</cite> adopted effective May 18, 1987 (14:10 Md. R. 1170)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1988-07-25"><cite path="|08|03|04|.13">Regulation .13</cite> adopted effective July 25, 1988 (15:15 Md. R. 1808)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-07-17"><cite path="|08|03|04|.13">Regulation .13</cite> repealed effective July 17, 2006(33:14 Md. R. 1162)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1988-07-25"><cite path="|08|03|04|.14">Regulation .14</cite> adopted effective July 25, 1988 (15:15 Md. R. 1808)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1991-09-02"><cite path="|08|03|04|.14">Regulation .14</cite> amended effective September 2, 1991 (18:17 Md. R. 1917)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-12-28"><cite path="|08|03|04|.14">Regulation .14</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective September 15, 1998 (25:21 Md. R. 1571); amended permanently effective December 28, 1998 (25:26 Md. R. 1920)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-06-26"><cite path="|08|03|04|.15">Regulation .15</cite> adopted effective June 26, 1989 (16:12 Md. R. 1334)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-08-15"><cite path="|08|03|04|.15">Regulation .15</cite> amended effective July 23, 1990 (17:14 Md. R. 1756); September 2, 1991 (18:17 Md. R. 1917); August 31, 1992 (19:17 Md. R. 1606); August 15, 1994 (21:16 Md. R. 1381)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1997-10-06"><cite path="|08|03|04|.15">Regulation .15</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 19, 1996 (23:16 Md. R. 1166); amended permanently effective January 13, 1997 (24:1 Md. R. 29); October 6, 1997 (24:20 Md. R. 1402)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-08-28"><cite path="|08|03|04|.15|B.">Regulation .15B</cite>, C amended effective August 28, 1995 (22:17 Md. R. 1317)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-08-16"><cite path="|08|03|04|.15|F.">Regulation .15F</cite>, G adopted effective August 16, 1993 (20:16 Md. R. 1276)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-08-28"><cite path="|08|03|04|.15|K.">Regulation .15K</cite> adopted effective August 28, 1995 (22:17 Md. R. 1317)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-12-28"><cite path="|08|03|04|.15">Regulation .15</cite> repealed and new Regulation .15 adopted as an emergency provision effective September 15, 1998 (25:21 Md. R. 1571); adopted permanently effective December 28, 1998 (25:26 Md. R. 1920)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-10-16"><cite path="|08|03|04|.15">Regulation .15</cite> amended effective July 26, 1999 (26:15 Md. R. 1147); October 16, 2000 (27:20 Md. R. 1838)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-08-19"><cite path="|08|03|04|.15">Regulation .15</cite> repealed and new Regulation .15 adopted effective August 19, 2002 (29:16 Md. R. 1287)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-08-23"><cite path="|08|03|04|.15">Regulation .15</cite> amended effective; August 23, 2010 (37:17 Md. R. 1184)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-10-08"><cite path="|08|03|04|.15|B.">Regulation .15B</cite> amended effective October 8, 2018 (45:20 Md. R. 917)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1991-09-02"><cite path="|08|03|04|.16">Regulation .16</cite> adopted effective September 2, 1991 (18:17 Md. R. 1917)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-07-17"><cite path="|08|03|04|.16">Regulation .16</cite> amended effective July 17, 2008 (35:14 Md. R. 1245)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-03-29"><cite path="|08|03|04|.17">Regulation .17</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective December 17, 1992 (20:1 Md. R. 25); adopted permanently effective March 29, 1993 (20:6 Md. R. 580)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-09-14"><cite path="|08|03|04|.18">Regulation .18</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective September 14, 1999 (26:21 Md. R. 1626); emergency status expired March 11, 2000</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-09-03"><cite path="|08|03|04|.18">Regulation .18</cite> adopted effective September 3, 2001 (28:17 Md. R. 1555)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-09-03"><cite path="|08|03|04|.19">Regulation .19</cite> adopted effective September 3, 2001 (28:17 Md. R. 1555)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-09-27"><cite path="|08|03|04|.19">Regulation .19</cite> amended effective September 27, 2004 (31:19 Md. R. 1430)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-09-27"><cite path="|08|03|04|.20">Regulation .20</cite> adopted effective September 27, 2004 (31:19 Md. R. 1430)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-07-17"><cite path="|08|03|04|.20|B.">Regulation .20B</cite>, D amended effective July 17, 2006(33:14 Md. R. 1162)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-08-04"><cite path="|08|03|04|.20|B.">Regulation .20B</cite>, E amended effective August 4, 2014 (41:15 Md. R. 889)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-08-15"><cite path="|08|03|04|.20|B.">Regulation .20B</cite>, E, J amended effective August 15, 2016 (43:16 Md. R. 899)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-07-17"><cite path="|08|03|04|.20|F.">Regulation .20F</cite> amended effective July 17, 2008 (35:14 Md. R. 1245)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-07-17"><cite path="|08|03|04|.21">Regulation .21</cite> adopted effective July 17, 2006(33:14 Md. R. 1162)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-08-14"><cite path="|08|03|04|.22">Regulation .22</cite> adopted effective August 14, 2006 (33:16 Md. R. 1365)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-08-15"><cite path="|08|03|04|.22">Regulation .22</cite> amended effective September 5, 2011 (38:18 Md. R. 1077); August 6, 2012 (39:15 Md. R. 963); August 15, 2016 (43:16 Md. R. 899)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-08-06"><cite path="|08|03|04|.23">Regulation .23</cite> adopted effective August 6, 2012 (39:15 Md. R. 963)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-10-08"><cite path="|08|03|04|.23">Regulation .23</cite> amended effective September 11, 2017 (44:18 Md. R. 864); October 8, 2018 (45:20 Md. R. 917)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-08-04"><cite path="|08|03|04|.24">Regulation .24</cite> adopted effective August 4, 2014 (41:15 Md. R. 889)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-10-13"><cite path="|08|03|04|.25">Regulation .25</cite> adopted effective October 13, 2025 (52:20 Md. R. 1000)</annotation>
    <annotation app="2025-10-13" doc="Maryland Register, Volume 52, Issue 20" eff="2025-10-13" path="regulations|final|25-158-F" type="History" display="false"/>
  </annotations>
</container>
