<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>General Regulations</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Succession of the Maryland Medical Cannabis Commission.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Maryland Cannabis Administration is the successor entity to the Natalie M. LaPrade Medical Cannabis Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Any bulletin, final order, notice of violation, or formal changes issued by the Natalie M. LaPrade Medical Cannabis Commission remains valid and stands as authorized by the Maryland Cannabis Administration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Except as otherwise provided in this subtitle or Alcoholic Beverages and Cannabis Article, Title 36, Annotated Code of Maryland, a registration issued by the Natalie M. LaPrade Medical Cannabis Commission shall be valid until the stated expiration date for each:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Patient or caregiver;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Certifying provider;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Clinical director;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Agent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Independent testing laboratory; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Other business registrants.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Maryland Cannabis Administration may rescind, revoke, correct, or reissue any bulletin, final order, notice of violation, or formal changes issued by the Natalie M. LaPrade Medical Cannabis Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Single Supply Chain for Cannabis Products.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as otherwise provided in this subtitle, all cannabis grown, harvested, processed, transported, delivered, produced, manufactured, or sold in Maryland shall follow the regulations in this subtitle.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A licensee shall accurately track, tag, or otherwise record inventory in the seed-to-sale tracking system designated by the Administration as specified:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Throughout this subtitle; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In guidance issued by the Administration or its vendor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="14|17|02|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Conversion of Medical Cannabis License.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This regulation applies to each licensee required to pay a conversion fee under Alcoholic Beverages and Cannabis Article, §36-403, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The conversion fee shall be based on the gross revenue of a licensee and calculated by the Administration using the State’s seed-to-sale tracking system for calendar year 2022.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Licensees choosing to convert their license shall, on or before July 1, 2023:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Pay the conversion fee as calculated by the Administration in full; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Enter into a payment plan with the Administration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The payment plan under <cite path="14|17|02|.03|C.|(2)">§C(2) of this regulation</cite> shall establish:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The conversion fee as calculated by Administration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The exact payment amount required under each payment installment; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Payment due dates as directed by the Administration for four equal payment installments over an 18-month period.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>On or before January 1, 2025, a licensee shall pay the installment payment in full in accordance with <cite path="14|17|02|.03|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A licensee that does not meet a payment deadline is subject to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An administrative hold on their ability to transfer cannabis or cannabis products to another licensee or distribute or dispense cannabis or cannabis products to a qualifying patient, registered caregiver, or consumer until payment is remitted to the Administration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A fine of up to $5,000 for each day past the deadline that the payment is not received; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>After a period of 30 days, license suspension or revocation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A converted license shall be valid for a period of 5 years, beginning on July 1, 2023.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>A converted license is not transferrable prior to July 1, 2028, except as provided under Alcoholic Beverages and Cannabis Article, §36-503, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Technical Authority.</heading>
    <text>The Maryland Cannabis Administration’s Technical Authority for Cannabis Testing (Effective January 2024), or Technical Authority, is incorporated by reference.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="14|17|02|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Sociological Information.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>For purposes of this regulation and as provided for under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-330">General Provisions Article, §4-330, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, “sociological information” means any of the following information requested from the Administration:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Academic or personal records provided to verify social equity status;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Records about an individual’s personal history, age, family, race, national origin, creed, color, sex, pregnancy, sexual orientation, ethnic background, ancestry, physiology, religion, academic achievement, employment, gender identity or expression, genetic information, veteran status, or physical or mental ability;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Family history, identity of relatives, emergency contacts, or representatives;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Medical or psychiatric history;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Social security number;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Date of birth;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Credit card or other banking information;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Personal addresses, personal phone numbers, personal electronic mail address, or personal social media account information;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Information regarding marital status, domestic partnership, dependents, or relatives, including related employment benefits elections;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Information regarding employment status, including disciplinary records and records related to an application for employment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Applicant information of those not selected for licensure;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Military service;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Driver’s license number;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>Immigration status, passport, or visa numbers;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>Any information obtained through employment coaching or surveys;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>Financial information, including income other than State salary, assets, and liabilities; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>Records not related to the transaction of State business.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Except for use in carrying out the Administration’s governmental functions or except as further provided in <cite path="14|17|02|.05|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, the Administration may not disclose under the Public Information Act, General Provisions Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-101">4-101</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-601">4-601</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland, and shall deny a request for inspection or copying of, any part of a public record that contains sociological information relating to an individual.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Administration may disclose sociological information:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To the person in interest or the agent or representative of the person in interest;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>With the consent of the person in interest;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Pursuant to a duly issued subpoena;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Pursuant to a court order;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If disclosure is otherwise required by law, including if required to be disclosed under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-333">General Provisions Article, §4-333, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, as part of a licensing record; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>If disclosure is otherwise permitted by law and the Administration determines that disclosure would be in the public’s best interests.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Alcoholic Beverages and Cannabis Article, §§36-201, 36-401, and 36-403, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-07-01">Regulations <cite path="|14|17|02|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|14|17|02|.03">.03</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective July 1, 2023 (50:14 Md. R. 559); emergency status expired June 30, 2024</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-06-07">Regulations <cite path="|14|17|02|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|14|17|02|.02">.02</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective June 7, 2024 (51:14 Md. R. 676)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-07-22">Regulations <cite path="|14|17|02|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|14|17|02|.04">.04</cite> adopted effective July 22, 2024 (51:14 Md. R. 678)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-04-14"><cite path="|14|17|02|.05">Regulation .05</cite> adopted effective April 14, 2025 (52:7 Md. R. 324)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
