<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>15</num>
  <heading>Cannabis Business Agents</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This chapter applies to agents as defined in <cite path="|14.17.01">COMAR 14.17.01</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This chapter applies to individuals who are employed, volunteer, or work for management companies as defined in <cite path="14.17.06.05">COMAR 14.17.06.05</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Registration.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>To volunteer or work for a licensee or registrant, an individual shall be registered with the Administration as an agent.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Agent registration shall be conducted pursuant to Alcoholic Beverages and Cannabis Article, §36-501, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A licensee shall apply to register an agent by submitting to the Administration:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The name, address, date of birth, and Social Security Number or Individual Tax Identification Number of an agent;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Documentation of the submission of fingerprints of the agent of to the Criminal Justice Information System’s Central Repository in accordance with Alcoholic Beverages and Cannabis Article, §36-505, Annotated Code of Maryland;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The request for the criminal history record information of the agent to be forwarded to the Administration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>As a condition of registration, an agent shall report to the Administration a conviction of or plea of nolo contendere to a crime involving moral turpitude within 14 days of the conviction or plea.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Administration may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Disqualify as an agent an individual who has been convicted of or pleaded nolo contendere to a crime involving moral turpitude, whether or not any appeal or other proceeding is pending to have the conviction or plea set aside; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Revoke the registration of an agent who is convicted of or pleads nolo contendere to a crime involving moral turpitude, whether or not any appeal or other proceeding is pending to have the conviction or plea set aside.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Administration may not deny a cannabis agent registration based on any cannabis-related offense occurring before July 1, 2023.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Registered Agent Identification Cards.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall issue to each registered agent an identification card which includes a photograph of the face of the registered agent taken no more than 6 months before the date of the application.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>At all times every registered agent at a licensed or registered premises shall visibly wear the identification card issued to the registered agent by the Administration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The agent shall apply for renewal of the identification card every 2 years.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If a registered agent’s identification card is lost, destroyed, or stolen, within 24 hours of becoming aware of the loss, destruction or theft, the licensee shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Report the loss, destruction, or theft to the Administration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Apply for a replacement card; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Pay a replacement card fee specified in <cite path="|14.17.21">COMAR 14.17.21</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An identification card remains the property of the Administration and the Administration may order the return or seizure of an identification card if the registration is revoked or expires.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If a registered agent’s identification card is lost, destroyed, or stolen, a copy of the notification to the Administration shall be evidence of registration until a new card is obtained from the Administration.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Termination.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Within 30 days of the termination of a registered agent, the licensee or registrant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Take custody of the terminated registered agent’s identification card;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Obtain any keys or other entry devices from the terminated registered agent; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Ensure the terminated registered agent can no longer gain access to the licensed premises.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Within 1 business day of the termination of a registered agent, a licensee or registrant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notify the Administration:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Of the termination and the circumstance of the termination; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Whether the terminated registered agent has returned the agent’s identification card; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Initiate delivery of the terminated registered agent’s identification card to the Administration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall revoke the registration of an agent upon receiving notification that an agent is no longer associated with a licensee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If a registered agent did not return the agent’s identification card within 30 days of the termination, the Administration shall notify the law enforcement agency with jurisdiction in the licensee’s area.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="14|17|15|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Training.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The licensee shall train all registered agents on:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Federal and State cannabis laws and regulation and other laws and regulations pertinent to the agent’s responsibilities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Standard operating procedures;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The State alcohol and drug free workplace policy, as identified in <cite path="21.11.08.03">COMAR 21.11.08.03</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Detection and prevention of diversion of cannabis;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Security procedures; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Safety procedures including responding to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A medical emergency;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A fire;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A chemical spill; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A threatening event such as:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>An armed robbery;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>An invasion;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A burglary; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Any other criminal incident.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The licensee shall retain training materials and attendance records and make the training materials available for inspection by the Administration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>On an annual basis, a registered agent employed by a cannabis licensee shall complete a responsible vendor training program that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Meets the minimum requirements under Alcoholic Beverages and Cannabis Article, §§36-1001—36-1003, Annotated Code of Maryland; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is registered with the Administration in accordance with <cite path="14|17|15|.05|E.|(3)">§E(3) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A responsible vendor training program required under <cite path="14|17|15|.05|E.">§E of this regulation</cite> shall be in addition to the training requirements under <cite path="14|17|15|.05|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Responsible Vendor Training Program.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To offer a responsible medical or adult-use cannabis vendor, server, and seller training program, a person shall submit an application to the Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>To be considered for approval, the proposed training program application shall meet the minimum educational standards established in Alcoholic Beverages and Cannabis Article, §36-1001(c), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Applications approved by the Administration shall be registered with the Administration for a period of 3 years from the date of approval.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Administration shall assess a fee for the application, registration, and renewal of a responsible vendor training program under this regulation as specified in <cite path="|14.17.21">COMAR 14.17.21</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A person offering a responsible vendor training program under this paragraph may not have ownership or control of any cannabis license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A person offering a responsible vendor training program shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Maintain records for at least 4 years; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Make these records available to the Administration upon request.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Alcoholic Beverages and Cannabis Article, §§36-202, 36-203, 36-501, and 36-1001—36-1003, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-07-01">Regulations <cite path="|14|17|15|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|14|17|15|.06">.06</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective July 1, 2023 (50:14 Md. R. 559); emergency status expired June 30, 2024</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-06-07">Regulations <cite path="|14|17|15|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|14|17|15|.05">.05</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective June 7, 2024 (51:14 Md. R. 676)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-07-22">Regulations <cite path="|14|17|15|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|14|17|15|.05">.05</cite> adopted effective July 22, 2024 (51:14 Md. R. 678)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-04-15"><cite path="|14|17|15|.05|C.">Regulation .05C</cite> amended effective April 15, 2025 (52:7 Md. R. 324)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
