<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>General</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Fishery Management Plans.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The following Fishery Management Plans are adopted and incorporated by reference:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Chesapeake Bay Alosid Management Plan (July 1989), and Amendment I 1989 Chesapeake Bay Alosid Management Plan (June 1998);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Chesapeake Bay Blue Crab Management Plan (July 1989); Chesapeake Bay Blue Crab Management Plan (June 1997), Amendment I 1997 Chesapeake Bay Blue Crab Fishery Management Plan (October 2003), and Amendment #2 1997 Chesapeake Bay Blue Crab Fishery Management Plan May 31, 2012;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Maryland Chesapeake Bay Oyster Management Plan (May 2019) and Amendment 1 to the 2019 Maryland Chesapeake Bay Oyster Management Plan (December 2023);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Chesapeake Bay Striped Bass Management Plan (December 1989), and Amendment I 1998 Chesapeake Bay Striped Bass Fishery Management Plan (CB SBFMP) (1998);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Chesapeake Bay Bluefish Management Plan (December 1990), and Amendment I of the 1990 Chesapeake Bay Program Bluefish Fishery Management Plan (October 2003);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Chesapeake Bay Weakfish and Spotted Sea Trout Management Plan (December 1990), and 2003 Chesapeake Bay Program (CBP) Weakfish (Cynoscion regalis) Fishery Management Plan (FMP) (December 2003);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Chesapeake Bay Summer Flounder Management Plan (December 1991) and Amendment I Chesapeake Bay Summer Flounder Management Plan (1998);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Chesapeake Bay Atlantic Croaker and Spot Fishery Management Plan (December 1991);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Chesapeake Bay American Eel Fishery Management Plan (December 1991) and Amendment 1 to the 1991 Chesapeake Bay American Eel Fishery Management Plan;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Chesapeake Bay Black Drum Fishery Management Plan (September 1993);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Chesapeake Bay Red Drum Fishery Management Plan (September 1993);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Chesapeake Bay and Atlantic Coast Horseshoe Crab Fishery Management Plan (1994);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Chesapeake and Atlantic Coast King and Spanish Mackerel Fishery Management Plan (1994);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>Chesapeake Bay and Atlantic Coast Black Sea Bass Fishery Management Plan (October 1996);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>Chesapeake Bay and Atlantic Coast Tautog Fishery Management Plan (December 1998);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>Coastal Bays Blue Crab Fishery Management Plan (September 2001);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>Coastal Bays Hard Clam Fishery Management Plan (February 2002);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>Maryland Tidewater Yellow Perch Fishery Management Plan (November 2002) and Amendment 1 to the 2002 Maryland Tidewater Yellow Perch Fishery Management Plan (December 2017);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>Fishery Management Plan for Largemouth Bass (Micropterus salmoides) in Maryland Tidewater (January 2014); and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>Fishery Management Plan for Tidewater Catfish (December 2021).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-215">Natural Resources Article, §4-215, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and a fishery management plan adopted in §A or B of this regulation, the Department has authority to substitute a regulation necessary to implement a plan for an otherwise applicable provision of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr">Natural Resources Article, Title 4, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>. In this subtitle, an intent to substitute an implementing regulation for a statutory provision is indicated by the phrase, "Notwithstanding Natural Resources Article, §4- . . . ".</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>General Commercial License Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Exemption from License Requirement. A buyer licensed by the Potomac River Fisheries Commission may buy seafood in Maryland without purchasing a Maryland license to buy, provided the seafood was caught in the Potomac River. In this regulation the term seafood includes finfish, crabs, lobsters, terrapin, oysters, hard-shell clams, and soft-shell clams.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Identification Number.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Unless otherwise required by this subtitle, all licensees shall display the identification number provided by the Department on every vessel, vehicle, gear, or place of business used to catch, hold, transport, process, sell, buy, or otherwise deal in seafood.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Display of Commercial Identification Number on Vessels and Vehicles.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The licensee’s commercial identification number shall be plain vertical block characters of not less than 3 inches in height and shall contrast with the color of the background.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>All numbers shall be distinctly visible and legible.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Display on Vessels.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The licensee’s commercial identification number shall be painted or firmly attached to both sides of the vessel.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The number shall be positioned on or above the hull, forward, but not on or near the bow, and in such a manner as to be clearly visible to passing boats.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Display on Vehicle.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The licensee’s commercial identification number shall be painted or firmly attached to the vehicle.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The number shall be positioned on the front part of the body on the driver’s side.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Violation of Regulations.</heading>
    <text>A person who violates any provision of these regulations is guilty of a misdemeanor and, upon conviction, is subject to a penalty as set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr">Natural Resources Article, Title 4, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Free Fishing Days.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Secretary may establish up to 3 free fishing days each calendar year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>During a free fishing day, a person may catch and possess finfish in the tidal and nontidal waters of the State for recreational purposes without an angler's license, Chesapeake Bay and coastal sport fishing license, or any fishing stamp normally required by the State, but shall otherwise observe all fishing laws and regulations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The free fishing days are the first two Saturdays in June and July 4.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|02|01|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Targets for the Number of Tidal Fish License Authorizations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The targets for the number of tidal fish license authorizations issued by the Department are the number of authorizations issued between September 1, 1998, and March 31, 1999, including adjustments made annually according to specifications listed in <cite path="08|02|01|.05|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, listed by the following categories:</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Abbreviation</th>
              <th>Authorization</th>
              <th>Number</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>FGR</td>
              <td>Fishing Guide Resident</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">517</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>FGN</td>
              <td>Fishing Guide Nonresident</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">57</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>HLI</td>
              <td>Finfish—Hook and Line</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">244</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>FIN</td>
              <td>Unlimited Finfish Harvester</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">299</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>LCC</td>
              <td>Limited Crab Harvester</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">2,598</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>LCCM</td>
              <td>Limited Crab Harvester—Male Only</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">461</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>CB3</td>
              <td>Crab Harvester—300 Pots</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">298</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>CB6</td>
              <td>Crab Harvester—600 Pots</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">220</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>CB9</td>
              <td>Crab Harvester—900 Pots</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">392</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>CLM</td>
              <td>Clam Harvester</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">67</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>OYH</td>
              <td>Oyster Harvester</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">732</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>ODB</td>
              <td>Oyster Dredge Boat</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">59</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>CTL</td>
              <td>Conch, Cancer Crab, Turtles, and Lobster Harvester</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">66</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>UTFL</td>
              <td>Unlimited Tidal Fish</td>
              <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">2,064</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The targets for the number of tidal fish licenses may be modified based on:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Recommendations of the Tidal Fisheries Advisory Commission;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Recommendations of fishery management plans adopted by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Department;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Chesapeake Bay Program;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Atlantic States Marine Fisheries Commission;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Mid-Atlantic Fisheries Management Council; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Any other appropriate management body;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The number of individuals historically participating;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Target species, size, number, weight, incidental catch, total biomass, annual harvest, mortality rates, and other factors which are necessary and appropriate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The number of license conversions made in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-701">Natural Resources Article, §4-701(m), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The number of authorizations purchased back from license holders by the Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Except for authorizations relinquished for conversions made in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-701">Natural Resources Article, §4-701, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, authorizations that are revoked or voluntarily relinquished to the Department may be reallocated to individuals on the commercial license waiting list maintained by the Department.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|02|01|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Dividing Lines of the Chesapeake Bay, Sounds, and Straits.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The boundaries set forth in <cite path="08|02|01|.06|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> are designated as official dividing lines of the Chesapeake Bay, sounds, and straits.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Any creek, cove, or other tributary less than 100 yards in width that intersects any segment of the following delineating lines is not a part of the described area:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Chesapeake Bay. All of the waters of the State enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near Maryland-Virginia Boundary Point 1, south of Smith Point, defined by Lat. 37°53.19'N and Long. 76°14.20'W; then running approximately 286° True to a point at or near the mean low water line of the shore, defined by Lat. 37°53.20'N and Long. 76°14.24'W; then running northerly along the mean low water line to a point at or near the south side of the south jetty at Smith Point, defined by Lat. 37°53.36'N and Long. 76°14.19'W; then running northeasterly along the mean low water line on the south side of the south jetty to a point at or near the east end of the south jetty, defined by Lat. 37°53.38'N and Long. 76°14.14'W; then running approximately 324° True to a point at or near the east end of the north jetty, defined by Lat. 37°53.41'N and Long. 76°14.17'W; then running southwesterly along the mean low water line on the north side of the north jetty to a point at or near the mean low water line of the shore, defined by Lat. 37°53.40'N and Long. 76°14.22'W; then running approximately 335° True to a point at or near Point Lookout, defined by Lat. 38°02.25'N and Long. 76°19.34'W; then running northerly along the shore to a point at or near Deep Point, defined by Lat. 38°07.16'N and Long. 76°20.47'W; then running approximately 71° True to a point at or near Saint Jerome Point, defined by Lat. 38°07.21'N and Long. 76°20.30'W; then running northerly along the shore to a point at or near Point No Point, defined by Lat. 38°08.28'N and Long. 76°19.25'W; then running northwesterly along the shore to a point at or near Cedar Point, defined by Lat. 38°17.93'N and Long. 76°22.38'W; then running westerly along the shore to a point at or near Hog Point, defined by Lat. 38°18.59'N and Long. 76°23.99'W; then running approximately 299° True to a point at or near Drum Point, defined by Lat. 38°19.14'N and Long. 76°25.27'W; then running northeasterly along the shore to a point at or near Cove Point, defined by Lat. 38°23.13'N and Long. 76°22.86'W; then running northwesterly along the shore to a point at or near the south side of Long Beach Harbor, defined by Lat. 38°27.87'N and Long. 76°28.25'W; then running approximately 358° True to a point at or near the north side of Long Beach Harbor, defined by Lat. 38°27.91'N and Long. 76°28.25'W; then running northerly along shore to a point at or near the south side of Fishing Creek, defined by Lat. 38°41.46'N and Long. 76°31.97'W; then running approximately 314° True to a point at or near the north side of Fishing Creek, defined by Lat. 38°41.48'N and Long. 76°31.10'W; then running northerly along shore to a point at or near Holland Point, defined by Lat. 38°43.58'N and Long. 76°31.62'W; then running approximately 349° True to a point at or near the shore at the southern entrance of Parker Creek, defined by Lat. 38°46.49'N and Long. 76°32.32'W; then running approximately 36° True to a point at or near the shore at the northern entrance of Parker Creek, defined by Lat. 38°46.63'N and Long. 76°32.20'W; then running northeasterly along shore to a point at or near the southern entrance of Broadwater Creek, defined by Lat. 38°47.37'N and Long. 76°31.44'W; then running approximately 43° True to a point at or near the northern entrance of Broadwater Creek, defined by Lat. 38°48.06'N and Long. 76°30.61'W; then running northerly along shore to a point at or near Curtis Point, defined by Lat. 38°51.19'N and Long. 76°29.83'W; then running approximately 330° True to a point at or near Dutchman Point, defined by Lat. 38°52.19'N and Long. 76°30.57'W; then running northeasterly along shore to a point at or near Saunders Point, defined by Lat. 38°53.19'N and Long. 76°29.44'W; then running approximately 49° True to a point at or near Thomas Point, defined by Lat. 38°54.44'N and Long. 76°27.61'W; then running approximately 10° True to a point at or near the northerly entrance of Fishing Creek, defined by Lat. 38°54.86'N and Long. 76°27.51'W; then running northerly along shore to a point at or near Tolley Point, defined by Lat. 38°56.48'N and Long. 76°27.02'W; then running approximately 355° True to a point at or near Greenbury Point, defined by Lat. 38°58.49'N and Long. 76°27.26'W; then running approximately 60° True to a point at or near Hacketts Point defined by Lat. 38°59.22'N and Long. 76°25.61'W; then running northeasterly along shore to a point at or near the southerly entrance of Moss Pond, defined by Lat. 39°00.01'N and Long. 76°24.71'W; then running approximately 5° True to a point at or near the northerly entrance of Moss Pond, defined by Lat. 39°00.14'N and Long. 76°24.69'W; then running northeasterly along shore to a point at or near the west entrance of Mezick Pond, defined by Lat. 39°00.45'N and Long. 76°24.28'W; then running approximately 55° True to a point at or near the easterly entrance of Mezick Pond, defined by Lat. 39°00.49'N and Long. 76°24.19'W; then running easterly along shore to a point at or near Sandy Point, defined by Lat. 39°00.70'N and Long. 76°23.67'W; then running northwesterly along shore to a point at or near the south entrance of the Little Magothy River, defined by Lat. 39°02.76'N and Long. 76°25.79'W; then running approximately 274° True to a point at or near the north entrance of the Little Magothy River, defined by Lat. 39°02.76'N and Long. 76°25.82'W; then running northwesterly along shore to a point at or near Persimmon Point, defined by Lat. 39°03.16'N and Long. 76°26.33'W; then running approximately 34° True to a point at or near Mountain Point, defined by Lat. 39°03.55'N and Long. 76°25.99'W; then running northerly along shore to a point at or near Bodkin Point, defined by Lat. 39°07.98'N and Long. 76°25.83'W; then running approximately 352° True to a point at or near North Point, defined by Lat. 39°11.72'N and Long. 76°26.53'W; then running northeasterly along shore to a point at or near the west entrance of Shallow Creek, defined by Lat. 39°12.19'N and Long. 76°26.20'W; then running approximately 71° True to a point at or near the east entrance of Shallow Creek, defined by Lat. 39°12.25'N and Long. 76°25.95'W; then running northeasterly along shore to a point at or near the east end of Back River Neck, defined by Lat. 39°13.76'N and Long. 76°23.91'W; then running approximately 65° True to a point at or near the west end of Pleasure Island, defined by Lat. 39°13.85'N and Long. 76°23.65'W; then running northeasterly along shore to a point at or near the east end of Pleasure Island, defined by Lat. 39°14.23'N and Long. 76°23.27'W; then running approximately 26° True to a point at or near the west end of Hart-Miller Island, defined by Lat. 39°14.36'N and Long. 76°23.19'W; then running easterly along shore to a point at or near the south end of Hart-Miller Island, defined by Lat. 39°14.23'N and Long. 76°22.44'W; then running northeasterly along shore to a point at or near the east end of Hart-Miller Island, defined by Lat. 39°15.44'N and Long. 76°20.62'W; then running northwesterly along shore to a point defined by Lat. 39°15.78'N and Long. 76° 21.28'W; then running approximately 316° True to a point at or near the east end of Booby Point, defined by Lat. 39°17.07'N and Long. 76°22.88'W; then running approximately 353° True to a point at or near Bowley Point, defined by Lat. 39°17.89'N and Long. 76°23.01'W; then running approximately 80° True to a point at or near Lower Island Point, defined by Lat. 39°18.25'N and Long. 76°20.39'W; then running easterly along shore to a point at or near Weir Point, defined by Lat. 39°18.30'N and Long. 76°20.15'W; then running northerly along shore to a point at or near the east tip of Carroll Island, defined by Lat. 39°18.89'N and Long. 76°19.68'W; then running approximately 121° True to a point at or near Ricketts Point, defined by Lat. 39°18.11'N and Long. 76°17.97'W; then running easterly along shore to a point at or near Robins Point, defined by Lat. 39°17.97'N and Long. 76°16.90'W; then running northerly along shore to a point at or near the south entrance of Boone Creek, defined by Lat. 39°19.85'N and Long. 76°15.97'W; then running approximately 23° True to a point at or near the north entrance of Boone Creek, defined by Lat. 39°19.92'N and Long. 76°15.94'W; then running northeasterly along shore to a point at or near Lego Point, defined by Lat. 39°20.21'N and Long. 76°15.25'W; then running approximately 58° True to a point at or near Abbey Point, defined by Lat. 39°20.97'N and Long. 76°13.69'W; then running northeasterly along shore to a point at or near the south entrance of Romney Creek, defined by Lat. 39°22.11'N and Long. 76°11.70'W; then running approximately 52° True to a point at or near Taylor Point, defined by Lat. 39°22.66'N and Long. 76°10.79'W; then running northeasterly along shore to a point at or near the south entrance of an unnamed creek, defined by Lat. 39°24.02'N and Long. 76°09.89'W; then running approximately 12° True to a point at or near the north entrance of an unnamed creek, defined by Lat. 39°24.04'N and Long. 76°09.88'W; then running northeasterly along shore to a point at or near the west entrance of Delph Creek, defined by Lat. 39°24.35'N and Long. 76°09.52'W; then running approximately 96° True to a point at or near the east entrance of Delph Creek, defined by Lat. 39°24.34'N and Long. 76°09.40'W; then running easterly along shore to a point at or near the west entrance of an unnamed creek, defined by Lat. 39°24.33'N and Long. 76°09.15'W; then running approximately 112° True to a point at or near Stoney Point, defined by Lat. 39°24.29'N and Long. 76°09.01'W; then running northeasterly along shore to a point at or near Black Point, defined by Lat. 39°26.11'N and Long. 76°06.11'W; then running approximately 11° True to a point at or near Mulberry Point, defined by Lat. 39°26.62'N and Long. 76°05.98'W; then running approximately 117° True to a point at or near Bear Point, defined by Lat. 39°26.20'N and Long. 76°04.93'W; then running northeasterly along the east shore of Spesutie Island to a point at or near Sandy Point, defined by Lat. 39°26.87'N and Long. 76°03.65'W; then running northerly along the east shore of Spesutie Island to a point at or near Locust Point, defined by Lat. 39°28.52'N and Long. 76°04.38'W; then running westerly along the north shore of Spesutie Island and the road causeway across Spesutie Narrows to a point at or near the southernmost point at the entrance of Swan Creek, defined by Lat. 39°29.22'N and Long. 76°06.82'W; then running approximately 289° True to a point at or near the northerly point at the entrance of Swan Creek, defined by Lat. 39°29.36'N and Long. 76°07.36'W; then running northerly along shore to a point at or near Concord Point, defined by Lat. 39°32.44'N and Long. 76°05.09'W; then running approximately 79° True to a point at or near Stump Point, defined by Lat. 39°32.79'N and Long. 76°02.80'W; then running approximately 105° True to a point at or near Carpenter Point, defined by Lat. 39°32.37'N and Long. 76°00.75'W; then running approximately 112° True to a point at or near Red Point defined by Lat. 39°31.75'N and Long. 75°58.84'W; then running southerly along the west shore of Turkey Point Neck to a point at or near Turkey Point, defined by Lat. 39°26.97'N and Long. 76°00.56'W; then running approximately 204° True to a point at or near the north side of Grove Point, defined by Lat. 39°23.87'N and Long. 76°02.34'W; then running southerly along shore to a point at or near Grove Point, defined by Lat. 39°23.49'N and Long. 76°02.47'W; then running approximately 251° True to a point at or near Howell Point, defined by Lat. 39°22.33'N and Long. 76°06.72'W; then running southeasterly along shore to a point at or near Meeks Point, defined by Lat. 39°20.77'N and Long. 76°08.21'W; then running approximately 210° True to a point at or near Rocky Point, defined by Lat. 39°20.07'N and Long. 76°08.73'W; then running southeasterly along shore to a point at or near Worton Point, defined by Lat. 39°19.14'N and Long. 76°11.13'W; then running approximately 202° True to a point at or near the west entrance of Fairlee Creek, defined by Lat. 39°16.19'N and Long. 76°12.67'W; then running southerly along the shore to a point at or near Swan Point, defined by Lat. 39°08.89'N and Long. 76°16.69'W; then running approximately 141° True to a point at or near Huntingfield Point, defined by Lat. 39°07.13'N and Long. 76°14.85'W; then running southerly along the shore of Eastern Neck to a point at or near Wilson Point, defined by Lat. 39°03.19'N and Long. 76°13.66'W; then running approximately 216° True to a point at or near the northwest corner of Eastern Neck Island, defined by Lat. 39°02.77'N and Long. 76°14.05'W; then running approximately 263° True to a point at or near Love Point, defined by Lat. 39°02.40'N and Long. 76°18.16'W; then running southerly along the west shore of Kent Island to a point at or near the easterly entrance of Broad Creek, defined by Lat. 38°58.52'N and Long. 76°20.28'W; then running approximately 254° True to a point at or near the westerly entrance of Broad Creek, defined by Lat. 38°58.50'N and Long. 76°20.39'W; then running southerly along the west and south shore of Kent Island to a point at or near Kent Point, defined by Lat. 38°50.18'N and Long. 76°22.10'W; then running approximately 102° True to a point at or near Wades Point, defined by Lat. 38°49.54'N and Long. 76°18.13'W; then running southerly along the shore to a point at or near Amys Marsh Point, defined by Lat. 38°43.78'N and Long. 76°20.54'W; then running approximately 172° True to a point at or near the northwest tip of Tilghman Island, defined by Lat. 38°43.23'N and Long. 76°20.44'W; then running southerly along the west shore of Tilghman Island to a point at or near Blackwalnut Point, defined by Lat. 38°40.24'N and Long. 76°20.37'W; then running approximately 137° True to a point at or near Cook Point, defined by Lat. 38°37.73'N and Long. 76°17.35'W; then running southeasterly along the west shore of Cook Point to a point at or near the northwest entrance of Covey Creek, defined by Lat. 38°36.11'N and Long. 76°16.23'W; then running approximately 158° True to a point at or near the southeast entrance of Covey Creek, defined by Lat. 38°35.86'N and Long. 76°16.10'W; then running southwesterly along shore to a point at or near the northeast entrance of Brannock Bay, defined by Lat. 38°35.54'N and Long. 76°16.38'W; then running approximately 237° True to a point at or near the southwest entrance of Brannock Bay at Mills Point, defined by Lat. 38°35.11'N and Long. 76°17.21'W; then running southwesterly along shore to a point at or near Hills Point, defined by Lat. 38°34.36'N and Long. 76°18.36'W; then running approximately 206° True to a point at or near the northerly tip of north James Island, defined by Lat. 38°31.54'N and Long. 76°20.14'W; then running along shore to a point at or near James Point, defined by Lat. 38°31.33'N and Long. 76°20.38'W; then running approximately 190° True to a point at or near the northwesterly tip of south James Island, defined by Lat. 38°30.99'N and Long. 76°20.46'W; then running southerly along shore to a point at or near the southerly tip of south James Island, defined by Lat. 38°30.13'N and Long. 76°20.28'W; then running approximately 181° True to a point at or near the westerly entrance of Oyster Creek, defined by Lat. 38°29.72'N and Long. 76°20.29'W; then running approximately 162° True to a point at or near the shore of Taylors Island, defined by Lat. 38°29.25'N and Long. 76°20.09'W; then running southeasterly along shore to a point at or near the north entrance of Punch Island Creek, defined by Lat. 38°25.35'N and Long. 76°17.26'W; then running approximately 161° True to a point at or near the south entrance of Punch Island Creek, defined by Lat. 38°25.16'N and Long. 76°17.17'W; then running southerly along the shore to a point at or near the north entrance of Barren Island Gap, defined by Lat. 38°22.23'N and Long. 76°16.43'W; then running approximately 163° True to a point at or near the entrance of Barren Island Gap, defined by Lat. 38°21.09'N and Long. 76°15.99'W; then running approximately 159° True to a point at or near Barren Island Point, defined by Lat. 38°20.62'N and Long. 76°15.77'W; then running southerly along the west shore of Barren Island to a point at or near the west shore of Barren Island, defined by Lat. 38°20.32'N and Long. 76°15.89'W; then running approximately 152° True to a point at or near the west shore of Barren Island, defined by Lat. 38°20.21'N and Long. 76°15.82'W; then running southerly along the west shore of Barren Island to a point at or near the west shore of Barren Island, defined by Lat. 38°19.90'N and Long. 76°15.61'W; then running approximately 171° True to a point at or near the west shore of Barren Island, defined by Lat. 38°19.85'N and Long. 76°15.60'W; then running southeasterly along the west shore of Barren Island to a point at or near the south end of Barren Island, defined by Lat. 38°19.46'N and Long. 76°15.43'W; then running approximately 124° True to a point at or near Pons Point, defined by Lat. 38°18.43'N and Long. 76°13.47'W; then running southeasterly along the west shore of Upper Hoopers Island to a point at or near Ferry Point, defined by Lat. 38°17.92'N and Long. 76°12.39'W; then running southeasterly along the Narrows Ferry Bridge to a point at or near the northwesterly point of Lower Hoopers Island, defined by Lat. 38°17.68'N and Long. 76°12.25'W; then running southeasterly along the west shore of Lower Hoopers Island to a point at or near the west side of Richland Cove, defined by Lat. 38°14.85'N and Long. 76°10.11'W; then running approximately 116° True to a point at or near the east side of Richland Cove, defined by Lat. 38°14.84'N and Long. 76°10.07'W; then running easterly along the shore to a point at or near the west side of Thorofare Creek, defined by Lat. 38°14.70'N and Long. 76°09.13'W; then running approximately 118° True to a point at or near the east side of Thorofare Creek, defined by Lat. 38°14.66'N and Long. 76°09.04'W; then running southerly and easterly to a point at or near Creek Point, defined by Lat. 38°13.97'N and Long. 76°07.87'W; then running approximately 140° True to a point at or near Okahanikan Point, defined by Lat. 38°11.54'N and Long. 76°05.26'W; then running southerly along the west shore of Bloodsworth Island to a point at or near the north side of Pone Cove, defined by Lat. 38°10.38'N and Long. 76°04.84'W; then running approximately 246° True to a point at or near the south side of Pone Cove, defined by Lat. 38°10.37'N and Long. 76°04.86'W; then running southerly along the west shore of Pone Island to a point at or near the south end of Pone Island, defined by Lat. 38°09.40'N and Long. 76°05.13'W; then running approximately 203° True to a point at or near the north end of Adam Island, defined by Lat. 38°09.25'N and Long. 76°05.20'W; then running along the west shore of Adam Island to a point at or near the south end of Adam Island, defined by Lat. 38°08.29'N and Long. 76°05.16'W; then running approximately 197° True to a point at or near the north end of Holland Island, defined by Lat. 38°07.76'N and Long. 76°05.36'W; then running southerly along the west side of Holland Island to a point at or near the south end of Holland Island, defined by Lat. 38°06.91'N and Long. 76°05.41'W; then running approximately 156° True to a point at or near the Dorchester-Somerset County line, defined by Lat. 38°04.78'N and Long. 76°04.18'W; then running approximately 154° True to a point at or near Fog Point, defined by Lat. 38°02.04'N and Long. 76°02.50'W; then running southerly along the west shore of Smith Island to a point at or near Channel Point, defined by Lat. 38°00.57'N and Long. 76°02.96'W; then running approximately 183° True to a point at or near the south entrance of Goose Harbor, defined by Lat. 37°59.45'N and Long. 76°03.04'W; then running southerly along the west shore of Smith Island to a point at or near the north side of Sheep Pen Gut, defined by Lat. 37°58.99'N and Long. 76°02.98'W; then running approximately 169° True to a point at or near the south side of Sheep Pen Gut, defined by Lat. 37°58.77'N and Long. 76°02.93'W; then running southerly along the west shore of Smith Island to a point at or near the intersection of the shoreline and the Maryland-Virginia state line, defined by Lat. 37°57.21'N and Long. 76°02.82'W; then running approximately 270° True to a point at or near Maryland-Virginia boundary point Sassafrass Hammock, defined by Lat. 37°57.21'N and Long. 76°03.12'W; then running approximately 245° True to the point of beginning, defined by Lat. 37°53.19'N and Long. 76°14.20'W.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Chesapeake Bay—Holland Straits. All of the waters of the State beginning at a point at or near the Dorchester-Somerset County line, where that line intersects with a line between Fog Point and the south end of Holland Island, defined by Lat. 38°04.78'N and Long. 76°04.18'W; then running approximately 336° True to a point at or near the south end of Holland Island, defined by Lat. 38°06.91'N and Long. 76°05.41'W; then running northerly along the east side of Holland Island to a point at or near the north end of Holland Island, defined by Lat. 38°07.76'N and Long. 76°05.36'W; then running approximately 17° True to a point at or near the south end of Adam Island, defined by Lat. 38°08.29'N and Long. 76°05.16'W; then running northerly along the east side of Adam Island to a point at or near the north end of Adam Island, defined by Lat. 38°09.25'N and Long. 76°05.20'W; then running approximately 23° True to a point at or near the south end of Pone Island, defined by Lat. 38°09.40'N and Long. 76°05.13'W; then running northeasterly along the south side of Pone Island to a point at or near the south side of Long Creek, defined by Lat. 38°09.78'N and Long. 76°04.17'W; then running approximately 7° True to a point at or near the north side of Long Creek, defined by Lat. 38°09.98'N and Long. 76°04.14'W; then running northeasterly along the south shore of Pone Island to a point at or near the west side of Swan Pond Creek, defined by Lat. 38°10.11'N and Long. 76°03.94'W; then running approximately 74° True to a point at or near the east side of Swan Pond Creek, defined by Lat. 38°10.16'N and Long. 76°03.72' W; then running southeasterly along the south shore of Bloodsworth Island to a point at or near Lower Island Point, defined by Lat. 38°08.86'N and Long. 76°01.90'W; then running approximately 133° True to a point at or near Sound Point, defined by Lat. 38°08.03'N and Long. 76°00.76'W; then running westerly along the north shore of South Marsh Island to a point at or near the east side of Gunbarrel Cove, defined by Lat. 38°07.81'N and Long. 76°01.49'W; then running approximately 239° True to a point at or near Gunbarrel Point, defined by Lat. 38°07.54'N and Long. 76°02.06'W; then running approximately 184° True to a point at or near the west side of Gunbarrel Cove, defined by Lat. 38°07.49'N and Long. 76°02.06'W; then running southerly to a point at or near the east side of Sheepshead Harbor Gut, defined by Lat. 38°05.12'N and Long. 76°02.09'W; then running approximately 226° True to a point at or near the west side of Sheepshead Harbor Gut, defined by Lat. 38°05.11'N and Long. 76°02.11'W; then running westerly along the shore of South Marsh Island to a point at or near Sedgy Point, defined by Lat. 38°05.64'N and Long. 76°03.36'W; then running approximately 281° True to a point at or near the easterly point of Pry Island, defined by Lat. 38°05.66'N and Long. 76°03.47'W; then running westerly along the north shore of Pry Island to a point at or near the southwesterly tip of Pry Island, defined by Lat. 38°05.68'N and Long. 76°03.70'W; then running approximately 203° True to the point of beginning, defined by Lat. 38°04.78'N and Long. 76°04.18'W.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Chesapeake Bay—Hoopers Straits. All of the waters of the State enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near Okahanikan Point, defined by Lat. 38°11.54'N and Long. 76°05.26'W; then running approximately 320° True to a point at or near Creek Point, defined by Lat. 38°13.97'N and Long. 76°07.87'W; then running approximately 50° True to a point at or near a point on the shore at Jimson Weed Marsh, defined by Lat. 38°15.21'N and Long. 76°05.99'W; then running southeasterly along the shore of Jimson Weed Marsh and Bishop Head Marsh to a point at or near Bishops Head Point, defined by Lat. 38°12.93'N and Long. 76°01.94'W; then running approximately 188° True to a point at or near Piney Island Point, defined by Lat. 38°11.58'N and Long. 76°02.16'W; then running westerly along the north shore of Bloodsworth Island and Pone Island to the point of beginning, defined by Lat. 38°11.54'N and Long. 76°05.26'W.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Chesapeake Bay—Kedges Straits. All of the waters of the State enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near Fishing Point at the northeast tip of Smith Island, defined by Lat. 38°01.39'N and Long. 75°59.14'W; then running westerly along the north shore of Smith Island to a point at or near Fog Point, defined by Lat. 38°02.04'N and Long. 76°02.50'W; then running approximately 334° True to a point at or near the intersection of the Dorchester-Somerset County line, defined by Lat. 38°04.78'N and Long. 76°04.18'W; then running approximately 23° True to a point at or near the southwesterly tip of Pry Island, defined by Lat. 38°05.68'N and Long. 76°03.70'W; then running easterly along the shore of Pry Island to a point at or near the east end of Pry Island, defined by Lat. 38°05.66'N and Long. 76°03.47'W; then running approximately 101° True to a point at or near Sedgy Point, defined by Lat. 38°05.64'N and Long. 76°03.36'W; then running southeasterly along the shore of South Marsh Island to a point at or near the west side of Sheepshead Harbor Gut, defined by Lat. 38°05.11'N and Long. 76°02.11'W; then running approximately 46° True to a point at or near the east side of Sheepshead Harbor Gut, defined by Lat. 38°05.12'N and Long. 76°02.09'W; then running easterly along the south shore of South Marsh Island to a point at or near Muscle Hole Point, defined by Lat. 38°04.67'N and Long. 76°00.34'W; then running approximately 164° True to the point of beginning, defined by Lat. 38°01.39'N and Long. 75°59.14'W.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Pocomoke Sound. All of the waters of the State enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near Boundary Point Watkins Point 1898, defined by Lat. 37°54.68'N and Long. 75°52.98'W; then running approximately 347° True to a point at or near the shore of Pocomoke Sound, defined by Lat. 37°54.72'N and Long. 75°52.99'W; then running northeasterly along the shore to a point at or near Watkins Point, defined by Lat. 37°54.73'N and Long. 75°52.90'W; then running approximately 58° True to a point at or near the shore on the east side of Fishing Creek, defined by Lat. 37°55.03'N and Long. 75°52.29'W; then running easterly along the shore to a point at or near Oyster Point, defined by Lat. 37°55.18'N and Long. 75°51.57'W; then running approximately 51° True to a point at or near Westward Point, defined by Lat. 37°55.36'N and Long. 75°51.29'W; then running approximately 77° True to a point at or near Eastward Point, defined by Lat. 37°55.43'N and Long. 75°50.93'W; then running easterly along the north shore of Pocomoke Sound, including its tributaries, to a point at or near the northeast corner of Fair Island Canal, defined by Lat. 37°57.79'N and Long. 75°39.33'W; then running approximately 82° True to a point at or near the Maryland-Virginia line, south of Corner "N", defined by Lat. 37°57.84'N and Long. 75°38.91'W; then running approximately 179° True to a point at or near Maryland-Virginia line Corner "M", defined by Lat. 37°56.80'N and Long. 75°38.89'W; then running approximately 256° True to a point at or near Maryland-Virginia line Corner "L", defined by Lat. 37°56.71'N and Long. 75°39.37'W; then running approximately 298° True to a point at or near Maryland-Virginia line Corner "K", defined by Lat. 37°56.99'N and Long. 75°40.04'W; then running approximately 286° True to a point at or near Maryland-Virginia line Corner "J", defined by Lat. 37°57.32'N and Long. 75°41.50'W; then running approximately 266° True to a point at or near Maryland-Virginia line Corner "H", defined by Lat. 37°57.27'N and Long. 75°42.29'W; then running approximately 254° True to a point at or near Maryland-Virginia line Corner "D", defined by Lat. 37°56.47'N and Long. 75°45.70'W; then running approximately 227° True to a point at or near Maryland-Virginia line Corner "A", defined by Lat. 37°54.73'N and Long. 75°48.06'W; then running approximately 269° True to the point of beginning, defined by Lat. 37°54.68'N and Long. 75°52.98'W.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Tangier Sound. All of the waters of the State enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near Maryland-Virginia Boundary Point "B", Tangier Sound, defined by Lat. 37°54.40'N and Long. 75°57.16'W; then running approximately 10° True to a point at or near Maryland-Virginia Boundary Point "A", Tangier Sound, defined by Lat. 37°56.76'N and Long. 75°56.62'W; then running approximately 281° True to a point at or near Maryland-Virginia line corner "Horse Hammock", defined by Lat. 37°57.20'N and Long. 75°59.61'W; then running approximately 270° True to a point at or near the intersection of the Maryland-Virginia line and the east shore of Smith Island, defined by Lat. 37°57.20'N and Long. 75°59.68'W; then running northerly along the shore of Smith Island to a point at or near the shore on the south side of Big Thorofare, defined by Lat. 37°58.00'N and Long. 75°59.72'W; then running approximately 356° True to a point at or near the shore on the north side of Big Thorofare, defined by Lat. 37°58.32'N and Long. 75°59.74'W; then running northerly along the shore to a point at or near the south side of Little Thorofare, defined by Lat. 37°58.48'N and Long. 75°59.68'W; then running approximately 78° True to a point at or near the north side of Little Thorofare, defined by Lat. 37°58.49'N and Long. 75°59.60'W; then running northerly along the shore to a point at or near the south side of Joes Ridge Creek, defined by Lat. 38°00.01'N and Long. 75°59.14'W; then running approximately 51° True to a point at or near the north side of Joes Ridge Creek, defined by Lat. 38°00.06'N and Long. 75°59.05'W; then running northerly along the shore to a point at or near the south side of Barnes Cove, defined by Lat. 38°00.20'N and Long. 75°59.04'W; then running approximately 22° True to a point at or near the north side of Barnes Cove, defined by Lat. 38°00.24'N and Long. 75°59.02'W; then running northerly along the shore to a point at or near Fishing Point, defined by Lat. 38°01.39'N and Long. 75°59.14'W; then running approximately 344° True to a point at or near Muscle Hole Point, defined by Lat. 38°04.67'N and Long. 76°00.34'W; then running northerly along the east shore of South Marsh Island to a point at or near Long Point, defined by Lat. 38°06.42'N and Long. 76°01.03'W; then running approximately 287° True to a point at or near the north shore of Pungers Creek, defined by Lat. 38°06.48'N and Long. 76°01.26'W; then running northerly along the shore to a point at or near Pungers Point, defined by Lat. 38°06.95'N and Long. 76°01.04'W; then running approximately 33° True to a point at or near Marsh Point, defined by Lat. 38°07.24'N and Long. 76°00.80'W; then running northerly along the shore to a point at or near Sound Point, defined by Lat. 38°08.03'N and Long. 76°00.76'W; then running approximately 313° True to a point at or near Lower Island Point on the south side of Bloodsworth Island, defined by Lat. 38°08.86'N and Long. 76°01.90'W; then running northerly along the east side of Bloodsworth Island to a point at or near Piney Island Point, defined by Lat. 38°11.58'N and Long. 76°02.16'W; then running approximately 8° True to a point at or near Bishops Head Point, defined by Lat. 38°12.93'N and Long. 76°01.94'W; then running approximately 70° True to a point at or near the southwest tip of Clay Island, defined by Lat. 38°13.97'N and Long. 75°58.35'W; then running easterly along the south shore of Clay Island to a point at or near Frog Point, defined by Lat. 38°14.21'N and Long. 75°56.90'W; then running approximately 101° True to a point at or near Stump Point, defined by Lat. 38°13.73'N and Long. 75°53.82'W; then running easterly along the shore of Stump Point Marsh to a point at or near Mollie Point, defined by Lat. 38°13.75'N and Long. 75°53.03'W; then running approximately 33° True to a point at or near Bay Point, defined by Lat. 38°14.57'N and Long. 75°52.34'W; then running approximately 147° True to a point at or near Wingate Point, defined by Lat. 38°13.71'N and Long. 75°51.62'W; then running approximately 221° True to a point at or near Long Point, defined by Lat. 38°12.21'N and Long. 75°53.26'W; then running westerly along the shore to a point at or near the east shore of Rock Creek, defined by Lat. 38°11.46'N and Long. 75°55.34'W; then running approximately 256° True to a point at or near the west shore of Rock Creek, defined by Lat. 38°11.44'N and Long. 75°55.46'W; then running west and south near the north side of Upper Thorofare, defined by Lat. 38°10.19'N and Long. 75°56.86'W; then running approximately 199° True to a point at or near the south side of Upper Thorofare, on Deal Island, defined by Lat. 38°10.13'N and Long. 75°56.88'W; then running southerly along the west shore of Deal Island to a point at or near the north side of Lower Thorofare, near Wenona, defined by Lat. 38°07.61'N and Long. 75°56.98'W; then running approximately 115° True to a point at or near the south side of Lower Thorofare, on Little Deal Island, defined by Lat. 38°07.51'N and Long. 75°56.72'W; then running southerly along the west shore of Little Deal Island to a point at or near Pin Point, defined by Lat. 38°06.71'N and Long. 75°56.46'W; then running approximately 126° True to a point at or near Hazard Point, defined by Lat. 38°04.54'N and Long. 75°52.73'W; then running southerly along the west shores of Hazard Island and Pat Island to a point at or near Porpoise Point, defined by Lat. 38°03.62'N and Long. 75°52.47'W; then running approximately 153° True to a point at or near Tenth Point, defined by Lat. 38°02.31'N and Long. 75°51.62'W; then running southerly along the west shore of Janes Island to a point at or near Janes Island Point, defined by Lat. 37°58.39'N and Long. 75°53.89'W; then running approximately 159° True to a point at or near Great Point, defined by Lat. 37°57.39'N and Long. 75°53.41'W; then running southerly along the west shore of Cedar Island Marsh to a point at or near the north side of Cow Point Creek, defined by Lat. 37°56.25'N and Long. 75°53.71'W; then running approximately 168° True to a point at or near the south side of Cow Point Creek, defined by Lat. 37°56.12'N and Long. 75°53.68'W; then running southerly along the west shore of Cedar Island Marsh to a point at or near the north side of Fishing Creek, defined by Lat. 37°55.79'N and Long. 75°53.70'W; then running approximately 187° True to a point at or near the south side of Fishing Creek, defined by Lat. 37°55.69'N and Long. 75°53.71'W; then running southerly along the west side of Cedar Island to a point at or near the westernmost point of Cedar Island, defined by Lat. 37°55.53'N and Long. 75°53.88'W; then running approximately 197° True to a point at or near the Maryland-Virginia line at Blizzard Island Range 1916, defined by Lat. 37°54.60'N and Long. 75°54.24'W; then running approximately 265° True to the point of beginning, defined by Lat. 37°54.40'N and Long. 75°57.16'W.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|02|01|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Recreational Fishing License and Registration.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Nontidal Angler’s License. A person shall be licensed in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-604">Natural Resources Article, §4-604, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, to fish in the nontidal waters of the State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Chesapeake Bay and Coastal Sport Fishing License and Registration.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person shall be licensed or registered in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-745">Natural Resources Article, §4-745, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, to fish for finfish in the Chesapeake Bay or its tidal tributaries up to tidal boundaries or in State waters of the Atlantic Ocean and the Atlantic coastal bays and tributaries.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Special Licenses.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Charter Boat License. The Department may issue a special charter boat license decal to an individual who pays the fee set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-745">Natural Resources Article, §4-745, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, that is valid in tidal waters of the State for all individuals on a:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Single vessel operated by a fishing guide licensed in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-210">Natural Resources Article, §4-210</cite>.1 or 4-701, Annotated Code of Maryland; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Vessel under the guidance of a fishing guide licensed in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-210">Natural Resources Article, §4-210, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Recreational Boat License.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The Department may issue a special Chesapeake Bay and coastal sport fishing license decal, which when permanently affixed to a boat registered in any state shall authorize any person on the boat to fish for finfish in the Chesapeake Bay or in its tributaries up to tidal boundaries or in State waters of the Atlantic Ocean and the Atlantic coastal bays and tributaries, to an individual who pays the fee set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-745">Natural Resources Article, §4-745, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The license decal may not be used on a boat that has been hired to take persons fishing.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>License Decals. Except as provided in <cite path="08|02|01|.07|B.|(4)">§B(4) of this regulation</cite>, a decal issued in place of a special license described in <cite path="08|02|01|.07|B.|(2)">§B(2) of this regulation</cite>:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Shall be permanently affixed and displayed on either side of the forward half of the vessel for which issued;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is not transferable;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Shall be color coded, dated, and of a size to be visible; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Shall, when displayed, exempt all persons aboard the vessel for which the decal was issued or under the guidance of a licensed fishing guide from the requirement of possessing an individual license to fish recreationally.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Exemption for License Decals. If the license decal is not permanently affixed to the vessel, all persons aboard the vessel or under the guidance of a licensed fishing guide are exempt from the requirement of possessing an individual license to fish recreationally only if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The individual who purchased the license decal is present on the vessel for which the decal was issued;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The individual who purchased the license decal is in possession of the proof of purchase issued by the Department; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The license decal was purchased within the previous 10 calendar days.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Replacement Decals. If the decal issued in place of a Chesapeake Bay and coastal sport fishing license is lost or destroyed, the person to whom the decal was originally issued may apply for Replacement decal by submitting to the Department:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An application on a form required by the Department that includes a statement regarding the need for replacement; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A fee of $5.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Registration. A person shall be registered in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-745">Natural Resources Article, §4-745, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite> prior to fishing in the following areas that do not require a fishing license:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A free fishing area described in <cite path="08|02|01|.07|D.">§D of this regulation</cite> with hook and line;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>On private real property bordering on tidal water as an owner or tenant of the property, or a spouse or an immediate family member who resides on the property with the owner or tenant; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>On a boat licensed as a recreational boat as described in <cite path="08|02|01|.07|B.|(2)|(b)">§B(2)(b) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Possession of License or Registration.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Chesapeake Bay and coastal sport fishing license or registration shall be in the possession of the person fishing and is not transferable.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>In addition to possession of the Chesapeake Bay and coastal sport fishing license or registration, the person fishing shall also possess a separate form of identification.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Consolidated Senior Sport Fishing License. A Maryland resident in the calendar year in which they attain the age of 65 shall be licensed in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-216">Natural Resources Article, §4-216, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, to fish for finfish in the nontidal waters of the State, Chesapeake Bay and its tributaries, or in State waters of the Atlantic Ocean and the Atlantic coastal bays and tributaries.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Free Fishing Areas in Tidal Waters. An individual fishing in an area described in this section shall be registered in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-745">Natural Resources Article, §4-745, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and is exempt from all other license fees and requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Anne Arundel County — Annapolis — Maryland Route 450 bridge over the Severn River.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Baltimore County — Cox’s Point on Back River and Deep Creek.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Baltimore City:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Canton Recreational Pier at Boston Street Pier Park;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Canton Waterfront Park; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Middle Branch Park from fishing pier south of the Hanover — Potee Street Bridges, to Hanover Street Bridge over Middle Branch.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Caroline County:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Denton — Pier associated with G. Daniel Crouse Memorial Park on the east side of Choptank River north of Maryland Route 404 Bridge;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Federalsburg Municipal Park — City-owned bulkhead, pier and banks within park boundaries on Marshyhope Creek; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Greensboro Waterfront Park — Upstream of the Sunset Avenue bridge within park boundaries on the Choptank River.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Cecil County:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Charlestown — Town-owned stone wharf on the Northeast River near the corner of Conestoga and Water Streets and the historic site of Charlestown Wharf;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>North East — North East Community Park at mouth of North East Creek; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Perryville — Within the park boundaries of Ice House Park downstream of the Route 40 bridge on the Susquehanna River.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Charles County — Friendship Landing — County-owned pier and property adjacent to the pier off Friendship Landing Road southeast of Ironsides Riverside Road (Route 425) on Nanjemoy Creek.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Dorchester County — Cambridge — Long Wharf from south end of city-owned bulkhead associated with the Municipal Yacht Basin within Cambridge Creek to the end of east breakwater at mouth of the Municipal Yacht Basin.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Harford County — Havre de Grace:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Tydings Memorial Park within designated area; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Pier at the end of Congress Street.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Kent County — Chestertown — Maryland Route 213 Bridge over Chester River.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Somerset County:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Janes Island State Park — Bulkhead area on Daugherty Creek within the boundaries of Janes Island State Park; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Crisfield City Dock — City dock/depot area at the end of West Main Street.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Wicomico County:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Salisbury — City-owned bulkhead on the Wicomico River between Mill Street and Division Street;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Sharptown — Pier and town dock off Ferry Street on the Nanticoke River; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Tyaskin Park — County-owned park on Wetipquin Creek west of Route 349 at Tyaskin.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Worcester County:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Pocomoke City — City docks from Laurel Street boat ramp to U.S. Route 13 overpass and Winter Quarter dock on Pocomoke River;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Snow Hill — County bridge on Porter’s Crossing Road west of U.S. Route 113 and east of Route 354 on the Pocomoke River; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Ocean City:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Bulkhead on Chicago Avenue between 2nd and 4th Streets; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Northside Park — Town-owned pier and park at 125th Street.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Free Fishing Area in Nontidal Waters.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An individual fishing in the area described in this section is exempt from all license and stamp requirements.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Frederick County — Gambrill State Park — Banks of the one acre pond located within Gambrill State Park boundaries, near the Park’s campground.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Change of Address.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A person who holds or is eligible to renew a license, registration, or permit, issued under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr">Natural Resources Article, Title 4, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or its implementing regulations shall update the person’s address of record within 30 days of any change.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Address updates shall be submitted in writing in the form and manner prescribed by the Department.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Unless updated, the address of record is the address a person provides to the Department when applying for or renewing a license, registration, or permit issued under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr">Natural Resources Article, Title 4, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or its implementing regulations.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Dividing Lines; Tidal and Nontidal Waters.</heading>
    <text>The following boundaries are designated as official dividing lines for tidal and nontidal waters. These boundary lines are for the purpose of delineating those areas in which nontidal fishing licenses or Chesapeake Bay and coastal sport fishing licenses are required and tidal or nontidal fishing regulations apply, and have no other legal significance.</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Harford County.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Winter's Run: dam located 1/2 mile south of Maryland Route 7, the Old Philadelphia Road.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Bynum Run: Old Philadelphia Road Bridge on Maryland Route 7.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>James Run: Old Philadelphia Road Bridge on Maryland Route 7.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Deer Creek: Railroad bridge located at the mouth of Deer Creek.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Gray's Run: CSX Railroad crossing upstream of U.S. 40.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Swan Creek: bridge on Old Post Road.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Baltimore County.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Big Gunpowder Falls: 3/4 of a mile south of Maryland Route 7, the Old Philadelphia Road at B&amp;O Railroad Bridge.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Little Gunpowder Falls: 3/4 of a mile south of Maryland Route 7, the Old Philadelphia Road at B&amp;O Railroad Bridge.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Stemmers Run: Golden Ring Road Bridge.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Stansbury Park Pond: base of dam.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Baltimore and Howard Counties. Patapsco River: B&amp;O Viaduct at Relay.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Anne Arundel and Prince George's Counties.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Patuxent River:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Mainstem: bridge on Maryland Route 214;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Lyons Creek: Maryland Route 4;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Stocketts Run: confluence with the river;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Rock Run: confluence with the river;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Ferry Branch: confluence with the river.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Severn River: bridge on Maryland Route 3.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Furnace Branch: Maryland Route 2.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Anacostia River: Northeast Branch Bridge at northbound lane of Alternate U.S. Route 1, Bladensburg Road; Northwest Branch Bridge at southbound lane of Rhode Island Avenue.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Marley Creek: Maryland Route 10.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Magothy River: Catherine Avenue.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>South River and its tributaries:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>North River: Rutland Road;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Bacon Ridge Branch: Chesterfield Road;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Beards Creek: Maryland Route 214;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Broad Creek: Harry S Truman Parkway.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Charles, Montgomery, and Prince George's Counties.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Potomac River: man-made dam at Little Falls.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Piscataway Creek: bridge on Maryland Route 224 (Livingston Road).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Henson Run: bridge on Old Broad Creek Road.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Western Branch: bridge on Maryland Route 4.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Nanjemoy Creek:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Mainstem: Maryland Route 6;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Mill Run (Burgess Cr.): Maryland Route 6;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Hill Top Fork: Maryland Route 6;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Wards Run: Maryland Route 6.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Wicomico River: Allens Fresh, bridge on Maryland Route 234.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Port Tobacco Creek: bridge on Maryland Route 6.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Mattawoman Creek: bridge on Maryland Route 225.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Patuxent River:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Swanson Creek: Maryland Route 381;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Mataponi Creek: St. Thomas Church Road;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Spice Creek: Maryland Route 382, Croom Road;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Full Mill Branch: Maryland Route 382, Croom Road;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Black Swamp Creek: Maryland Route 382, Croom Road.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Pomonkey Creek: Fenwick Road.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Hoghole Run: Maryland Route 6.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Oxen Creek (Run): Maryland Route 210.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Kent and Queen Anne's Counties.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Chester River: 500 yards upstream from the Pennsylvania Railroad Bridge at Millington at the point where the Cypress Branch empties into the Chester River.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Unicorn Branch: the U.S. Geological Survey weir just east of Maryland Route 313.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Sassafras River: Maryland Route 299.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Herring Branch: Maryland Route 299.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Morgan Creek: Wallis Road.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Red Lion Branch: confluence with the Chester River.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Wye East River: Wye Mills Lake dam.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Caroline County.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Choptank River: bypass bridge on Maryland Route 313 on the outskirts of Greensboro.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Tuckahoe Creek: abandoned stone railroad bridge upstream of Maryland Route 404.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Watt's Creek: bridge on American Legion Road.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Fowling Creek: wooden bridge on Stratum Road about 1 mile below Maryland Route 16.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Chapel Branch: Maryland Route 313 near Piney Grove Church.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Marshy Hope Creek: confluence with Faulkner Branch.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Mill Creek: Maryland Route 16.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Hunting Creek: Maryland Route 331.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Wicomico and Worcester Counties.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Pocomoke River: bridge on Whiton Crossing, 3 miles south of Powellville.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Wicomico River: Isabella Street in Salisbury.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Beaverdam Creek: dam just upstream of U.S. Route 13 (Business).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Nassawango Creek: Furnace Road.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Barren Creek: U.S. Route 50 Bridge</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>St. Mary's County.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Park Hall Run: Maryland Route 5.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>McIntosh Run: Maryland Route 5.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Great Mills Run: bridge on Maryland Route 5.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Town Run: bridge on Maryland Route 5.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Chaptico Run: Chaptico Bridge on Maryland Route 234.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Eastern Branch: Maryland Route 5.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Dynard Run: Maryland Route 242.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Tomakokin Creek: Maryland Route 470.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Buds Creek: Maryland Route 234.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Gilbert Swamp Run: Maryland Route 234.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>St. Clements Creek: Maryland Route 234, bridge at town of Clements.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Calvert County.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>St. Leonard's Creek: Parran Road.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Battle Creek: bridge about 2 miles east of Bowens (Sixes Road).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Parker's Creek: Maryland Route 765.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Hunting Creek: bridge on Maryland Route 263 about 100 yards west of Maryland Route 4.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Hall's Creek: Bridge on Maryland Route 4.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Lyons Creek: Bridge on Maryland Route 4.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Fishing Creek: 1-1/2 miles upstream from the mouth of the creek at Chesapeake Beach.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Plum Point Creek: bridge on Maryland Route 263.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Mills Creek: Maryland Route 760.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Hellen Creek: Mill Branch Road, near Solomons.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Island Creek: Ross Road, near Brooms Island.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>St. Johns Creek: Maryland Route 4.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Quaker Swamp: Maryland Routes 2 and 4.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Susquehanna River. Conowingo Dam at U.S. Route 1.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Cecil County.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Octoraro Creek: bridge on U.S. Route 222.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Rock Run: confluence with the Susquehanna River.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Mill Creek: Old Elk Neck Road.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Principio Creek: Amtrak crossing below Maryland Route 7.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>North East River: Maryland Route 7.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Little Elk Creek: U.S. Route 40.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Big Elk Creek: Maryland Route 213.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Bohemia River: Telegraph Road.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Happy Valley Branch: confluence with Susquehanna River.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>Dorchester County.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Chicamicomico River: U.S. Route 50.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Transquaking River: dam at Higgins Mill Pond.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Pilot Programs.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Department may conduct pilot projects to demonstrate and evaluate new approaches to managing fisheries under the fishery management plans as incorporated by reference in <cite path="|08|02|01|.01">Regulation .01 of this chapter</cite> for the following species:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Blue crabs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Striped bass;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Oysters;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Hard clams;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Yellow perch;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Summer flounder;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Black sea bass;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Tautog;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Bluefish;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Weakfish and spotted sea trout;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Black drum;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Red drum;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Horseshoe crabs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>American eel;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>Alosid;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>Croaker and Spot; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>Catfish.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Pilot Project Activities. Notwithstanding Natural Resources, Title 4 (except for §4-1002), Annotated Code of Maryland, and <cite path="|08.02">COMAR 08.02</cite>, pilot projects may be conducted to implement conservation and management measures as defined by a fishery management plan.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Department may select and designate certain persons licensed under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-701">Natural Resources Article, §4-701, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, to participate in a pilot project. A participating licensee shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Apply for a pilot program permit on forms provided by the Department;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Have a pilot program permit in order to participate in a pilot program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Comply with any conditions of the permit; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Be eliminated from the pilot project at the discretion of the Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Department shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Develop pilot projects in cooperation with the commercial fishing industry;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Prepare a written evaluation of the pilot project to be included in the annual Fisheries Management Plan report to the General Assembly; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Provide adequate notice of a pilot program through various media so that an interested individual has reasonable opportunity to be informed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Black Bass Tournaments.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Species. The following species are defined as black bass:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Largemouth bass (Micropterus salmoides); and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Smallmouth bass (Micropterus dolomieu).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Unless exempted by the black bass tournament permit, all regulations pertaining to the harvest of black bass are in effect for black bass tournaments and can be found in <cite path="08.02.05.19">COMAR 08.02.05.19</cite> and <cite path="08.02.11.03">08.02.11.03</cite>—.04 and .06.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Black Bass Tournament Permit.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person shall obtain a black bass tournament permit prior to conducting a fishing tournament that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Has ten or more boats participating;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has a specific location where fish are weighed, measured, counted, or otherwise entered into the tournament; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Provides anglers an offer, reward, or incentive for catching black bass.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person shall apply to the Department, on forms provided by the Department, a minimum of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>15 business days prior to the tournament if the tournament has ten to 49 boats entered; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>30 business days prior to the tournament if the tournament has 50 or more boats entered.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The black bass tournament permit may authorize more than one tournament provided the tournaments occur within the same calendar year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Transfers of black bass tournament permits are not permitted.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The permittee or release boat operator shall be in possession of the black bass tournament permit while engaged in the fishing tournament activities specified on the permit.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A person with a valid black bass tournament permit shall follow all conditions on the permit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Dead Fish Disposal. If fish die during the tournament the permittee shall dispose of the dead fish in accordance with the conditions specified on the black bass tournament permit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Release Boats. A person operating a vessel used to distribute fish following a tournament shall comply with the conditions specified on the black bass tournament permit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The Department may deny an application for a black bass tournament permit for failing to comply with the conditions of the applicant’s most recent black bass tournament permit.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|02|01|.12">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Submerged Aquatic Vegetation (SAV) Protection Zones.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General. A person may not use the following gear in the areas established in <cite path="08|02|01|.12|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Hydraulic clam dredge;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Bottom dredge; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Shinnecock rake.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Submerged Aquatic Vegetation (SAV) Protection Zones.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Somerset County.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Saint Peter's Creek and Manokin River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the north shore of Champ Point defined by Lat. 38° 08.725' N, Long. 75°49.161' W; then running approximately 43° True to a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 38° 08.972' N, Long. 75°48.872' W; then running southwesterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Big Sound Creek, Little Sound Creek, Laws Gut and Laws Thorofare enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the eastern shore of Big Sound Creek defined by Lat. 38°08.453' N, Long. 75°54.454' W; then running approximately 340° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°08.841' N, Long. 75°54.631' W; then running approximately 220° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°08.596' N, Long. 75°54.895' W; then running approximately 297° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°08.689' N, Long. 75°55.120' W; then running approximately 313° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°08.915' N, Long. 75°55.431' W; then running approximately 306° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°09.000' N, Long. 75°55.580' W; then running approximately 252° True to a point at or near the shore of Laws Thorofare defined by Lat. 38°08.963' N, Long. 75°55.730' W; then running easterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Fishing Creek, Manokin River, Broad Creek, and Geanquakin Creek enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore at the west side of Fishing Creek defined by Lat. 38°08.383' N, Long. 75°54.458' W; then running approximately 175° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°08.354' N, Long. 75°54.455' W; then running along the southern shore to a point defined by Lat. 38°08.281' N, Long. 75°54.370' W; then running approximately 84° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°08.294' N, Long. 75°54.154’ W; then running approximately 38° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°08.481' N, Long. 75°53.970’ W; then running approximately 7° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°08.780' N, Long. 75°53.919' W; then running approximately 85° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°08.865' N, Long. 75°52.885’ W; then running approximately 181° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°08.193 N, Long. 75°52.906’ W; then running approximately 105° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°08.018' N, Long. 75°52.083’ W; then running approximately 57° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°08.477' N, Long. 75°51.200' W; then running approximately 348° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°08.641' N, Long. 75°51.245' W; then running approximately 88° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°08.658' N, Long. 75°50.402' W; then running approximately 36° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°08.988' N, Long. 75°50.105' W; then running approximately 110° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°08.765' N, Long. 75°49.331' W; then running approximately 78° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°08.784' N, Long. 75°49.216' W; then running approximately 49° True to a point at or near the western shore of Saint Peter’s Creek defined by Lat. 38°08.850' N, Long. 75°49.126' W; then running westerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Manokin River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 38° 08.478' N, Long. 75°48.570' W; then running approximately 304° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°08.636' N, Long. 75°48.867' W; then running approximately 261° True to a point at or near the south shore of Champ Point defined by Lat. 38° 08.587' N, Long. 75°49.242' W; then running easterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Manokin River surrounding Saint Pierre's Island enclosed by a line beginning at a point defined by Lat. 38°07.874' N, Long. 75°51.309' W; then running approximately 327° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°07.890' N, Long. 75°51.322' W; then running approximately 37° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°07.946' N, Long. 75°51.270' W; then running approximately 158° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°07.909' N, Long. 75°51.251' W; then running approximately 223° True to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Manokin River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 38°07.851' N, Long. 75°55.424' W; then running approximately 66° True to a point at or near the southern shore of Shark Point defined by Lat. 38°07.893' N, Long. 75°55.306' W; then running westerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Lower Thorofare and Manokin River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the southern shore of Deal Island defined by Lat. 38°07.569' N, Long. 75°55.821' W; then running approximately 122° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°07.561' N, Long. 75°55.819' W; then running approximately 80° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°07.583' N, Long. 75°55.644' W; then running approximately 4° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°07.595' N, Long. 75°55.643' W; then running northerly along the shore to a point defined by Lat. 38°07.603' N, Long. 75°55.652' W; then running approximately 341° True to a point at or near the south shore of Deal Island defined by Lat. 38°07.617' N, Long. 75°55.657' W; then running westerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Lower Thorofare and Tangier Sound enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the western shore of Little Deal Island at Webster Point defined by Lat. 38°07.128' N, Long. 75°56.782' W; then running approximately 2° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°07.394' N, Long. 75°56.773' W; then running approximately 6° True to a point at or near the western shore of the Lower Thorofare inlet defined by Lat. 38°07.611' N, Long. 75°56.743' W; then running southerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Manokin River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the southern shore of Little Deal Island defined by Lat. 38°06.932' N, Long. 75°56.271' W; then running approximately 45° True to a point at or near the southern shore of Little Deal Island near Claw Point defined by Lat. 38°07.014' N, Long. 75°56.167' W; then running southwesterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Piney Creek, Manokin River and Tangier Sound enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the southern shore of Little Deal Island at Pin Point defined by Lat. 38°06.757' N, Long. 75°56.556' W; then running approximately 127° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°06.733' N, Long. 75°56.519' W; then running easterly along the shore to a point defined by Lat. 38°06.728' N, Long. 75°56.473' W; then running approximately 27° True to a point at the eastern shore of the entrance to Piney Creek defined by Lat. 38°06.873' N, Long. 75°56.379' W; then running westerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Hall Creek and Big Annemessex River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near Myrtle Point defined by Lat. 38°05.169' N, Long. 75°47.276' W; then running approximately 244° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°05.161' N, Long. 75° 47.298' W; then running approximately 297° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°05.172' N, Long. 75°47.326' W; then running approximately 337° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°05.273' N, Long. 75°47.380' W; then running approximately 271° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°05.275' N, Long. 75°47.442' W; then running approximately 256° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°05.252' N, Long. 75°47.552' W; then running approximately 12° True to a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 38°05.263' N, Long. 75°47.549' W; then running easterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Hall Creek, Moon Bay, Crane Cove, Fords Cove, Muddy Creek, Flatland Cove, Shirtpond Cove, Mine Cove, Hazard Cove, Goose Creek, Drum Point Cove, Teague Creek, Broad Creek, Big Annemessex River and Manokin River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore at the west side of Hall Creek defined by Lat. 38°05.129' N, Long. 75°47.498' W; then running approximately 49° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°05.181' N, Long. 75°47.429' W; then running approximately 164° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°05.048' N, Long. 75°47.378' W; then running approximately 179° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°04.661' N, Long. 75°47.368' W; then running approximately 144° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°04.399' N, Long. 75°47.131' W; then running approximately 243° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°04.188' N, Long. 75°47.669' W; then running approximately 293° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°04.421' N, Long. 75°48.381' W; then running approximately 144° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°03.882' N, Long. 75°47.903' W; then running approximately 206° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°03.657' N, Long. 75°48.048' W; then running approximately 281° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°03.722' N, Long. 75°48.468' W; then running approximately 227° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°03.506' N, Long. 75°48.761' W; then running approximately 316° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°04.096' N, Long. 75°49.469' W; then running approximately 252° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°03.958' N, Long. 75°50.012' W; then running approximately 298° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°04.252' N, Long. 75°50.718' W; then running approximately 221° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°04.031' N, Long. 75°50.967' W; then running approximately 270° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°04.036' N, Long. 75°51.353' W; then running approximately 199° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°03.575' N, Long. 75°51.545' W; then running approximately 270° True to a point at or near the southern shore of Pat Island defined by Lat. 38°03.572' N, Long. 75°52.016' W; then running northwesterly along the shore to a point at or near the southern shore of Hazard Cove defined by Lat. 38°03.960' N, Long. 75°52.335' W; then running approximately 334° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°04.540' N, Long. 75°52.700' W; then running approximately 17° True to a point at or near the western shore of Hazard Island defined by Lat. 38°04.652' N, Long. 75°52.655' W; then running approximately 21° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°05.395' N, Long. 75°52.297' W; then running approximately 22° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°06.045' N, Long. 75°51.973' W; then running approximately 46° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°07.209' N, Long. 75°50.436' W; then running approximately 13° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°07.598' N, Long. 75°50.324' W; then running approximately 54° True to a point at Cormal Point defined by Lat. 38°08.006' N, Long. 75°49.639' W; then running approximately 147° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°07.608' N, Long. 75°49.303' W; then running approximately 32° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°07.884' N, Long. 75°49.090' W; then running approximately 51° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°08.064' N, Long. 75°48.811' W; then running approximately 66° True to a point at or near the shore on the western shore of Fishing Point defined by Lat. 38°08.127' N, Long. 75°48.634' W; then running southerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Gales Creek and Big Annemessex River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 38°04.598' N, Long. 75°45.961' W; then running approximately 92° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°04.605' N, Long. 75° 46.440' W; then running approximately 303° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°04.696' N, Long. 75°46.622' W; then running approximately 254° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°04.658' N, Long. 75°46.789' W; then running approximately 294° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°04.724' N, Long. 75°46.978' W; then running approximately 70° True to a point at or near the shore of Persimmon Point defined by Lat. 38°04.747' N, Long. 75°46.905' W; then running easterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(n)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Colbourn Creek, Ipsenancy Creek, Gales Creek and Big Annemessex River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the Colbourn Creek Boat Ramp defined by Lat. 38°02.988' N, Long. 75°48.246' W; then running approximately 20° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°03.146' N, Long. 75°48.170' W; then running approximately 67° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°03.285' N, Long. 75°47.767' W; then running approximately 141° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°03.643' N, Long. 75°47.436' W; then running approximately 55° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°03.922' N, Long. 75°46.943' W; then running approximately 24° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°04.405' N, Long. 75°46.667' W; then running approximately 57° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°04.473' N, Long. 75°46.534' W; then running approximately 87° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°04.485' N, Long. 75°46.371' W; then running approximately 29° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°04.528' N, Long. 75°46.347' W; then running approximately 77° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°04.576' N, Long. 75°46.073' W; then running approximately 137° True to a point at or near the shore on the southern shore of Gales Creek defined by Lat. 38°04.514' N, Long. 75°46.001' W; then running southwesterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(o)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Colbourn Creek and Big Annemessex River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore west of Long Point defined by Lat. 38°02.934' N, Long. 75°48.575' W; then running approximately 18° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°03.286' N, Long. 75° 48.428' W; then running approximately 75° True to a point defined by Lat. 38° 03.335' N, Long. 75° 48.202' W; then running approximately 170° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°03.235' N, Long. 75°48.180' W; then running approximately 217° True to a point at or near the eastern shore of Long Point defined by Lat. 38°03.071' N, Long. 75°48.333' W; then running westerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(p)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Colbourn Creek enclosed by a line beginning at a point at the southern shore of Colbourn Creek defined by Lat. 38°02.647' N, Long. 75°47.649' W; then running approximately 281° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°02.747' N, Long. 75° 48.318' W; then running approximately 356° True to a point at or near the eastern side of Long Point at the entrance to Colbourn Creek defined by Lat. 38°03.021' N, Long. 75°48.345' W; then running southeasterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(q)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Jones Creek, Joes Cove and Big Annemessex River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the north shore of Jones Creek defined by Lat. 38°01.725' N, Long. 75°49.255' W; then running approximately 244° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°01.704' N, Long. 75°49.318' W; then running approximately 307° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°01.752' N, Long. 75°49.397' W; then running approximately 275° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°01.761' N, Long. 75°49.519' W; then running approximately 3° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°01.870' N, Long. 75°49.513' W; then running approximately 333° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°01.995' N, Long. 75°49.594' W; then running approximately 66° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°02.043' N, Long. 75°49.455' W; then running approximately 324° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°02.077' N, Long. 75°49.488' W; then running approximately 286° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°02.132' N, Long. 75°49.723' W; then running approximately 245° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°02.082' N, Long. 75°49.862' W; then running approximately 329° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°02.298' N, Long. 75°50.023' W; then running approximately 234° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°02.156' N, Long. 75°50.259' W; then running approximately 256° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°02.118' N, Long. 75°50.458' W; then running approximately 26° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°02.550' N, Long. 75°50.186' W; then running approximately 47° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°02.796' N, Long. 75°49.857' W; then running approximately 59° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°02.995' N, Long. 75°49.436' W; then running approximately 104° True to a point at or near the shore on the southwest side of Long Point defined by Lat. 38°02.842' N, Long. 75°48.666' W; then running southerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(r)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Daugherty Creek, West Creek, Back Creek, Island Gut, Janes Island Gut, Old House Gut, Old House Cove, Big Annemessex River, Rock Hole, Rock Pond, Thru Creek, Red Hole, Acre Creek, Annemessex Canal, Ward Creek, Jones Creek and Little Annemessex River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the west shore of Daugherty Creek defined by Lat. 37°58.774' N, Long. 75°51.883' W; then running approximately 210° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°58.458' N, Long. 75°52.138' W; then running approximately 229° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°58.141' N, Long. 75°52.584' W; then running approximately 265° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°58.138' N, Long. 75°52.726' W; then running approximately 302° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°58.331' N, Long. 75°53.120' W; then running approximately 230° True to a point at or near the shore south of Old House Cove defined by Lat. 37°58.202' N, Long. 75°53.338' W; then running northerly along shore past James Island Point to a point along the southern shore of Rock Hole defined by Lat. 38°01.181' N, Long. 75°52.181' W; then running approximately 344° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°01.414' N, Long. 75°52.273' W; then running approximately 329° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°01.630' N, Long. 75°52.428' W; then running approximately 64° True to a point along the shore at or near the northern shore of Rock Hole defined by Lat. 38°01.652' N, Long. 75°52.391' W; then running along the shore to a point at or near Tenth Point defined by Lat. 38°02.263' N, Long. 75°51.448' W; then running approximately 32° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°02.329' N, Long. 75°51.393' W; then running approximately 105° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°02.300' N, Long. 75°51.246' W; then running approximately 115° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°02.170' N, Long. 75°50.893' W; then running approximately 144° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°02.039' N, Long. 75°50.776' W; then running approximately 175° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°01.840' N, Long. 75°50.755' W; then running approximately 238° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°01.747' N, Long. 75°50.940' W; then running approximately 263° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°01.727' N, Long. 75°51.136' W; then running approximately 174° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°01.647' N, Long. 75°51.132' W; then running approximately 87° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°01.651' N, Long. 75°51.043' W; then running approximately 164° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°01.535' N, Long. 75°51.004' W; then running approximately 38° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°01.716' N, Long. 75°50.831' W; then running approximately 81° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°01.740' N, Long. 75°50.622' W; then running approximately 27° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°01.849' N, Long. 75°50.556' W; then running approximately 55° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°02.074' N, Long. 75°50.157' W; then running approximately 101° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°02.041' N, Long. 75°49.976' W; then running approximately 156° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°01.926' N, Long. 75°49.913' W; then running approximately 66° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°02.007' N, Long. 75°49.688' W; then running approximately 164° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°01.901' N, Long. 75°49.649' W; then running approximately 129° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°01.845' N, Long. 75°49.552' W; then running approximately 187° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°01.749' N, Long. 75°49.564' W; then running approximately 102° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°01.732' N, Long. 75°49.442' W; then running approximately 138° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°01.638' N, Long. 75°49.326' W; then running approximately 253° True to a point at the western shore of Jones Creek defined by Lat. 38°01.621' N, Long. 75°49.397' W; then running along shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(s)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Daugherty Creek, Jenkins Creek and Little Annemessex River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the southern shore of the entrance to Jenkins Creek defined by Lat. 37°57.187' N, Long. 75°51.821' W; then running approximately 354° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°57.495' N, Long. 75°51.863' W; then running approximately 344° True to a point at the shore defined by Lat. 37°57.910' N, Long. 75°52.007' W; then running northerly along the shore to a point defined by Lat. 37°57.939' N, Long. 75°52.009' W; then running approximately 20° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°58.124' N, Long. 75°51.925' W; then running approximately 26° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°58.353' N, Long. 75°51.787’ W; then running approximately 0° True to a point at or near the shore on the south side of the entrance to Somers Cove defined by Lat. 37°58.501' N, Long. 75°51.789' W; then running southerly to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(t)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Cow Point Creek, Fishing Creek, Pond Creek, Muddy Creek, Cedar Straits, Cedar Island Creek, Green Straits, Crooked Creek, Crooked Creek Gut, the Prong Broad Creek, Daugherty Creek, Little Annemessex River, Pocomoke Sound, and Tangier Sound enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the western shore of Daugherty Creek/Broad Creek on Cedar Island defined by Lat. 37°56.567' N, Long. 75°51.539'W; then running approximately 172° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°56.302' N, Long. 75°51.492' W; then running approximately 174° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°56.076' N, Long. 75°51.470' W; then running approximately 141° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°55.805' N, Long. 75°51.195' W; then running approximately 182° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°55.683' N, Long. 75°51.204' W; then running approximately 192° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°55.390’ N, Long. 75°51.282' W; then running approximately 220° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°55.160' N, Long. 75°51.517' W; then running approximately 239° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°54.993’ N, Long. 75°51.866’ W; then running approximately 271° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°54.995’ N, Long. 75°52.386’ W; then running approximately 190° True to a point at or near the Maryland-Virginia state line defined by Lat. 37°54.689’ N, Long. 75°52.458’ W; then running approximately 269° True to a point at or near the Maryland-Virginia state line defined by Lat. 37°54.678’ N, Long. 75°52.982’ W; then running approximately 266° True to a point at or near the Maryland-Virginia state line defined by Lat. 37°54.620’ N, Long. 75°53.834’ W; then running approximately 22° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°55.005’ N, Long. 75°53.646’ W; then running approximately 346° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°55.378’ N, Long. 75°53.760’ W; then running 33° True to a point at the northern shore of Cedar Island Creek defined by Lat. 37°55.431’ N, Long. 75°53.710’ W; then running northerly along the western shore of Cedar Island to a point defined by Lat. 37°56.548’ N, Long. 75°53.454' W; then running approximately 2° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°56.707' N, Long. 75°53.444' W; then running approximately 77° True to a point at or near the south shore of Great Point Pond defined by Lat. 37°56.708' N, Long. 75°53.428' W; then running northerly along the shore to a point along the western shore of Muddy Creek defined by Lat. 37°57.208' N, Long. 75°53.348' W; then running approximately 37° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°57.447' N, Long. 75°53.125' W; then running approximately 116° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°57.270' N, Long. 75°52.665' W; then running approximately 161° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°57.115' N, Long. 75°52.599' W; then running approximately 96° True to a point at or near the western shore of the entrance to Daugherty Creek/Broad Creek defined by Lat. 37°57.068' N, Long. 75°51.985' W; then running southeasterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(u)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Fishing Ditch, Broad Creek and Pocomoke Sound enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the western shore of Eastward Pont defined by Lat. 37°55.458' N, Long. 75°50.940' W; then running approximately 345° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°55.916' N, Long. 75°51.095' W; then running approximately 303° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°56.050' N, Long. 75°51.357' W; then running approximately 324° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°56.126' N, Long. 75°51.429' W; then running approximately 356° True to a point along the eastern shore of Daugherty Creek/Broad Creek defined by Lat. 37°56.426' N, Long. 75°51.456' W; then running easterly along the shore to a point at or near the western shore of Straight Gut defined by Lat. 37°56.343' N, Long. 75°50.970' W; the running approximately 133° True to a point along the eastern shore of Straight Gut defined by Lat. 37°56.325' N, Long. 75°50.946' W; then running southerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(v)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Broad Creek Gut, Cow Gap Creek, Massey Creek, Little Ware Point Creek and Pocomoke Sound enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the eastern shore of Eastward point defined by Lat. 37°55.455' N, Long. 75°50.917' W; then running approximately 69° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°55.579' N, Long. 75°50.513' W; then running approximately 61° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°55.820' N, Long. 75°49.968' W; then running approximately 19° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°56.201' N, Long. 75°49.803' W; then running approximately 72° True to a point along the eastern shore of Little Ware Point Creek at or near Ware Point defined by Lat. 37°56.344' N, Long. 75°49.247' W then running southwesterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(w)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Ware Point Creek enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore at the west side of the entrance of Ware Point Creek defined by Lat. 37°56.367' N, Long. 75°49.240' W; then running approximately 48° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°56.445' N, Long. 75°49.131' W; then running approximately 14° True to a point at or near the shore at the east side of the entrance to Ware Point Creek defined by Lat. 37°56.472' N, Long. 75°49.123' W; then running westerly along shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(x)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Ape Hole Creek and Pocomoke Sound enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the north shore of Big Island defined by Lat. 37°56.554' N, Long. 75°49.120' W; then running approximately 356° True to a point at or near Long Point defined by Lat. 37°56.774' N, Long. 75°49.137' W then running southerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(y)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Ape Hole Creek enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 37°57.075' N, Long. 75°49.573' W; then running approximately 352° True to a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 37°57.245' N, Long. 75°49.604' W then running southerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(z)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Ape Hole Creek enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 37°57.874' N, Long. 75°49.228' W; then running approximately 39° True to a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 37°58.027' N, Long. 75°49.070' W then running southwesterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(aa)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Gunby Creek and Pocomoke Sound enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the western shore of the island at the mouth of Gunby Creek defined by Lat. 37°58.426' N, Long. 75°46.587' W; then running approximately 307° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°58.431' N, Long. 75°46.596' W; then running approximately 354° True to a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 37°58.522' N, Long. 75°46.609' W; then running easterly along the shore to a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 37°58.509' N, Long. 75°46.539' W; then running approximately 198° True to a point at or near the shore of the island at the mouth of Gunby Creek defined by Lat. 37°58.428' N, Long. 75°46.574' W; then running westerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(bb)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Sheepshead Harbor, Goose Creek, Sedgy Point Cove, Pry Cove, Johnson Cove, Little Pungers Creek, Gunbarrel Cove, Old Ground Gut, Sound Gut, Pungers Creek, Pungers Cove, Muscle Hole Creek, Kedges Straits, Holland Straits and Tangier Sound enclosed by, a line beginning at a point at or near the eastern shore of Sheepshead Harbor defined by Lat. 38°04.384’ N, Long. 76°00.900’ W; then running approximately 292° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°04.683’ N, Long. 76° 01.819’ W; then running westerly along the southern shore of Jones Island to a point at or near Sedgy Point defined by Lat. 38°05.490’ N, Long. 76°03.330’ W; then running approximately 24° True to a point at or near the shore on the south shore of Pry Cove defined by Lat. 38°05.640’ N, Long. 76°03.243’ W; then running southeasterly along the shore to a point a defined by Lat. 38°05.461’ N, Long. 76°02.755’ W; then approximately 25° True to a point along the north shore of Pry Cove defined by Lat. 38°06.109' N, Long. 76°02.384' W; then running northerly along the shore past Johnson Point to a point along the southern shore of Johnson Cove defined by Lat. 38°06.538' N, Long. 76° 02.682' W; then running approximately 350° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°06.659' N, Long. 76°02.711' W; then running approximately 15° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°07.019' N, Long. 76°02.583' W; then running approximately 78° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°07.030' N, Long. 76°02.515' W; then running approximately 41° True to a point at or near the southern shore of Gunbarrel Cove defined by Lat. 38°07.425' N, Long. 76°02.087' W; then running approximately 37° True to a point at or near Gunbarrel Point defined by Lat. 38°07.516' N, Long. 76°01.995’ W; then running approximately 58° True to a point at or near the shore along the north shore of Gunbarrel Cove defined by Lat. 38°07.905' N, Long. 76°01.229' W; then running along the north shore of South Marsh Island to a point defined by Lat. 38°07.251' N, Long. 76°00.822' W; then running approximately 169° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°07.104' N, Long. 76°00.548' W; then running approximately 190° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°06.105' N, Long. 76°00.526' W; then running approximately 227° True to a point at or near the shore on the south side of Pungers Cove defined by Lat. 38°06.227' N, Long. 76°01.045' W; then running southerly along the shore to a point on the western shore at the entrance to Thomas Island Gut defined by Lat. 38°05.957' N, Long. 76°00.860' W; then running approximately 137° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°05.892' N, Long. 76°00.784' W; then running southerly along the shore to a point at or near the eastern shore of Muscle Hole Creek near Muscle Hole Point defined by Lat. 38°04.679' N, Long. 76°00.409' W; then running approximately 178° True to a point defined by Lat. 38° 04.661' N, Long. 76° 00.401' W; then running approximately 233° True to a point at or near the western shore of Muscle Hole Creek defined by Lat. 38°04.523' N, Long. 76°00.636' W; then running easterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(cc)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Big Thorofare, Shanks Creek, Tyler Creek, Parks Ditch, Sheep Pen Gut, Rhodes Point Gut, Long Branch, Little Thorofare, Jones Creek, Long Creek, Indian Creek, Tyler Ditch, Levering Creek, The Canal, Goose Harbor Cove, North End Bottom, Barnes Cove, Joes Ridge Creek, Twitch Cove, Otter Creek, Terrapin Sand Cove, Back Cove, Sawney Cove, Channel Point Gut, Lightning Knot Cove, Rock Creek, Juggling Creek, Joes Ridge Creek, Fishing Creek, Bridges Creek, Fog Point Cove, Kedges Straits, Tangier Sound and Chesapeake Bay enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the Maryland-Virginia line defined by Lat. 37°57.205' N, Long. 75°59.754' W; then running approximately 270° True to a point at or near the eastern shore of Tyler Creek defined by Lat. 37°57.208' N, Long. 76°00.300' W; then running along the Maryland-Virginia state line approximately 270° True to a point along the western shore of Tyler Creek defined by Lat. 37°57.209' N, Long. 76°01.068' W; then running along the Maryland-Virginia state line approximately 270° True to a point at or near the eastern shore of Shanks Creek defined by Lat. 37°57.211' N, Long. 76°01.753' W; then running along the Maryland-Virginia state line approximately 270° True to a point at or near the western shore of Shanks Creek defined by Lat. 37°57.211' N, Long. 76°02.289' W; then running along the Maryland-Virginia state line approximately 270° True to a point along the western shore of Smith Island defined by Lat. 37°57.212' N, Long. 76°02.638' W; then running northerly along the shore to a point defined by Lat. 37°57.457' N, Long. 76°02.747' W; then running approximately 336° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°58.056' N, Long. 76°03.089 W; then running approximately 0° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°59.866' N, Long. 76°03.107' W; then running approximately 290° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°59.926' N, Long. 76°03.287 W; then running approximately 1° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°00.075' N, Long. 76°03.281' W; then running approximately 73° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°00.117' N, Long. 76°03.108’ W; then running approximately 13° True to a point on the eastern shore of Smith Island defined by Lat. 38°01.190' N, Long. 76°02.812' W; then running approximately 14° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°02.074' N, Long. 76°02.526' W; then running approximately 62° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°02.454' N, Long. 76°01.653' W; then running approximately 89° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°02.443' N, Long. 76°00.765' W; then running approximately 107° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°02.202' N, Long. 75°59.740' W; then running approximately 143° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°01.433' N, Long. 75°58.998' W; then running approximately 161° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°59.332' N, Long. 75°58.075' W; then running approximately 187° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°58.598' N, Long. 75°58.187' W; then running approximately 212° True to a point at the Maryland-Virginia state line defined by Lat. 37°57.166' N, Long. 75°59.358' W; then running approximately 279° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°57.203' N, Long. 75°59.613' W; then running approximately 278° True to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Dorchester County.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Chapel Creek, Todd’s Bay and Choptank River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 38°36.668' N, Long. 76°13.390' W; then running approximately 75° True to a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 38°37.002' N, Long. 76°11.753' W; then running westerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Chapel Creek, Todd’s Bay and Choptank River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 38°36.668' N, Long. 76°13.390' W; then running approximately 335° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°37.109' N, Long. 76°13.655' W; then running approximately 324° True to a point along the shore defined by Lat. 38°37.558' N, Long. 76°14.074' W; then running southerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Cook's Point Cove and Choptank River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore of Cook's Point defined by Lat. 38°37.253' N,76°16.573' W; then running approximately 110° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°37.067' N, Long. 76°15.903' W; then running approximately 60° True to a point on the shore defined by Lat. 38°37.391' N, Long. 76°15.199' W; then running westerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Trippe Bay, Brannock Bay, and Covey Creek enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near Mills Point defined by Lat. 38°34.948’ N, Long. 76°17.316’ W; then running approximately 27° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°36.211’ N, Long. 76°16.492’ W; then running approximately 89° True to a point along the shore defined by Lat. 38°36.215’ N, Long. 76°16.441’ W; then running southerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Hooper Strait and Tangier Sound enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the northeastern shore of Bloodsworth Island west of Piney Island Point defined by Lat. 38°11.627’ N, Long. 76°2.335’ W; then running approximately 48° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°11.709’ N, Long. 76°2.218’ W; then running approximately 351° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°12.007’ N, Long. 76°2.281’ W; then running approximately 286° True to a point along the shore east of Fin Creek defined by Lat. 38°12.150’ N, Long. 76°2.900’ W; then running southeasterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Piney Island Cove and Tangier Sound enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the southern shore at the entrance of Piney Island Cove defined by Lat. 38°11.012’ N, Long. 76°1.807’ W; then running approximately 329° True to a point at or near the northern shore at the entrance to Piney Island Cove defined by Lat. 38°11.553’ N, Long. 76°2.212’ W; then running southerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Great Cove and Tangier Sound enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the southern shore at the entrance of Great Cove defined by Lat. 38°9.473’ N, Long. 76°1.979’ W; then running approximately 49° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°9.880’ N, Long. 76°1.392’ W; then running approximately 1° to a point at or near Great Cove Point at the northern shore of Great Cove defined by Lat. 38°10.390’ N, Long. 76°1.382’ W; then running southwesterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Northeast Cove, Holland Straits and Tangier Sound enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near Cove Point along the southern shore of Bloodsworth Island defined by Lat. 38°8.864’ N, Long. 76°3.090’ W; then running approximately 152° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°8.847’ N, Long. 76°3.080’ W; then running approximately 99° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°8.823’ N, Long. 76°2.903’ W; then running approximately 90° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°8.823’ N, Long. 76°2.232’ W; then running approximately 74° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°8.854’ N, Long. 76°2.102’ W; then running approximately 46° True to a point along the shore at or near Lower Island Point defined by Lat. 38°8.901’ N, Long. 76°2.042’ W; then running westerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Northeast Cove, Muddy Creek, Swan Pond, Swan Pond Creek, Long Creek, Okahanikan Cove, Pone Cove, Holland Straits, Hooper Strait, and Chesapeake Bay enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near Cove Point along the southern shore of Bloodsworth Island defined by Lat. 38°8.864’ N, Long. 76°3.090’ W; then running approximately 277° True to a point at the southern shore of Northeast Island defined by Lat. 38°8.968’ N, Long. 76°4.237’ W; then running approximately 199° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°7.827’ N, Long. 76°4.742’ W; then running approximately 322° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°7.967’ N, Long. 76°4.875’ W; then running approximately 291° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°8.143’ N, Long. 76°5.472’ W; then running approximately 0° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°8.930’ N, Long. 76°5.476’ W; then running approximately 1° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°10.307’ N, Long. 76°5.455’ W; then running approximately 2° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°11.618’ N, Long. 76°5.397’ W; then running approximately 93° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°11.537’ N, Long. 76°3.527’ W; then running approximately 136° True to a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 38°11.506’ N, Long. 76°3.489’ W; then running southerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Talbot County.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Shaw Bay enclosed by a line beginning at a point on the shore southeast of Bruffs Island defined by Lat. 38°51.047' N, Long. 76°11.163' W; then running approximately 50° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°51.429' N, Long. 76°10.586' W; then running approximately 13° True to a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 38°51.607' N, Long. 76°10.536' W; then running southwesterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Miles River between Woodland Creek and Leeds Creek enclosed by a line beginning at a point defined by Lat. 38°48.992’ N, Long. 76°11.820’ W; then running approximately 282° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°48.998’ N, Long. 76°11.851’ W; then running approximately 12° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°49.914’ N, Long. 76°11.600’ W; then running approximately 46° True to a point at or near the southern shore of the mouth of Woodland Creek defined by Lat. 38°50.065’ N, Long. 76°11.399’ W; then running southerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Leeds Creek enclosed by a line beginning at a point on the northern shore of Leeds Creek defined by Lat. 38°48.558’ N, Long. 76°11.232’ W; then running approximately 188° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°48.525’ N, Long. 76°11.238’ W; then running approximately 304° True to a point near the northern shore of Leeds Creek defined by Lat. 38°48.577’ N, Long. 76°11.338’ W; then running easterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Leeds Creek and Blakes Cove enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the southern shore of Leeds Creek defined by Lat. 38°48.269' N, Long. 76°11.182' W; then running approximately 355° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°48.292' N, Long. 76°11.185' W; then running approximately 35° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°48.384' N, Long. 76°11.103' W; then running approximately 103° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°48.371' N, Long. 76°11.029' W; then running approximately 170° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°48.328' N, Long. 76°11.020' W; then running approximately 235° True to a point at or near the southern shore of Blakes Cove defined by Lat. 38°48.320' N, Long. 76°11.035' W; then running westerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Darmands Creek and Miles River enclosed by a line beginning at a point north of the entrance to Hunting Creek defined by Lat. 38°47.022’ N, Long. 76°10.781’ W; then running approximately 276° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°47.062’ N, Long. 76°11.240’ W; then running approximately 355° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°47.492’ N, Long. 76°11.285’ W; then running approximately 53° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°47.527’ N, Long. 76°11.223’ W; then running approximately 141° True to a point at or near the shoreline defined by Lat. 38°47.520’ N, Long. 76°11.215’ W; then running southeasterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Hunting Creek and Miles River enclosed by a line beginning at a point on the eastern shore of Hunting Creek defined by Lat. 38°46.814' N, Long. 76°10.183' W; then running approximately 308° True to a point at or near the shoreline defined by Lat. 38°47.020' N, Long. 76°10.524' W; then running southeasterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Hunting Creek and Miles River enclosed by a line beginning at a point on the northern shore of Miles River defined by then Lat. 38°46.516' N, Long. 76°09.541' W; running approximately 165° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°46.501' N, Long. 76°09.536' W; then running approximately 251° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°46.483' N, Long. 76°09.605' W; then running approximately 256° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°46.433' N, Long. 76°09.865' W; then running approximately 288° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°46.524' N, Long. 76°10.213' W; then running approximately 319° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°46.559' N, Long. 76°10.252' W; then running approximately 37° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°46.749' N, Long. 76°10.067' W; then running approximately 53° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°46.807' N, Long. 76°09.969' W; then running approximately 78° True to a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 38°46.819' N, Long. 76°09.898' W; then running southerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Hunting Creek and Miles River enclosed by a line that surrounds Long Point Island beginning at a point defined by Lat. 38°46.214' N, Long. 76°10.362' W; then running approximately 314° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°46.576' N, Long. 76°10.843' W; then running approximately 15° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°46.815' N, Long. 76°10.764' W; then running approximately 66° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°46.883' N, Long. 76°10.567' W; then running approximately 141° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°46.785' N, Long. 76°10.472' W; then running approximately 151° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°46.659' N, Long. 76°10.389' W; then running approximately 163° True to a point at or near the shore northeast of Long Point defined by Lat. 38°46.373' N, Long. 76°10.279' W; then running southerly to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Oak Creek, Newcomb Creek, and Miles River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the eastern shore of Oak Creek defined by Lat. 38°45.210' N, Long. 76°10.356' W; then running approximately 5° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°45.249' N, Long. 76°10.355' W; then running approximately 30° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°46.013' N, Long. 76°09.788' W; then running approximately 68° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°46.116' N, Long. 76°09.463' W; then running approximately 21° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°46.346' N, Long. 76°09.352' W; then running approximately 58° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°46.371' N, Long. 76°09.304' W; then running approximately 151° True to a point at or near the western shore of Peach Orchard Point defined by Lat. 38°46.343' N, Long. 76°09.286' W; then running southerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Oak Creek enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the eastern shore of Oak Creek defined by Lat. 38°45.097’ N, Long. 76°10.441’ W; then running approximately 1° True to a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 38°45.198’ N, Long. 76°10.440’ W; then running northeasterly along the shore at or near the western shore of Oak Creek defined by Lat. 38°45.208’ N, Long. 76°10.428’ W; then running 98° True to a point at or near the eastern shore of Oak Creek defined by Lat. 38°45.199’ N, Long. 76°10.355’ W; then running southerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Miles River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 38°46.045' N, Long. 76°11.223' W; then running approximately 310° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°46.157' N, Long. 76°11.392' W; then running approximately 262° True to a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 38°46.140' N, Long. 76°11.548' W; then running easterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Spencer Creek enclosed by a line beginning at or near a point on the shore of Maiden Point defined by Lat. 38°46.379' N, Long. 76°12.070' W; then running approximately 342° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°46.451' N, Long. 76°12.100' W; then running approximately 349° True to a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 38°46.509' N, Long. 76°12.115' W; then running approximately 21° True to a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 38°46.535' N, Long. 76°12.102' W; then running southeasterly along the shore to a point defined by Lat. 38°46.503' N, Long. 76°12.065' W; then running approximately 68° True to a point at or near the shore of Maiden Point defined by Lat. 38°46.536' N, Long. 76°11.961' W; then running southerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Spencer Creek enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the eastern shore defined by Lat. 38°46.124' N, Long. 76°12.030' W; then running approximately 311° True to a point at or near the western shore defined by Lat. 38°46.188' N, Long. 76°12.122' W; then running southeasterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(n)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Miles River and Porter Creek enclosed by a line beginning at a point on the western shore of Hambleton Point defined by Lat. 38°49.195’ N, Long. 76°14.312’ W; then running approximately 310° True to a point at or near the shore of Emerson Point defined by Lat. 38°49.657’ N, Long. 76°15.016’ W; then running then running southeasterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(o)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Miles River and Tilghman Creek enclosed by a line beginning at a point defined by Lat. 38°49.673’ N, Long. 76°15.341’ W; then running approximately 314° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°49.769’ N, Long. 76°15.469’ W; then running approximately 24° True to a point to a point at or near the western shore of Emerson Point defined by Lat. 38°49.988’ N, Long. 76°15.347’ W; then running southeasterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(p)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Tilghman Creek and Eastern Bay enclosed by a line beginning at a point on the eastern shore of Rich Neck defined by Lat. 38°50.643' N, Long. 76°15.951' W; then running approximately 72° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°50.686' N, Long. 76°15.801' W; then running approximately 337° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°50.894' N, Long. 76°15.913' W; then running approximately 8° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°51.080' N, Long. 76°15.880' W; then running approximately 109° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°51.039' N, Long. 76°15.731' W; then running approximately 52° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°51.197' N, Long. 76°15.476' W; then running approximately 34° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°51.370' N, Long. 76°15.327' W; then running approximately 87° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°51.374' N, Long. 76°15.193' W; then running approximately 35° True to a point at or near the shore on the eastern shore of Tilghman Point defined by Lat. 38°51.392' N, Long. 76°15.181' W; then running southwesterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(q)</num>
          <text>All of the water of Eastern Bay enclosed by a line beginning at a point at Wades Point defined by Lat. 38°49.668' N, Long. 76°17.730' W; then running approximately 66° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°49.876' N, Long. 76°17.131' W; then running approximately 23° True to a point at or near the midpoint of the Claiborne Jetty defined by Lat. 38°50.247' N, Long. 76°16.932' W; then running approximately 62° True to a point at or near the shore at the end of the Claiborne Jetty defined by Lat. 38°50.289' N, Long. 76°16.831' W; then running southwesterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(r)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Harbor Cove, Poplar Island Narrows and Eastern Bay enclosed by a line beginning at or near a point on the shore of Lowes Point defined by Lat. 38°46.565’ N, Long. 76°19.813’ W; then running approximately 11° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°46.621’ N, Long. 76°19.803’ W; then running approximately 28° True to a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 38°48.514’ N, Long. 76°18.537’ W; then running southerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(s)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Ferry Cove, Cabin Cove, Poplar Island Narrows and Eastern Bay enclosed by a line beginning at or near a point on the shore of Punch Point defined by Lat. 38°45.653’ N, Long. 76°20.182’ W; then running approximately 12° True to a point at or near the shore of the southern tip of Lowes Point defined by Lat. 38°46.324’ N, Long. 76°19.997’ W; then running southerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(t)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Back Creek enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore near Tilghman Back Creek Park defined by Lat. 38°43.324' N, Long. 76°20.052' W; then running approximately 273° True to a point at or near the eastern shore of Anne Arundel Island defined by Lat. 38°43.328' N, Long. 76°20.138' W; then running northwest along the shore of Anne Arundel Island to a point defined by Lat. 38°43.447' N, Long. 76°20.314' W; then running approximately 17° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°43.622' N, Long. 76°20.245' W; then running approximately 42° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°43.725' N, Long. 76°20.128' W; then running approximately 101° True to a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 38°43.723' N, Long. 76°20.113' W; then running southerly along the shore of Back Creek to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(u)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Blackwalnut Cove enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the west shore of Blackwalnut Cove defined by Lat. 38°40.376' N, Long. 76°20.327' W; then running approximately 38° True to a point at or near the east shore of Blackwalnut Cove defined by Lat. 38°40.790' N, Long. 76°19.913' W; then running northwesterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(v)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of the Harris Creek and Choptank River enclosed by a line beginning at a point near Lower Bar Neck Point defined by Lat. 38°41.007’ N, Long. 76°19.384’ W; then running approximately 347° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°41.060’ N, Long. 76°19.400’ W; then running approximately 18° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°41.118’ N, Long. 76°19.375’ W; then running approximately 162° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°41.065’ N, Long. 76°19.354’ W; then running approximately 202° True to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(w)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Dogwood Harbor, Harris Creek and Choptank River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the Upper Bar Neck Point defined by Lat. 38°41.446’ N, Long. 76°19.413’ W; then running approximately 330° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°41.955’ N, Long. 76°19.793’ W; then running approximately 322° True to a point at or near the shore of Tilghman Island defined by Lat. 38°42.091’ N, Long. 76°19.929’ W; then running southeasterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(x)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of River Cove, Harris Creek, Muddy Cove and Choptank River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the tip of Nelson Point defined by Lat. 38°42.551' N, Long. 76°16.288' W; then running approximately 298° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°42.889' N, Long. 76°17.109' W; then running approximately 267° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°42.850' N, Long. 76°18.170' W; then running approximately 14° True to a point at or near the shore of Turkey Neck Point defined by Lat. 38°43.607' N, Long. 76°17.938' W; then running easterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Saint Mary's County.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Potomac River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the western shore at the entrance to Flood Creek defined by Lat. 38°13.559' N, Long. 76°37.999' W; then running approximately 185° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°13.479' N, Long. 76°38.008' W; then running approximately 265° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°13.440' N, Long. 76°38.591' W; then running approximately 261° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°13.483' N, Long. 76°38.987' W; then running approximately 292° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°13.571' N, Long. 76°39.272' W; then running approximately 300° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°13.687' N, Long. 76°39.517' W; then running approximately 314° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°13.840' N, Long. 76°39.720' W; then running approximately 288° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°14.021' N, Long. 76°40.426' W; then running approximately 347° True to a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 38°14.071' N, Long. 76°40.442' W; then running southeasterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Saint Mary’s River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore at Windmill Point defined by Lat. 38°09.488’ N, Long. 76°27.142’ W; then running approximately 94° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°09.470’ N, Long. 76°26.822’ W; then running approximately 32° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°09.520’ N, Long. 76°26.784’ W; then running approximately 334° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°09.589’ N, Long. 76°26.827’ W; then running approximately 308° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°09.634’ N, Long. 76°26.899’ W; then running approximately 240° True to a point at or near the shore north of Windmill Point defined by Lat. 38°09.581’ N, Long. 76°27.018’ W; then running southerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of St Inigoe's Creek enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore northeast of Priests Point defined by Lat. 38°09.301' N, Long. 76°26.030' W; then running approximately 28° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°09.354' N, Long. 76°25.993' W; then running approximately 72° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°09.378' N, Long. 76°25.904' W; then running approximately 41° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°09.479' N, Long. 76°25.791' W; then running approximately 57° True to a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 38°09.519' N, Long. 76°25.712' W; then running approximately 84° True to a point at or near the western shore of Molls Cove defined by Lat. 38°09.521' N, Long. 76°25.690' W; then running southeasterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Saint Mary's River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the eastern shore of Cherryfield Point defined by Lat. 38°07.730' N, Long. 76°27.858' W; then running approximately 141° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°07.641' N, Long. 76°27.764' W; then running approximately 40° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°07.910' N, Long. 76°27.470' W; then running approximately 342° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°08.151' N, Long. 76°27.571' W; then running approximately 335° True to a point at or near the shore north of Cherryfield Point defined by Lat. 38°08.347' N, Long. 76°27.682' W; then running southerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of St. George’s Creek enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore on Ball Point defined by Lat. 38°07.251' N, Long. 76°28.380' W; then running approximately 305° True to a point at or near shore south of Dodson Point defined by Lat. 38°07.979' N, Long. 76°29.714' W; then running southeasterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Saint Mary's River and Saint George's Creek enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore at the mouth of Island Creek defined by Lat. 38°06.513' N, Long. 76°28.012' W; then running approximately 357° True to a point at or near the shore at Indigo Point defined by Lat. 38°06.551' N, Long. 76°28.015' W; then running northerly along the shore to a point near Russell Point defined by Lat. 38°07.148' N, Long. 76°28.194' W; then running approximately 41° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°07.154' N, Long. 76°28.189' W; then running approximately 117° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°07.075' N, Long. 76°27.996' W; then running approximately 179° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°06.912' N, Long. 76°27.992' W; then running approximately 146° True to a point at or near the tip of the jetty defined by Lat. 38°06.632' N, Long. 76°27.754' W; then running along the jetty to a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 38°06.498' N, Long. 76°27.941' W; then running westerly along to shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Saint Mary's River enclosed by a line beginning at a point defined by Lat. 38°06.553' N, Long. 76°25.503' W; then running approximately 310° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°06.721' N, Long. 76°25.748' W; then running approximately 342° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°07.029' N, Long. 76°25.870' W; then approximately 137° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°06.794' N, Long. 76°25.590' W; then running approximately 163° True to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Calvert Bay enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 38°06.002' N, Long. 76°23.406' W; then running approximately 292° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°06.035' N, Long. 76°23.510' W; then running approximately 6° True to a point at or near the shore south of the entrance to Calvert Creek defined by Lat. 38°06.135' N, Long. 76°23.496' W; then running southeasterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Worcester County.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Sinepuxent Bay enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore south of Ocean City Municipal Airport defined by Lat. 38°18.198' N, Long. 75° 07.016' W; then running approximately 28° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°18.346' N, Long. 75°06.915' W; then running southerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Snug Harbor and Sinepuxent Bay enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore south of Snug Harbor defined by Lat. 38°17.918' N, Long. 75° 07.415' W; then running approximately 67° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°18.007' N, Long. 75°07.148' W; then running approximately 9° True to a point at or near the shore south of Coffins Point defined by Lat. 38° 18.077' N, Long. 75° 07.134' W; then running southwesterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Sinepuxent Bay enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the western shore of Assateague Island National Seashore defined by Lat. 38°17.806' N, Long. 75° 06.904' W; then running approximately 355° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°17.820' N, Long. 75°06.906' W; then running approximately 18° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°18.173' N, Long. 75°06.757' W; then running approximately 26° True to a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 38°18.244' N, Long. 75°06.713' W; then running southerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Grays Cove and Sinepuxent Bay enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near Grays Cove Landing defined by Lat. 38°17.162' N, Long. 75° 08.226' W; then running approximately 175° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°16.852' N, Long. 75°08.191' W; then running approximately 121° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°16.832' N, Long. 75° 08.147' W; then running approximately 19° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°17.289' N, Long. 75°07.947' W; then running approximately 277° True to a point at or near the shore on the north side of Grays Cove defined by Lat. 38° 17.301' N, Long. 75° 08.053' W; then running southwesterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Sinepuxent Bay enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the west shore of Assateague Island National Seashore defined by Lat. 38°16.374' N, Long. 75°07.408' W; then running approximately 276° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°16.419' N, Long. 75°07.904' W; then running approximately 2° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°16.807' N, Long. 75°07.881' W; then running approximately 14° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°17.252' N, Long. 75°07.747' W; then running approximately 32° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°17.695' N, Long. 75°07.394' W; then running approximately 102° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°17.685' N, Long. 75°07.281' W; then running approximately 71° True to a point at or near the west shore of Assateague Island defined by Lat. 38°17.782' N, Long. 75°06.916' W; then running southerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Sinepuxent Bay enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore at Sandy Cove defined by Lat. 38°15.864' N, Long. 75°08.875' W; then running approximately 66° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°16.024' N, Long. 75°08.420' W; then running approximately 4° True to a point at or near the shore south of Grays Point defined by Lat. 38°16.275' N, Long. 75°08.398' W; then running southwesterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Sinepuxent Bay enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore on the north side of the MD Route 611 causeway defined by Lat. 38°14.561' N, Long. 75°08.861' W; then running approximately 39° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°15.002' N, Long. 75°08.235' W; then running approximately 4° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°15.381' N, Long 75°08.202' W; then running approximately 65° True to a point at or near the west shore of Assateague Island defined by Lat. 38°15.535' N, Long. 75°07.795' W;; then running southerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Sinepuxent Bay enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near Green Point defined by Lat. 38°13.865' N, Long. 75°10.259' W; then running approximately 44° True to a point at or near the shore of Sandy Point on the south side of the MD Route 611 causeway defined Lat. 38°14.772' N, Long 75°09.138' W; then running westerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Newport Bay and Sinepuxent Bay enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near South Point defined by Lat. 38°12.532' N, Long. 75°11.511' W; then running approximately 197° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°12.444' N, Long. 75°11.549' W; then running approximately 258° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°12.407' N, Long. 75°11.764' W; then running approximately 326° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°12.776' N, Long. 75°12.070' W; then running approximately 356° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°13.220' N, Long. 75°12.106' W; then running approximately 23° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°13.507' N, Long. 75°11.955' W; then running approximately 135° True to a point at or near the western shore of Lower Sinepuxent Neck defined by Lat. 38°13.467’ N, Long. 75°11.901' W; then running southeasterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Purnell Pond, Martin Bay and Sinepuxent Bay enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore at Martin Point defined by Lat. 38°05.716' N, Long. 75°17.890' W; then running approximately 222° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°05.580' N, Long. 75°18.047' W; then running approximately 316° True to a point at or near the eastern shore at the entrance to Purnell Pond defined by Lat. 38°06.104' N, Long. 75°18.686' W; then running easterly along the shore to a point defined by Lat. 38°05.939' N, Long. 75°17.931' W; then running approximately 172° True to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Ready Cove, Easter Opening and Chincoteague Bay enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the southern shore south of Big Bay Point defined by Lat. 38°04.520' N, Long. 75° 17.598' W; then running approximately 255° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°04.325' N, Long. 75°18.525' W; then running approximately 339° True to a point at or near the western tip of an island along the southern side of Ready Cove defined by Lat. 38°04.620' N, Long. 75° 18.665' W; then running approximately 339° True to a point at or near the southwestern tip of an island along the northern side of Ready Cove defined by Lat. 38°04.984' N, Long. 75° 18.844' W; then running easterly along the shore to a point at or near the eastern tip of an island defined by Lat. 38°04.905' N, Long. 75° 18.436' W; then running approximately 100° True to a point at or near Big Bay Point defined by Lat. 38°04.766' N, Long. 75° 17.474' W; then running southerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Johnson Bay and Rowley Cove enclosed by a line beginning at a point along the southern shore of Tizzard Island defined by Lat. 38°04.307' N, Long. 75°19.703' W; then running approximately 192° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°04.296' N, Long. 75°19.706' W; then running approximately 267° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°04.289' N, Long. 75°19.883' W; then running approximately 289° to a point defined by Lat. 38°04.459' N, Long. 75°20.491' W; then running approximately 314° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°04.613' N, Long. 75°20.688' W; then running approximately 59° True to a point at or near the western shore of Tizzard Island defined by Lat. 38°04.726' N, Long. 75°20.448' W; then running southerly along the shore of Tizzard Island to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Chincoteague Bay enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore of a cove on the east side of Mills Island defined by Lat. 38°02.736' N, Long. 75°19.996' W; then running approximately 60° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°02.885' N, Long. 75°19.668' W; then running approximately 28° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°03.170' N, Long. 75°19.479' W; then running approximately 347° True to a point at or near the shore of a cove on the east side of Mills Island defined by Lat. 38°03.196' N, Long. 75°19.486' W; then running southwesterly along the shore of Mills Island to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(n)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Chincoteague Bay enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore of a cove on the east side of Mills Island defined by Lat. 38°02.197' N, Long. 75°21.135' W; then running approximately 137° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°02.114' N, Long. 75°21.031' W; then running approximately 75° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°02.192' N, Long. 75°20.684' W; then running approximately 23° True to a point at or near the shore of a cove on the east side of Mills Island defined by Lat. 38°02.500' N, Long. 75°20.525' W; then running southwesterly along the shore of Mills Island to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(o)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Chincoteague Bay and Sinepuxent Bay enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the west side of Assateague Island near the Maryland-Virginia state line defined by Lat. 38°01.591' N, Long. 75°15.159' W; then running along the Maryland-Virginia state line approximately 264° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°01.414' N, Long. 75°17.127' W; then running approximately 30° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°02.048' N, Long. 75°16.661' W; then running approximately 74° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°02.110' N, Long. 75°16.392' W; then running approximately 32° to a point defined by Lat. 38°02.786' N, Long. 75°15.871' W; then running approximately 352° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°04.191' N, Long. 75°16.126' W; then running approximately 23° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°05.748' N, Long. 75°15.359' W; then running approximately 45° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°07.958' N, Long. 75°12.710' W; then running approximately 0° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°11.172' N, Long. 75°12.676' W; then running approximately 45° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°11.849' N, Long. 75°11.829' W; then running approximately 59° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°12.659' N, Long. 75°10.139' W; then running approximately 358° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°13.478' N, Long. 75°10.170' W; then running approximately 41° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°13.779' N, Long. 75°09.844' W; then running approximately 36° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°14.353' N, Long. 75°09.309' W; then running approximately 49° True to a point at or near the shore of the south side of the MD Route 611 causeway defined by Lat. 38°14.664' N, Long. 75°08.862' W; then running southerly along the west shore of Assateague Island to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Anne Arundel County. All of the waters of Old Colony Cove and Herring Bay enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore of Old Colony Cove at the entrance to Herrington Harbour defined by Lat. 38°43.691' N, Long. 76°32.520' W; then running northwesterly along the shore of Old Colony Cove to a point defined by Lat. 38°44.035' N, Long. 76°33.099' W; then running approximately 121° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°43.750' N, Long. 76°32.494' W; then running southwesterly along the jetty to the point of beginning.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Calvert County.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Rock Creek, Nan Cove and Patuxent River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the eastern shore of the mouth of Rock Creek defined by Lat. 38°25.304' N, Long. 76°33.572' W; then running along the shore to a point on the western shore of Rock Creek defined by 38°25.307' N, Long. 76°33.680' W; then running approximately 121° True to a point defined by 38°25.235' N, Long. 76°33.525' W; then running approximately 99° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°25.209' N, Long. 76°33.310' W; then running approximately 59° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°25.254' N, Long. 76°33.215' W; then running approximately 34° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°25.334' N, Long. 76°33.147' W; then running approximately 308° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°25.354' N, Long. 76°33.178' W; then running approximately 182° True to a point at or near the western shore at the entrance of Nan Cove defined by Lat. 38°25.338' N, Long. 76°33.179' W; then running westerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Nan Cove, and Patuxent River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the western shore of Broomes Island defined by Lat. 38°25.162' N, Long. 76°33.080' W; then running approximately 295° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°25.173' N, Long. 76°33.110' W; then running approximately 345° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°25.199' N, Long. 76°33.118' W; then running approximately 358° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°25.309' N, Long. 76°33.124' W; the running approximately 9° True to a point at or near the eastern shore at the entrance of Nan Cove defined by Lat. 38°25.345' N, Long. 76°33.117' W; then running southerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>All the waters of Grapevine Cove and Patuxent River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the southern shore of Grapevine Cove defined by Lat. 38°24.698' N, Long. 76°33.152' W; then running approximately 27° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°24.718' N, Long. 76°33.140' W; then running approximately 143° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°24.658' N, Long. 76°33.083' W; then running approximately 23° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°24.797' N, Long. 76°33.007' W; then running approximately 353° True to a point at or near the northern shore at the entrance of Grapevine Cove defined by Lat. 38°25.010' N, Long. 76°33.043' W; then running southerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Island Creek and Patuxent River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the eastern shore of Broomes Island defined by Lat. 38°24.427' N, Long. 76°33.021' W; then running approximately 70° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°24.431' N, Long. 76°33.008' W; then running approximately 8° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°24.510' N, Long. 76°32.993' W; then running approximately 40° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°24.601' N, Long. 76°32.894' W; then running approximately 58° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°24.691' N, Long. 76°32.711' W; then running approximately 326° True to a point at or near the western shore at the entrance of Island Creek defined by Lat. 38°24.701' N, Long. 76°32.720' W; then running southwesterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Island Creek, Rattlesnake Gut and Patuxent River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 38°24.472' N, Long. 76°32.216' W; then running approximately 273° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°24.474' N, Long. 76°32.261' W; then running approximately 0° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°24.494' N, Long. 76°32.261' W; then running approximately 288° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°24.506' N, Long. 76°32.306' W; then running approximately 346° True to a point along the shore defined by Lat. 38°24.526' N, Long. 76°32.312' W; then running easterly along the shore to a point defined by Lat. 38°24.506' N, Long. 76°32.218' W; then running approximately 165° True to a point along the shore defined by Lat. 38°24.483' N, Long. 76°32.210' W; then running southwesterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>All the waters of Rattlesnake Gut and Patuxent River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 38°24.525' N, Long. 76°32.219' W; then running approximately 73° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°24.540' N, Long. 76°32.152' W; then running approximately 334° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°24.652' N, Long. 76°32.220' W; then running approximately 248° True to a point at or near the western shore of Rattlesnake Gut defined by Lat. 38°24.649' N, Long. 76°32.228' W; then running southerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>All the waters of Rattlesnake Gut and Patuxent River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 38°24.697' N, Long. 76°32.208' W; then running approximately 160° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°24.691' N, Long. 76°32.205' W; then running approximately 58° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°24.708' N, Long. 76°32.169' W; then running approximately 32° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°24.750' N, Long. 76°32.137' W; then running approximately 10° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°24.768' N, Long. 76°32.133' W; then running approximately 315° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°24.779' N, Long. 76°32.147' W; then running approximately 218° True to a point along the shore defined by Lat. 38°24.766' N, Long. 76°32.159' W; then running southwesterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>All the waters of Rattlesnake Gut and Patuxent River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 38°24.723' N, Long. 76°31.975' W; then running approximately 210° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°24.705' N, Long. 76°31.988' W; then running approximately 303° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°24.731' N, Long. 76°32.038' W; then running approximately 9° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°24.797' N, Long. 76°32.025' W; then running approximately 338° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°24.827' N, Long. 76°32.041' W; then running approximately 289° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°24.834' N, Long. 76°32.065' W; then running approximately 340° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°24.844' N, Long. 76°32.070' W; then running southeasterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>All the waters of Grammers Cove and Patuxent River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 38°24.507' N, Long. 76°31.265' W; then running approximately 283° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°24.512' N, Long. 76°31.291' W; then running approximately 338° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°24.624' N, Long. 76°31.349' W; then running approximately 317° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°24.745' N, Long. 76°31.495' W; then running approximately 272° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°24.750' N, Long. 76°31.746' W; then running approximately 348° True to a point along the shore defined by Lat. 38°24.765' N, Long. 76°31.751' W; then running southeasterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Patuxent River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the western shore of Hungerford Creek defined by Lat. 38°20.985' N, Long. 76°28.265' W; then running approximately 239° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°20.974' N, Long. 76°28.289' W; then running approximately 320° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°21.028' N, Long. 76°28.348' W; then running approximately 345° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°21.046' N, Long. 76°28.353' W; then running approximately 40° True to a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 38°21.070' N, Long. 76°28.328' W; then running southeasterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Patuxent River enclosed by a line beginning at a point east of Ship Point defined by Lat. 38°19.450' N, Long. 76°26.701' W; then running approximately 176° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°19.428' N, Long. 76°26.698' W; then running approximately 83° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°19.478' N, and Long. 76°26.205' W; then running approximately 1° True to a point at or near the southern shore of Drum Point defined by Lat. 38°19.512' N, Long. 76°26.204' W; then running westerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Kent County.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Rock Hall Harbor enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore at Lat. 39°07.840’N, Long. 76°14.697’W; then running approximately 280° True along the jetty to a point defined by Lat. 39°07.868’ N, Long. 76°14.856’ W; then running approximately 280° True to a point at or near the jetty defined by 39°07.876’ N, Long. 76°14.920’ W; then running northwesterly along the jetty to a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 39°07.964’ N, Long. 76°15.008’W; then running northeasterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Huntingfield Creek, Rock Hall Harbor and Chesapeake Bay enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore on the north side of Huntingfield Point defined by Lat. 39°07.122’ N, Long. 76°14.827’ W; then running approximately 3° True to a point at or near the jetty defined by Lat. 39°07.850’ N, Long. 76°14.760’ W; then running approximately 103° True along the jetty to a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 39°07.840’ N, Long. 76°14.697’ W; then running south along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>All the waters of Chesapeake Bay, Chester River and Wilson Pond enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore on the western side of Wilson Point defined by Lat. 39°03.192’ N, Long. 76°13.635’ W; then running approximately 259° True to a point defined by Lat. 39°03.083’ N, Long. 76°14.328’ W; then running approximately 19° True to a point defined by Lat. 39°03.544’ N, Long. 76°14.122’ W; then running approximately 6° True to a point defined by Lat. 39°04.119’ N; Long. 76°14.042’ W; then running approximately 7° True to a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 39°04.997’ N, Long. 76°13.891’ W; then running south along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>All the waters of Long Cove, Short Cove, Eastern Neck Narrows and Chester River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore on the eastern side of Wilson Point defined by Lat. 39°03.171’N, Long. 76°13.586’ W; then running approximately 85° True to a point defined by Lat. 39°03.174’ N, Long. 76°13.543’ W; then running approximately 25° True to a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 39°03.306’ N, Long 76°13.465’ W; then running approximately 75° True to a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 39°03.334’ N, Long. 76°13.330’ W; then running northwesterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Calfpasture Cove, Tubby Cove, Eastern Neck Narrows, and Chester River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore on the west side of Ingleside defined by 39°02.731’ N, Long. 76°14.198’ W; then running approximately 297° True to a point defined by Lat. 39°02.817’ N, Long. 76°14.414’ W; then running approximately 49° True to a point defined by Lat. 39°02.997’ N, Long 76°14.146’ W; then running approximately 125° True to a point defined by Lat. 39°02.898’ N, Long 76°13.965’ W; then running approximately 65° True to a point defined by Lat. 39°03.015’ N, Long. 76°13.644’ W; then running approximately 39° True to a point defined by Lat. 39°03.164’ N, Long. 76°13.487’ W; then running approximately 28° True to a point defined by Lat. 39°03.285’ N, Long. 76°13.406’ W; then running approximately 79° True to a point at or near the shore south of the Eastern Neck Narrows defined by Lat. 39°03.295’ N, Long. 76°13.340’ W; then running southwesterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Frying Pan Cove, Eastern Neck Narrows and Chester River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore on the north side of Eastern Neck Island defined by Lat. 39°02.909’ N, Long. 76°12.972’ W; then running approximately 11° True to a point defined by Lat. 39°03.201’ N, Long. 76°12.902’ W; then running approximately 293° True to a point defined by Lat. 39°03.312’ N, Long. 76°13.246’ W; then running approximately 264° True to a point at or near the shore along the Eastern Neck Island Road Bridge defined by Lat. 39°03.305’ N, Long. 76°13.330’ W; then running southeasterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Church Creek, Eastern Neck Narrows and Chester River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore northeast of the Eastern Neck Island Bridge defined by Lat. 39°03.363’ N, Long. 76°13.308’ W; then running approximately 103° True to a point defined by Lat. 39°03.271’ N, Long. 76°12.807’ W; then running approximately 17° True to a point defined by Lat. 39°03.371’ N, Long. 76°12.770’ W; then running approximately 293° True to a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 39°03.487’ N, Long. 76°13.124’ W; then running southwesterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Queen Anne's County.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Crab Alley Bay enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore northwest of Normans Point defined by Lat. 38°55.478' N, Long. 76°15.870' W; then running approximately 309° True to a point at or near the shore on the southeast side of Little Creek defined by Lat. 38°56.169' N, Long. 76°16.955' W; then running easterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Crab Alley Bay and Eastern Bay enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the western shore of Normans Point defined by Lat. 38°55.156' N, Long. 76°15.481' W; then running approximately 294° True to a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 38°55.211' N, Long. 76°15.641' W; then running easterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Hoghole Creek and Prospect Bay enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the western shore of Piney Neck defined by Lat. 38°54.620' N, Long. 76°12.301' W; then running approximately 345° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°55.957' N, Long. 76°12.766' W; then running approximately 20° True to a point at or near the south shore of Brian Point defined by Lat. 38°56.019' N, Long. 76°12.744' W; then running southeasterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Wye River enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the eastern shore of Wye Island east of Drum Point defined by Lat. 38°52.810' N, Long. 76°10.756' W; then running approximately 73° True to a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 38°52.857' N, Long. 76°10.565' W; then running southerly along the shore to the point defined by Lat. 38°52.822' N, Long. 76°10.565' W; then running approximately 137° True to a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 38°52.762' N, Long. 76°10.493' W; then running westerly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|02|01|.13">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Fishery Management Areas.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The fishery management areas of the State consist of the units in §§B and C of this regulation as delineated on maps filed in the Office of the Secretary of Natural Resources.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Fishery Management Propagation Areas.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The following areas are Fishery Management Propagation Areas:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Albert Powell Hatchery — Washington County;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Bear Creek Hatchery — Garrett County;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Lewistown Work Center — Frederick County;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Manning Hatchery — Charles County;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Piney Point Aquaculture Center — St. Mary’s County;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Unicorn Lake Hatchery — Queen Anne’s County;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Cushwa Hatchery — Washington County; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>North Branch of the Potomac River downstream of Jennings Randolph Reservoir and upstream of the overhead cable and red bank post located approximately 345 yards below the Jennings Randolph Reservoir spillway — Garrett County.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Public access to any Fishery Management Propagation Area is prohibited except with prior permission of the facility staff or as otherwise posted.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Fishery Management Public Fishing Areas.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The following areas are Fishery Management Public Fishing Areas:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Brownsville Pond — Washington County;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Brunswick Pond — Frederick County;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Bynum Run Pond — Harford County;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Evitts Creek Pond — Allegany County;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Forest Hill Lake — Harford County;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Frank Bentz Pond — Frederick County;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Hughesville Pond — Charles County;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>North Branch Potomac River — Folly and Laurel Runs — Garrett County;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>North Branch Potomac River — Gary A. Yoder Landing — Allegany County;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>North Branch Potomac River — McCoole — Allegany County;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Rising Sun Pond — Cecil County;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>Smithville Lake — Caroline County;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>Unicorn Lake — Queen Anne’s County;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(n)</num>
          <text>Urbana Lake — Frederick County;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(o)</num>
          <text>Urieville Lake — Kent County; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(p)</num>
          <text>Wye Mills Lake — Queen Anne’s County.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Public access to any Fishery Management Public Fishing Area is allowed from the hours of 5:30 a.m. to 10 p.m.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Camping.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>For the purpose of this regulation, “camping” means erecting tents or other shelters for the purpose of residing temporarily upon the property overnight.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A person may not camp on Fishery Management Public Fishing Areas except on designated sites or by written permit, or both.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Use of Vehicles.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>For the purpose of this regulation, “vehicle” means a vehicle or vessel propelled by mechanical power that is capable of travelling on land, snow, or ice.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A person may not operate any vehicle on a Fishery Management Public Fishing Area without written permission of the Fisheries Service except on those roads, lanes, or areas which are open to automobile traffic or which are specifically marked by the Fisheries Service.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Feeding Wildlife.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In this section, “wildlife” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|10-101">Natural Resources Article, §10-101(cc), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Except for lawful fishing and hunting activities, a person may not feed wildlife in a Fishery Management Public Fishing Area.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Hunting and Trapping.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Hunting and trapping are only allowed in the areas described in <cite path="08|02|01|.13|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> by written permission of the Fisheries Service.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Hunting is allowed in the following areas described in <cite path="08|02|01|.13|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>North Branch Potomac River — Laurel and Folly Run; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>North Branch Potomac River — McCoole.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Urbana Lake.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Hunting is allowed only with archery equipment.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Firearms are prohibited.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Trapping is only allowed in the areas described in <cite path="08|02|01|.13|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> by written permission of the Fisheries Service.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Projectile fishing gears, as described in <cite path="08.02.25.02">COMAR 08.02.25.02</cite> and .03, are prohibited in all Fishery Management Areas.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|02|01|.14">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Interpretation of Coordinates in Regulations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If the beginning or end point of a regulatory line is defined by coordinates and a physical description of a point or object on the shoreline, and the coordinates place the coordinated point in the water rather than on the shoreline, then the regulatory line shall be fixed to the location of the coordinates and be connected to the shoreline by the closest possible distance.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="08|02|01|.14|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>, if the beginning or ending point of a regulatory line is defined by coordinates and no statement is made in the regulation about the physical description of the coordinated point, and the coordinates place the coordinated point in the water rather than on the shoreline, then the point on the regulatory line shall be fixed to the location of the coordinates and be connected to the shoreline by the closest possible distance.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If a point in a series of points between the beginning and ending points of a regulatory line is defined by coordinates and a physical description or location of the coordinated point, and the coordinates do not agree with the physical description or location, then the point on the regulatory line shall be fixed at the location of the coordinates.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If a point in a series of points between the beginning and ending points of a regulatory line is defined by coordinates and no statement is made in the regulation about the physical description of the coordinated point, then the point on the regulatory line shall be fixed at the location of the coordinates.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If the beginning point of a regulatory line that forms a closed polygon is defined by coordinates and no statement is made in the regulation about the physical description of the coordinated point, then the beginning point on the regulatory line shall be fixed at the location of the coordinates.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If the beginning or end point of a regulatory line is defined by coordinates and no statement is made in the regulation about the physical description of the coordinated point, and the coordinates place the coordinated point on land, then the point on the regulatory line shall be fixed at the location of the coordinates and be connected to the shoreline along the line or lines of direction to any preceding or following points in the regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Scientific Collection Permits.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-212">Natural Resources Article, §4-212, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, a person shall obtain a scientific collection permit prior to collecting fish, fish eggs, shellfish, or aquatic invertebrates from the wild for scientific or educational purposes.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Application.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person shall apply for a scientific collection permit on a form provided by the Department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person shall apply at least 45 days prior to when the activity is requested to begin.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The fee for a scientific collection permit is $10 and shall be submitted with the application.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A permittee shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Comply with all of the terms and conditions described on the permit; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Report to the Department as specified by their permit.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Denial or Revocation of a Scientific Collection Permit.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In addition to any other penalty, failure to comply with the terms and conditions of the permit may result in the revocation of the current permit or the denial of a subsequent permit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Prior to denying an application for a permit or revoking a current permit, the Department shall give the permittee notice of its intended action and an opportunity to appear at a hearing conducted in accordance with the contested case procedures set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 10, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and <cite path="|08.01.04">COMAR 08.01.04</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|02|01|.16">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Importation of Finfish.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Release of Finfish.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In accordance with Natural Resources Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-205">4-205</cite>.1, 4-11A-20, and 4-11A-21, Annotated Code of Maryland, and <cite path="08.02.11.04">COMAR 08.02.11.04</cite> and <cite path="|08.02.14">08.02.14</cite>, a person shall obtain permission from the Department prior to releasing finfish into Maryland waters.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person who is permitted by the Department to release finfish may obtain finfish from an out-of-State supplier only if the supplier is permitted in accordance with this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Prior to providing finfish from out-of-State to anyone in Maryland who plans to release the finfish into Maryland waters, a person shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Submit an application in accordance with <cite path="08|02|01|.16|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Obtain an out-of-State supplier permit.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Application.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person shall apply for an out-of-State supplier permit by submitting a completed application on a form provided by the Department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person shall submit required fish health testing documentation for viral, bacterial, protozoan, or parasitic infections so that the Department may determine if the finfish to be stocked in Maryland waters pose an unacceptable risk to native or naturalized aquatic resources.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Out-of-State Supplier Permit.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A permittee shall comply with all of the terms and conditions described on the permit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The permit is valid during the calendar year of issuance.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>There is no fee for the permit.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Denial or Revocation of an Out-of-State Supplier Permit.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Department may deny issuance of an out-of-State supplier permit if the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Applicant submits an incomplete or untruthful application; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Department receives test results that indicate that the supplier’s stock may present an unacceptable health risk to native or naturalized aquatic resources.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In addition to any other penalty, failure to comply with the terms and conditions of the permit may result in the revocation of the current permit or the denial of a subsequent permit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Prior to denying an application for a permit or revoking a current permit, the Department shall give the permittee notice of its intended action and an opportunity to appear at a hearing conducted in accordance with the contested case procedures set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 10, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and <cite path="|08.01.04">COMAR 08.01.04</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Natural Resources Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-205">4-205</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-205">4-205</cite>.1, 4-206, 4-212, 4-214, 4-215, 4-215.2, 4-2A-03, 4-216, 4-306, 4-405, 4-407, 4-602, 4-604, 4-701, 4-701.1, 4-735, 4-745, 4-1006, 4-1006.1, 4-1009, 4-1011, 4-1012, 4-1103, 4-11A-02, 4-11A-04—4-11A-09, 4-11A-11, 4-11A-20, and 4-11A-21; <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-206">State Government Article, §10-206</cite>;  Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1991-04-29"><cite path="|08|02|01|.01">Regulation .01</cite> adopted effective April 29, 1991 (18:8 Md. R. 863)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-03-26"><cite path="|08|02|01|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective November 11, 1991 (18:22 Md. R. 2395); December 6, 1993 (20:24 Md. R. 1864); July 8, 2002 (29:13 Md. R. 990); March 26, 2018 (45:6 Md. R. 317)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-09-12"><cite path="|08|02|01|.01|A.">Regulation .01A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 13, 1994 (21:16 Md. R. 1378); adopted permanently effective September 12, 1994 (21:18 Md. R. 1508)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-08-05"><cite path="|08|02|01|.01|A.">Regulation .01A</cite> amended effective February 28, 1994 (21:4 Md. R. 274); July 3, 1995 (22:13 Md. R. 966); October 20, 1997 (24:21 Md. R. 1446); December 1, 1997 (24:24 Md. R. 1670); December 29, 1997 (24:26 Md. R. 1756); November 29, 1999 (26:24 Md. R. 1857); October 27, 2003 (30:21 Md. R. 1528); November 16, 2009 (36:23 Md. R. 1816); September 6, 2010 (37:18 Md. R. 1213); September 3, 2012 (39:17 Md. R. 1147); August 29, 2016 (43:17 Md. R. 952); August 26, 2019 (46:17 Md. R. 725); November 4, 2019 (46:22 Md. R. 976); August 8, 2022 (49:16 Md. R. 757); August 5, 2024 (51:15 Md. R. 706)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-03-29"><cite path="|08|02|01|.01|G.">Regulation .01G</cite> adopted effective March 29, 1993 (20:6 Md. R. 580)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1991-04-29"><cite path="|08|02|01|.02">Regulation .02</cite> adopted as <cite path="|08.02.07">COMAR 08.02.07</cite> effective July 23, 1975 (2:16 Md. R. 1138); amended effective August 15, 1983 (10:16 Md. R. 1450); recodified from <cite path="|08.02.07">COMAR 08.02.07</cite> to <cite path="08.02.01.02">08.02.01.02</cite> effective April 29, 1991 (18:8 Md. R. 863)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-04-04"><cite path="|08|02|01|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective April 4, 2011 (38:7 Md. R. 429)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1983-10-11"><cite path="|08|02|01|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective October 11, 1983 (10:22 Md. R. 1963); emergency status expired February 7, 1984</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-08-29"><cite path="|08|02|01|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective August 29, 2016 (43:17 Md. R. 952)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-08-29"><cite path="|08|02|01|.02|C.">Regulation .02C</cite> repealed effective August 29, 2016 (43:17 Md. R. 952)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1991-04-29"><cite path="|08|02|01|.03">Regulation .03</cite> adopted as <cite path="08.02.10.01">COMAR 08.02.10.01</cite> effective June 25, 1975 (2:14 Md. R. 1014); amended effective August 15, 1983 (10:16 Md. R. 1450); recodified from <cite path="08.02.10.01">COMAR 08.02.10.01</cite> to <cite path="08.02.01.03">COMAR 08.02.01.03</cite> effective April 29, 1991 (18:8 Md. R. 863)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-01-20"><cite path="|08|02|01|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective January 20, 1992 (19:1 Md. R. 23)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1991-05-27"><cite path="|08|02|01|.04">Regulation .04</cite> adopted as <cite path="08.02.07.04">COMAR 08.02.07.04</cite> and recodified to <cite path="08.02.01.04">08.02.01.04</cite> effective May 27, 1991 (18:10 Md. R. 1115)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-10-10"><cite path="|08|02|01|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective October 10, 2001 (28:22 Md. R. 1931); emergency status expired December 31, 2001</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-04-04"><cite path="|08|02|01|.04|B.">Regulation .04B</cite> amended effective April 4, 2011 (38:7 Md. R. 429)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-03-13"><cite path="|08|02|01|.04|C.">Regulation .04C</cite> amended effective April 13, 1992 (19:7 Md. R. 744); April 12, 1993 (20:7 Md. R. 640); March 14, 1994 (21:5 Md. R. 402); March 13, 1995 (22:5 Md. R. 366)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-03-20"><cite path="|08|02|01|.05">Regulation .05</cite> adopted effective March 20, 2000 (27:5 Md. R. 582)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-03-26"><cite path="|08|02|01|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective June 23, 2003 (30:12 Md. R. 787); April 9, 2007 (34:7 Md. R. 697); April 2, 2012 (39:6 Md. R. 407); February 16, 2015 (42:3 Md. R. 314); March 26, 2018 (45:6 Md. R. 317)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-03-14"><cite path="|08|02|01|.05|A.">Regulation .05A</cite> amended effective March 14, 2005 (32:5 Md. R. 579)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-12-16"><cite path="|08|02|01|.05|A.">Regulation .05A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective June 1, 2008 (35:13 Md. R. 1174); emergency status extended to December 16, 2008 (35:23 Md. R. 2011)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-07-07"><cite path="|08|02|01|.05|A.">Regulation .05A</cite> amended effective December 1, 2008 (35:24 Md. R. 2077); February 8, 2010 (37:3 Md. R. 175); April 4, 2011 (38:7 Md. R. 429); February 15, 2016 (43:3 Md. R. 271); January 30, 2017 (44:2 Md. R. 84); January 27, 2020 (47:2 Md. R. 62);  July 7, 2025 (52:13 Md. R. 655)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-02-08"><cite path="|08|02|01|.05|I.">Regulation .05I</cite> adopted effective February 8, 2010 (37:3 Md. R. 175)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-07-26"><cite path="|08|02|01|.05|I.">Regulation .05I</cite> amended effective July 26, 2010 (37:15 Md. R. 998)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-04-12"><cite path="|08|02|01|.06">Regulation .06</cite> adopted effective April 12, 2004 (31:7 Md. R. 582)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-02-14"><cite path="|08|02|01|.06|B.">Regulation .06B</cite> amended effective February 14, 2005 (32:3 Md. R. 289)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-04-04"><cite path="|08|02|01|.07">Regulation .07</cite> adopted effective April 4, 2011 (38:7 Md. R. 429)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-03-23"><cite path="|08|02|01|.07|B.">Regulation .07B</cite> amended effective July 1, 2019 (46:13 Md. R. 589); March 23, 2020 (47:6 Md. R. 340)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-03-26"><cite path="|08|02|01|.07|D.">Regulation .07D</cite> amended effective March 2, 2015 (42:4 Md. R. 432); March 26, 2018 (45:6 Md. R. 317)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-04-04"><cite path="|08|02|01|.08">Regulation .08</cite> adopted effective April 4, 2011 (38:7 Md. R. 429)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-10-17"><cite path="|08|02|01|.09">Regulation .09</cite> adopted effective October 17, 2011 (38:21 Md. R. 1276)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-11-11"><cite path="|08|02|01|.09|A.">Regulation .09A</cite> amended effective November 11, 2024 (51:22 Md. R. 963)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-02-13"><cite path="|08|02|01|.09|H.">Regulation .09H</cite> amended effective February 13, 2017 (44:3 Md. R. 188)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-05-28"><cite path="|08|02|01|.10">Regulation .10</cite> adopted effective May 28, 2012 (39:10 Md. R. 659)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-08-08"><cite path="|08|02|01|.10|A.">Regulation .10A</cite> amended effective August 8, 2022 (49:16 Md. R. 757)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container"><cite path="|08|02|01|.11">Regulation .11</cite> adopted effective October 29. 2012 (39:21 Md. R. 1377)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-11-25"><cite path="|08|02|01|.12">Regulation .12</cite> adopted effective November 25, 2013 (40:23 Md. R. 1932)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-01-06"><cite path="|08|02|01|.12|B.">Regulation .12B</cite> amended effective June 15, 2020 (47:12 Md. R. 595); February 8, 2021 (48:3 Md. R. 93); December 11, 2023 (50:24 Md. R. 1040); January 6, 2025 (51:26 Md. R. 1186)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-03-30"><cite path="|08|02|01|.13">Regulation .13</cite> adopted effective March 30, 2015 (42:6 Md. R. 510)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-12-12"><cite path="|08|02|01|.13|B.">Regulation .13B</cite> amended effective December 14, 2020 (47:25 Md. R. 1067); December 12, 2022 (49:25 Md. R. 1049)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-06-05"><cite path="|08|02|01|.13|D.">Regulation .13D</cite> amended effective June 5, 2017 (44:11 Md. R. 524)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-12-11"><cite path="|08|02|01|.13|E.">Regulation .13E</cite> adopted effective December 11, 2023 (50:24 Md. R. 1040)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-11-09"><cite path="|08|02|01|.14">Regulation .14</cite> adopted effective November 9, 2015 (42:22 Md. R. 1377)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-08-29"><cite path="|08|02|01|.15">Regulation .15</cite> adopted effective August 29, 2016 (43:17 Md. R. 953)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-02-11"><cite path="|08|02|01|.16">Regulation .16</cite> adopted effective February 11, 2019 (46:3 Md. R. 106)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-03-09"><cite path="|08|02|01|.16|C.">Regulation .16C</cite> amended effective September 23, 2019 (46:19 Md. R. 813); March 9, 2020 (47:5 Md. R. 310)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
