<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Blue Crabs</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Crabbing Gear.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Lawful Gear.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may catch crabs in the tidal waters of Maryland only with the gear authorized in this chapter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Diving Apparatus. A person may not possess or catch crabs in the tidal waters of Maryland using diving apparatus by itself, or in conjunction with any of the other methods authorized in this chapter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Gear designated to catch crabs and defined in this chapter, except for a seine, is not considered a net under the definition listed in <cite path="08.02.05.02">COMAR 08.02.05.02</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Recreational Gear — Definitions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The gear defined in this section may be used to catch crabs for recreational purposes.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Bushel” means a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Circular container with the following inside dimensions:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>18 inches top diameter;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>13-1/2 inches bottom diameter; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>12 inches height; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Rectangular container with the following inside dimensions:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>11 inches height;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>19½ inches length; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>12½ inches width.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Collapsible crab trap" means a manually operated, portable device:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Having a flat bottom not more than 20 inches by 15 inches, and not more than four articulated sides; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Designed so that failure to apply manually exerted tension on the closing mechanism allows the crabs to escape.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Crab net ring" means a manually operated, portable device that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Consists of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Two rings, each of a different diameter, connected by netting, where the larger of the two rings shall be less than or equal to 30 inches in diameter; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>One ring that shall be less than or equal to 30 inches in diameter, connected to netting;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>When baited and lowered to the bottom, lies flat on the bottom; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>When pulled to the surface, forms a deep pocket out of the netting.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Crab pot" means a cube-shaped or rectangular shaped device with openings toward the inside for the entrance of crabs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Dip net" means a mesh bag of netting or wire which is suspended from a circular, oval, or a rectangular frame attached to a handle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Handline" means an unbuoyed fishing line managed primarily by hand.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Trotline" means a length of rope or line, buoyed at both ends with one or more anchors, which is baited without hooks or snares at intervals for the purpose of catching crabs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Seine" means an encircling type of net which is not more than 50 feet long and 5 feet wide.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Commercial Gear.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In addition to the gear listed in §B(2)—(8) of this regulation, the gear defined in this section may also be used for commercial crab harvesting.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Bank trap" means an enclosure constructed of wire mesh not more than 4 feet long and not more than 4 feet wide, with a single row of hedging not more than 75 feet long.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Barrel” means a container which holds not more than 2-1/2 U.S. standard bushels of crabs and does not exceed the following inside dimensions:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>20½ inches across the top diameter;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>27½ inches height; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>18 inches along the bottom diameter.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Channel pound" means an enclosure constructed of wire mesh not more than 8 feet long and not more than 4 feet wide, with two rows of hedging, each not longer than 100 feet long.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Crab scrape" means a scoop or other device which is dragged along the bottom for the purpose of catching crabs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Hand scrape" means a single scoop or other device which is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Dragged along the bottom for the purpose of catching crabs; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Retrieved by hand without the aid of any mechanical device during any stage of the retrieval.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Lug” means a rectangular-shaped container that does not exceed the following inside dimensions:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>22-7/8 inches in length across the top;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>14-7/8 inches in width across the top;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>21 inches length across the bottom;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>13 inches width across the bottom; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>12-3/8 inches height.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Seines.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A seine may be used for recreational purposes only.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The seine may not be emptied:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>On the shore or beach; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In any water of less than sufficient depth to enable the unwanted fish to return to the waters alive.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Trotlines.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An individual may not set or fish a trotline within 100 feet of another individual’s set trotline, collapsible crab trap, or net ring.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The length of a trotline shall be measured along the bait line from the first bait to the last bait.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In the coastal bays of the Atlantic Ocean and their tidal tributaries:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An individual may not use or possess on board a vessel a trotline or trotlines with a baited portion more than 600 feet in length to catch or attempt to catch crabs for recreational purposes; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If two or more individuals are on a boat, not more than two trotlines with a baited portion more than 600 feet each  may be used or possessed on board a vessel to catch or attempt to catch crabs for recreational purposes.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>In the Chesapeake Bay and its tidal tributaries:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Trotline gear may only be used to catch or attempt to catch crabs:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>For commercial purposes by an individual licensed in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-701">Natural Resources Article, §4-701, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For recreational purposes by an individual licensed in accordance with <cite path="|08|02|03|.09">Regulation .09 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An individual licensed to catch crabs for recreational purposes may not use or possess on board a vessel a trotline or trotlines with a baited portion more than 1,200 feet in length to catch or attempt to catch crabs for recreational purposes; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The trotline gear used from the boat may not exceed 1,200 feet in length for the baited portion:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Regardless of the number of individuals licensed to catch crabs for recreational purposes on a boat; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the boat is licensed as a recreational crabbing boat.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Buoy Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A trotline shall have a three-dimensional buoy of the same color, size, and shape attached to each end.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Buoys that have a spherical shape shall be at least 12 inches in diameter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Buoys that do not have a spherical shape shall be at least:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>12 inches long;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>10 inches wide; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>10 inches high.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Buoys shall be marked with the owner’s:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>DNR id number, if recreationally crabbing in the Chesapeake Bay or its tidal tributaries;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Name and address, if recreationally crabbing in the Atlantic Ocean, its coastal bays, or their tidal tributaries; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Commercial license number.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|02|03|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Crab Scrapes.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A crab scrape may not:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Have a bar wider than 60 inches;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Have teeth or projections of any kind;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Have a flat plate attached to the scraping bar, which is the bar that touches the bottom;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Have a diver, chain, or other device attached to it or the taking line to hold the scrape to the bottom; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Exceed 80 pounds in weight, including the bag.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Number of Scrapes Permitted.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may not use more than two scrapes in any vessel that is propelled by an engine.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Scrapes may not be affixed to each other so as to form a single fishing unit.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Prohibited Areas. Scrapes are prohibited in the following areas:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>St. Mary's River—that portion lying upriver from a line drawn between Chancellor Point and Portobello Point;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Calvert Bay and Smith Creek—that portion north of a line drawn between Kitts Point and Lawson Point;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All submerged lands leased for shellfish cultivation in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr">Natural Resources Article, Title 4, Subtitle 11A, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The waters of the Chesapeake Bay and tidal tributaries north of a line extending in a westerly direction from the southern point of the mouth of Punch Island Creek in Dorchester County defined by Lat. 38°25'15.2"N., Long. 76°17'19.7"W. to Cove Point in Calvert County defined by Lat. 38°23'05.4"N., Long. 76°22'52.3"W.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Hand Scrapes. Notwithstanding <cite path="08|02|03|.04|C.|(4)">§C(4) of this regulation</cite>, a person may use a single scrape not wider than 48 inches and not heavier than 45 pounds north of the line defined in <cite path="08|02|03|.04|C.|(4)">§C(4) of this regulation</cite> in the following areas:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The area of the Chesapeake Bay east of a line drawn from a point at or near Cook Point in Dorchester County defined by Lat. 38°37'41.5"N., Long. 76°17'21.1"W.; then running approximately 193° True to a point at or near Hills Point in Dorchester County defined by Lat. 38°34'19.9"N., Long. 76°18'21.2"W.; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The waters of Queen Anne's County and Kent County.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|02|03|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Bank Traps and Channel Pounds.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A bank trap and channel pound shall meet the following structural requirements:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A row of hedging attached to any bank trap or channel pound may not exceed more than 1/3 the distance across the body of water in which the bank trap or channel pound is placed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>To permit trapped air-breathing animals to survive, each bank trap and channel pound shall be constructed and placed in the water to provide an airspace safety chamber in the top of the trap which shall extend 12 inches above the water at mean high tide, and consist of a cube not less than 12 inches on each side and 12 inches high, or a cylinder not less than 18 inches in diameter and 12 inches high; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A marker shall be attached to each bank trap and channel pound, which clearly identifies the name and license number of the owner in letters at least 2 inches high.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Areas Where Bank Traps and Channel Pounds May Be Placed.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An individual may place a bank trap or channel pound only in the following tidal waters:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The waters surrounding Eastern Neck Island from Baybush Point along the south and easterly sides of the island to the bridge crossing Eastern Neck Narrows, except within 300 feet of another bank trap or channel pound; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The tidal waters of Somerset County except within:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>300 feet of another bank trap or channel pound; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>500 feet of the point, formed at the intersection of a line from the nearest part of the dwelling to the water and a line along the mean high water mark, of property that contains an occupied dwelling.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In Somerset County, a bank trap or channel pound may not be placed closer than the distance specified in <cite path="08|02|03|.05|B.|(1)|(b)|(ii)">§B(1)(b)(ii) of this regulation</cite> from a waterfront residence, unless written permission has been obtained from the owner, tenant, or lessee of the waterfront property. This permission shall include the signature, address, and telephone number of the owner, tenant, or lessee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If written permission is required, it shall be shown to a Natural Resources Police officer or other law enforcement officer upon request.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An individual may not set more than 35 bank traps or channel pounds in the tidal waters of Somerset County.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Times for Staking Out and Removing Bank Traps or Channel Pounds.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>After 8 a.m. on March 15, a licensee may use in each instance a single stake with the licensee's name and license number to stake out one or more sites for bank traps or channel pounds.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Beginning on March 1 of each year, a landowner or lessee may use in each instance a single stake with the landowner's or lessee's name and address to stake out one site in the area riparian to the landowner's or lessee's land where the landowner or lessee may maintain a trap or pound. An individual other than the landowner or lessee may not place or maintain a trap or pound in that area, if the area is staked by a landowner or lessee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Each bank trap and hedging shall be in place not later than May 1 or the staking of the site is void and may be staked out by another licensee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>An individual shall remove a bank trap or channel pound, including all hedging and stakes, by December 1.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If a bank trap or channel pound is removed before December 1, all hedging and stakes shall be removed 30 days after the trap is removed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Collapsible Crab Traps and Crab Net Rings.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An individual may not set or fish a crab net ring or collapsible crab trap within 100 feet of another individual’s set trotline, collapsible crab trap, or net ring.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In the coastal bays of the Atlantic Ocean and their tidal tributaries:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An individual may not catch or attempt to catch crabs for recreational purposes with any combination of more than ten collapsible traps and net rings; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If two or more individuals are catching or attempting to catch crabs for recreational purposes on a boat, not more than any combination of 25 collapsible traps and net rings may be set per boat.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In the Chesapeake Bay and its tidal tributaries:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An individual may not catch or attempt to catch crabs for recreational purposes with collapsible traps or net rings unless the individual is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Licensed to catch crabs for recreational purposes; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>On a boat licensed as a recreational crabbing boat;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If an individual is licensed to catch crabs for recreational purposes, not more than 30 collapsible traps or net rings or not more than 30 of a combination of collapsible traps and net rings may be set; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Not more than 30 collapsible traps or net rings or not more than 30 of a combination of collapsible traps and net rings may be set per boat:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Regardless of the number of individuals licensed to catch crabs for recreational purposes on a boat; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the boat is licensed as a recreational crabbing boat.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A collapsible crab trap or crab net ring which is not attached to a pier, wharf, or boat shall be marked with a buoy bearing the owner’s:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>DNRid number, if recreationally crabbing in the Chesapeake Bay or its tidal tributaries;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Name and address, if recreationally crabbing in the Atlantic Ocean, its coastal bays, or their tidal tributaries; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Commercial license number.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|02|03|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Crab Pots.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>“Cull ring” means a device in a crab pot, for the escapement of undersized crabs, described as a:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Ring with an opening of the established measurement for the inside diameter; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Square opening cut from the crab pot measuring at least 4-1/2 inches by 4-1/2 inches and covered by a panel of 2-inch by 2-inch mesh so that there are at least four complete 2-inch by 2-inch square meshes.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A crab pot shall meet the following structural requirements:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A standard cube type crab pot may not have sides which are more than 24 inches long;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Rectangular crab pots may not have dimensions which are greater than 12 inches high, 24 inches wide, and 48 inches long in total;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A crab pot shall be constructed of wire having a mesh measuring along its longest axis when the wire is unstretched of not less than:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>1-1/2 inches for the purpose of catching hard crabs; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>1 inch for the purpose of catching peeler crabs;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Except for a crab pot constructed with unstretched mesh measuring less than 1-1/2 inches or at least 2 inches on each side, a crab pot set in the Chesapeake Bay or its tidal tributaries shall have two cull rings, one of at least 2-3/16 inches and one of at least 2-5/16 inches inside diameter located in exterior side panels or the top panel of the crab pot; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A crab pot set for recreational purposes shall have a turtle reduction device which:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is firmly attached to each entrance or funnel in the lower chamber;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is constructed of wire or plastic;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Is rectangular in shape; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Has dimensions which do not exceed 1-3/4 inches high and 4-3/4 inches long.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Times for Setting and Removing Crab Pots.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Crab pots may not be set in State waters before March 31 of each year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All crab pots shall be removed from the waters of the Chesapeake Bay and its tidal tributaries by December 31 of each year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All crab pots shall be removed from the waters of the coastal bays of the Atlantic Ocean and their tidal tributaries:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If set for commercial purposes, by November 16 of each year; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If set for recreational purposes, by December 31 of each year.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>General Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may use crab pots to catch crabs for recreational purposes only:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If the person is:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>An owner, lessee, or tenant of a private property along the shore; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A guest of an owner, lessee, or tenant of a private property along the shore;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If using the crab pot in accordance with §§B, C, D, and H of this regulation; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If crabbing from a property located on the Chesapeake Bay or its tidal tributaries, only if the crab pots have been properly registered with the Department.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Not more than two crab pots set for recreational purposes may be attached to a property or privately owned pier, regardless of the number of owners or lessees of that property.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Notwithstanding §§E and G of this regulation, a crab pot set for recreational purposes shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Set in front of the person's property, within 100 yards of the shore, and:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Attached by a line to the property or a privately owned pier or dock; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Marked by a buoy or pole and sign; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Marked with the owner's:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>DNR id number, if crabbing in the Chesapeake Bay or its tidal tributaries; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Name and address, if crabbing in the Atlantic Ocean, its coastal bays, or their tidal tributaries.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Buoys for Commercially Set Crab Pots.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Each pot individually set shall be marked with a buoy that is easily visible on the surface.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Each string of pots shall be marked at each end with a buoy that is easily visible on the surface.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Each buoy shall be clearly marked with the identification number of the licensee in letters at least 2 inches high, and, if the buoy is attached to a string of crab pots, with the number of pots in the string.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Department may require individual numbered markers supplied by the Department to be attached to every buoy.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>While crabbing in the Chesapeake Bay and its tidal tributaries, a person licensed to catch crabs with more than 50 crab pots may not at any time set or fish more than 300 crab pots unless the person is authorized to set or fish 600 or 900 crab pots.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A person commercially licensed to catch crabs may set crab pots in the coastal bays of the Atlantic Ocean and their tidal tributaries subject to the following limitations:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A person licensed to catch crabs with more than 50 pots may not set or fish more than 300 pots; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Regardless of the number of licensees per boat, not more than 300 pots may be set or fished.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Crabs may not be in the bait box of the crab pot.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Except as specifically allowed, crab pots may not be set in the waters described in §§F—I of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Upper Chesapeake Bay — North of the William Preston Lane Jr. Memorial Bridge (Chesapeake Bay Bridge).</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Western Shore and Susquehanna Flats.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Susquehanna Flats. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near the shore at Rocky Point defined by Lat. 39° 29.361' N, Long. 75° 59.707' W then running approximately 257° True to a point at or near Locust Point defined by Lat. 39° 28.517' N, Long. 76° 4.372' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Spesutie Narrows. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near the shore at Bear Point defined by Lat. 39° 26.227' N, Long. 76° 4.913' W then running approximately 263° True to a point at or near Black Point defined by Lat. 39° 26.116' N, Long. 76° 6.143' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Romney Creek. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near the shore at Taylor Point defined by Lat. 39° 22.762' N, Long. 76° 10.770' W then running approximately 231° True to a point on the south side entrance to Romney Creek defined by Lat. 39° 22.169' N, Long. 76° 11.727' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Bush River. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near the shore at Abbey Point defined by Lat. 39° 20.997' N, Long. 76° 13.688' W then running approximately 242° True to a point at or near Lego Point defined by Lat. 39° 20.286' N, Long. 76° 15.409’ W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Boone Creek. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near the shore at the north side of the mouth of Boone Creek defined by Lat. 39° 19.947' N, Long. 76° 15.953' W then running approximately 202° True to a point on the southwest side of the entrance to Boone Creek defined by Lat. 39° 19.836' N, Long. 76° 16.004' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Gunpowder River. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near the shore at the southwestern tip of Rickett Point defined by Lat. 39° 18.126' N, Long. 76° 17.805' W then running approximately 298° True to the point at the eastern tip of Carroll Island defined by Lat. 39° 18.778' N, Long. 76° 19.372' W then along the shore to the western tip of Carroll Island defined by Lat. 39° 18.817' N, Long. 76° 19.536' W then running 297° True to a point at or near Carroll Point defined by Lat. 39° 18.904' N, Long. 76° 19.758' W then running 208° True to a point at or near Weir Point defined by Lat. 39° 18.306' N, Long. 76° 20.196' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Seneca Creek, Middle River, Hawk Cove, and Back River. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near the shore at Lower Island Point defined by Lat. 39° 18.254' N, Long. 76° 20.389' W then running approximately 197° True to the most northern point of Hart-Miller Island defined by Lat. 39° 15.693' N, Long. 76° 21.388’ W then running along the northwestern shore of Hart-Miller Island to a point on the western side of Hart-Miller Island defined by Lat. 39° 14.547' N, Long. 76° 23.078' W then running approximately 208° True to the northern tip of Pleasure Island defined by Lat. 39° 14.120' N, Long. 76° 23.378' W then running along the southern shore to the southern tip of Pleasure Island defined by Lat. 39° 13.896' N, Long. 76° 23.649' W then running approximately 235° True to the southeastern point of Back River Neck defined by Lat. 39° 13.759' N, Long. 76° 23.897' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Shallow Creek. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at the entrance on the north side of Shallow Creek defined by Lat. 39° 12.270' N, Long. 76° 25.959' W then running approximately 235° True to a point at the entrance on the south side of Shallow Creek define by Lat. 39° 12.140' N, Long. 76° 26.180' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Patapsco River.  All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near North Point defined by Lat. 39° 11.720' N, Long. 76° 26.557' W then running approximately 227° True to the point at or near Buoy R "6" defined by Lat. 39° 11.152' N, Long. 76° 27.336' W then running approximately 160° True to a point at or near Bodkin Point defined by Lat. 39° 7.937' N, Long. 76° 25.860' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Magothy River. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near Mountain Point defined by Lat. 39° 3.553' N, Long. 76° 25.996' W then running approximately 212° True to a point at or near Persimmon Point defined by Lat. 39° 3.170' N, Long. 76° 26.310' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Little Magothy River. All the waters upstream of a line beginning of the west jetty at the entrance to the Little Magothy River defined by Lat. 39° 2.765' N, Long. 76° 25.783' W then running approximately 14° True to tip of the west jetty at the entrance to the Little Magothy River defined by Lat. 39° 2.782' N, Long. 76° 25.778' W then running approximately 97° True to a point on the tip of the east jetty at the entrance to Little Magothy River defined by Lat. 39° 2.782' N, Long. 76° 25.765' W then running approximately 193° True along the east jetty to a point on shore defined by Lat. 39° 2.770' N, Long. 76° 25.769' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>Podickory Point Marina. All the waters enclosed by a line at the beginning of the north Podickory Point Marina jetty defined by Lat. 39° 1.980' N, Long. 76° 24.239' W then running approximately 45° True to a point at the tip of the north Podickory Point Marina jetty defined by Lat. 39° 2.004' N, Long. 76° 24.214' W then running approximately 191° True to a point at the tip of the south Podickory Point Marina jetty defined by Lat. 39° 1.969' N, Long. 76° 24.223' W then running approximately 220° True along the jetty to a point at the shore defined by Lat. 39° 1.906' N, Long. 76° 24.294' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>Sandy Point Boat Exclusion Zone. All the waters enclosed by a line at the beginning of the northernmost jetty at Sandy Point defined by Lat. 39° 1.089' N, Long. 76° 23.816' W then running approximately 71° True to a point at the tip of the northernmost jetty at Sandy Point defined by Lat. 39° 1.114' N, Long. 76° 23.739' W then running approximately 155° True to a point offshore of Sandy Point defined by Lat. 39° 0.655' N, Long. 76° 23.458' W then running approximately 243° True to the Mezick Pond Jetty south of Sandy Point defined by Lat. 39° 0.390' N, Long. 76° 24.108' W then running approximately 330° True along the jetty to the point along the shore defined by Lat. 39° 0.464' N, Long. 76° 24.158' W.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Eastern Shore.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Elk River. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near the east side of Turkey Point defined by Lat. 39° 26.997' N, Long. 76° 0.184' W then running approximately 121° True towards the entrance to Pearce Creek defined by Lat. 39° 26.337' N, Long. 75° 58.792' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Pond Creek.  All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point north of the entrance to Pond Creek defined by Lat. 39° 24.903' N, Long. 76° 0.340' W then running approximately 235° True to a point south of the entrance to Pond Creek defined by Lat. 39° 24.766' N, Long. 76° 0.597' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Sassafras River. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near Grove Point defined by Lat. 39° 23.204' N, Long. 76° 2.238' W then running approximately 255° True to a point at or near Howell Point defined by Lat. 39° 22.320' N, Long. 76° 6.373' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Still Pond. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near Meeks Point defined by Lat. 39° 20.717' N, Long. 76° 8.2082' W then running approximately 211° True to a point at or near Rocky Point defined by Lat. 39° 20.070' N, Long. 76° 8.731' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Worton Creek. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point on the north side of the entrance to Worton Creek defined by Lat. 39° 18.058' N, Long. 76° 10.713' W then running approximately 199° True to a point at or near Handy Point defined by Lat. 39° 17.420' N, Long. 76° 10.993' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Fairlee Creek. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point on the north side of the entrance to Fairlee Creek defined by Lat. 39° 16.280' N, Long. 76° 12.122' W then running approximately 256° True to a point on the western side of the entrance to Fairlee Creek defined by Lat. 39° 16.183' N, Lon. 76° 12.677' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Rock Hall Harbor/Swan Creek/Tavern Creek. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near Swan Point defined by Lat. 39° 8.778' N, Long. 76° 16.523' W then running approximately 140° True to a point at a known sunken island defined by Lat. 39° 7.240' N, Long. 76° 14.870' W then running approximately 170° True to a point at or near the northern tip of Huntingfield Point defined by Lat. 39° 7.118' N, Long. 76° 14.842' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Chester River. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near Wilson Point defined by Lat. 39° 03.193' N, Long. 76° 13.635' W then running approximately 227° True to a point at or near Love Point defined by Lat. 39° 2.693' N, Long. 76° 14.27' W then running approximately 265° True to a point at or near the Eastern Neck Island rock jetty defined by Lat. 39° 2.392' N, Long. 76° 18.156' W.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Lower Western Shore — South of the William Preston Lane Jr. Memorial Bridge (Chesapeake Bay Bridge).</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Mezick Pond to South River.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Mezick Pond. All the waters enclosed by a line beginning at a point east of the entrance to Mezick Pond defined by Lat. 39° 0.464' N, Long. 76° 24.158' W then running approximately 275° True to a point west of the entrance to Mezick Pond defined by Lat. 39° 0.468' N, Long. 76° 24.238' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Whitehall Bay. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near Hackett Point defined by Lat. 38° 59.223' N, Long. 76° 25.600' W then running approximately 241° True to the point at or near Greenbury Point defined by Lat. 38° 58.483' N, Long. 76° 27.295' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Severn River. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near Greenbury Point defined by Lat. 38° 58.483' N, Long. 76° 27.295' W then running approximately 174° True to the point at or near Tolly Point defined by Lat. 38° 56.490' N, Long. 76° 27.025' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Blackwalnut Creek. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point on the north side of the entrance to Blackwalnut Creek defined by Lat. 38° 55.842' N, Long. 76° 27.774' W then running approximately 207° True to a point on the south side of the entrance to Blackwalnut Creek defined by Lat. 38° 55.827' N, Long. 76° 27.784' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Oyster Creek. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point on the north side of the entrance to Oyster Creek defined by Lat. 38° 55.644' N, Long. 76° 27.796' W then running approximately 133° True to a point on the jetty south of the entrance to Oyster Creek defined by Lat. 38° 55.626' N, Long. 76° 27.772' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Fishing Creek (South River). All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point on the north side of the entrance to Fishing Creek defined by Lat. 38° 54.898' N, Long. 76° 27.557' W then running approximately 186° True to a point at or near Thomas Point defined by Lat. 38° 54.448' N, Long. 76° 27.622' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>South River. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near Thomas Point defined by Lat. 38° 54.448' N, Long. 76° 27.622' W then running approximately 227° True to a point at or near Saunders Point defined by Lat. 38° 53.100' N, Long. 76° 29.444' W.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>West River to Herring Bay.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Rhode and West Rivers. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near Dutchman Point defined by Lat. 38° 52.183' N, Long. 76° 30.570' W then running approximately 152° True to a point at or near Curtis Point defined by Lat. 38° 51.184' N, Long. 76° 29.891' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Jack Creek. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point on the north side of the entrance to Jack Creek defined by Lat. 38° 50.791' N, Long. 76° 29.650' W then running approximately 163° True to a point on the south side of the entrance to Jack Creek defined by Lat. 38° 50.636' N, Long. 76° 29.588' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Flag Pond Creek. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point on the north side of the entrance to Flag Pond Creek defined by Lat. 38° 48.646' N, Long. 76° 30.320' W then running approximately 200° True to a point on the south side of the entrance to Flag Pond Creek defined by Lat. 38° 48.499' N, Long. 76° 30.388' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Deep Creek and Deep Cove Creek. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point on the north side of the entrance to Deep Creek/Deep Cove Creek defined by Lat. 38° 48.341' N, Long. 76° 30.543' W then running approximately 186° True to a point on the south side of the entrance to Deep Creek/Deep Cove Creek defined by Lat. 38° 48.280' N, Long. 76° 30.551' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Broadwater Creek. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point north of the entrance to Broadwater Creek at Franklin Manor Beach defined by Lat. 38° 48.060' N, Long. 76° 30.617' W then running approximately 225° True to a point on the south side of the entrance to Broadwater Creek defined by Lat. 38° 47.264' N, Long. 76° 31.618' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Carrs Creek. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point on the north side of the entrance to Carrs Creek defined by Lat. 38° 47.264' N, Long. 76° 31.618' W then running approximately 196° True to a point on the south side of the entrance to Carrs Creek defined by Lat. 38° 47.198' N, Long. 76° 31.649' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Herring Bay. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point on the north side of the entrance to Parkers Creek defined by Lat. 38° 46.691' N, Long. 76° 32.220' W then running approximately 172° True to the point at or near Holland Point defined by Lat. 38° 43.661' N, Long. 76° 31.664' W.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Fishing Creek to Cove Point.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Fishing Creek (Chesapeake Beach). All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point on shore at the beginning of the rock jetty defined by Lat. 38° 41.534' N, Long. 76° 31.960' W then running approximately 96° True to a point at the tip of the rock jetty on the north side of the entrance to Fishing Creek defined by Lat. 38° 41.518' N, Long. 76° 31.770' W then running approximately 186° True to a point at the tip of the rock jetty on the south side of the entrance to Fishing Creek defined by Lat. 38° 41.448' N, Long. 76° 31.779' W then running approximately 251° True along the rock jetty to a point on shore at the beginning of the rock jetty defined by Lat. 38° 41.399' N, Long. 76° 31.960' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Naval Research Lab Prohibited Area near Randle Cliff Beach (via CFR § 334.170 Area A). All the waters enclosed by a line beginning at a point on the shore defined by Lat. 38° 39.917' N, Long. 76° 31.782' W then running approximately 90° True to a point at defined by Lat. 38° 39.918' N, Long. 76° 31.050' W then running approximately 180° True to a point at defined by Lat. 38° 39.150' N, Long. 76° 31.050' W then running approximately 270° True to a point on the shore defined by Lat. 38° 39.150' N, Long. 76° 31.620' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Plum Point Creek. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point on shore at the beginning of the north jetty defined by Lat. 38° 36.9425' N, Long. 76° 30.729' W then running approximately 87° True to the tip of the jetty at the north side of the entrance to Plum Point Creek defined by Lat. 38° 36.944' N, Long. 76° 30.669' W then running approximately 176° True to the tip of the jetty at the south side of the entrance to Plum Point Creek defined by Lat. 38° 36.925' N, Long. 76° 30.667' W then running approximately 263° True to the point along the shore at the beginning of the south jetty defined by Lat. 38° 36.922' N, Long. 76° 30.697' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Parkers Creek (near Port Republic). All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point on the north side of the entrance to Parkers Creek defined by Lat. 38° 32.243' N, Long. 76° 31.086' W then running approximately 169° True to a point on the south side of the entrance to Parkers Creek defined by Lat. 38° 32.215' N, Long. 76° 31.080' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Long Beach. All the waters enclosed by a line running from a point on shore at the beginning of the north jetty defined by Lat. 38° 27.894' N, Long. 76° 28.255' W then running approximately 45° True to a point at the tip of the rock jetty on the north side of the entrance to Long Beach defined by Lat. 38° 27.945' N, Long. 76° 28.192' W then running approximately 171° True to a point at the tip of the rock jetty on the south side of the entrance to Long Beach defined by Lat. 38° 27.916' N, Long. 76° 28.187' W then running approximately 223° True along the south jetty to the point on shore defined by Lat. 38° 27.847' N, Long. 76° 28.268' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Calvert Cliffs (via Security Zone 165.505). All the waters enclosed by a line beginning at a point along the shore north of the Calvert Cliffs Nuclear Power Plant defined by Lat. 38° 26.233' N, Long. 76° 26.550' W then running approximately 28° True to a point defined by Lat. 38° 26.350' N, Long. 76° 26.467' W then running approximately 131° True to a point defined by Lat. 38° 26.167' N, Long. 76° 26.200' W then running approximately 227° True to a point on the shore south of the Calvert Cliffs Nuclear Power Plant defined by Lat. 38° 26.089' N, Long. 76° 26.310' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Cove Point Liquified Natural Gas Terminal (via Safety Zone 165.502). All the waters enclosed by a line beginning at a point defined by Lat. 38° 24.450' N, Long. 76° 23.700' W then running approximately 55° True to a point defined by Lat. 38° 24.734' N, Long. 76° 23.184' W then running approximately 145° True to a point defined by Lat. 38° 23.917' N, Long. 76° 22.450' W then running approximately 234° True to a point defined by Lat. 38° 23.617' N, Long. 76° 22.967' W then running approximately 325° True to a point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Patuxent River to St. Jerome’s Creek.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Patuxent River. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near Drum Point defined by Lat. 38° 19.138' N, Long. 76° 25.295' W then running approximately 120° True to a point at or near Hog Point defined by Lat. 38° 18.555' N, Long. 76° 24.028' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Goose Creek. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point on the north side of the entrance to Goose Creek defined by Lat. 38° 17.508' N, Long. 76° 22.758' W then running approximately 221° True to a point on the south side of the entrance to Goose Creek defined by Lat. 38° 17.494' N, Long. 76° 22.775' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>St. Jerome Creek. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near St. Jerome Point defined by Lat. 38° 7.213' N, Long. 76° 20.301' W then running approximately 265° True to a point at or near Deep Point defined by Lat. 38° 7.201' N, Long. 76° 20.486' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Deep Creek and Long Neck Creek. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point on the north side of the entrance to Deep Creek/Long Neck Creek defined by Lat. 38° 5.221' N, Long. 76° 19.860' W then running approximately 175° True to a point on the south side of the entrance to Deep Creek/Long Neck Creek defined by Lat. 38° 5.195' N, Long. 76° 19.858' W.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Tanner Creek. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at the shore at the beginning of the north jetty at the entrance to Tanner Creek defined by Lat. 38° 3.934' N, Long. 76° 19.662' W then running approximately 82° True to a point at the tip of the north jetty defined by Lat. 38° 3.943' N, Long. 76° 19.588' W then running approximately 170° True to a point at the tip of the south jetty defined by Lat. 38° 3.916' N, Long. 76° 19.584' W then running approximately 260° True to a point at the beginning of the south jetty at the shore defined by Lat. 38° 3.903' N, Long. 76° 19.676' W.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Potomac River — Maryland Tributaries and Sounds.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Potomac River. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near Point Lookout defined by Lat. 38° 2.275' N, Long. 76° 19.326' W then running approximately 155° True to a point at or near the tip of the north Smith Point jetty defined by Lat. 37° 53.418' N, Long. 76° 14.177' W then running approximately 147° True to a point at or near the tip of the south Smith Point jetty defined by Lat. 37° 53.381' N, Long. 76° 14.146' W then running approximately 240° True along the jetty to a point on shore at the beginning of the jetty defined by Lat. 37° 53.331' N, Long. 76° 14.252' W then southerly along the shore to the Maryland/Virginia State Line defined by Lat. 37° 53.159' N, Long. 76° 14.247' W, except as provided in <cite path="08|02|03|.07|G.|(6)|(b)">§G(6)(b) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Exceptions.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Calvert Bay. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near the eastern shore of the entrance to Rowley Bay defined by Lat. 38° 5.463' N, Long. 76° 23.011' W then running approximately 298° True to a point at or near Gray Point defined by Lat. 38° 5.555' N, Long. 76° 23.231' W then running approximately 299° True to a point at or near Kitts Point defined by Lat. 38° 6.326' N, Long. 76° 25.020' W and downstream of a line beginning at a point on the east shore at the entrance to Calvert Creek defined by Lat. 38° 6.158' N, Long. 76° 23.524' W then running approximately 313° True to a point on the west sore at the entrance to Calvert Creek defined by Lat. 38° 6.210' N, Long. 76° 23.601' W.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>All the waters downstream of a line running from the east entrance to unnamed creek west of Charles Davis Lane defined by Lat. 38° 6.284' N, Long. 76° 23.858' W then running approximately 291° True to a point on the west entrance to unnamed creek west of Charles Davis Lane defined by Lat. 38° 6.310' N, Long. 76° 23.938' W.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>All the waters downstream of a line running from the east entrance to Smith Creek defined by Lat. 38° 6.434' N, Long. 76° 24.319' W then running approximately 267° True to a point on the west entrance to Smith Creek defined by Lat. 38° 6.416' N, Long. 76° 24.816' W.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>St. Mary’s River. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near the southwestern tip of St Inigoes Neck defined by Lat. 38° 6.367' N, Long. 76° 25.281' W then running approximately 270° True to a point at the southeasternmost point of St. George Island defined by Lat. 38° 6.384' N, Long. 76° 27.937' W and downstream of a line beginning at a point at or near Priest’s Point defined by Lat. 38° 9.045' N, Long. 76° 26.491' W then running approximately 235° True to a point at or near Edmund Point defined by Lat. 38° 8.378' N, Long. 76° 27.703' W.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>All the waters downstream of a line beginning at a point at or near Cherryfield Point defined by Lat. 38° 7.772' N, Long. 76° 28.004' W then running approximately 209° True to the point at or near Ball Point defined by Lat. 38° 7.252' N, Long. 76° 28.381' W.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Breton Bay/St. Clements Bay. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near Huggins Point defined by Lat. 38° 14.023' N, Long. 76° 41.138' W then running approximately 235° True to a point on the eastern extremity of the sand bar known as Heron Island defined by Lat. 38° 12.962' N, Long. 76° 43.075' W then running approximately 286° True to a point on the western extremity of Heron Island bar defined by Lat. 38° 13.127' N, Long. 76° 43.827' W then running approximately 223° True to a point at or near the most southeasterly tip of Blackistone/St. Clement’s Island defined by Lat. 38° 12.493' N, Long. 76° 44.576' W then running along the southern and western shores to the most western point of Blackistone/St. Clement’s Island defined by Lat. 38° 12.760' N, Long. 76° 44.840' W then running approximately 338° True to a point at or near Colton Point defined by Lat. 38° 13.337' N, Long. 76° 45.133' W and downstream of a line beginning at a point at or near Protestant Point defined by Lat. 38° 14.923' N, Long. 76° 40.456' W then running approximately 292° True to a point at or near Clem Point defined by Lat. 38° 15.347' N, Long. 76° 41.771' W then running along the shore of Newtown Neck past Kaywood Point and Long Point to a point at or near Chapel Point defined by Lat. 38° 15.485' N, Long. 76° 42.409' W then running approximately 325° True to a point at or near Shipping Point defined by Lat. 38° 15.952' N, Long. 76° 42.811' W then running along the shore to the point at the northern entrance to Canoe Neck Creek defined by Lat. 38° 15.256' N, Long. 76° 43.612' W then running approximately 235° True to the point at the southern entrance to Canoe Neck Creek defined by Lat. 38° 15.107' N, Long. 76° 43.839' W then along the shore to a point at the northern entrance to St. Patrick Creek defined by Lat. 38° 14.129' N, Long. 76° 44.472' W then running approximately 211° True to a point on the southern entrance to St. Patrick Creek defined by Lat. 38° 13.900' N, Long. 76° 44.656' W.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>St. Catherine’s Sound. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at the southeasterly entrance to St. Catherine’s Sound between Waterloo Point and Dukehart Creek defined by Lat. 38° 13.643' N, Long. 76° 46.447' W then running approximately 274° True to the southernmost extension of St. Catherine Island Sandbar defined by Lat. 38° 13.696' N, Long. 76° 47.272' W then running approximately 328° True to a point at the southern tip of St. Catherine’s Island defined by Lat. 38° 14.109' N, Long. 76° 47.603' W and downstream of a line beginning at a point at or near Yellow Bank Point defined by Lat. 38° 14.761' N, Long. 76° 47.169' W then running approximately 240° True to a point at the northeasternmost tip of St. Catherine’s Island defined by Lat. 38° 14.452' N, Long. 76° 47.851' W.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Wicomico River. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near Cobb Point defined by Lat. 38° 15.314' N, Long. 76° 50.523' W then running approximately 136° True to a point at or near Cobb Point bar lighthouse defined by Lat. 38° 14.555' N, Long. 76° 49.597' W then running approximately 96° True to a point at or near the northwestern tip of St. Catherine’s Island defined by Lat. 38° 14.429' N, Long. 76° 47.958' W then running approximately 320° True to a point at or near the southern tip of St. Margaret’s Island defined by Lat. 38° 15.031' N, Long. 76° 48.594' W then along the western shore to a point at or near the eastern tip of St. Margaret’s Island defined by Lat. 38° 15.125' N, Long. 76° 48.569' W then running approximately 84° True to a point on the eastern shore of the Wicomico River defined by Lat. 38° 15.151' N, Long. 76° 48.311' W and downstream of a line beginning at a point at or near White Point defined by Lat. 38° 17.214' N, Long. 76° 48.842' W then running approximately 250° True to a point at the western tip of White Point Sand Bar defined by Lat. 38° 17.096' N, Long. 76° 49.261' W then running approximately 222° True to a point at or near Rock Point defined by Lat. 38° 16.409' N, Long. 76° 50.041' W then running approximately 196° True to a point at or near Shipping Point defined by Lat. 38° 15.707' N, Long. 76° 50.291' W then along the eastern shore of Cobb Island to the point at or near Cobb Point defined by Lat. 38° 15.314' N, Long. 76° 50.523' W.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ix)</num>
            <text>Liverpool Point to Smith Point (Charles County). All the waters enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near Liverpool Point defined by Lat. 38° 27.851' N, Long. 77° 16.236' W then running approximately 175° True to a point at or near Smith Point defined by Lat. 38° 24.964' N, Long. 77° 15.918' W.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Lower Eastern Shore — South of the William Preston Lane Jr. Memorial Bridge (Chesapeake Bay Bridge).</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Broad Creek to Knapps Narrows.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Bay Bridge Marina. All the waters enclosed by a line beginning at a point on the north side of the entrance to the Bay Bridge Marina defined by Lat. 38° 58.809' N, Long. 76° 20.097' W then running approximately 223° True to a point on the south side of the entrance to the Bay Bridge Marina defined by Lat. 38° 58.785' N, Long. 76° 20.127' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Broad Creek. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point on the north side of the entrance to Broad Creek defined by Lat. 38° 58.645' N, Long. 76° 20.164' W then running approximately 230° True to a point on the south side of the entrance to Broad Creek defined by Lat. 38° 58.476' N, Long. 76° 20.424' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Matapeake. All the waters enclosed by a line beginning at a point on the north side of the entrance to Matapeake defined by Lat. 38° 57.389' N, Long. 76° 21.427' W then running approximately 201° True to a point on the south side of the entrance to Matapeake defined by Lat. 38° 57.371' N, Long. 76° 21.436' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Kentmorr. All the waters enclosed by a line beginning at a point on the north side of the entrance to Kentmorr Marina defined by Lat. 38° 54.906' N, Long. 76° 21.970' W then running approximately 173° True to a point on the south side of the entrance to Kentmorr Marina defined by Lat. 38° 54.886' N, Long. 76° 21.968' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Price Creek. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point on the north side of the entrance to Price Creek defined by Lat. 38° 53.909' N, Long. 76° 21.955' W then running approximately 195° True to a point on the south side of the entrance to Price Creek defined by Lat. 38° 53.892' N, Long. 76° 21.958' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Tolson Creek. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point on the north side of the entrance to Tolson Creek defined by Lat. 38° 53.111' N, Long. 76° 21.854' W then running approximately 164° True to a point on the south side of the entrance to Tolson Creek defined by Lat. 38° 53.024' N, Long. 76° 21.819' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Carter Creek. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point on the north side of the entrance to Carter Creek defined by Lat. 38° 52.719' N, Long. 76° 21.854' W then running approximately 190° True to a point on the south side of the entrance to Tolson Creek defined by Lat. 38° 52.650' N, Long. 76° 21.869' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Eastern Bay. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near Kent Point defined by Lat. 38° 50.188' N, Long. 76° 22.125' W then running approximately 148° True to a point on the eastern side of Harbor Cove defined by Lat. 38° 46.735' N, Long. 76° 19.395' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Knapps Narrows. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near the north side of the entrance to Front Creek defined by Lat. 38° 43.976' N, Long. 76° 20.417' W then running approximately 175° True to a point at or near Amy’s Marsh Point defined by Lat. 38° 43.783' N, Long. 76° 20.387' W then running approximately 181° True to a point at the northwestern tip of Tilghman Island defined by Lat. 38° 43.234' N, Long. 76° 20.398' W.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Choptank, Little Choptank, and James Island. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near Black Walnut Point defined by Lat. 38° 40.234' N, Long. 76° 20.372' W then running approximately 175° True to a point at or near Black Walnut Bar Bell Buoy defined by Lat. 38° 38.302' N, Long. 76° 20.219' W then running approximately 158° True to a point at or near Hills Point defined by Lat. 38° 34.370' N, Long. 76° 18.265' W then running approximately 205° True to a point at or near the northeastern tip of James Island defined by Lat. 38° 31.229' N, Long. 76° 20.129' W then running approximately 207° True to a point on the northern side of a James Island defined by Lat. 38° 30.989' N, Long. 76° 20.296' W then running along the shore to a point on the southern side of a James Island defined by Lat. 38° 30.974' N, Long. 76° 20.294' W then running approximately 176° True to a point defined by Lat. 38° 30.490' N, Long. 76° 20.243' W then running approximately 189° True to a point at the southernmost James Island defined by Lat. 38° 30.241' N, Long. 76° 20.294' W then running approximately 164° True to a point at or near the northeastern tip of Taylor Island on the western side of Oyster Cove defined by Lat. 38° 29.211' N, Long. 76° 19.928' W.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Punch Island Creek. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point on the north side of the entrance to Punch Island Creek defined by Lat. 38° 25.457' N, Long. 76° 17.425' W then running approximately 141° True to a point on the south side of the entrance to Punch Island Creek defined by Lat. 38° 25.142' N, Long. 76° 17.102' W.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Tar Bay and Barren Island. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near the point on Meekins Neck near The Big Broads defined by Lat. 38° 22.512' N, Long. 76° 16.162' W then running approximately 172° True to a point at or near the northern tip of the northern Barren Island defined by Lat. 38° 20.636' N, Long. 76° 15.794' W then running southerly along the western shore of the northern Barren Island to a point at or near the southern tip of the northern Barren Island at the entrance to Great Cove defined by Lat. 38° 19.903' N, Long. 76° 15.569' W then running approximately 83° True to a point at or near the northwestern tip of the southern Barren Island at the entrance to Great Cove defined by Lat. 38° 19.915' N, Long. 76° 15.435' W then running southerly along the western shore to a point at or near the southwestern tip of Barren Island defined by Lat. 38° 19.502' N, Long. 76° 15.385' W then running approximately 125° True to a point at or near Pons Point defined by Lat. 38° 18.482' N, Long. 76° 13.501' W.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Upper Honga River to Tangier Sound.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Upper Honga River. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near Ferry Point defined by Lat. 38° 17.968' N, Long. 76° 12.445' W then running approximately 155° True to a point at or near the northern tip of Middle Hooper Island defined by Lat. 38° 17.626' N, Long. 76° 12.238' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Richland, Cow, and Thorofare Coves. All the waters enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near Richland Point defined by Lat. 38° 14.876' N, Long. 76° 10.307' W then running approximately 134° True to a point at or near Cow Point defined by Lat. 38° 14.575' N, Long. 76° 9.914' W then running approximately 124° True to a point at or near Eel Hope Point defined by Lat. 38° 14.107' N, Long. 76° 9.047' W then running approximately 121° True to the point at or near Fishing Point defined by Lat. 38° 14.078' N, Long. 76° 08.976' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Lower Honga River and Hooper Strait. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near Billy’s Point defined by Lat. 38° 14.472' N, Long. 76° 7.569' W then running approximately 120° True to a point at or near the Honga River Light Fl. 4 § 16 ft. 4M defined by Lat. 38° 13.993' N, Long. 76° 6.533' W then running approximately 159° True to a point at or near nun Buoy N "2" defined by Lat. 38° 13.240' N, Long. 76° 6.179' W then running approximately 163° True to a point at or near the Navy-maintained tower defined by Lat. 38° 11.690' N, Long. 76° 5.583' W then running approximately 120° True to a point at or near the western tip of Bloodsworth Island at the entrance to Okahanikan Cove defined by Lat. 38° 11.518' N, Long. 76° 5.195' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Pone Cove. All the waters enclosed by a line beginning at a point on the north side of the entrance to Pone Cove defined by Lat. 38° 10.496' N, Long. 76° 4.881' W then running approximately 235° True to a point on the south side of the entrance to Pone Cove defined by Lat. 38° 10.411' N, Long. 76° 05.013' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Pone, Bloodsworth, Adam, Holland, and South Marsh Islands. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near the south end of Pone Island defined by Lat. 38° 9.407' N, Long. 76° 5.083' W then running approximately 215° True to a point defined by Lat. 38° 9.136' N, Long. 76° 5.316' W then running approximately 218° True to a point defined by Lat. 38° 9.097' N, Long. 76° 5.354' W then running southerly along the shore to a point defined by Lat. 38° 9.050' N, Long. 76° 5.376' W then running approximately 216° True to a point defined by Lat. 38° 9.005' N, Long. 76° 5.425' W then running southerly along the shore to a point defined by Lat. 38° 8.986' N, Long. 76° 5.341' W then running approximately 153° True to a point at or near the northern tip of Adam Island defined by Lat. 38° 8.858' N, Long. 76° 5.341' W then southerly along the shore to a point at or near the south end of Adam Island defined by Lat. 38° 8.321' N, Long. 76° 5.149' W then running approximately 182° True to a point at or near the north end of Holland Island defined by Lat. 38° 7.453' N, Long. 76° 5.180' W then southerly along the shore to a point at or near the south end of Holland Island defined by Lat. 38° 6.927' N, Long. 76° 5.378' W then running approximately 131° True to a point at or near where the Dorchester County-Somerset County line meets a line running from the south end of Holland Island to a point at or near Sedgy Point on South Marsh Island defined by Lat. 38° 5.781' N, Long. 76° 3.724' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Holland Strait and Northern end of Tangier Sound (Malkus Line). All the waters north of a line beginning at a point at or near where the Dorchester County-Somerset County line meets a line running from the south end of Holland Island to Sedgy Point on South Marsh Island defined by Lat. 38° 5.781' N, Long. 76° 3.724' W then running approximately 21° True to a point at or near Johnson Point defined by Lat. 38° 6.665' N, Long. 76° 3.297' W then running approximately 28° True along the Dorchester County-Somerset County line to a point defined by Lat. 38° 7.508' N, Long. 76° 2.725' W then running approximately 27° True to a point at or near Lower Island Point defined by Lat. 38° 8.845' N, Long. 76° 1.873' W then running approximately 63° True following the Dorchester County-Somerset County line to its junction with county line buoy A defined by Lat. 38° 9.792' N, Long. 75° 59.517' W then running approximately 6° True toward Sharkfin Shoal Light to its junction with a straight line running from range marker AA northeasterly to range marker BB and the Dorchester County-Somerset County line defined by Lat. 38° 11.167' N, Long. 75° 59.338' W then running approximately 50° True to a point where the Dorchester County-Somerset County line meets a line running from point at or near the shore immediately adjacent to the Thomas Tigner house near Haines Point to the southwesterly most point of land on Clay Island defined by Lat. 38° 12.339' N, Long. 75° 57.552' W then running approximately 164° True to a point at or near the shore immediately adjacent to the Thomas Tignor house near Haines Point defined by Lat. 38° 10.771' N, Long. 75° 56.979' W.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Upper Thorofare. All the waters enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the shore at the beginning of the Upper Thorofare jetty defined by Lat. 38° 10.198' N, Long. 75° 56.833' W then running southwesterly to a point at or near the tip of the Upper Thorofare jetty defined by Lat. 38° 10.183' N, Long. 75° 56.864' W then running approximately 219° True to a point at or near the tip of the Lower Thorofare jetty defined by Lat. 38° 10.159' N, Long. 75° 56.890' W then running southerly along the jetty to a point on the shore defined by Lat. 38° 10.119' N, Long. 75° 56.874' W.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Lower Thorofare. All the waters enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near the western side of the entrance to Lower Thorofare defined by Lat. 38° 7.646' N, Long. 75° 56.834' W then running approximately 120° True to a point at or near the eastern side of the entrance to Lower Thorofare defined by Lat. 38° 7.606' N, Long. 75° 56.744' W.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Manokin River to State Line, Except as Provided in §H(8)(t).</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Manokin River. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near Pin Point defined by Lat. 38° 6.761' N, Long. 75° 56.568' W then running approximately 130° True to a point on the western side of the small island off of Pin Point defined by Lat. 38° 6.728' N, Long. 75° 56.517' W then running southeasterly along the shore to a point on the southeastern side of the small island off of Pin Point defined by Lat. 38° 6.717' N, Long. 75° 56.492' W then running approximately 126° True to a point offshore of Hazard Point defined by Lat. 38° 4.595' N, Long. 75° 52.736' W then running approximately 57° True to a point at or near Hazard Point defined by Lat. 38° 4.643' N, Long. 75° 52.649' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Hazard Cove. All the waters enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near Hazard Point defined by Lat. 38° 4.643' N, Long. 75° 52.649' W then running approximately 234° True to a point offshore of Hazard Point then running approximately 164° True to a point on the most westerly point of marsh on Pat Island defined by Lat. 38° 3.665' N, Long. 75° 52.403' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Big Annemessex River. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point on the most westerly point of marsh on Pat Island defined by Lat. 38° 3.665' N, Long. 75° 52.403' W then running approximately 156° True to a point at the east entrance of Thru Creek on Lawson’s Marsh defined by Lat. 38° 2.291' N, Long. 75° 51.607' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Little Annemessex River. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near Janes Island Point defined by Lat. 37° 58.474' N, Long. 75° 53.875' W then running approximately 162° True to a point at or near Great Point defined by Lat. 37° 57.165' N, Long. 75° 53.344' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Cedar Island Creek. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point on the north entrance of Cedar Island Creek defined by Lat. 37° 55.388' N, Long. 75° 53.754' W then running approximately 155° True to a point on the south entrance of Cedar Island Creek defined by Lat. 37° 55.045' N, Long. 75° 53.526' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Fishing Creek/Crooked Creek/Crooked Gut Creek. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near Watkins Point defined by Lat. 37° 54.739' N, Long. 75° 52.941' W then running approximately 69° True to a point on the western entrance of Crooked Creek defined by Lat. 37° 55.126' N, Long.75° 51.693' W then running approximately 53° True to a point at or near an island at the mouth of Crooked Creek defined by Lat. 37° 55.184' N, Long. 75° 51.606' W then running approximately 45° True to a point at or near Westward Point defined by Lat. 37° 55.378' N, Long. 75° 51.363' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Broad Creek. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near Westward Point defined by Lat. 37° 55.378' N, Long. 75° 51.363' then running approximately 77° True to a point at or near Eastward Point defined by Lat. 37° 55.459' N, Long. 75° 50.921' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Broad Creek Gut. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near Eastward Point defined by Lat. 37° 55.459' N, Long. 75° 50.921' W then running approximately 64° True to a point on the eastern entrance to Broad Creek Gut defined by Lat. 37° 55.658' N, Long. 75° 50.412' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Cow Gap Creek. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point on the eastern entrance to Broad Creek Gut defined by Lat. 37° 55.658' N, Long. 75° 50.412' W then running approximately 57° True to a point at or near Oystershell Point defined by Lat. 37° 55.868' N, Long. 75° 50.008' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Massey Creek/Little Ware Point Creek. All the waters upstream of line beginning at a point at or near Oystershell Point defined by Lat. 37° 55.868' N, Long. 75° 50.008' W then running approximately 51° True to a point at or near Ware Point defined by Lat. 37° 56.348' N, Long. 75° 49.264' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Ware Point Creek. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near Ware Point defined by Lat. 37° 56.348' N, Long. 75° 49.264' W then running approximately 40° True to a point on the eastern entrance to Ware Point Creek defined by Lat. 37° 56.475' N, Long. 75° 49.136' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>Unnamed Creek. All the waters enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or north of the eastern entrance to Ware Point Creek defined by Lat. 37° 56.546' N, Long. 75° 49.125' W then running approximately 355° True to a point at or near Long Point defined by Lat. 37° 56.759' N, Long. 75° 49.147' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>Ape Hole Creek. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near Long Point defined by Lat. 37° 56.759' N, Long. 75° 49.147' W then running approximately 50° True to a point at or near Gap Point defined by Lat. 37° 57.353' N, Long. 75° 48.246' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(n)</num>
          <text>Gunby Creek. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at the western entrance to Gunby Creek defined by Lat. 37° 58.364' N, Long. 75° 46.864' W then running approximately 92° True to a point at the eastern entrance to Gunby Creek defined by Lat. 37° 58.354' N, Long. 75° 46.404' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(o)</num>
          <text>East Creek. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near East Creek Point defined by Lat. 37° 58.234' N, Long. 75° 44.764' W then running approximately 95° True to a point on the western shore of Richardson Marsh defined by Lat. 37° 58.204' N, Long. 75° 44.328' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(p)</num>
          <text>Marumsco Creek. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point on shore at the western entrance of Marumsco Creek defined by Lat. 37° 58.635' N, Long. 75° 43.351' W then running approximately 89° True to a point on shore at the eastern entrance of Marumsco Creek defined by Lat. 37° 58.638' N, Long. 75° 42.785' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(q)</num>
          <text>Fair Island Canal. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at a point on the northern entrance to Cliftons Creek defined by Lat. 37° 57.752' N, Long. 75° 39.990' W then running approximately 164° True to a point at the extension of the southwestern entrance of Fair Island Canal defined by Lat. 37° 57.572' N, Long. 75° 39.922' W then running approximately 71° True to a point at the southwest entrance to the canal defined by Lat. 37° 57.641' N, Long. 75° 39.686' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(r)</num>
          <text>Pocomoke River. All the waters upstream of a line beginning at the northeasterly point on Fair Island on southside of Fair Island Canal defined by Lat. 37° 57.757' N, Long. 75° 39.351' W then running approximately 76° True to a point at the intersection of the Maryland/Virginia border and a line running from the northeasterly point on Fair Island on southside of Fair Island Canal to Bullbegger Point defined by Lat. 37° 57.837' N, Long. 75° 38.914' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(s)</num>
          <text>Smith Island. All of the waters of Smith Island, Chesapeake Bay, Kedges Straits, and Tangier Sound upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near the intersection of the Maryland/Virginia state line and the eastern (Tangier Sound) shoreline of Smith Island defined by Lat. 37° 57.205' N, Long. 75° 59.750' W then running along the Maryland/Virginia state line to a point at or near the intersection of the Maryland/Virginia state line and the western (Chesapeake Bay) shoreline of Smith Island defined by Lat. 37° 57.211' N, Long. 76° 2.643' W then northerly along the west shore of Smith Island to a point at or near the south side of Sheep Pen Gut at the beginning of the jetty defined by Lat. 37° 58.692' N, Long. 76° 2.754' W then running northwesterly along the jetty to a point at or near the tip of the south jetty at Sheep Pen Gut defined by Lat. 37° 58.774' N, Long. 76° 2.947' W then running approximately 26° True to the tip of the north jetty at Sheep Pen Gut defined by Lat. 37° 58.798' N, Long. 76° 2.932' W then running approximately 79° True along the jetty to a point along the west shore of Smith Island defined by Lat. 37° 58.815' N, Long. 76° 2.825' W then northerly along the shore to a point at or near Chaisey Point at the beginning of the south Big Thorofare/Goose Harbor jetty defined by Lat. 37° 59.791' N, Long. 76° 2.909' W then running approximately 296° True to a point at or near the tip of the south Big Thorofare/Goose Harbor jetty defined by Lat. 37° 59.924' N, Long. 76° 3.279' W then running approximately 0° True to a point at or near the tip of the north Big Thorofare/Goose Harbor jetty defined by Lat. 38° 0.074' N, Long. 76° 3.281' W then running approximately 36° True to a point at or near Channel Point north of Channel Island Gut defined by Lat. 38° 0.624' N, Long. 76° 2.794' W then running northerly along the west shore of Smith Island to a point at or near the tip of the south entrance to Lightning Knot Cove defined by Lat. 38° 1.083' N, Long. 76° 2.818' W then running approximately 0° True to a point at or near the tip of the north entrance to Lightning Knot Cove defined by Lat. 38° 1.156' N, Long. 76° 2.822' W then running northerly along the shore to a point at or near Fog Point defined by Lat. 38° 1.931' N, Long. 76° 2.394' then running easterly along the shore to a point at the western entrance to Fog Point Cove Creek defined by Lat. 38° 2.012' N, Long. 76° 1.859' W then running approximately 67° True to a point at or near the eastern shore at the entrance to Fog Point Creek defined by Lat. 38° 2.047' N, Long. 76° 1.761' W then running northeasterly along the shore to the western side of Bridge Creek at or near Bards Point defined by Lat. 38° 2.151' N, Long. 76° 1.651' W then running approximately 85° True to a point at or near the east shore of Bridge Creek defined by Lat. 38° 2.164' N, Long. 76° 1.432' W then running easterly along the shore to a point at or near Fishing Point on the northwestern side of Back Cove defined by Lat. 38° 2.212' N, Long. 76° 0.461' W then running approximately 136° True to a point on the southwestern side of Back Cove defined by Lat. 38° 1.435' N, Long. 75° 59.507' W then running approximately 100° True to a point north of Terrapin Sand Cove defined by Lat. 38° 1.387' N, Long. 75° 59.164' W then running approximately 118° True to a point at the former location of Terrapin Sands Point defined by Lat. 38° 0.950' N, Long. 75° 58.150' W then running approximately 197° True to a point at or near on the north side of the channel at Big Thorofare defined by Lat. 37° 58.129' N, Long. 75° 59.271' W then running approximately 187° True to a point at or near the south side of Big Thorofare defined by Lat. 37° 57.619' N, Long. 75° 59.353' W then running approximately 214° True to a point along the shore defined by Lat. 37° 57.281' N, Long. 75° 59.646' W then southerly along the shore to the point of beginning defined by Lat. 37° 57.205' N, Long. 75° 59.750' W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(t)</num>
          <text>Exception. Crab pots may be set from April 1st to June 15th, outside of marked channels in Tyler Creek, in the area upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near the intersection of the Maryland/Virginia state line and the west side of Tyler Creek defined by Lat. 37° 57.209' N, Long. 76° 1.061' W then running northerly along the western shore of Tyler Creek past Parks Ditch and Rhodes Point Gut to a point at or near the southside of the Canal defined by Lat. 37° 59.082' N, Long. 76° 1.272' W then running approximately 3° True to a point at or near the north side of The Canal defined by Lat. 37° 59.189' N, Long. 76° 1.266' W then running along the western shore of Tyler Creek to a point defined by Lat. 37° 59.554' N, Long. 76° 1.412' W then running approximately 114° True to a point at or near Easter Point defined by Lat. 37° 59.353' N, Long. 76° 0.846' W then running southerly along the east shore of Tyler Creek to a point at or near the intersection of the Maryland/Virginia state line and the east side of Tyler Creek defined by Lat. 37° 57.208' N, Long. 76° 0.342' W then running along Maryland/Virginia state line to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Atlantic Coastal Bays. Crab pots may not be set in waters designated as having a speed zone in accordance with <cite path="08.18.18.01">COMAR 08.18.18.01</cite>, <cite path="08.18.18.03">08.18.18.03</cite>, <cite path="08.18.18.05">08.18.18.05</cite>, and <cite path="08.18.18.06">08.18.18.06</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Crab pots may not be set in waters that are less than 4 feet deep at mean low tide except as provided below:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In Pocomoke Sound, all the waters shoreward of the Maryland-Virginia state line, starting with the junction with a line running from Bullbegger Point westward to the northeasternmost point of land on Fair Island defined by Lat. 37° 57.837' N, Long. 75° 38.914' W, then following the State line in a westerly direction to State line marker "A" defined by Lat. 37° 54.732' N, Long. 75° 48.065' W, thence northwesterly to Ware Point defined by Lat. 37° 56.348' N, Long. 75° 49.264' W.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In Tangier Sound, all the waters shoreward of a line drawn from the southern tip of Deal Island at Lower Thorofare defined by Lat. 38° 7.619' N, Long. 75° 56.993' W then running approximately 223° to Lower Thorofare entrance Red Nun "2" defined by Lat. 38° 7.363' N, Long. 75° 57.315' W then running approximately 338° to a point offshore of Twiggs Point defined by Lat. 38° 8.099' N, Long. 75° 57.677' W then running approximately 356° to a point at Haines Point Light Fl. 4 § defined by Lat. 38° 10.324' N, Long. 75° 57.871' W then running approximately 105° true to the northernmost tip of Deal Island defined by Lat. 38° 10.119' N, Long. 75° 56.874' W.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>In Tangier Sound, all the waters shoreward of a line drawn from Flatcap Point defined by Lat. 38° 1.981' N, Long. 75° 52.290' W then running approximately 208° true to Janes Island Light Fl. 4 § defined by Lat. 37° 57.803' N, 75° 55.109' W then running approximately 56° true to James Island Point defined by Lat. 37° 58.474' N, Long. 75° 53.875' W.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>All the waters of Tangier Sound, Pungers Cove and Sound Gut west of a line drawn from Muscle Hole Point defined by Lat. 38° 7.617' N, Long. 76° 0.817' W then running approximately 354° true to Sound Point defined by Lat. 38° 4.724' N, Long. 76° 0.403' W on South Marsh Island.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>In addition to the rivers and channels listed in <cite path="08.02.05.08">COMAR 08.02.05.08</cite>, a person may not set buoyed fish gear, including crab pots, in the following river or entrance channels:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Bush River — 100 yards each side of a line from G "29" Qk. Fl. G to G "3" Fl. G 2.5 §;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Middle River — 100 yards each side of a line from Pooles Island Light to "1" Qk. Fl. G to G "3" Fl. G 4 § and 100 yards each side of a line from R "2" Fl. R 4 § to "1" Qk. Fl. G;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Bodkin Creek — 100 yards channelward of a line extending northwesterly beginning at Bodkin Point Shoal Buoy 1, at or near Lat. 39°07'54"N., Long. 76°24'36"W., then running approximately 306° True to Bodkin Point Shoal Light 3, at or near Lat. 39°08'10"N., Long. 76°25'03"W., then running approximately 276° True to Bodkin Creek Approach Day Beacon 5, at or near Lat. 39°08'12"N., Long 76°25'28"W., then running approximately 276° True to Bodkin Creek Entrance Light 7, at or near Lat. 39°08'14"N., Long. 76°25'48"W., and 100 yards channelward of a line extending northwesterly beginning at Bodkin Creek Entrance Light 7, at or near Lat. 39°08'14"N., Long. 76°25'48"W., then running approximately 44° True toward Seven Foot Knoll Light, at or near Lat. 39°09'19"N., Long. 76°24'32"W., to the southwestern edge of the Craighill Channel Upper Range (Cutoff Channel), at or near Lat. 39°09'02"N., Long. 76°24'52"W.;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Gunpowder River — 100 yards each side of a line from G "1" Qk. Fl. G to R "4" Fl. R 4 § to R "6" Fl. R 4 § to R "8" Fl. R 4 § to G "9" Fl. G 4 §;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Magothy River — 100 yards each side of a line from Baltimore Light to Fl. G 4 § 14 ft. 4M "3";</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Whitehall Creek — 100 yards channelward of a line from Fl. 4 § 12 ft. 4M "2" inside Whitehall Creek to R "2" Fl. 2.5 § Bell;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Severn River — Channel marked by: C "1", R "2" Fl. 2.5 § Bell, C "3", R N "4", C "5", R N "6";</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Fishing Creek (Anne Arundel County) — 100 yards channelward of a line from Fl. 4 § "3" to Fl. R 2.5 § 15 ft. 4M "2" thence a 100 yard wide channel eastward, (090° True) for a distance of 1/2 nautical mile;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>South River — 200 yards channelward of a line from Thomas Point Light to Fl. 2.5 § 15 ft. 4M "4" and 100 yards each side of a line 1 Qk. Fl. 10 ft. 5M to Fl. R 2.5 § 15 ft. 4M "4";</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>West River — 100 yards each side of a line running from "73" Fl. G 4 § to 1 Qk. Fl. 10 ft. 5M, then 200 yards channelward from a line running from 1 Qk. Fl. 10 ft. 5M to Fl. R 2.5 § 15 ft. 4M "2" and G "3";</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Poplar Island — 200 yards channelward of a line from Fl. 4 § 14 ft. 4M "1" in Knapps Narrows Channel to "1" Fl. 4 § 14 ft. 4M;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Poplar Island Narrows Channel — 200 yards channelward of a line from "1" Fl. 4 § 14 ft. 4M to G "3", R "4", C "5", and R N "8" (closed to potting only from Memorial Day to Labor Day);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>Pocomoke River — 10 yards channelward of a line running from Williams Point, defined by Lat. 37°57.20'N., Long. 75°39.33'W., northward to Fl. "23", defined by Lat. 37°57.88'N., Long. 75°39.05'W.;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>Rock Hall — 100 yards southwesterly of a line from Fl. G 4 § 5M "5" PA Bell to G C "1";</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>Sandy Point State Park — Within 100 yards of Qk. Fl. 11 ft. PA at the breakwater entrance;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>Chesapeake Beach — 100 yards north of a line from Fl. G 6 § "3" PA to Fl. G 4 § 4M "1";</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>Flag Harbor — Within 100 yards of the stone jetty of Flag Harbor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>Patuxent River — 35 yards each side of a line extending northeasterly beginning at a point at or near the mouth of the Patuxent River, defined by Lat. 38°18.86'N., Long. 76°24.61'W.; then running approximately 52° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°19.57'N., Long. 76°23.47'W.; then running approximately 51° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°19.98'N., Long. 76°22.82'W.; then running approximately 52° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°20.47'N., Long. 76°22.03'W.;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>St. Clements Bay — St. Patrick Creek — Channel marked by Fl. R 4 § 14 ft. 3M "2" PA westerly to the entrance to St. Patrick Creek R "6";</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>St. George Island Straits — Channel marked by GPA "3" northeasterly to the bridge between Straits Point and St. George Island;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>Honga River — Tar Bay — 50 yards channelward of a line from Fishing Creek Bridge westerly to Fl. R 4 § 16 ft. 4M "8", Fl. 4 § 4M "7", Fl. R 4 § 15 ft. 3M "6", Fl. 4 § 5M "5", Fl. R 4 § 15 ft. 3M "4", Fl. 4 § 16 ft. 5M "3", Fl. R 4 § 14 ft. 3M "2", Fl. G 4 § 14 ft. 6M "1";</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>Honga River — Middle Hooper Island — 50 yards channelward of a line from Middle Hooper Island Bridge to Fl. G 4 § 15 ft. 3M "1";</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>Deal Island — 50 yards channelward of a line from Deal Island Harbor to Fl. R 6 § "6", Fl. G 2.5 § 15 ft. 3M "1";</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(24)</num>
        <text>Wenona — 50 yards channelward of a line from Wenona Harbor to Qk. Fl. "6" to Fl. R 4 § "4";</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(25)</num>
        <text>Pocomoke Sound — Broad Creek — 50 yards channelward of a line northerly from Fl. 2.5 § 14 ft. 4M "2", R "4", R "6" into Broad Creek;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(26)</num>
        <text>Pocomoke River — 50 yards channelward of a line easterly from Fl. 4 § "1", R N "2", C "3", R N "4", C "5";</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(27)</num>
        <text>Smith Island — 50 yards channelward of a line easterly from the entrance to Smith Island to R "8", Fl. G 4 § 14 ft. "3", R "2", Fl. 2.5 § 14 ft. "1";</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(28)</num>
        <text>Isle Of Wight Bay — Eastern Channel, 50 yards channelward of a line southward from day marker "13", C "11", R N "10", G C "9", R N "8", G C "7", R N "6", C "5", C "3", R N "2", C "1", Fl. R 4 § 14 ft. 3M "2", G "1A" to U.S. Route 50 Bridge;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(29)</num>
        <text>Isle Of Wight Bay — Western Channel, 50 yards channelward of a line southward from Fl. R 2.5 § "14", R N "12", R N "10", R N "8", R N "6", C "1";</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(30)</num>
        <text>Isle Of Wight Bay — 100 feet channelward of a line from Ocean Pines Yacht Club easterly to Fl. R 2 § 6 ft. "4", Fl. G 2 § 6 ft. "3", Fl. 2 § 6 ft. "2";</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(31)</num>
        <text>Sinepuxent Bay — 50 yards channelward of a line southward from C "1", R N "2", C "3", Fl. G 4 § 15 ft. 5M "5", C "5A", R "6", Fl. R 4 § 15 ft. 4M "8", R "10", Fl. G 4 § 4M "11", R "12", Fl. G 4 § 16 ft. 4M "13", R "14", Fl. G 4 § 16 ft. 3M "15", R "16", G "17", Fl. G 4 § 16 ft. 3M "19", R "20", G "21", G "23", Fl. G 4 § 16 ft. 3M "25", G "27", G "27A", R "28", G "29", Fl. G 4 § 16 ft. 4M "31", G "33", R "34", Fl. 4 § 14 ft. 5M "35", G "37", Fl. G 4 § 14 ft. 3M "39";</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(32)</num>
        <text>Chincoteague Bay — 50 yards channelward of a line from Public Landing Harbor easterly to Fl. G 2.5 § 15 ft. 3M "1";</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(33)</num>
        <text>Chincoteague Bay — 50 yards channelward of a line from the entrance to Tanhouse Creek easterly to Fl. R 2.5 § 14 ft. 4 M "2";</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(34)</num>
        <text>Herring Bay — In a channel defined by corner coordinates beginning at the northeast corner at Lat. 38°44'31"N., Long. 76°30'50"W., and then southerly to Lat. 38°44'25"N., Long. 76°30'50"W., and then westerly to Lat. 38°44'22"N., Long. 76°31'47"W., and then northerly to Lat. 38°44'28"N., Long. 76°31'48"W., and then easterly to the point of origin;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(35)</num>
        <text>Susquehanna Flats — 100 yards either side of line from Junction Buoy "A" Fl. (2+1) 6 § to G "1" Fl. G 2.5 § to R N "2" to Fl. G "3"; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(36)</num>
        <text>Susquehanna Flats — 200 yards west of a line from Junction Buoy "A" Fl. (2+1) 6 § to R "2" Fl. R 4 §</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|02|03|.08">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Egg-Bearing Female Crabs.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="08|02|03|.08|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, a person may not possess, transport, or pack a female crab from which the egg pouch or bunion has been removed, or an egg-bearing female crab known as the sponge crab.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A female crab from which the egg pouch or bunion has been removed, or an egg-bearing female crab known as the sponge crab may be imported into Maryland from another state by a dealer or crab processing plant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If accompanied by a bill of sale or bill of lading from the jurisdiction of origin; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Only during the time period specified in the public notice issued in accordance with <cite path="08|02|03|.08|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Public Notice.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In consultation with blue crab industry advisory groups, the Department shall issue a public notice to establish a time period of 71 consecutive days when a female crab from which the egg pouch or bunion has been removed, or an egg-bearing female crab known as the sponge crab may be imported into Maryland from another state.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The import time period may not begin prior to April 10 or end after July 20.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The public notice shall be published on the Department’s website by April 1 of each year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Secretary shall make a reasonable effort to disseminate a public notice issued under this section through various other media so that an affected individual has a reasonable opportunity to be informed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A violation of the restrictions set by the Secretary in accordance with section is a violation of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|02|03|.09">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Recreational Crabbing Licenses — Chesapeake Bay and Its Tidal Tributaries.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Recreational Crabbing License.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="08|02|03|.09|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>, an individual who catches or attempts to catch crabs for recreational purposes in the waters of the Chesapeake Bay and its tidal tributaries shall pay the fee and obtain a recreational crabbing license in order to use the following gear to catch crabs:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Trotline;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Collapsible traps or net rings;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Up to ten eel pots for catching the individual's own bait, which are:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Clearly labeled with the individual's name;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Not placed in a buoy free channel as listed in <cite path="|08|02|03|.07|H.">Regulation .07H of this chapter</cite> or <cite path="08.02.05.08|F.">COMAR 08.02.05.08F</cite>; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Used only for catching eels; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Seines.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The annual fee for a recreational crabbing license to catch or attempt to catch crabs for recreational purposes from the waters of the Chesapeake Bay and its tidal tributaries with the gear specified in <cite path="08|02|03|.09|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite> is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>For a Maryland resident — $5;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For a Maryland resident, in possession of a Maryland Chesapeake Bay and coastal sport fishing license or a resident consolidated senior sport fishing license — $2;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>For a nonresident — $10.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An individual who has purchased a recreational crabbing license shall have the license in possession when:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Engaged in crabbing for recreational purposes with the gear listed under <cite path="08|02|03|.09|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>In possession of more crabs than provided for in the daily catch limits set forth in Regulation .10A(2)(a), A(3)(a) and (b), and A(4)(a) of this chapter and not on a boat that has been licensed as a recreational crab boat.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Recreational Crabbing Boat License.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A recreational crabbing boat license authorizes an individual to use the following gear to catch or attempt to catch crabs in the licensed boat in the Chesapeake Bay and its tidal tributaries:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Trotline; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Collapsible traps or net rings.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The annual fee for a recreational crabbing boat license to catch or attempt to catch crabs for recreational purposes from the waters of the Chesapeake Bay and its tidal tributaries with the gear specified in <cite path="08|02|03|.09|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite> is $15.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>To the recreational crabbing boat licensee, the Department shall issue:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A recreational crabbing boat decal; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A complimentary recreational crabbing license.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="08|02|03|.09|B.|(5)">§B(5) of this regulation</cite>, the recreational crabbing boat decal:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Shall be permanently affixed and displayed on either side of the forward half of the vessel for which issued;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is not transferable; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Shall, when displayed, exempt all persons aboard from the requirement of possessing an individual license to crab recreationally.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Exemption for Crabbing Boat Decals. If the crabbing boat decal is not permanently affixed to the vessel, all persons aboard are exempt from the requirement of possessing an individual license to crab recreationally only if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The individual who purchased the crabbing boat decal is present on the vessel;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The individual who purchased the crabbing boat decal is in possession of the proof of purchase issued by the Department; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The crabbing boat decal was purchased within the previous 10 calendar days.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Complimentary Recreational Crabbing License.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Department shall issue a complimentary recreational crabbing license to an individual who purchases a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Recreational crabbing boat license; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Chesapeake Bay and coastal sport fishing boat license in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-745">Natural Resources Article, §4-745(d)(2), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The individual issued the complimentary recreational crabbing license has the same restrictions as an individual with a recreational crabbing license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The recreational crabbing boat license and the complimentary recreational crabbing license count as a single license for the individual who purchases the recreational crabbing boat license.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Private Waterfront Property Crab Pot Registration.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Only a person who owns or leases private property along the shore of the Chesapeake Bay and its tidal tributaries may obtain a private waterfront property crab pot registration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person who owns or leases private property along the shore of the Chesapeake Bay and its tidal tributaries shall obtain a private waterfront property crab pot registration in order to use a crab pot from the person’s property.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>There is no fee for a private waterfront property crab pot registration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Exceptions. An individual who catches or attempts to catch crabs for recreational purposes in the waters of the Chesapeake Bay and its tidal tributaries is not required to have a recreational crabbing license if the individual:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Uses any of the following gear:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A dipnet;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A handline; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Up to two crab pots, if qualified to use crab pots as set forth in <cite path="|08|02|03|.07|D.">Regulation .07D of this chapter</cite>;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is assisting an individual who has a recreational crabbing license; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Is crabbing for recreational purposes from a boat that has been licensed by the Department as a recreational crabbing boat.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>General.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A recreational crabbing license, recreational crabbing boat license, or private waterfront property crab pot registration is valid for 365 days following the date of issuance.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A recreational crabbing license, recreational crabbing boat license, or private waterfront property crab pot registration may be obtained from any authorized agent of the Department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Department may designate a person engaged in a commercial enterprise as an agent to sell recreational crabbing licenses, recreational crabbing boat licenses, or issue private waterfront property crab pot registrations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>An agent may retain:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>50 cents for each recreational crabbing license issued by the agent; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>$1.50 for each recreational crabbing boat license issued by the agent.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|02|03|.10">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Recreational Crabbing Catch and Possession Limits — Chesapeake Bay and its Tidal Tributaries.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Daily Catch and Possession Limits.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An individual exempt from the licensing requirements of <cite path="|08|02|03|.09">Regulation .09 of this chapter</cite> is considered an unlicensed individual and may not exceed the catch and possession limits for an unlicensed individual.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Daily catch and possession limits for individuals harvesting crabs from shore or from crab pots.</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(a) Unlicensed individual</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">2 dozen male <br/>hard crabs</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">1 dozen soft crabs,1 dozen male peeler crabs, or a combination of 1 dozen soft crabs and male peeler crabs</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(b) Licensed individual</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">1 bushel male hard crabs if storing crabs in a bushel<br/><br/>6 dozen male hard crabs if storing crabs in any container other than a bushel</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">2 dozen soft crabs, 2 dozen male peeler crabs, or a combination of 2 dozen soft crabs and male peeler crabs</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Daily catch and possession boat limits for a vessel without a recreational crabbing boat license.</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(a) One unlicensed individual on board an unlicensed vessel</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">2 dozen male hard crabs</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">1 dozen soft crabs,1 dozen male peeler crabs, or a combination of 1 dozen soft crabs and male peeler crabs</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(b) Two or more unlicensed individuals on board an unlicensed vessel</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">4 dozen male hard crabs</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">1 dozen soft crabs, 1 dozen male peeler crabs, or a combination of 1 dozen soft crabs and male peeler crabs</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(c) One licensed individual or one licensed individual accompanied by any number of unlicensed individuals on board an unlicensed vessel</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">1 bushel male hard crabs if storing crabs in a bushel<br/><br/>6 dozen male hard crabs if storing crabs in any container other than a bushel</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">2 dozen soft crabs, 2 dozen male peeler crabs, or a combination of 2 dozen soft crabs and male peeler crabs</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(d) Two or more licensed individuals or two or more licensed individuals accompanied by any number of unlicensed individuals on board an unlicensed vessel</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">2 bushels male hard crabs if storing crabs in bushels<br/><br/>12 dozen male hard crabs if storing crabs in any container other than a bushel</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">2 dozen soft crabs, 2 dozen male peeler crabs, or a combination of 2 dozen soft crabs and male peeler crabs</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Daily catch and possession boat limits for a vessel with a recreational crabbing boat license.</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(a) One or more unlicensed individuals on board a licensed vessel</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">1 bushel male hard crabs if storing crabs in a bushel<br/><br/>6 dozen male hard crabs if storing crabs in any container other than a bushel</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">2 dozen soft crabs,2 dozen male peeler crabs, or a combination of 2 dozen soft crabs and male peeler crabs</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(b) One licensed individual on board a licensed vessel</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">1 bushel male hard crabs if storing crabs in a bushel<br/><br/>6 dozen male hard crabs if storing crabs in any container other than a bushel</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">2 dozen soft crabs, 2 dozen male peeler crabs, or a combination of 2 dozen soft crabs and male peeler crabs</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(c) An individual who purchased a recreational crabbing boat license accompanied by any number of unlicensed individuals on board a licensed vessel</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">1 bushel male hard crabs if storing crabs in a bushel<br/><br/>6 dozen male hard crabs if storing crabs in any container other than a bushel</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">2 dozen soft crabs, 2 dozen male peeler crabs, or a combination of 2 dozen soft crabs and male peeler crabs</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(d) Two or more licensed individuals accompanied by any number of unlicensed individuals on board a licensed vessel</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">2 bushels male hard crabs if storing crabs in bushels<br/><br/>12 dozen male hard crabs if storing crabs in any container other than a bushel</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">2 dozen soft crabs, 2 dozen male peeler crabs, or a combination of 2 dozen soft crabs and male peeler crabs<br/><br/>The catch limit is a bushel per licensed individual when using a bushel to hold male crabs. When not using a bushel the catch limit is 6 dozen male hard crabs per licensed individual.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">(e) One licensed individual, who is not the owner of the licensed vessel, accompanied by any number of unlicensed individuals on board a licensed vessel</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">2 bushels male hard crabs if storing crabs in bushels<br/><br/>12 dozen male hard crabs if storing crabs in any container other than a bushel</td>
                <td data-vertical-align="middle">2 dozen soft crabs, 2 dozen male peeler crabs, or a combination of 2 dozen soft crabs and male peeler crabs<br/><br/>The catch limit is a bushel per licensed individual when using a bushel to hold male crabs. When not using a bushel the catch limit is 6 dozen male hard crabs per licensed individual.</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Female Hard Crabs and Female Peelers.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="08|02|03|.10|B.|(2)">§B(2) of this regulation</cite>, an individual may not catch or possess female hard crabs or female peelers.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Exception.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Female crabs are accompanied by a bill of sale; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Individual is not catching or attempting to catch crabs.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|02|03|.11">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Season and Time for Catching Crabs.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Commercial.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An individual licensed to catch crabs for sale may remove crabs from commercial gear in the Chesapeake Bay and its tidal tributaries only during the following time periods:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Trotlines:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Except as provided in <cite path="08|02|03|.11|A.|(1)|(a)|(iii)">§A(1)(a)(iii) of this regulation</cite>, between 1 hour before sunrise to 9 hours after sunrise during the period May through September;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Between 1/2 hour before sunrise and 9½ hours after sunrise during April, October, November, and December; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Between 2 hours before sunrise to 9 hours after sunrise on Memorial Day, Juneteenth National Independence Day, July 4, Labor Day, and the day immediately preceding each of those holidays; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Crab Scrapes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Except as provided in <cite path="08|02|03|.11|A.|(1)|(b)|(iii)">§A(1)(b)(iii) of this regulation</cite>, between 1 hour before sunrise to 9 hours after sunrise during the period May through September;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Between sunrise and 10 hours after sunrise during April and October; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Between 2 hours before sunrise to 9 hours after sunrise on Memorial Day, Juneteenth National Independence Day, July 4, Labor Day, and the day immediately preceding each of those holidays; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Crab pots, bank traps, channel pounds, collapsible traps, net rings, handlines, dip nets, and pound nets:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Except as provided in <cite path="08|02|03|.11|A.|(1)|(c)|(ii)">§A(1)(c)(ii) of this regulation</cite>, between 1/2 hour before sunrise to 7½ hours after sunrise; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Between 1½ hours before sunrise to 7½ hours after sunrise on Memorial Day, Juneteenth National Independence Day, July 4, Labor Day, and the day immediately preceding each of those holidays.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not catch crabs using a crab scrape from October 31 to April 14, inclusive.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An individual licensed to catch crabs for sale may set or place overboard scrapes only during the following time periods:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Except as provided in <cite path="08|02|03|.11|A.|(3)|(c)">§A(3)(c) of this regulation</cite>, between 1 hour before sunrise to 9 hours after sunrise during the period May through September;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Between sunrise and 10 hours after sunrise during April and October; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Between 2 hours before sunrise to 9 hours after sunrise on Memorial Day, Juneteenth National Independence Day, July 4, Labor Day, and the day immediately preceding each of those holidays.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Crab Pot Set Times. Crab pots may only be set:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>During the time periods established in <cite path="08|02|03|.11|A.|(1)|(c)">§A(1)(c) of this regulation</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If already onboard a boat at the end of the time periods established in <cite path="08|02|03|.11|A.|(1)|(c)">§A(1)(c) of this regulation</cite>, for 1 hour after the end of the time periods established in <cite path="08|02|03|.11|A.|(1)|(c)">§A(1)(c) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Time limits specified in this regulation are not applicable to the fishing of bank traps before May 1.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Recreational.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="08|02|03|.11|B.|(2)">§B(2) of this regulation</cite>, a person may not set any recreational crabbing gear or catch crabs for recreational purposes during:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>May through September between:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>5 p.m. and 1/2 hour before sunrise in the main Chesapeake Bay; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Sunset and 1/2 hour before sunrise in tidal tributaries of the Chesapeake Bay; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>April, October, November, and December between:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>5 p.m. and 1/2 hour after sunrise in the main Chesapeake Bay; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Sunset and 1/2 hour after sunrise in tidal tributaries of the Chesapeake Bay.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Crab pots, dip nets, and handlines. At all times during the recreational season for crabbing, a person may use:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Crab pots on private property that have been registered in accordance with <cite path="|08|02|03|.09">Regulation .09 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Dip nets; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Handlines.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A person may not catch blue crabs in the Chesapeake Bay and its tidal tributaries from December 16 through March 31, inclusive.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|02|03|.12">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Special Regulations for Crabbing in Worcester County.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Structural Requirements of Crab Pots. Notwithstanding Regulation .07A and B of this chapter, a crab pot set in the coastal bays of the Atlantic Ocean and their tidal tributaries shall have one unobstructed 2-5/16 inch cull ring on a side panel of the upper compartment and one 2-5/16 inch cull ring on a panel at the lower compartment of the crab pot. The cull ring is not required in a crab pot constructed with unstretched mesh measuring less than 1½ inches or at least 2 inches on each side.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Daily Catch Limits.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Commercial. The daily catch limit in the coastal bays of the Atlantic Ocean and their tidal tributaries is 25 bushels, 16 lugs, or 10 barrels per commercial boat.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Recreational. The daily catch limit in the waters of the coastal bays of the Atlantic Ocean and their tidal tributaries is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>1 bushel per individual if storing crabs in a bushel;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>6 dozen crabs per individual if storing crabs in any container other than a bushel;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>2 bushels per boat if two or more individuals are on the boat and storing crabs in bushels; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>12 dozen crabs per boat if two or more individuals are on the boat and storing crabs in any container other than bushels.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Seasons for Catching Crabs.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Commercial. A person licensed to catch crabs for sale may not catch crabs in the coastal bays of the Atlantic Ocean and their tidal tributaries between October 31 and April 1.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Recreational. A person may not catch crabs for recreational purposes in the coastal bays of the Atlantic Ocean and their tidal tributaries between December 31 and April 1.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Commercial Daily Time Restrictions. A person licensed to catch crabs for sale may remove crabs from commercial gear and set or retrieve crab pots in the coastal bays of the Atlantic Ocean and their tidal tributaries only during the following time periods:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Between sunrise and 8½ hours after sunrise during April and October;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="08|02|03|.12|D.|(3)">§D(3) of this regulation</cite>, between ½ hour before sunrise to 8 hours after sunrise during the period May through September; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Between 1½ hours before sunrise to 8 hours after sunrise on Memorial Day, Juneteenth National Independence Day, July 4, Labor Day, and the day immediately preceding each of those holidays.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Gear Restrictions. A person may not catch crabs in the coastal bays of the Atlantic Ocean and their tidal tributaries by scrape.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Landing Provision. Crabs caught in the waters of Worcester County may be landed out of the State.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Commercial Harvest of Crabs from Finfish Gear.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Notwithstanding Regulations <cite path="|08|02|03|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|08|02|03|.07">.07</cite> of this chapter, an individual licensed to harvest both crabs and finfish for commercial purposes may catch crabs from pound nets.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The harvest and possession of crabs from a pound net is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Prohibited on any day during which a licensee is otherwise prohibited from harvesting crabs as provided in <cite path="|08|02|03|.14">Regulation .14 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Restricted to the seasons and times provided in Regulations .11 and .12 of this chapter;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Restricted by the size limits provided in <cite path="|08|02|03|.14">Regulation .14 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Restricted to a maximum of 2 bushels or 1 lug of male crabs per licensee per day; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Restricted to the daily maximum number of female crabs allowed by the individual's license type.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Notwithstanding <cite path="08.02.25.04">COMAR 08.02.25.04</cite>, a licensee may only harvest or possess crabs from a pound net or combination of pound nets registered in the licensee's name.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|02|03|.14">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>General.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Recreational.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except for crab pots from private property, dipnets, or handlines, a person may not set any crabbing gear or catch crabs for recreational purposes on Wednesdays in the Chesapeake Bay and its tidal tributaries.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When a State or federal holiday falls on a Wednesday or Thursday, recreational crabbing is permitted on the Wednesday of that week.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An individual may not offer to sell or sell crabs that were caught for recreational purposes.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>An individual may not knowingly buy or offer to buy crabs which were caught for recreational purposes.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>An individual licensed to provide services as a fishing guide or to fish recreationally in the Chesapeake Bay and its tidal tributaries may possess any number of soft crabs or male peeler crabs for the purposes of fishing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>An individual licensed to catch crabs for commercial purposes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>May catch crabs for recreational purposes with recreational crabbing gear without paying the fee for recreational crabbing set forth in <cite path="|08|02|03|.09">Regulation .09 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has the same restrictions as an individual with a recreational crabbing license when engaged in recreational crabbing activities.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Commercial — General.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person licensed to catch crabs for sale may not set or retrieve gear or catch crabs for commercial purposes in the Chesapeake Bay and its tidal tributaries on Sundays and Mondays unless the person:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Declares intent under <cite path="08|02|03|.14|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is granted an alternate day off under <cite path="08|02|03|.14|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Is operating as a licensee's authorized user on the vessel designated in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-701">Natural Resources Article, §4-701, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Is assisting as an unlicensed crew member on another licensee's vessel.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person who is granted an alternate day off under <cite path="08|02|03|.14|D.">§D of this regulation</cite> may not set or retrieve gear or catch crabs for commercial purposes on the alternate day off.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The vessel of a person licensed to catch crabs for sale may not be used to set or retrieve gear or catch crabs for commercial purposes on the day or days on which the vessel's owner may not set or retrieve gear or catch crabs for commercial purposes.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A person licensed to catch crabs for commercial purposes, who declares under <cite path="08|02|03|.14|C.|(1)">§C(1) of this regulation</cite>, may set or retrieve gear or catch crabs for commercial purposes on a Sunday or Monday of a particular week if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A State or federal holiday falls on the Sunday or Monday, or the immediately preceding Saturday; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Sunday or Monday precedes a State or federal holiday that falls on a Tuesday, Wednesday, Thursday, or Friday of the particular week.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Mature female hard crabs shall be kept in separate bushels, lugs, or barrels from male hard crabs or peeler crabs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Mature female hard crabs on board a vessel shall be stored in the same type of containers of similar dimensions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Male hard crabs on board a vessel shall be stored in the same type of containers of similar dimensions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Except as specified in <cite path="08|02|03|.14|F.|(2)">§F(2) of this regulation</cite>, an individual licensed to catch crabs for commercial purposes may not catch or possess in the Chesapeake Bay and its tidal tributaries more than:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Six mature female hard crabs per container smaller than a barrel of male crabs; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>13 mature female hard crabs per barrel of male crabs.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Beginning in 2010, an individual with a limited crab harvester (LCC) license will be considered as limited crab harvester  frozen license status, as specified in <cite path="08|02|03|.14|F.|(2)|(b)">§F(2)(b) of this regulation</cite>, if that license is not designated as a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Limited crab harvester  active license; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Limited crab harvester  male only license.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>The commercial female crab daily catch limit shall be determined by the license type based on the abundance target for spawning age crabs recommended by the Chesapeake Bay Stock Assessment Committee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="08|02|03|.14|B.|(11)">§B(11) of this regulation</cite>, an individual licensed to catch crabs for commercial purposes may not harvest or possess more mature female hard crabs daily than the catch limit specified by the individual's license type.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="08|02|03|.14|B.|(11)">§B(11) of this regulation</cite>, more than two licensees' daily catch limits from 1 day may not be harvested from, carried on, or possessed on a vessel while the licensees are on board.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>An individual may possess and transport crabs harvested from the waters of the Potomac River or Virginia if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The individual is not engaged in harvesting crabs in Maryland waters while the crabs harvested in the waters of the Potomac River or Virginia are on board the vessel; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The individual is in possession of a Virginia commercial crab harvester license or Potomac River Fisheries Commission commercial license.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>A float used for holding or shedding peelers shall have a base that is a minimum of 16 square feet.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>An individual commercially harvesting crabs aboard a vessel may only have crabs that are commercially harvested on board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Closed Day Declaration of Intent.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person licensed to catch crabs for sale and who wishes to set or retrieve gear or catch crabs on one of the required days off in <cite path="08|02|03|.14|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite> shall declare that person's intent to set or retrieve gear or catch crabs in the Chesapeake Bay and its tidal tributaries for commercial purposes on one of the required days off as specified in <cite path="08|02|03|.14|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Display of Declaration. The letters for the abbreviation of the day off shall be identified and displayed on the vessel and shall be painted or firmly attached to the port side near the stern of the vessel as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The letters shall be positioned in such a manner as to be clearly visible to persons in passing boats;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The letters shall be plain vertical block characters of not less than 3 inches in height and shall contrast with the color of the background;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The letters "SUN" shall be displayed as the abbreviation for Sundays; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The letters "MON" shall be displayed as the abbreviation for Monday.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person licensed to catch crabs for sale who declares a day off under <cite path="08|02|03|.14|C.|(1)">§C(1) of this regulation</cite> shall declare a Sunday or Monday day off only at the time of license renewal or issuance on forms provided by the Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Alternate Closed Day.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person licensed to catch crabs for sale may apply to the Department for an alternate to the closed days specified in <cite path="08|02|03|.14|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite>. The Department may grant a licensee's request for an alternate closed day if the licensee demonstrates the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Imposition of substantial hardship on the licensee's exercise of religion by observing one of the closed days specified in <cite path="08|02|03|.14|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Absence of substantial hardship on the licensee's exercise of religion by observing the alternate closed day requested in the application.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An alternate closed day shall be displayed on the vessel in the manner set forth in <cite path="08|02|03|.14|C.|(2)">§C(2) of this regulation</cite> using the first three letters of the day of the week.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A licensee who is granted an alternate closed day may set gear and catch crabs on the closed days specified in <cite path="08|02|03|.14|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A person licensed to catch crabs for sale who declares a day off under <cite path="08|02|03|.14|D.|(1)">§D(1) of this regulation</cite> shall declare an alternate day off only at the time of license renewal or issuance on forms provided by the Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Notwithstanding <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-809">Natural Resources Article, §4-809, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, a person may not:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Catch or possess more than 6 hard crabs per container smaller than a barrel or 13 hard crabs per barrel which measure less than the minimum size specified in these regulations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Possess hard crabs imported from another State which:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Measure less than 5 inches across the shell from tip to tip of the spike;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Do not comply with the tolerance limits of the jurisdiction of origin;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Are not accompanied by a bill of sale or bill of lading from the jurisdiction of origin; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Were not caught in full compliance with the laws of the jurisdiction of origin;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>From April 1 through July 14, catch or possess a hard crab which measures less than 5 inches across the shell from tip to tip of the spike, from the waters of the Chesapeake Bay and its tidal tributaries, except that the minimum size of crabs does not apply to mature female crabs, identified by the apron;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>After July 14, catch or possess a hard crab which measures less than 5¼ inches across the shell from tip to tip of the spike from the waters of the Chesapeake Bay and its tidal tributaries, except that the minimum size of crabs does not apply to mature female crabs, identified by the apron;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Catch or possess a hard crab which measures less than 5 inches across the shell from tip to tip of the spike from the waters of Worcester County, except that the minimum size of crabs does not apply to mature female crabs, identified by the apron;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="08|02|03|.14|E.|(7)">§E(7) of this regulation</cite>, catch or possess more than 10 peeler crabs per bushel or more than 20 per float which are:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Less than 3-1/4 inches across the shell from tip to tip of the spike during the period from April 1 through July 14; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Less than 3-1/2 inches across the shell from tip to tip of the spike during the period from July 15 through December 15;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Catch or possess more than 10 female peeler crabs per bushel or more than 20 per float which are less than 3½ inches across the shell from tip to tip of the spike in the Chesapeake Bay and its tidal tributaries during the period from April 1, 2015 through December 15, 2015; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Catch or possess more than one soft crab per 2 dozen soft crabs which is less than 3½ inches across the shell from tip to tip of the spike.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Limited Crab Harvester.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Latent Effort Limited Crab Harvester License.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A limited crab harvester (LCC) authorization of a tidal fish license that has no reported crab harvest between January 1, 2004 and December 15, 2008 on reports submitted to the Department by January 30, 2009, shall be determined to be a latent effort limited crab harvester license, except for those licenses specified in <cite path="08|02|03|.14|F.|(1)|(b)">§F(1)(b) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Exceptions to Latent Effort Designation. The following are exceptions to the latent effort designation:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>An LCC authorization received through the apprenticeship program;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>An LCC authorization received through a permanent license transfer between August 1, 2006 and July 8, 2009;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>An LCC authorization assigned to an individual who provides appropriate documentation of active military service during the period January 1, 2004 and January 30, 2009;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>An LCC assigned to an individual who completed a successful female bushel limit hardship appeal in 2008; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>An LCC assigned to an individual who currently resides and has resided for at least 5 years on an island in the State that is at least 3 miles from the mainland.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Latent Effort Limited Crab Harvester Status.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An individual with a license that has been determined to be a latent effort license as described in <cite path="08|02|03|.14|F.|(1)">§F(1) of this regulation</cite> is required to have declared their LCC license as a limited crab harvester — male only as described in <cite path="08|02|03|.14|F.|(2)|(b)">§F(2)(b) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An individual with a limited crab harvester license — male only status:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Shall only harvest male crabs beginning on April 1, 2010;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>May not harvest females at any time regardless of the blue crab population target level being achieved for 3 consecutive years;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Shall renew the license annually in accordance with the schedule and fees designated for a LCC authorization in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-701">Natural Resources Article, §4-701, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>May apply to the Department for a permanent or temporary transfer of the license through a family, business, or beneficiary transfer as described in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-701">Natural Resources Article, §4-701, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The latent effort license status may not be modified after declaration even if the license has been transferred to a new owner.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Conditions for using an LCC male only authorization as one of the required authorizations to upgrade to an unlimited tidal fish authorization are described in <cite path="08.02.01.05|I.">COMAR 08.02.01.05I</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Notwithstanding <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-701">Natural Resources Article, §4-701, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, any LCC which was previously frozen due to latent license status as described in <cite path="08|02|03|.14|F.|(1)">§F(1) of this regulation</cite> will not be required to pay the authorization fee for the 2012 commercial crabbing season.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Public Notice.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Secretary may establish or modify catch limits or modify seasons for blue crabs in order to implement the Chesapeake Bay Blue Crab Fishery Management Plan by issuing a public notice on the Department's website.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The public notice shall state its effective hour and date and shall be published on the Department's website at least 48 hours in advance of the effective hour and date.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Secretary shall make a reasonable effort to disseminate a public notice issued under this section through various other media so that an affected person has a reasonable opportunity to be informed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A violation of the restrictions set by the Secretary in accordance with this section is a violation of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|02|03|.15">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Crabbing Charters.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>This regulation applies to any trip to catch crabs offered by a tidal fish licensee to an individual or individuals for any form of compensation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Any individual receiving compensation from customers for any trip to catch crabs shall be in possession of the appropriate federal licenses.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An individual who, in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-701">Natural Resources Article, §4-701, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, is licensed as a fishing guide, is licensed as a master fishing guide or operates a vessel for a master fishing guide and possesses a valid commercial crabbing authorization:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>May carry customers during a commercial crabbing trip;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shall follow all commercial crabbing rules;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>May not count customers as crew members;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>May sell their catch to a seafood dealer or, if licensed as a seafood dealer in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-701">Natural Resources Article, §4-701, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, to a customer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Shall report their catch in accordance with <cite path="08.02.13.06">COMAR 08.02.13.06</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Shall be penalized for any violation of statute or regulation in accordance with <cite path="08.02.13.03">COMAR 08.02.13.03</cite></text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Crabbing Charters.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Definition. In this chapter, “crabbing charter” means any guided trip for the purpose of catching crabs recreationally, offered by an individual who, in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-701">Natural Resources Article, §4-701, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, is licensed as a fishing guide or master fishing guide, or operates a vessel for a master fishing guide.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Crabbing Charter Decal.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Prior to operating a crabbing charter, a fishing guide shall obtain a crabbing charter decal.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Except as provided in <cite path="08|02|03|.15|D.|(2)|(c)">§D(2)(c) of this regulation</cite>, a decal issued for a crabbing charter:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Shall be permanently affixed and displayed on either side of the forward half of the vessel for which issued;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Is not transferable;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Shall, when displayed, exempt all persons aboard from the requirement of possessing an individual license to crab recreationally; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Is valid for the current commercial license year.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Exemption for Crabbing Charter Decals. If the crabbing charter decal is not permanently affixed to the vessel, all persons aboard are exempt from the requirement of possessing an individual license to crab recreationally only if:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The individual who purchased the crabbing charter decal is present on the vessel;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The individual who purchased the crabbing charter decal is in possession of the proof of purchase issued by the Department; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The crabbing charter decal was purchased within the previous 10 calendar days.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A crabbing charter:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>May only be offered by an individual  licensed as a fishing guide or a master fishing guide, or who operates a vessel for a master fishing guide in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-701">Natural Resources Article, §4-701, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Shall have at least one customer on board;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>May not harvest female hard crabs or female peelers from the Chesapeake Bay and its tidal tributaries; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Shall comply with the recreational season, times, size limits, and gear restrictions established in this chapter for a licensed recreational crabber.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Crabs caught on a crabbing charter may not be sold.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Catch Limit. A crabbing charter with one or more customers on board may not catch more than two bushels of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Male hard crabs and two dozen soft crabs or male peeler crabs from the Chesapeake Bay and its tidal tributaries; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Crabs from the Atlantic Ocean and its coastal bays.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Reporting. Crabs harvested on a crabbing charter shall be reported on forms provided by the Department and in the time specified by the Department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Any violation of statute or regulation shall be penalized in accordance with <cite path="08.02.13.08">COMAR 08.02.13.08</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Natural Resources Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-206">4-206</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-215">4-215</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-701">4-701</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-745">4-745</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-803">4-803</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-804">4-804</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-809">4-809</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-810">4-810</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1975-03-24">Effective date: March 24, 1975 (2:8 Md. R. 555)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-12-04"><cite path="|08|02|03|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective March 30, 1977 (4:7 Md. R. 578); May 23, 1983 (10:10 Md. R. 872); December 30, 1985 (12:26 Md. R. 2543); December 4, 1995 (22:24 Md. R. 1894)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-04-04"><cite path="|08|02|03|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective April 4, 1985 (12:9 Md. R. 806); emergency status expired June 29, 1985</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-09-15"><cite path="|08|02|03|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective September 15, 1995 (22:20 Md. R. 1538); emergency status expired December 31, 1995</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1996-06-01"><cite path="|08|02|03|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective June 1, 1996 (23:13 Md. R. 937); emergency status expired October 31, 1996</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1997-09-08"><cite path="|08|02|03|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective April 2, 1997 (24:9 Md. R. 653); amended permanently effective September 8, 1997 (24:18 Md. R. 1295)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-02-14"><cite path="|08|02|03|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective July 23, 2001 (28:14 Md. R. 1320); November 11, 2002 (29:22 Md. R. 1720); April 14, 2003 (30:7 Md. R. 486); February 14, 2005 (32:3 Md. R. 289)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-03-22"><cite path="|08|02|03|.01|D.">Regulation .01D</cite> amended effective April 1, 1976 (3:8 Md. R. 424); October 17, 1980 (7:21 Md. R. 1994); January 17, 1983 (10:1 Md. R. 27); August 15, 1983 (10:16 Md. R. 1450); September 10, 1984 (11:18 Md. R.1583); March 28, 1994 (21:6 Md. R. 466); October 10, 1994 (21:20 Md. R. 1731); March 22, 1999 (26:6 Md. R. 483)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-08-10">Regulations .01D, I, J, and .05 amended as an emergency provision effective August 10, 1994 (21:18 Md. R. 1505)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-08-02"><cite path="|08|02|03|.01|D.">Regulation .01D</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective March 31, 2004 (31:8 Md. R. 643); amended permanently effective August 2, 2004 (31:15 Md. R. 1185)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-02-14"><cite path="|08|02|03|.01|D.">Regulation .01D</cite> amended effective February 14, 2005 (32:3 Md. R. 289)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-02-14"><cite path="|08|02|03|.01|G.">Regulation .01G</cite> repealed effective February 14, 2005 (32:3 Md. R. 289)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-12-04"><cite path="|08|02|03|.01|H.">Regulation .01H</cite> amended effective April 1, 1976 (3:6 Md. R. 357); March 30, 1977 (4:7 Md. R. 578);  April 7, 1978 (5:7 Md. R. 521); May 4, 1979 (6:9 Md. R. 726); October 17, 1980 (7:21 Md. R. 1994); May 24, 1982 (9:10 Md. R. 1019); August 15, 1983 (10:16 Md. R. 1450); May 6, 1985 (12:9 Md. R. 810); December 4, 1995 (22:24 Md. R. 1894)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1988-07-25"><cite path="|08|02|03|.01|H.">Regulation .01H</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective February 10, 1988 (15:5 Md. R. 612); adopted permanently effective July 25, 1988 (15:15 Md. R. 1808)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-09-14"><cite path="|08|02|03|.01|H.">Regulation .01H</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective September 14, 1995 (22:20 Md. R. 1538); emergency status expired March 14, 1996</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1996-06-17"><cite path="|08|02|03|.01|H.">Regulation .01H</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective April 1, 1996 (23:8 Md. R. 602); amended permanently effective June 17, 1996 (23:12 Md. R. 868)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-07-23"><cite path="|08|02|03|.01|H.">Regulation .01H</cite> amended effective March 24, 2000 (27:5 Md. R. 582); July 23, 2001 (28:14 Md. R. 1320)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-08-02"><cite path="|08|02|03|.01|H.">Regulation .01H</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective March 31, 2004 (31:8 Md. R. 643); amended permanently effective August 2, 2004 (31:15 Md. R. 1185)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1978-10-20"><cite path="|08|02|03|.01|I.">Regulation .01I</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 24, 1978 (5:16 Md. R. 1252); adopted permanently effective October 20, 1978 (5:21 Md. R. 1586)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-03-22"><cite path="|08|02|03|.01|I.">Regulation .01I</cite> amended effective March 30, 1977 (4:7 Md. R. 578); August 15, 1983 (10:16 Md. R. 1456); September 10, 1984 (11:18 Md. R. 1583); March 28, 1994 (21:6 Md. R. 466); October 10, 1994 (21:20 Md. R. 1731); March 22, 1999 (26:6 Md. R. 483)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-08-02"><cite path="|08|02|03|.01|I.">Regulation .01I</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective March 31, 2004 (31:8 Md. R. 643); amended permanently effective August 2, 2004 (31:15 Md. R. 1185)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-02-14"><cite path="|08|02|03|.01|I.">Regulation .01I</cite> amended effective February 14, 2005 (32:3 Md. R. 289)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1987-02-09"><cite path="|08|02|03|.01|J.">Regulation .01J</cite> amended effective May 9, 1975 (2:12 Md. R. 865); April 1, 1976 (3:6 Md. R. 357); as an emergency provision May 17, 1976 (3:12 Md. R. 641), permanently adopted effective August 18, 1976 (3:17 Md. R. 914); March 30, 1977 (4:7 Md. R. 578); August 3, 1977 (4:16 Md. R. 1210); April 7, 1978 (5:7 Md. R. 521); as an emergency provision effective June 29, 1978 (5:14 Md. R. 1131); adopted permanently effective September 22, 1978 (5:19 Md. R. 1444); amended effective March 7, 1980 (7:5 Md. R. 473); October 17, 1980 (7:21 Md. R. 1994); amended as an emergency provision effective June 24, 1981 (8:14 Md. R. 1251), adopted permanently effective September 28, 1981 (8:19 Md. R. 1565); amended effective February 1, 1982 (9:2 Md. R. 113); May 24, 1982 (9:10 Md. R. 1019); August 16, 1982 (9:16 Md. R. 1602); September 13, 1982 (9:18 Md. R. 1800); October 11, 1982 (9:20 Md. R. 1981); January 17, 1983 (10:1 Md. R. 27); March 14, 1983 (10:5 Md. R. 465); March 28, 1983 (10:6 Md. R. 554); April 25, 1983 (10:8 Md. R. 724); August 15, 1983 (10:16 Md. R. 1450); October 10, 1983 (10:20 Md. R. 1785); January 16, 1984 (11:1 Md. R. 41); April 9, 1984 (11:7 Md. R. 622); May 6, 1985 (12:9 Md. R. 810); February 9, 1987 (14:3 Md. R. 271)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1988-11-14"><cite path="|08|02|03|.01|J.">Regulation .01J</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective June 23, 1987 (14:15 Md. R. 1655); emergency status expired October 23, 1987; amended as an emergency provision effective April 1, 1988 (15:9 Md. R. 1106); amended permanently effective November 14, 1988 (15:23 Md. R. 2658)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-04-01"><cite path="|08|02|03|.01|J.">Regulation .01J</cite> amended effective September 5, 1988 (15:18 Md. R. 2145); April 16, 1990 (17:7 Md. R. 847); February 4, 1991 (18:2 Md. R. 148); January 1, 1993 (19:18 Md. R. 1655); March 28, 1994 (21:6 Md. R. 466); June 6, 1994 (21:11 Md. R. 950); October 10, 1994 (21:20 Md. R. 1731); June 17, 1996 (23:12 Md. R. 869); March 22, 1999 (26:6 Md. R. 483); June 26, 2000 (27:12 Md. R. 1138); July 23, 2001 (28:14 Md. R. 1320); August 20, 2001 (28:16 Md. R. 1481); April 1, 2002 (29:6 Md. R. 566)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-12-04"><cite path="|08|02|03|.01|J.">Regulation .01J</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective June 30, 1995 (22:15 Md. R. 1110); amended permanently effective December 4, 1995 (22:24 Md. R. 1894)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-11-13"><cite path="|08|02|03|.01|J.">Regulation .01J</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective November 13, 1995 (22:25 Md. R. 1958); emergency status expired December 31, 1995</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-08-02"><cite path="|08|02|03|.01|J.">Regulation .01J</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective March 31, 2004 (31:8 Md. R. 643) amended permanently effective August 2, 2004 (31:15 Md. R. 1185)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-02-14"><cite path="|08|02|03|.01|J.">Regulation .01J</cite> amended February 14, 2005 (32:3 Md. R. 289)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1983-07-04"><cite path="|08|02|03|.01|K.">Regulation .01K</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective April 7, 1983 (10:9 Md. R. 788); emergency status extended to June 20, 1983 (10:11 Md. R. 962); adopted permanently effective July 4, 1983 (10:13 Md. R. 1179)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1983-03-14"><cite path="|08|02|03|.02">Regulation .02</cite> repealed effective March 14, 1983 (10:4 Md. R. 315)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-01-09"><cite path="|08|02|03|.02">Regulation .02</cite> adopted effective January 9, 1989 (15:27 Md. R. 3127)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-04-01"><cite path="|08|02|03|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective April 1, 2002 (29:6 Md. R. 566)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-07-07"><cite path="|08|02|03|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective April 1, 2003 (30:8 Md. R. 537); amended permanently effective July 7, 2003 (30:13 Md. R. 853)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1996-06-17"><cite path="|08|02|03|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective June 17, 1996 (23:12 Md. R. 869)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-03-28"><cite path="|08|02|03|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective September 10, 1984 (11:18 Md. R. 1583); March 28, 1994 (21:6 Md. R. 466)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-03-22"><cite path="|08|02|03|.03">Regulation .03</cite> repealed and new Regulation .03 adopted effective March 22, 1999 (26:6 Md. R. 483)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-04-14"><cite path="|08|02|03|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite> amended effective April 14, 2003 (30:7 Md. R. 486)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-08-02"><cite path="|08|02|03|.03">Regulation .03</cite> repealed and new Regulation .03 adopted as an emergency provision effective March 31, 2004 (31:8 Md. R. 643); adopted permanently effective August 2, 2004 (31:15 Md. R. 1185)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-02-14"><cite path="|08|02|03|.03|D.">Regulation .03D</cite> amended effective February 14, 2005 (32:3 Md. R. 289)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1983-03-28"><cite path="|08|02|03|.04">Regulation .04</cite> adopted effective March 28, 1983 (10:6 Md. R. 555)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-08-02"><cite path="|08|02|03|.04">Regulation .04</cite> repealed and new Regulation .04 adopted as an emergency provision effective March 31, 2004 (31:8 Md. R. 643); adopted permanently effective August 2, 2004 (31:15 Md. R. 1185)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-02-14"><cite path="|08|02|03|.04|E.">Regulation .04E</cite> adopted effective February 14, 2005 (32:3 Md. R. 289)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-08-02"><cite path="|08|02|03|.04-1">Regulation .04-1</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective March 31, 2004 (31:8 Md. R. 643); adopted permanently effective August 2, 2004 (31:15 Md. R. 1185)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-02-14"><cite path="|08|02|03|.04-1">Regulation .04-1</cite> repealed effective February 14, 2005 (32:3 Md. R. 289)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-03-28"><cite path="|08|02|03|.05">Regulation .05</cite> adopted effective March 28, 1994 (21:6 Md. R. 466)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-08-10"><cite path="|08|02|03|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective August 10, 1994 (21:18 Md. R. 1505)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-10-10"><cite path="|08|02|03|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective October 10, 1994 (21:20 Md. R. 1731)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-09-15"><cite path="|08|02|03|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective September 15, 1995 (22:20 Md. R. 1538); emergency status expired December 31, 1995</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-04-12"><cite path="|08|02|03|.05|A.">Regulation .05A</cite> amended effective July 23, 2001 (28:14 Md. R. 1320); April 1, 2002 (29:6 Md. R. 566); April 12, 2004 (31:7 Md. R. 582)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-11-11"><cite path="|08|02|03|.05|B.">Regulation .05B</cite> amended effective November 11, 2002 (29:22 Md. R. 1720)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-12-04"><cite path="|08|02|03|.06">Regulation .06</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective June 30, 1995 (22:15 Md. R. 1110); adopted permanently effective December 4, 1995 (22:24 Md. R. 1894)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-08-02"><cite path="|08|02|03|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective March 31, 2004 (31:8 Md. R. 643); amended permanently effective August 2, 2004 (31:15 Md. R. 1185)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-07-23"><cite path="|08|02|03|.06|D.">Regulation .06D</cite> adopted effective July 23, 2001 (28:14 Md. R. 1321)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-11-13"><cite path="|08|02|03|.07">Regulation .07</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective September 15, 1995 (22:20 Md. R. 1538); Regulation .07A emergency text amended effective November 13, 1995 (22:25 Md. R. 1958); emergency status expired December 31, 1995</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1996-06-17"><cite path="|08|02|03|.07">Regulation .07</cite> adopted effective June 17, 1996 (23:12 Md. R. 869)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-04-01"><cite path="|08|02|03|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective August 20, 2001 (28:16 Md. R. 1481); April 1, 2002 (29:6 Md. R. 566)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1996-06-17"><cite path="|08|02|03|.08">Regulation .08</cite> adopted effective June 17, 1996 (23:12 Md. R. 869)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-07-23"><cite path="|08|02|03|.08">Regulation .08</cite> amended effective July 23, 2001 (28:14 Md. R. 1320)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-07-07"><cite path="|08|02|03|.08|B.">Regulation .08B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective April 1, 2003 (30:8 Md. R. 537); amended permanently effective July 7, 2003 (30:13 Md. R. 853)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1997-07-28"><cite path="|08|02|03|.08|E.">Regulation .08E</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective March 21, 1997 (24:8 Md. R. 613); adopted permanently effective July 28, 1997 (24:15 Md. R. 1061)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-04-01"><cite path="|08|02|03|.08|E.">Regulation .08E</cite> adopted effective April 1, 2002 (29:6 Md. R. 566)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-11-11"><cite path="|08|02|03|.08|E.">Regulation .08E</cite> amended effective November 11, 2002 (29:22 Md. R. 1720)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-07-07"><cite path="|08|02|03|.08|E.">Regulation .08E</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective April 1, 2003 (30:8 Md. R. 537); amended permanently effective July 7, 2003 (30:13 Md. R. 853)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-04-12"><cite path="|08|02|03|.08">Regulation .08</cite> amended and recodified to Regulation .09, and new Regulation .08 adopted effective April 12, 2004 (31:7 Md. R. 582)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-02-14"><cite path="|08|02|03|.09|A.">Regulation .09A</cite> amended effective February 14, 2005 (32:3 Md. R. 289)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-11-24" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective November 24, 2005 (32:23 Md. R. 1825)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-02-25"><cite path="|08|02|03|.01|A.">Regulation .01A</cite> amended effective February 25, 2008 (35:4 Md. R. 512)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-04-01"><cite path="|08|02|03|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective March 23, 2009 (36:6 Md. R. 487); March 27, 2017 (44:6 Md. R. 324); February 7, 2022 (49:3 Md. R. 138); April 1, 2024 (51:6 Md. R. 269)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-12-16"><cite path="|08|02|03|.01|C.">Regulation .01C</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective June 1, 2008 (35:13 Md. R. 1174); emergency status extended to December 16, 2008 (35:23 Md. R. 2011); emergency status expired December 16, 2008</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-03-23"><cite path="|08|02|03|.01|C.">Regulation .01C</cite> amended effective March 23, 2009 (36:6 Md. R. 487)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-08-31"><cite path="|08|02|03|.01|C.">Regulation .01C</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective August 31, 2023 (50:19 Md. R. 852); emergency status expired December 31, 2023</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-04-01"><cite path="|08|02|03|.01|C.">Regulation .01C</cite> amended effective April 1, 2024 (51:6 Md. R. 269)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-01-01"><cite path="|08|02|03|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective March 23, 2009 (36:6 Md. R. 487); January 1, 2014 (40:25 Md. R. 2067)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-03-30"><cite path="|08|02|03|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite>, E amended effective March 30, 2015 (42:6 Md. R. 510)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-03-22"><cite path="|08|02|03|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite> amended effective March 22, 2021 (48:6 Md. R. 237)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-03-22"><cite path="|08|02|03|.03|E.">Regulation .03E</cite> amended effective March 25, 2019 (46:6 Md. R. 345); March 22, 2021 (48:6 Md. R. 237)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-02-26"><cite path="|08|02|03|.05|D.">Regulation .05D</cite> amended effective February 26, 2007 (34:4 Md. R. 399)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-01-01"><cite path="|08|02|03|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective January 1, 2014 (40:25 Md. R. 2067)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-03-30"><cite path="|08|02|03|.06|A.">Regulation .06A</cite>, D amended effective March 30, 2015 (42:6 Md. R. 510)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-03-25"><cite path="|08|02|03|.06|B.">Regulation .06B</cite> amended effective March 25, 2019 (46:6 Md. R. 345)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-04-01"><cite path="|08|02|03|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective April 1, 2024 (51:6 Md. R. 269)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-02-26"><cite path="|08|02|03|.07|A.">Regulation .07A</cite>, B amended effective February 26, 2007 (34:4 Md. R. 399)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-03-28"><cite path="|08|02|03|.07|B.">Regulation .07B</cite>, D amended effective March 28, 2016 (43:6 Md. R. 404)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-03-21"><cite path="|08|02|03|.07|D.">Regulation .07D</cite> amended effective October 19, 2009 (36:21 Md. R. 1590); October 31, 2011 (38:22 Md. R. 1345); January 1, 2014 (40:25 Md. R. 2067); March 30, 2015 (42:6 Md. R. 510); January 1, 2018 (44:26 Md. R. 1214); March 21, 2022 (49:6 Md. R. 404)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-03-21"><cite path="|08|02|03|.07|E.">Regulation .07E</cite> amended effective October 5, 2020 (47:20 Md. R. 874); March 22, 2021 (48:6 Md. R. 237); March 21, 2022 (49:6 Md. R. 404)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-03-23"><cite path="|08|02|03|.07|G.">Regulation .07G</cite> amended effective March 23, 2009 (36:6 Md. R. 487)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-03-17"><cite path="|08|02|03|.07|H.">Regulation .07H</cite> amended effective March 17, 2025 (52:4 Md. R. 236)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-03-26"><cite path="|08|02|03|.08|B.">Regulation .08B</cite> amended effective March 26, 2018 (45:6 Md. R. 317)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-03-26"><cite path="|08|02|03|.08|C.">Regulation .08C</cite> adopted effective March 26, 2018 (45:6 Md. R. 317)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-09-28"><cite path="|08|02|03|.09">Regulation .09</cite> amended effective March 23, 2009 (36:6 Md. R. 488); April 4, 2011 (38:7 Md. R. 429); January 1, 2014 (40:25 Md. R. 2067); September 28, 2015 (42:19 Md. R. 1228)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-02-07"><cite path="|08|02|03|.09|A.">Regulation .09A</cite> amended effective February 25, 2008 (35:4 Md. R. 512); March 27, 2017 (44:6 Md. R. 324); February 7, 2022 (49:3 Md. R. 138)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-07-01"><cite path="|08|02|03|.09|B.">Regulation .09B</cite> amended effective March 27, 2017 (44:6 Md. R. 324); July 1, 2019 (46:13 Md. R. 589)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-02-26"><cite path="|08|02|03|.10">Regulation .10</cite> repealed and new Regulation .10 adopted effective February 26, 2007 (34:4 Md. R. 399)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-12-16"><cite path="|08|02|03|.10">Regulation .10</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective June 1, 2008 (35:13 Md. R. 1174); emergency status extended to December 16, 2008 (35:23 Md. R. 2011); emergency status expired December 16, 2008</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-01-01"><cite path="|08|02|03|.10">Regulation .10</cite> amended effective March 23, 2009 (36:6 Md. R. 488); January 1, 2014 (40:25 Md. R. 2067)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-04-01"><cite path="|08|02|03|.10|A.">Regulation .10A</cite> amended effective April 1, 2024 (51:6 Md. R. 269)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-03-22"><cite path="|08|02|03|.10|B.">Regulation .10B</cite> amended effective September 28, 2015 (42:19 Md. R. 1228); March 22, 2021 (48:6 Md. R. 237)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-03-22"><cite path="|08|02|03|.10|C.">Regulation .10C</cite> repealed effective March 22, 2021 (48:6 Md. R. 237)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-10-31"><cite path="|08|02|03|.10|E.">Regulation .10E</cite> amended effective February 8, 2010 (37:3 Md. R. 175); October 31, 2011 (38:22 Md. R. 1345)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-02-25"><cite path="|08|02|03|.11|A.">Regulation .11A</cite> amended effective February 25, 2008 (35:4 Md. R. 512)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-12-16"><cite path="|08|02|03|.11|A.">Regulation .11A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective June 1, 2008 (35:13 Md. R. 1174); emergency status extended to December 16, 2008 (35:23 Md. R. 2011); emergency status expired December 16, 2008</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-07-10"><cite path="|08|02|03|.11|A.">Regulation .11A</cite> amended effective January 1, 2014 (40:25 Md. R. 2067); March 27, 2017 (44:6 Md. R. 324); September 25, 2017 (44:19 Md. R. 896); February 7, 2022 (49:3 Md. R. 138); July 10, 2023 (50:13 Md. R. 511)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-10-19"><cite path="|08|02|03|.11|A.">Regulation .11A</cite>, C amended effective March 23, 2009 (36:6 Md. R. 488); October 19, 2009 (36:21 Md. R. 1590)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-03-25"><cite path="|08|02|03|.11|B.">Regulation .11B</cite> amended effective March 25, 2019 (46:6 Md. R. 345)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-03-28"><cite path="|08|02|03|.12|A.">Regulation .12A</cite> amended effective March 28, 2016 (43:6 Md. R. 404)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-04-01"><cite path="|08|02|03|.12|B.">Regulation .12B</cite> amended effective April 1, 2024 (51:6 Md. R. 269)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-10-19"><cite path="|08|02|03|.12|C.">Regulation .12C</cite> amended effective October 19, 2009 (36:21 Md. R. 1590)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-07-10"><cite path="|08|02|03|.12|D.">Regulation .12D</cite> amended effective March 27, 2017 (44:6 Md. R. 324); September 25, 2017 (44:19 Md. R. 896); July 10, 2023 (50:13 Md. R. 511)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-12-16"><cite path="|08|02|03|.13|B.">Regulation .13B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective June 1, 2008 (35:13 Md. R. 1174); emergency status extended to December 16, 2008 (35:23 Md. R. 2011); emergency status expired December 16, 2008</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-04-01"><cite path="|08|02|03|.13|B.">Regulation .13B</cite> amended effective March 23, 2009 (36:6 Md. R. 488); March 22, 2021 (48:6 Md. R. 237); April 1, 2024 (51:6 Md. R. 269)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-03-22"><cite path="|08|02|03|.13|C.">Regulation .13C</cite> adopted effective March 22, 2021 (48:6 Md. R. 237)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-12-16"><cite path="|08|02|03|.14">Regulation .14</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective June 1, 2008 (35:13 Md. R. 1174); emergency status extended to December 16, 2008 (35:23 Md. R. 201); emergency status expired December 16, 2008</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-04-02"><cite path="|08|02|03|.14">Regulation .14</cite> amended effective March 23, 2009 (36:6 Md. R. 488); February 8, 2010 (37:3 Md. R. 175); October 31, 2011 (38:22 Md. R. 1345); April 2, 2012 (39:6 Md. R. 407)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-01-01"><cite path="|08|02|03|.14|A.">Regulation .14A</cite> amended effective January 1, 2014 (40:25 Md. R. 2067)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-02-25"><cite path="|08|02|03|.14|A.">Regulation .14A</cite>, E amended effective February 25, 2008 (35:4 Md. R. 512)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-03-28"><cite path="|08|02|03|.14|B.">Regulation .14B</cite> amended effective February 7, 2011 (38:3 Md. R. 152); March 28, 2016 (43:6 Md. R. 404)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-08-31"><cite path="|08|02|03|.14|B.">Regulation .14B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective August 31, 2023 (50:19 Md. R. 852); emergency status expired December 31, 2023</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-04-01"><cite path="|08|02|03|.14|B.">Regulation .14B</cite> amended effective April 1, 2024 (51:6 Md. R. 269)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-07-10"><cite path="|08|02|03|.14|B.">Regulation .14B</cite>, E amended effective July 10, 2023 (50:13 Md. R. 511)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-03-27"><cite path="|08|02|03|.14|B.">Regulation .14B</cite>—D amended effective March 27, 2017 (44:6 Md. R. 324)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-03-22"><cite path="|08|02|03|.14|B.">Regulation .14B</cite>, G amended effective March 22, 2021 (48:6 Md. R. 237)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-03-26"><cite path="|08|02|03|.14|C.">Regulation .14C</cite> amended effective March 26, 2018 (45:6 Md. R. 317)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-03-30"><cite path="|08|02|03|.14|E.">Regulation .14E</cite> amended effective March 30, 2015 (42:6 Md. R. 510)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-07-26"><cite path="|08|02|03|.14|F.">Regulation .14F</cite> amended effective July 26, 2010 (37:15 Md. R. 998)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-07-07"><cite path="|08|02|03|.15">Regulation .15</cite> adopted effective July 7, 2014 (41:13 Md. R. 751)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-07-01"><cite path="|08|02|03|.15|D.">Regulation .15D</cite> amended effective March 28, 2016 (43:6 Md. R. 404): October 10, 2016 (43:20 Md. R. 1109); July 1, 2019 (46:13 Md. R. 589)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" discontinuity="true">Annotation: An amendment to Regulation .01J promulgated at 14:2 Md. R. 126 was declared invalid by the Department of Natural Resources and is not reflected in the 1987 COMAR supplement.</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
