<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>04</num>
  <heading>Oysters</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|02|04|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Patent Tong Areas.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A person may not use patent tongs to catch oysters in any of the waters listed in this section.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Tidal waters of the following counties, other than those waters included as part of the Chesapeake Bay, Tangier Sound, and Pocomoke Sound as defined by <cite path="08.02.01.06|B.">COMAR 08.02.01.06B</cite>:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Wicomico County;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Queen Anne’s County, except as provided in <cite path="08|02|04|.01|B.|(5)">§B(5) of this regulation</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Talbot County;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Dorchester County; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Kent County, except as provided in §§B(1)—(4) of this regulation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Patuxent River, except as provided in <cite path="08|02|04|.01|B.|(6)">§B(6) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Tributaries of the Potomac River.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>South River in Anne Arundel County north and west of a straight line drawn between Thomas Point defined by Lat. 38°54.440’ N, Long. 76°27.610’ W and Saunders Point defined by Lat. 38°53.190’ N, Long. 76°29.440’ W.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Chesapeake Bay. All of the waters of the Chesapeake Bay enclosed by a line beginning at a point on the shore at Richland Point defined by Lat. 38°14.846’ N, Long. 76°10.332’ W; then running 315° True to a point on the shore at the south end of Barren Island, defined by Lat. 38°19.460’ N, Long. 76°15.430’ W; then running 112° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°18.424’ N, Long. 76°13.400’ W; then running southeasterly along the shore to a point near the north end of the Narrows Ferry Bridge, defined by Lat. 38°17.917’ N, Long. 76°12.389’ W; then running 155° True to a point near the south end of the Narrows Ferry Bridge, defined by Lat. 38°17.676’ N, Long. 76°12.250’ W; then running southeasterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Exceptions. A person may catch oysters by patent tong in the areas listed in this section.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Natural Oyster Bar 5-2: All of the waters enclosed by a line beginning at a point defined by Lat. 39°6.272’ N, Long. 76°17.175’ W; then running 335° True to a point defined by Lat. 39°6.765’ N, Long. 76°17.464’ W; then running 63° True to a point defined by Lat. 39°6.861’ N, Long. 76°17.222’ W; then running 143° True to a point defined by Lat. 39°6.575’ N, Long. 76°16.944’ W; then running 211° True to the point of beginning.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Natural Oyster Bar 2-9: All of the waters enclosed by a line beginning at a point defined by Lat. 39°7.507’ N, Long. 76°18.981’ W; then running 0° True to a point defined by Lat. 39°8.857’ N, Long. 76°18.981’ W; then running 38° True to a point defined by Lat. 39°11.002’ N, Long. 76°16.858’ W; then running 62° True to a point defined by Lat. 39°11.665’ N, Long. 76°15.225’ W; then running southwesterly along shore excluding all creeks and coves less than 300 feet in width to a point defined by Lat. 39°10.830’ N, Long. 76°16.017’ W; then running 240° True to a point defined by Lat. 39°10.508’ N, Long. 76°16.732’ W; then running 195° True to a point defined by Lat. 39°8.416’ N, Long. 76°17.469’ W; then running 168° True to a point defined by Lat. 39°7.602’ N, Long. 76°17.245’ W; then running 259° True to a point defined by Lat. 39°7.507’ N, Long. 76°17.858’ W; then running 270° True to the point of beginning.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Natural Oyster Bar 2-10: All of the waters enclosed by a line beginning at a point defined by Lat. 39°7.508’ N, Long. 76°15.842’ W; then running 349° True to a point defined by Lat. 39°7.736’ N, Long. 76°15.899’ W; then running 85° True to a point defined by Lat. 39°7.793’ N, Long. 76°14.979’ W; then running 180° True to a point defined by Lat. 39°7.503’ N, Long. 76°14.982’ W; then running 270° True to the point of beginning.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Natural Oyster Bar 5-1: All of the waters enclosed by a line beginning at a point defined by Lat. 39°7.349’ N, Long. 76°18.981’ W; then running 0° True to a point defined by Lat. 39°7.507’ N, Long. 76°18.981’ W; then running 90° True to a point defined by Lat. 39°7.507’ N, Long. 76°17.858’ W; then running 260° True to the point of beginning.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>All of the waters of Eastern Bay south and west of a line beginning at a point defined by Lat. 38°49.904’ N, Long. 76°20.384’ W; then running 48° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°50.871’ N, Long. 76°19.031’ W; then running 115° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°50.746’ N, Long. 76°18.686’ W; then running 233° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°50.574’ N, Long. 76°18.978’ W; then running 201° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°48.693’ N, Long. 76°19.884’ W; then running 90° True to a point on shore, defined by Lat. 38°48.686’ N, Long. 76°18.54’ W; then running southerly along the shore to Lowes Point defined by Lat. 38°46.416’ N, Long. 76°20.02’ W; then running 323° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°47.861’ N, Long. 76°21.394’ W; then running 210° True to a point on Poplar Island defined by Lat. 38°46.553’ N, Long. 76°22.342’ W.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Patuxent River. All of the waters of the Patuxent River enclosed by a line beginning at a point on the shore at Hog Point defined by Lat. 38°18.586' N, Long. 76°23.993' W; then running westerly along the shore to a point on the shore at Fishing Point defined by Lat. 38°18.285' N, Long. 76°25.355' W; then running 345° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°18.525' N, Long. 76°25.434' W; then running 251° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°18.271' N, Long. 76°26.356' W; then running 196° True to a point on the shore, defined by Lat. 38°17.503' N, Long. 76°26.640' W; then running northwesterly along the shore to a point on shore at Sotterly Wharf, defined by Lat. 38°22.728' N, Long. 76°32.003' W; then running 77° True to a point near St Leonard’s Creek Beacon, defined by Lat. 38°23.065' N, Long. 76°30.177' W; then running 77° True to a point on the shore, defined by Lat. 38°23.128' N, Long. 76°29.826' W; then running southeasterly along the shore to a point defined by Lat. 38°20.631' N, Long. 76°28.241' W; then running 282° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°20.638' N, Long. 76°28.287' W; then running 213° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°20.008' N, Long. 76°28.815' W; then running 132° True to a point on the shore, defined by Lat. 38°19.983' N, Long. 76°28.780' W; then running southeasterly along the shore to a point at the south entrance of Solomon’s Harbor, defined by Lat. 38°19.263' N, Long. 76°27.103' W; then running 7° True to a point at the north entrance of Solomon’s Harbor, defined by Lat. 38°19.370' N, Long. 76°27.087' W; then running easterly along the shore to Drum Point defined by Lat. 38°19.143' N, Long. 76°25.266' W; then running 119° True to the point of beginning, excluding the waters of Neal Addition Sanctuary which is defined as: All of the waters of the area enclosed by a line beginning at a point defined by Lat. 38°22.480' N, Long. 76°31.460' W; then running approximately 307° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°22.552' N, Long. 76°31.580' W; then running approximately 28° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°22.612' N, Long. 76°31.540' W; then running approximately 127° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°22.540' N, Long. 76°31.420' W; then running approximately 208° True to the point of beginning.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|02|04|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Recreational Oyster Fishery.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The recreational season, daily catch limits, days of the week, and times for catching oysters shall be established, and may be modified, through a public notice issued in accordance with <cite path="|08|02|04|.11">Regulation .11 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Department shall issue a public notice that establishes the parameters described in <cite path="08|02|04|.02|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> for the recreational oyster fishery not later than July 1 of each year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Prohibition. Except as specified in this regulation and in any public notice issued in accordance with <cite path="|08|02|04|.11">Regulation .11 of this chapter</cite>, it is illegal for a person to catch oysters for recreational purposes.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Lawful Methods. A person may catch oysters for recreational purposes only by hand, rake, shaft tong, or diving with or without scuba equipment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A person may not take oysters for recreational purposes while aboard a vessel where any other person is engaged in commercial oystering.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|02|04|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Catching Oysters for Commercial Purposes.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Season, Days, and Catch Limits.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The season for catching oysters and the days of the week that an individual may catch oysters for commercial purposes shall be established for each gear type, and may be modified, through a public notice issued in accordance with <cite path="|08|02|04|.11">Regulation .11 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The daily commercial catch limits shall be established for each gear type, and may be modified, through a public notice issued in accordance with <cite path="|08|02|04|.11">Regulation .11 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Department shall issue a public notice that establishes the parameters described in §A(1) and (2) of this regulation for the commercial oyster fishery not later than July 1 of each year.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Lawful Methods. A person may catch oysters for commercial purposes only by shaft tong, patent tong, diving apparatus, dredge boat, dredge boat propelled by means of an auxiliary yawl boat, or power dredge.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Times for Catching.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>During an open season in November and December, a person may catch oysters for commercial purposes only from:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Sunrise until sunset when using shaft tong, patent tong, diving apparatus, dredge boat, or dredge boat propelled by means of an auxiliary yawl boat; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Sunrise until 3 p.m. when using a power dredge.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Except as described in <cite path="08|02|04|.03|C.|(1)">§C(1) of this regulation</cite>, during an open season a person may catch oysters for commercial purposes only from:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Sunrise until 3 p.m. when using shaft tong, patent tong, dredge boat, diving apparatus, or power dredge; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Sunrise until sunset when using a dredge boat propelled by means of an auxiliary yawl boat.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An individual who harvests oysters for commercial purposes shall deliver oysters:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>To a person who is licensed and certified to sell shellfish by the Maryland Department of Health in accordance with <cite path="|10.15.04">COMAR 10.15.04</cite> and <cite path="|10.15.07">10.15.07</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Not later than 9 p.m. on the same day of harvest.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A person may not land or possess oysters on a vessel more than 2 hours after sunset or anytime before sunrise.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An individual shall notify the Natural Resources Police when there is an emergency which would prevent compliance with the times specified in §§C and D of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Oysters may only be sold in accordance with <cite path="08.02.08.02">COMAR 08.02.08.02</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>In addition to the requirements of this chapter, a commercial licensee shall harvest oysters in accordance with the National Shellfish Sanitation Program Model Ordinance that is incorporated by reference by the Maryland Department of Health in <cite path="10.15.07.01|A.">COMAR 10.15.07.01A</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|02|04|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Oyster Container and Tagging Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Containers.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Oysters harvested from waters of the State shall be stored prior to leaving the bar from which they were harvested in a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Metal oyster tub that does not exceed the following inside dimensions:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>18 inches top diameter;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>16-1/2 inches bottom diameter; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>12 inches height;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Rectangular shaped container that does not exceed the following inside dimensions:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>12-5/8 inches width across the top;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>12 inches width across the bottom;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>20 inches in length; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>11-1/4 inches height;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Round container that does not exceed the following inside dimensions:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>16-1/2 inches top diameter;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>13-1/2 inches bottom diameter; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>14-1/4 inches height; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Container with dimensions approved in writing by the Department which shall have a volume that is comparable to the containers described in §A(1)(a)—(c) of this regulation, and, upon request, the Department's letter approving the container shall be displayed to any Natural Resources Police officer.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A container described in <cite path="08|02|04|.04|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite> shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Made of a rigid, open mesh;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Made of smooth, impervious, corrosion-resistant, and non-toxic materials which will not readily disintegrate or crack;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Constructed so that it may be easily cleaned and kept in good repair; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Constructed to allow either one side or one end to be opened to unload or inspect the oysters.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Oysters stored in accordance with <cite path="08|02|04|.04|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite> may not extend beyond the top of the container.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Oysters stored in accordance with <cite path="08|02|04|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall remain in the original container until a tag is no longer required on the container in accordance with <cite path="08|02|04|.04|D.|(1)|(d)">§D(1)(d) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Oysters on board a skipjack harvested in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-1013">Natural Resources Article, §4-1013, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, from:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Only one bar are exempt from §A(1)—(3) of this regulation; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>More than one bar may have oysters from one bar not in containers and all other oysters from different bars shall follow the container requirements of §A(1)—(4) of this regulation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Tagging of Individual Containers.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="08|02|04|.04|B.|(3)">§B(3) of this regulation</cite>, an individual storing oysters in accordance with §A(1)—(3) of this regulation shall complete and affix a Department-issued tag to each container of oysters prior to leaving the bar from which the oysters were harvested.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="08|02|04|.04|B.|(3)">§B(3) of this regulation</cite>, an individual storing oysters in accordance with <cite path="08|02|04|.04|A.|(5)">§A(5) of this regulation</cite> shall complete one Department-issued tag for the group of oysters not in containers and affix a Department-issued tag to each container of oysters prior to leaving the bar from which the oysters were harvested.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An individual storing oysters in accordance with §A(1)—(3) or (5) of this regulation may use a tag not supplied by the Department if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The individual:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Is licensed and certified to sell shellfish by the Maryland Department of Health in accordance with <cite path="|10.15.04">COMAR 10.15.04</cite> and <cite path="|10.15.07">10.15.07</cite>; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Follows the tagging requirements of the National Shellfish Sanitation Program Model Ordinance, incorporated by reference by the Maryland Department of Health in <cite path="10.15.07.01">COMAR 10.15.07.01</cite>; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Each tag the individual uses contains the statement “Wild Shellfish”, the state in which the harvest occurred, and, in the order specified, the following information:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The harvester’s license number as assigned by the Department;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The date of harvest, including the year;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The bar name;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>The name of the region or the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration code for the area in which the harvest occurred;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>The type and quantity of shellfish; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>The statement “THIS TAG IS REQUIRED TO BE ATTACHED UNTIL CONTAINER IS EMPTY OR IS RETAGGED AND THEREAFTER KEPT ON FILE FOR 90 DAYS” in bold capitalized type.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Bulk Tagging.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Definitions.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In this regulation, the following terms have the meaning indicated.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Bulk tag” means a tag that provides the necessary information as required by the National Shellfish Sanitation Program Model Ordinance for a single lot of oysters.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>“Single lot” means oysters coming from a single oyster bar, harvested during a single trip on a single day by a single harvester.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="08|02|04|.04|C.|(3)">§C(3) of this regulation</cite>, an individual storing oysters in accordance with §A(1)—(3) of this regulation may complete and affix a Department-issued bulk tag to a single container of oysters prior to leaving the bar from which the oysters were harvested.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An individual storing oysters in accordance with §A(1)—(3) or (5) of this regulation may use a bulk tag not supplied by the Department if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The individual:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Is licensed and certified to sell shellfish by the Maryland Department of Health in accordance with <cite path="|10.15.04">COMAR 10.15.04</cite> and <cite path="|10.15.07">10.15.07</cite>; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Follows the tagging requirements of the National Shellfish Sanitation Program Model Ordinance, incorporated by reference by the Maryland Department of Health in <cite path="10.15.07.01">COMAR 10.15.07.01</cite>; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Each tag the individual uses contains the statement “Wild Shellfish”, the state in which the harvest occurred, and, in the order specified, the following information:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The harvester’s license number as assigned by the Department;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The date of harvest, including the year;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The bar name;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>The name of the region or the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration code for the area in which the harvest occurred;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>The type of shellfish;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>The statement “THIS TAG IS REQUIRED TO BE ATTACHED UNTIL CONTAINER IS EMPTY OR IS RETAGGED AND THEREAFTER KEPT ON FILE FOR 90 DAYS” in bold capitalized type;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>The following statement in bold capitalized letters: “ALL SHELLFISH CONTAINERS IN THIS LOT HAVE THE SAME HARVEST DATE AND ARE FROM A SINGLE AREA OF HARVEST”; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>The number of individual containers in the lot.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If one licensee is present on the vessel, only one bulk tag may be used.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If a bulk tag is used, the vessel may only harvest from one bar on that day.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Tagging Provisions for Both Tagging of Individual Containers and Bulk Tags.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Tags:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Shall be durable and waterproof;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Shall be at least 5-1/2 x 2-3/4 inches in size;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Shall be completed legibly in indelible ink;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Shall stay affixed to the container until the container is in the possession of a person who is licensed and certified to sell shellfish by the Maryland Department of Health in accordance with <cite path="|10.15.04">COMAR 10.15.04</cite> and <cite path="|10.15.07">10.15.07</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>May not be reused.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In addition to the tagging requirements of this regulation, a person who is licensed and certified to sell shellfish by the Maryland Department of Health in accordance with <cite path="|10.15.04">COMAR 10.15.04</cite> and <cite path="|10.15.07">10.15.07</cite> shall follow the tagging requirements of the National Shellfish Sanitation Program Model Ordinance, incorporated by reference by the Maryland Department of Health in <cite path="10.15.07.01">COMAR 10.15.07.01</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An individual shall only possess one type of tag, wild shellfish or farm-raised shellfish, while harvesting oysters.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Only one type of tag, individual or bulk, may be present on a vessel while harvesting oysters.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>An individual may not use a farm-raised shellfish tag to tag wild shellfish.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>An individual may not use a wild shellfish tag to tag farm-raised shellfish.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>If a tidal fish licensee obtains tags from the Department, the licensee shall be assessed an annual surcharge for the costs incurred by the Department for the tags.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Exemptions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Oysters harvested for recreational purposes and not for sale are exempt from the requirements of §§A — D of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Oysters harvested from a lease and stored and tagged in accordance with <cite path="|08.02.23">COMAR 08.02.23</cite> are exempt from the requirements of §§A — D of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Use of Diving Apparatus to Catch Oysters Commercially.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>When using diving apparatus to catch oysters for commercial purposes, the diver or the diver’s attendant shall be authorized to catch oysters for commercial purposes in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-701">Natural Resources Article, §4-701, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Not more than two divers may work from a boat at one time.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Each diver shall have one attendant on the boat.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If there is more than one diver on the boat, a different attendant shall be present for each diver.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A diving flag that is a rigid replica of the International Code Flag "A" not less than 1 meter in height shall be displayed while the diver is in the water.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Distances Required. A person may not conduct a shellfish harvesting operation within 50 feet of a vessel involved in a diving operation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Power assisted lifting devices including, but not limited to, hydraulic winders or motor driven windlasses may be used subject to the following conditions:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The total length of cable or rope on the winding apparatus may not exceed 100 feet; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The container used when lifting the oysters from the bottom to the vessel shall be rigged with a self-closing lid that is automatically held in the closed position by the pressure of the retrieval line while the container is being retrieved.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Daily Catch Limit — Repealed.</heading>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Election of Committees of Oystermen.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Eligibility for Oyster Committee Members. A licensed oyster harvester who has paid the oyster license surcharge for the current license year or for at least one of the previous two license years is eligible to be a representative on a county oyster committee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Balloting Procedure.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>When an election for a county is to be held, the Department shall publish notice of the election on the Department’s website. The notice shall state the ballot procedure.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A licensed oyster harvester may vote only for the oyster committee candidates for the county in which the licensed oyster harvester resides. The elections shall be conducted by the Department and shall be by secret ballot. After the election has been closed, the Department shall tally and announce the results. The persons receiving the most votes shall be elected to the vacancies on the committee, and the Department shall notify those persons of their election by certified mail. If a person elected is unable or unwilling to serve on the committee, the person receiving the highest number of votes who is able or willing to serve shall be elected.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If a vacancy cannot be filled because two or more persons have received an equal number of votes, the representative shall be selected by a process determined by the Department in consultation with the current oyster committee of the county in which the tie occurred.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If a county has less than five licensed oyster harvesters who are eligible to be a committee representative, then all of the eligible licensed oyster harvesters of that county shall constitute the respective committee.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|02|04|.08">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Dredge Boat Areas.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as listed in <cite path="08|02|04|.08|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> a person may catch oysters by a dredge boat, as defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-1001">Natural Resources Article, §4-1001(g), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, only in the following waters:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All of the waters of Hoopers Straits enclosed by a line beginning at a point defined by Lat. 38°11.923’ N, Long. 76°5.674’ W; then running 309° True to a point defined by the shore of Richland Point defined by Lat. 38°14.846’ N, Long. 76°10.332’ W; then running easterly along the shore of Lower Hoopers Island to a point defined by Lat. 38°13.968’ N, Long. 76°7.871’ W; then running 92° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°13.93’ N, Long. 76°6.66’ W; then running 150° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°13.203’ N, Long. 76°6.122’ W; then running 165° True to the point of beginning;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All of the waters of the Honga River enclosed by a line beginning at a point defined by Lat. 38°14.877’ N, Long. 76°6.956’ W; then running 305° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°14.974’ N, Long. 76°7.134’ W; then running 35° True to a point on the shore at Crab Point defined by Lat. 38°15.77’ N, Long. 76°6.439’ W; then running southerly along the shore to a point defined by Lat. 38°15.25’ N, Long. 76°6.052’ W; then running 242° True to the point of beginning;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All of the waters of Dorchester and Talbot Counties enclosed by a line beginning at a point defined by Lat. 38°41.359’ N, Long. 76°19.302’ W; then running 107° True to a point at Benoni (Choptank River) Lighthouse, defined by Lat. 38°39.344’ N, Long. 76°11.069’ W; then running 123° True to a point at Chlora Point defined by Lat. 38°38.222’ N, Long. 76°8.829’ W; then running easterly along the shore to a point on the west side of La Trappe Creek, defined by Lat. 38°37.695’ N, Long. 76°7.323’ W; then running 106° True to a point on the east side of La Trappe Creek, defined by Lat. 38°37.62’ N, Long. 76°6.997’ W; then running southerly along the shore to a point at the south end of Howell Point defined by Lat. 38°36.675’ N, Long. 76°6.646’ W; then running 254° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°36.479’ N, Long. 76°7.652’ W; then running 308° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°36.557’ N, Long. 76°7.780’ W; then running 250° True to a point defined by Lat. 38° 36.507’ N, Long. 76° 7.92’ W; then running 320° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°36.534’ N, Long. 76°7.949’ W; then running 333° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°36.671’ N, Long. 76°8.039’ W; then running 349° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°36.846’ N, Long. 76°8.08’ W; then running 360° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°37.26’ N, Long. 76°8.084’ W; then running 356° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°37.496’ N, Long. 76°8.108’ W; then running 345° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°37.81’ N, Long. 76°8.212’ W; then running 308° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°37.866’ N, Long. 76°8.302’ W; then running 286° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°37.89’ N, Long. 76°8.408’ W; then running 272° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°37.898’ N, Long. 76°8.684’ W; then running 267° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°37.884’ N, Long. 76°9.023’ W; then running 283° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°37.933’ N, Long. 76°9.296’ W; then running 302° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°38.095’ N, Long. 76°9.631’ W; then running 314° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°38.536’ N, Long. 76°10.221’ W; then running 303° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°38.68’ N, Long. 76°10.498’ W; then running 288° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°38.789’ N, Long. 76°10.919’ W; then running 271° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°38.79’ N, Long. 76°11.095’ W; then running 240° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°38.732’ N, Long. 76°11.226’ W; then running 251° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°38.576’ N, Long. 76°11.793’ W; then running 264° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°38.518’ N, Long. 76°12.494’ W; then running 278° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°38.562’ N, Long. 76°12.874’ W; then running 292° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°38.664’ N, Long. 76°13.197’ W; then running 218° True to a point on the shore at Todds Point defined by Lat. 38°37.683’ N, Long. 76°14.168’ W; then running 267° True to a point on the shore at Cooks Point defined by Lat. 38°37.581’ N, Long. 76°17.109’ W; then running southerly along the shore to a point defined by Lat. 38°37.453’ N, Long. 76°17.045’ W; then running 120° True to a point on the shore, defined by Lat. 38°37.426’ N, Long. 76°16.984’ W; then running southerly and westerly along the shore of Trippe Bay and Brannock Bay to a point at Hills Point defined by Lat. 38°34.358’ N, Long. 76°18.292’ W; then running 206° True to a point on shore at the north end of James Island, defined by Lat. 38°31.387’ N, Long. 76°20.14’ W; then running 345° True to Sharps Island Lighthouse, defined by Lat. 38°38.345’ N, Long. 76°22.541’ W; then running 42° True to a point on shore at Blackwalnut Point defined by Lat. 38°40.239’ N, Long. 76°20.373’ W; then running northeasterly along the shore of Tilghman Island to a point defined by Lat. 38°41.366’ N, Long. 76°19.333’ W; then running 107° True to the point of beginning, excluding the area defined as Cook Point Sanctuary in <cite path="|08|02|04|.15|A.">Regulation .15A of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>All the waters of Somerset County except as provided in §B(1)—(5) of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Talbot County. All of the waters bayward of a line beginning at Kent Point, defined by Lat. 38°50.180’ N, Long. 76°22.100’ W; then running approximately 102° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°49.904’ N, Long. 76°20.384’ W; then running approximately 48° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°50.871’ N, Long. 76°19.031’ W; then running approximately 115° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°50.564’ N, Long. 76°18.203’ W; then running approximately 163° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°49.702’ N, Long. 76°17.865’ W; then running southwesterly along the shore to a point defined by Lat. 38°46.416’ N, Long. 76°20.020’ W; then running approximately 323° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°47.861’ N, Long. 76°21.394’ W; then running approximately 210° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°46.553’ N, Long. 76°22.342’ W.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Chesapeake Bay. All of the waters of the Chesapeake Bay mainstem as defined by <cite path="08.02.01.06|B.|(1)">COMAR 08.02.01.06B(1)</cite>, except as provided in <cite path="08|02|04|.08|B.|(6)">§B(6) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Exceptions. A person may not catch oysters by dredge boat in the areas listed in this section.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Pocomoke Sound, as defined by <cite path="08.02.01.06|B.|(5)">COMAR 08.02.01.06B(5)</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Wicomico River. All of the waters of the Wicomico River easterly of a straight line drawn from a point defined by Lat. 38°10.767’ N, Long. 75°57.004’ W; then running 343° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°12.311’ N, Long. 75°57.587’ W.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Manokin River. All of the waters of the Manokin River landward or upstream of a straight line beginning at a point on Little Deals Island, defined by Lat. 38°6.750’ N, Long. 75°56.552’ W; then running 126° True to Hazard Point on the mainland, defined by Lat. 38°4.571’ N, Long. 75°52.694’ W.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Big Annemessex River. All of the waters of the Big Annemessex River easterly of a straight line beginning at a point defined by Lat. 38°2.303’ N, Long. 75°51.610’ W; then running 334° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°3.648’ N, Long. 75°52.422’ W.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Tangier Sound. All of the waters east of Smith Island south and west of a line drawn in an easterly course from Terrapin Sands Point on the west side of Tangier Sound, defined by Lat. 38°0.247' N, Long. 75°58.181' W; then running 94° True to the channel, to a point defined by Lat. 38° 0.008' N, Long. 75° 54.977' W; and then running 200° True following the channel in a southerly direction to a point defined by Lat. 37°57.845' N, Long. 75°55.770' W; then running 190° following the channel to the Virginia Line, to a point defined by Lat. 37°54.453' N, Long. 75°56.413' W.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Chesapeake Bay. All areas described in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-1012">Natural Resources Article, §4-1012(a), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Areas Reserved for Hand Tonging, Exceptions.</heading>
    <text>Except in areas established as oyster sanctuaries in <cite path="|08|02|04|.15|A.">Regulation .15A of this chapter</cite> or power dredge areas in <cite path="|08|02|04|.12|B.">Regulation .12B of this chapter</cite>, oysters may be taken only by hand tongs in the following areas, except that scooping, dredging, or scraping by hand may be permitted by the Department in certain areas reserved for hand tonging when watermen are denied access to oyster taking because of icing conditions.</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Wicomico River, Charles and St. Mary's Counties: All the waters north of a line beginning at the southern tip of Cobb Island, defined by Lat. 38°15.307’ N, Long. 76°50.532’ W; then running 46° True to a point defined by Lat. 38° 16.193'  N, Long. 76° 49.359' W, then running 22° True to a point defined by, Lat. 38° 16.272' N, Long. 76° 49.318' W, then running 18° True to a point defined by, Lat. 38° 16.645' N, Long. 76° 49.164' W, then running 41° True to a point defined by, Lat. 38° 16.943' N, Long. 76° 48.839' W, then running 104° True to a point at or near the shore southeast of Bushwood Wharf defined by, Lat. 38° 16.800'  N, Long. 76° 48.128' W.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Breton Bay and St. Clement Bay: All the waters northerly of a line beginning at or near Huggins Point, defined by Lat. 38°13.988’ N, Long. 76°41.137’ W; then running 236° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°13.103’ N, Long. 76°42.810’ W; then running 336° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°13.777’ N, Long. 76°43.186’ W; then running 256° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°13.440’ N, Long. 76°44.929’ W; then running 298° True to a point at or near the shore defined by Lat. 38°13.475’ N, Long. 76°45.013’ W ; and south of a line beginning at a point at or near the shore at Huggins Point defined by Lat. 38°13.980' N, Long. 76°41.138' W; then running 274° True to a point at or near the shore at Kaywood Point defined by Lat. 38°14.040' N, Long. 76°42.299' W.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>St. George Creek: All the waters northwesterly of a line beginning at a tower on St. George Island defined by Lat. 38°7.738’ N, Long. 76°29.582’ W; then running 32° True to a point at or near shore defined by Lat. 38°8.316’ N, Long. 76°29.130’ W , except for all of the waters of the Piney Point Oyster Sanctuary enclosed by a line beginning at a point at or near  the mean low water line on the shore defined by Lat. 38°09.922'N, Long. 76°31.275'W; then running 48° True about 78 meters to a point defined by Lat. 38°09.950'N, Long. 76°31.235'W; then running 118° True about 386 meters a point defined by Lat. 38°09.850'N, Long. 76°31.003'W; then running 175° True about 207 meters to a point defined by Lat. 38°09.738'N, Long. 76°30.993'W; then running 270° True about 100 meters to a point at or near the mean low water line on the shore defined by Lat. 38°09.738'N, Long. 76°31.062' W; then running northwesterly along the mean low water line of the shore, excluding all creeks and coves less than 100 yards in width, to the point of beginning.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>South River: All the waters:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Upstream of a line beginning at or near the northeast tip of Turkey Point defined by Lat. 38°54.545’ N, Long. 76°29.679’ W; then running 62° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°54.642’ N, Long. 76°29.448’ W; then running 7° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°55.649’ N, Long. 76°29.293’ W; then running 26° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°55.732’ N, Long. 76°29.242’ W; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Downstream of a line beginning at a point defined by Lat. 38°55.910’ N, Long. 76°31.927’ W; then running northeasterly approximately 42° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°56.495’ N, Long. 76°31.235’ W.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Chester River: All the waters:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Upstream of a line beginning at a point at or near the shore north of Ringgold Point, defined by Lat. 39° 03.759'  N, Long. 76° 12.625' W, then running 126° True to a point at or near the shore north of Piney Point, defined by Lat. 39° 02.813'  N, Long. 76° 10.980' W; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Downstream of a line beginning at a point at or near the shore at Grays Inn Point defined by Lat. 39°5.415’ N, Long. 76°11.556’ W; then running 146° True to a point at or near the shore of Gordon Point defined by Lat. 39°3.757’ N, Long. 76°10.109’ W.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Eastern Bay and Shipping Creek: All the waters northerly of a line beginning at or near the southwest tip of Turkey Point defined by Lat. 38°54.125’ N, Long. 76°17.980’ W; then running 254° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°53.932’ N, Long. 76°18.851’ W; then running 283° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°54.057’ N, Long. 76°19.554’ W; then running 283° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°54.173’ N, Long. 76°20.205’ W; and southerly of a line beginning at a point at or near the shore at Turkey Point defined by Lat. 38°54.129' N, Long. 76°17.978' W; then running 303° True to a point at or near the shore at the west entrance of Cox Creek, defined by Lat. 38°54.686' N, Long. 76°19.083' W.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Crab Alley Bay: All the waters northerly of a line beginning at or near Normans Point defined by Lat. 38°55.138’ N, Long. 76°15.349’ W; then running 241° True to a point at or near the southeast tip of Turkey Point defined by Lat. 38°54.177’ N, Long. 76°17.573’ W.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Prospect Bay: All the waters:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>South of a line beginning at a point at or near the MD Route 18 Bridge, defined by Lat. 38°58.212’ N, Long. 76°14.771’ W; then running 286° True to a point at or near the west end of the bridge defined by Lat. 38°58.242’ N, Long. 76°14.906’ W; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>North of a line beginning at or near the shore of Cabin Creek defined by Lat. 38°56.510’ N, Long. 76°13.610’ W; then running 178° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°55.096’ N, Long. 76°13.567’ W; then running 272° True to a point at or near shore at Normans Point defined by Lat. 38°55.138’ N, Long. 76°15.349’ W.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Miles River: All the waters:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Upstream of a line beginning at or near the shore of Rich Neck defined by Lat. 38°51.390’ N, Long. 76°15.174’ W; then running 113° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°50.298’ N, Long. 76°11.810’ W; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Downstream of a line beginning at a point at or near shore at the east entrance of Spencer Creek, defined by Lat. 38°46.539’ N, Long. 76°11.920’ W; then running 46° True to a point at or near the north shore of the Miles River, defined by Lat. 38°47.076’ N, Long. 76°11.205’ W.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Poplar Island Narrows: All the waters:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>North of a line beginning at or near the south end of the Poplar Island dike defined by Lat. 38°44.650’ N, Long. 76°22.279’ W; then running 154° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°43.588’ N, Long. 76°21.619’ W; then running 71° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°43.908’ N, Long. 76°20.436’ W; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>South of a line beginning at a point defined by Lat. 38°46.416’ N, Long. 76°20.020’ W; then running 274° True to a point at or near Lowes Point defined by Lat. 38°46.553’ N, Long. 76°22.343’ W.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Broad Creek: All the waters north of a line beginning at a point at or near the shore at Nelson Point defined by Lat. 38°42.549’ N, Long. 76°16.281’ W; then running 61° True to a point at or near the south side of Bridge Creek, defined by Lat. 38°43.440’ N, Long. 76°14.196’ W.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Irish Creek: All the waters north of a line beginning at a point at or near the shore at Holland Point defined by Lat. 38°41.879’ N, Long. 76°13.611’ W; then running 186° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°41.838’ N, Long. 76°13.617’ W; then running 92° True to a point at or near the shore at Lucy Point defined by Lat. 38°41.825’ N, Long. 76°13.178’ W.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>Tred Avon River: All the waters:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>North of a line beginning at or near the southeastern tip of Benoni Point defined by Lat. 38°40.247’ N, Long. 76°11.982’ W; then running 96° True to a point at or near the shore at the north side of Boone Creek, defined by Lat. 38°40.070’ N, Long. 76°10.117’ W;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>West of a line beginning at a point at or near the shore on the east side of Town Creek, defined by Lat. 38°41.835’ N, Long. 76°9.923’ W; then running 255° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°41.823’ N, Long. 76°9.981’ W; then running 0° True to a point at or near the shore of the east side of Plaindealing Creek, defined by Lat. 38°42.576’ N, Long. 76°9.978’ W; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>West of a line beginning at a point defined by Lat. 38°40.965’ N, Long. 76°10.407’ W; then running 239° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°40.909’ N, Long. 76°10.528’ W; then running 210° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°40.830’ N, Long. 76°10.586’ W; then running 183° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°40.741’ N, Long. 76°10.593’ W; then running 154° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°40.641’ N, Long. 76°10.531’ W.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>Choptank River: All the waters north of a line beginning at or near Howell Point defined by Lat. 38°36.746’ N, Long. 76°6.626’ W; then running 209° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°36.295’ N, Long. 76°6.938’ W; then running 170° True to a point defined by Lat.38°36.006’ N, Long. 76°6.871’ W; then running 90° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°36.012’ N, Long. 76°5.958’ W; then running 88° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°36.030’ N, Long. 76°5.082’ W; then running 131° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°34.833’ N, Long. 76°3.344’ W; then running 30° True to a point at or near the north shore of the Choptank River, defined by Lat. 38°35.484’ N, Long. 76°2.860’ W.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>Little Choptank River: All the waters:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>South of a line beginning at a point at or near shore on Hills Point Neck defined by Lat. 38°32.678’ N, Long. 76°16.528’ W; then running 245° True to a point at or near the northeast tip of James Island defined by Lat. 38°31.373’ N, Long. 76°20.092’ W; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>West of a line beginning at a point at or near the shore of Susquehanna Point defined by Lat. 38°30.642’ N, Long. 76°15.492’ W; then running 329° True to a point at or near shore at the south end of Ragged Point Island, defined by Lat. 38°31.886’ N, Long. 76°16.440’ W.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>P.</num>
      <text>Fishing Bay: All the waters northerly of a line beginning at a point at or near shore defined by corner 9 of Natural Oyster Bar 24-7, defined by Lat. 38°19.480’ N, Long. 76°01.888’ W; then running approximately 182° True to a point defined by corner 10 of Natural Oyster Bar 24-7, defined by Lat. 38°19.452’ N, Long. 76°01.888’ W; then running approximately 144° True to a point at or near shore defined by corner 5 of Natural Oyster Bar 24-6, defined by Lat. 38°18.557’ N, Long. 76°01.065’ W.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>Q.</num>
      <text>Nanticoke River: All the waters:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>North of a line beginning at or near Sandy Point, defined by Lat. 38°14.803’ N, Long. 75°56.385’ W; then running approximately 96° True to a point at or near the shore north of Jones Creek, defined by Lat. 38°14.635’ N, Long. 75°54.352’ W; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>South of a line beginning at a point at or near the shore at Sandy Point defined by Lat. 38°14.803’ N, Long. 75°56.403’ W; then running 43° True to a point at or near the shore at Roaring Point defined by Lat. 38°15.870’ N, Long. 75°55.155’ W; except</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All the waters of the Roaring Point Oyster Sanctuary enclosed by a line beginning at a point defined by Lat. 38°15.120'N, Long. 75°54.788'W; then running approximately 358° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°15.337'N, Long. 75°54.798'W; then running approximately 88° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°15.123'N, Long. 75°54.717'W; then running approximately 177° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°15.338'N, Long. 75°54.732'W; then running approximately 267° True to the point of beginning.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>R.</num>
      <text>Holland Straits: All the Somerset County waters in Holland Straits:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Southeast of a line beginning at or near Sedgy Point defined Lat. 38°05.484' N, Long. 76°03.352' W; then running approximately 306° True to a point at or near Pry Island defined by Lat. 38°05.705' N, Long. 76°03.734' W; then running 21° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°6.664’ N, Long. 76°3.283’ W; then running 27° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°8.845’ N, Long. 76°1.873’ W; then running 140° True to a point at or near Sound Point defined by Lat. 38°7.883’ N, Long. 76°0.852’ W;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>North of a line in Pungers Creek beginning at a point defined by Lat. 38°7.165’ N, Long. 76°1.877’ W; then running 257° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°7.139’ N, Long. 76°2.022’ W;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>North of a line in Little Pungers Creek beginning at a point defined by Lat. 38°6.760’ N, Long. 76°2.325’ W; then running 175° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°6.691’ N, Long. 76°2.317’ W; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>North of a line in Pry Cove beginning at a point defined by Lat. 38°5.173’ N, Long. 76°2.098’ W; then running 267° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°5.169’ N, Long. 76°2.187’ W.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>S.</num>
      <text>Island Creek, Choptank River: All the waters northeasterly of a line beginning at a point at or near the shore at the north side of Island Creek, defined by Lat. 38°39.697’ N, Long. 76°9.699’ W; then running 120° True to a point at or near the shore at the south side of Island Creek, defined by Lat. 38°39.517’ N, Long. 76°9.300’ W.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>T.</num>
      <text>La Trappe Creek, Choptank River: All the waters:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Northerly of a line beginning at a point at or near the shore of Martin Point defined by Lat. 38°37.716’ N, Long. 76°7.324’ W; then running 109° True to a point at or near the west shore of Grubin Neck defined by Lat. 38°37.609’ N, Long. 76°6.927’ W; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Southerly of a line beginning at or near the south entrance of an unnamed cove on the east side of La Trappe Creek defined by Lat. 38°38.157’N, Long. 76°06.462’W; then running approximately 269° True to a point at or near the north entrance of an unnamed cove on the west side of La Trappe Creek defined by Lat. 38°38.162’N, Long. 76°06.937’W.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|02|04|.10">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Dredging with an Auxiliary Yawl Boat.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A dredge boat may be propelled by means of an auxiliary yawl boat carried on the dredge boat to catch oysters in areas where dredge boats are permitted, except in:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The waters upstream of a line in the Choptank River extending from a point at or near Martin Point defined by Lat. 38°37.695’ N, Long. 76°7.323’ W; then running approximately 212° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°36.791’ N, Long. 76°8.067’ W;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>All of the waters enclosed by a line beginning at or near Kent Point, defined by Lat. 38°50.180’ N, Long. 76°22.100’ W; then running approximately 183° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°50.036’ N, Long. 76°22.108’ W; then running approximately 269° True to a point at or near Bloody Point Lighthouse defined by Lat. 38°50.027’ N, Long. 76°23.511’ W; then running approximately 354° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°51.958’ N, Long. 76°23.547’ W; then running approximately 4° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°56.762’ N, Long. 76°22.807’ W; then running approximately 19° True to a point south of the William Preston Lane Jr. Memorial Bridge defined by Lat. 38°59.311’ N, Long. 76°21.908’ W; then running approximately 102° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°58.911’ N, Long. 76°20.087’ W; then running southerly along the shore to the point of beginning; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Areas established as oyster sanctuaries in <cite path="|08|02|04|.15|A.">Regulation .15A of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A dredge boat may be propelled in accordance with <cite path="08|02|04|.10|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> for not more than 2 of the days of the week, specified by public notice, that a person may catch oysters for commercial purposes during the season for dredging oysters.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Notice shall be provided to the Department in advance of each day a dredge boat is propelled in accordance with <cite path="08|02|04|.10|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|02|04|.11">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>General Provisions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Definitions.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Terms Defined.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Bushel means an amount of oysters that would fill a container that meets the requirements of <cite path="|08|02|04|.04|A.">Regulation .04A of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Marketable oyster” means an oyster that measures at least 3 inches in length from hinge to bill.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Oyster Harvest Area.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>"Oyster harvest area” means submerged ground where an individual may catch oysters.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>“Oyster harvest area” does not include an area leased for aquaculture, restricted by the Maryland Department of the Environment, or designated as a submerged aquatic vegetation protection zone, harvest reserve area, or sanctuary.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>“Spat” means an oyster that measures less than 1 inch in length from hinge to bill.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>“Undersized oyster” means an oyster that measures at least 1 inch in length from hinge to bill and less than 3 inches in length from hinge to bill.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This chapter does not apply in areas leased for shellfish cultivation under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr">Natural Resources Article, Title 4, Subtitle 11A, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Oyster Culling.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person who catches oysters shall cull the oysters on the natural bar from which they were caught and return every shell to the bar. Any oysters whose shell measures less than 3 inches in length, from hinge to bill, shall be included in the culling and replaced upon the bar from which caught.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in §C(4) and (5) of this regulation, any oyster whose shell measures less than 3 inches in length, from hinge to bill, shall be included in the culling and replaced upon the bar from which caught.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person may not possess more than 5 percent shells and oysters less than the allowable size specified in <cite path="08|02|04|.11|C.|(2)">§C(2) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A person may possess marketable oysters that have undersized oysters attached to them that cannot be separated without destroying the undersized oyster.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A person may possess marketable oysters that have spat attached to them.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Fees for Moving Oyster Seed.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Subject to the other conditions and terms agreed to each year, the rates to be paid by the Department to any person for the moving of oyster seed shall be adjusted yearly in coordination with the hiring of the captains to move the seed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A captain hired to move seed shall be notified of the rates by certified mail.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Fees for Purchasing, Hauling, and Planting Fresh Oyster Shell.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Subject to other conditions and terms agreed to each year, the rate to be paid by the Department to any person for the hauling and planting of fresh oyster shell shall be established by public notice in accordance with <cite path="08|02|04|.11|G.">§G of this regulation</cite>, based on current fair market value.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The rate to be paid to purchase fresh oyster shell shall be established by public notice in accordance with <cite path="08|02|04|.11|G.">§G of this regulation</cite>, based on current fair market value.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A licensed commercial oyster harvester may not have more than one type of oyster harvest gear on board a vessel with oysters on board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>General.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notwithstanding Natural Resources Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-1004">4-1004</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-1008">4-1008</cite>.1, 4-1009, 4-1013, and 4-1015.1, Annotated Code of Maryland, in order to implement the Maryland Chesapeake Bay Oyster Management Plan, the Secretary may issue a public notice to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Establish or modify the season, daily catch limits, days of the week, or times for catching oysters for recreational or commercial purposes;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Open or close an oyster harvest area for the harvesting or conservation of oysters;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Establish or modify the rates to be paid for the purchase, hauling, and planting of fresh oyster shell.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A public notice issued to implement <cite path="08|02|04|.11|G.|(1)|(b)">§G(1)(b) of this regulation</cite> shall state:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The specific area;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The specific period of time that the area is opened or closed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Daily bushel limits; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The days of the week a person may catch oysters in the area.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A public notice shall state its effective hour and date and shall be published on the Department’s website at least 48 hours in advance of the effective hour and date.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Secretary shall make a reasonable effort to disseminate a public notice issued under <cite path="08|02|04|.11|G.">§G of this regulation</cite> through various other media so that an affected individual has a reasonable opportunity to be informed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A violation of the restrictions set by the Secretary in accordance with <cite path="08|02|04|.11|G.">§G of this regulation</cite> is a violation of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|02|04|.12">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Power Dredging.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notwithstanding <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-1012">Natural Resources Article, §4-1012(b), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, a power dredge may only be used in the following areas:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Leased areas;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Power Dredge Zones established in <cite path="08|02|04|.12|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Power Dredge Study Areas established in <cite path="08|02|04|.12|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Portions of the Wild Grounds Study Area established in <cite path="08|02|04|.12|D.|(1)">§D(1) of this regulation</cite> that have been opened in accordance with <cite path="08|02|04|.12|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person may not use or possess a power dredge bar that is more than 42 inches in length measuring from the outside teeth or that exceeds a weight of 200 pounds.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Power Dredge Zone.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Calvert County. All of the waters of the State that lie contiguous to Calvert County enclosed by a line beginning at a point at the intersection of the Calvert-Saint Mary’s county line and the contiguous waters line running from Hog Point to Drum Point defined by Lat. 38°18.883’ N, Long. 76°24.683’ W; then running 300° True to a point at Drum Point defined by Lat. 38°19.150’ N, Long. 76°25.267’ W; then running northerly along the shore, excluding all creeks and coves less than 300 feet wide at the mouth, to a point on the shore at Cove Point defined by Lat. 38°23.174’ N, Long. 76°22.906’ W; then running 329° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°25.237’ N, Long. 76°24.499’ W; then running 321° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°27.127’ N, Long. 76°26.455’ W; then running 241° True to a point at the shore, defined by Lat. 38°26.769’ N, Long. 76°27.277’ W; then running northerly along the shore, excluding all creeks and coves less than 300 feet wide at the mouth, to a point defined by Lat. 38°33.482’ N, Long. 76°30.924’ W; then running 79° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°33.683’ N, Long. 76°29.550’ W; then running 346° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°34.867’ N, Long. 76°29.915’ W; then running 50° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°35.933’ N, Long. 76°28.283’ W; then running 351° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°37.450’ N, Long. 76°28.582’ W; then running 323° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°39.250’ N, Long. 76°30.286’ W; then running 256° True to a point at the shore, defined by Lat. 38°38.995’ N, Long. 76°31.552’ W; then running northerly along the shore, excluding all creeks and coves less than 300 feet wide at the mouth, to a point at the shore south of Chesapeake Beach, defined by Lat. 38°41.278’ N, Long. 76°31.974’ W; then running 92° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°41.237’ N, Long. 76°30.213’ W; then running 14° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°42.635’ N, Long. 76°29.769’ W; then running 92° True to a point at the junction of the Calvert-Anne Arundel-Talbot county line defined by Lat. 38°42.567’ N, Long. 76°27.650’ W; then running 172° True to a point on the Calvert-Dorchester county line, defined by Lat. 38°30.000’ N, Long. 76°25.483’ W; then running 147° True to a point on the Calvert-Dorchester county line, defined by Lat. 38°23.183’ N, Long. 76°19.967’ W; then running 172° True to a point on the Calvert-Dorchester-Saint Mary’s county line, defined by Lat. 38°19.633’ N, Long. 76°19.299’ W; then running 270° True to a point on the Calvert-Saint Mary’s county line, defined by Lat. 38°19.617’ N, Long. 76°22.883’ W; then running 270° True to a point on the Calvert-Saint Mary’s county line, defined by Lat. 38°19.617’ N, Long. 76°22.983’ W; then running 247° True to a point on the Calvert-Saint Mary’s county line, defined by Lat. 38°19.600’ N, Long. 76°23.033’ W; then running 241° True to the point of beginning; except the waters of Plum Point Sanctuary, which is described as: All of the waters of the area enclosed by a line beginning at a point defined by Lat. 38°39.050' N, Long. 76°31.283’ W; then running approximately 75° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°39.250’ N, Long. 76°30.300’ W; then running approximately 143° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°37.450’ N, Long. 76°28.583’ W; then running approximately 171° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°35.933’ N, Long. 76°28.283’ W; then running approximately 230° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°34.867’ N, Long. 76°29.917’ W; then running approximately 166° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°33.683’N, Long. 76°29.550’ W; then running approximately 259° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°33.500’ N, Long. 76°30.800’ W; then running approximately 358° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°34.900’ N, Long. 76°30.867’ W; then running approximately 6° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°37.483’ N, Long. 76°30.500’ W; then running approximately 325° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°38.300’ N, Long. 76°31.217’ W; then running approximately 356° True to the point of beginning.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Dorchester and Wicomico Counties.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Dorchester County. All of the waters enclosed by a line beginning at a point defined by Lat. 38°3.667’ N, Long. 76°5.636’ W; then running 351° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°9.181’ N, Long. 76°6.720’ W; then running 261° True to a point defined by Lat. 38° 8.366'N, Long. 76° 13.580' W; then running 162° True to a point defined by Lat. 38° 4.586'N, Long. 76° 11.983' W; then running 162° True to a point defined by Lat. 38° 3.517' N, Long. 76° 11.532' W; then running 268° True to a point defined by Lat. 38° 3.498'N, Long. 76° 12.198' W; then running 9° True to a point defined by Lat. 38° 4.586'N, Long. 76° 11.983' W; then running 338° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°17.967’ N, Long. 76°18.967’ W; then running 351° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°23.183’ N, Long. 76°19.967’ W; then running 328° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°30.000’ N, Long. 76°25.483’ W; then running 353° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°30.032’ N, Long. 76°25.488’ W; then running 88° True to a point at or near the south end of James’ Island, defined by Lat. 38°30.177’ N, Long. 76°20.302’ W; then running 167° True to a point at or near the entrance of Oyster Creek, defined by Lat. 38°29.215’ N, Long. 76°20.022’ W; then running southerly along the shore to a point at or near the north entrance of Punch Island Creek, defined by Lat. 38°25.355’ N, Long. 76°17.257’ W; then running 161° True to a point at or near the south entrance of Punch Island Creek, defined by Lat. 38°25.159’ N, Long. 76°17.171’ W; then running southerly along the shore to a point at or near the south end of Meekins Neck, defined by Lat. 38°22.039’ N, Long. 76°15.771’ W; then running 181° True to a point at or near the north end of North Barren Island, defined by Lat. 38°20.634’ N, Long. 76°15.792’ W; then running southerly along the shore True to a point at or near the south end of North Barren Island, defined by Lat. 38°20.014’ N, Long. 76°15.643’ W; then running 94° True to a point at or near the north end of South Barren Island, defined by Lat. 38°20.001’ N, Long. 76°15.425’ W; then running southerly along the shore to a point at or near the south end of South Barren Island, defined by Lat. 38°19.478’ N, Long. 76°15.399’ W; then running 124° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°18.425’ N, Long. 76°13.394’ W; then running southeasterly along the shore to a point at or near the north end of Narrows Ferry Bridge, defined by Lat. 38°17.917’ N, Long. 76°12.389’ W; then running 155° True to a point at or near the south end of Narrows Ferry Bridge, defined by Lat. 38°17.676’ N, Long. 76°12.250’ W; then running southerly along the shore to a point at or near the shore at Richland Point defined by Lat. 38°14.846’ N, Long. 76°10.332’ W; then running 121° True to a point at Cow Point defined by Lat. 38°14.553’ N, Long. 76°9.922’ W; then running 126° True to a point at or near Fishing Point defined by Lat. 38°14.065’ N, Long. 76°9.065’ W; then running easterly along the shore to a point at or near the easterly tip of Lower Hoopers Island, defined by Lat. 38° 14.674' N, Long. 76° 7.795' W; then running 117° True to a point, defined by Lat. 38° 14.603'N, Long. 76° 7.618' W; then running 132° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°13.930’ N, Long. 76°6.660’ W; then running 150° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°13.203’ N, Long. 76°6.122’ W; then running 165° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°11.693’ N, Long. 76°5.593’ W; then running 121° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°11.601’ N, Long. 76°5.397’ W; then running 182° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°10.307’ N, Long. 76°5.454’ W; then running 181° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°9.652’ N, Long. 76°5.462’ W; then running 181° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°9.143’ N, Long. 76°5.471’ W; then running 177° True to a point at or near the shore at the north end of Holland Island, defined by Lat. 38°7.351’ N, Long. 76°5.419’ W; then running southerly along the shore to a point at or near the shore at the south end of Holland Island, defined by Lat. 38°6.903’ N, Long. 76°5.409’ W; then running 132° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°5.705’ N, Long. 76°3.740’ W; then running 201° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°3.690’ N, Long. 76°4.708’ W; then running 268° True to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Dorchester County and Honga River Area. The power dredge zone consists of the waters of the State that lie within Dorchester County beginning at a point defined by Lat. 38°14.603' N, Long. 76°07.618' W; then running 297° True to a point at or near the shore of Lower Hooper Island, defined by Lat. 38°14.674' N. and Long. 76°07.795' W.; then running northwesterly along the shore of Lower Hooper Island to a point at or near the shore of Lower Hooper Island, defined by Lat. 38°14.907' N. and Long. 76°09.172' W.; then running approximately 264° True to a point at or near the shore of Middle Hooper Island, defined by Lat. 38°14.899' N. and Long. 76°09.284' W.; then running northerly along the shore of Middle Hooper Island to a point at or near the shore at the south end of Narrows Ferry Bridge, defined by Lat. 38°17.675' N. and Long. 76°12.250' W.; then running approximately 335° True to a point at or near the shore at the north end of Narrows Ferry Bridge, defined by Lat. 38°17.917' N. and Long. 76°12.390' W.; then running northerly along the shore of Upper Hooper Island to a point at or near corner 5 of Natural Oyster Bar 23-1, defined by Lat. 38°20.885' N. and Long. 76°13.482' W.; then running approximately 332° True to a point at or near corner 6 of Natural Oyster Bar 23-1, defined by Lat. 38°21.095' N. and Long. 76°13.625' W.; then running northerly along the shore of Meekins Neck to a point at or near corner 7 of Natural Oyster Bar 23-1, defined by Lat. 38°21.395' N. and Long. 76°13.712' W.; running approximately 346° True to a point at or near corner 8 of Natural Oyster Bar 23-1, defined by Lat. 38°22.008' N. and Long. 76°13.912' W.; then running approximately 100° True to a point at or near corner 9 of Natural Oyster Bar 23-1, defined by Lat. 38°21.890' N. and Long. 76°13.045' W.; then running easterly along the shore to a point at or near corner 10 of Natural Oyster Bar 23-1, defined by Lat. 38°22.078' N. and Long. 76°12.402' W; then running approximately 76° True to a point at or near corner 11 of Natural Oyster Bar 23-1, defined by Lat. 38°22.148' N, Long. 76°12.038' W; then running southerly along the shore of Kirwan Neck to a point at or near corner 12 of Natural Oyster Bar 23-1, defined by Lat. 38°21.755' N, Long. 76°11.742' W; then running approximately 134° True to a point at or near corner 13 of Natural Oyster Bar 23-1, defined by Lat. 38°20.690' N, Long. 76°10.332' W; then running southerly along the shore of Kirwan Neck to a point at or near corner 14 of Natural Oyster Bar 23-1, defined by Lat. 38°20.233' N, Long. 76°10.362' W; then running approximately 231° True to a point at or near corner 1 of Natural Oyster Bar 23-1, defined by Lat. 38°20.045' N, Long. 76°10.657' W; then running southwesterly along the north shore of Wroten Island to a point at or near the south tip of Wroten Island, defined by Lat. 38°18.968' N, Long. 76°11.647' W; then running easterly along the south side of Wroten Island to a point at or near corner 4 of Natural Oyster Bar 23-5, defined by Lat. 38°19.475' N, Long. 76°10.460' W; then running approximately 90° True to a point at or near corner 5 of Natural Oyster Bar 23-5, defined by Lat. 38°19.475' N, Long. 76°10.398' W.; then running southerly along the shore of Parks Neck, Lakes Cove, and Asquith Island to a point at or near corner 7 of Natural Oyster Bar 23-10, defined by Lat. 38°16.293' N, Long. 76°08.895' W; then running easterly and southerly along the shore of Asquith Island, Fox Creek, Duck Point Cove, and Jimson Weed Marsh to a point at or near corner 1 of Natural Oyster Bar 23-9, defined by Lat. 38°15.770' N, Long. 76°06.440' W; then running southerly along the shore of Crab Point to a point defined by Lat. 38°15.250' N, Long. 76°06.052' W; then running 242° True to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Fishing Bay Area. The power dredge zone consists of the waters of the State that lie within Dorchester and Wicomico Counties beginning at a point near Lower Island Point at the turn in the Dorchester-Somerset County Line, defined by Lat. 38°08.845' N. and Long. 76°01.873' W.; then running approximately 17° True to a point at or near the shore of Bloodsworth Island at Great Cove Point defined by Lat. 38°10.310' N. and Long. 76°01.315' W.; then running northerly along the shore of Bloodsworth Island to a point at or near the south entrance of Piney Island Cove, defined by Lat. 38°10.978' N. and Long. 76°01.567' W.; then running approximately 322° True to a point at or near the north entrance of Piney Island Cove, defined by Lat. 38°11.573' N. and Long. 76°02.163' W.; then running northwesterly along the shore of Bloodsworth Island to a point at or near Tigs Point, defined by Lat. 38°12.393' N. and Long. 76°03.688' W.; then running approximately 64° True to a point at or near Bishops Head Point, defined by Lat. 38°12.918' N. and Long. 76°01.963' W.; then running northerly along the shore of Fishing Bay to a point at or near corner 2 of Natural Oyster Bar 28-2, defined by Lat. 38°14.597' N. and Long. 76°02.755' W; then running approximately 1° True to a point at or near corner 3 of Natural Oyster Bar 28-2, defined by Lat. 38°14.947' N. and Long. 76°02.748' W.; then running northerly along the shore of Fishing Bay to a point at or near corner 3 of Natural Oyster Bar 24-10, defined by Lat. 38°16.017'N. and Long. 76°01.957' W.; then running approximately 14° True to a point at or near corner 4 of Natural Oyster Bar 24-10, defined by Lat. 38°16.633' N. and Long. 76°01.813' W.; then running northerly along the shore of Little Creek Marsh to a point at or near corner 3 of Natural Oyster Bar 24-7, defined by Lat. 38°18.025' N. and Long. 76°02.980' W.; then running approximately 0° True to a point at or near corner 4 of Natural Oyster Bar 24-7, defined by Lat. 38°18.540' N. and Long. 76°02.982' W.; then running northeasterly along the shore of Cedar Creek Marsh to a point at or near corner 5 of Natural Oyster Bar 24-7, defined by Lat. 38°18.858' N. and Long. 76°02.773' W.; then running approximately 4° True to a point at or near corner 6 of Natural Oyster Bar 24-7, defined by Lat. 38°18.977' N. and Long. 76°02.762' W.; then running northeasterly along the shore of Cedar Creek Marsh to a point at or near corner 7 of Natural Oyster Bar 24-7, defined by Lat. 38°19.267' N. and Long. 76°02.555' W.; then running approximately 56° True to a point at or near corner 8 of Natural Oyster Bar 24-7, defined by Lat. 38°19.303' N. and Long. 76°02.503' W.; then running easterly along the shore of Cedar Creek Marsh to a point at or near corner 9 of Natural Oyster Bar 24-7, defined by Lat. 38°19.480' N. and Long. 76°01.888' W.; then running approximately 182° True to a point at or near corner 10 of Natural Oyster Bar 24-7, defined by Lat. 38°19.452' N. and Long. 76°01.888' W.; then running approximately 144° True to a point at or near corner 5 of Natural Oyster Bar 24-6, defined by Lat. 38°18.557' N. and Long. 76°01.065' W.; then running southeasterly along the east shore of Fishing Bay to a point at or near the southwest end of Clay Island, defined by Lat. 38°13.970' N. and Long. 75°58.352' W.; then running northeasterly along the shore of Clay Island to a point at or near Sandy Point, defined by Lat. 38°14.803' N. and Long. 75°56.385' W.; then running approximately 96° True to a point at or near the shore north of Jones Creek, defined by Lat. 38°14.635' N. and Long. 75°54.352' W; then running southeasterly along the shore of Stump Point Marsh to a point at or near Mollie Point, defined by Lat. 38°13.745' N. and Long. 75°53.028' W.; then running approximately 91° True to point at or near the Wicomico-Somerset County Line, defined by Lat. 38°13.737' N. and Long. 75°52.238' W.; then running approximately 183° True to a point at or near the Wicomico-Somerset County Line, defined by Lat. 38°12.888' N. and Long. 75°52.302' W.; then running approximately 210° True to a point at or near the Wicomico-Somerset County Line, defined by Lat. 38°12.835' N. and Long. 75°52.342' W.; then running approximately 255° True to a point at or near the Wicomico-Somerset County Line, defined by Lat. 38°12.737' N. and Long. 75°52.815' W.; then running approximately 283° True to a point at or near the Wicomico-Somerset County Line, defined by Lat. 38°12.913' N. and Long. 75°53.810' W.; then running approximately 251° True to a point at or near the Wicomico-Somerset County Line, defined by Lat. 38°12.317' N. and Long. 75°55.972' W.; then running approximately 274° True to a point at or near the intersection of the Wicomico-Somerset County Line and the Dorchester County Line, defined by Lat. 38°12.403' N. and Long. 75°57.467' W.; then running approximately 230° True to a point at or near the Dorchester –Somerset County Line, defined by Lat. 38°11.837' N. and Long. 75°58.325' W.; then running approximately 230° True to a point at or near buoy "C" on an existing crab line south of Sharkfin Shoal Lighthouse, defined by Lat. 38°11.167' N. and Long. 75°59.338' W; then running approximately 186° True to a point at or near buoy "A" on the intersection of an existing crab line and the Dorchester-Somerset County Line, defined by Lat. 38°09.792' N. and Long. 75°59.517' W.; then running approximately 243° True to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>St. Mary's County and St. Mary’s River.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>St. Mary’s County. All of the waters of the State that lie contiguous to Saint Mary’s County enclosed by a line beginning at a point on the shore at the north side of the north jetty at Smith Point defined by Lat. 37°53.383’ N, Long. 76°14.217’ W; then running 335° True to a point on the shore at Point Lookout, defined by Lat. 38°2.250’ N, Long. 76°19.332’ W; then running 107° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°2.172’ N, Long. 76°19.016’ W; then running 90° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°2.169’ N, Long. 76°18.358’ W; then running 22° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°3.009’ N, Long. 76°17.932’ W; then running 271° True to a point on the shore, defined by Lat. 38°3.020’ N, Long. 76°19.268’ W; then running northerly along the shore, excluding all creeks and coves less than 300 feet in width to a point on the shore south of Cedar Point defined by Lat. 38°15.005’ N, Long. 76°23.805’ W; then running 90° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°15.007’ N, Long. 76°22.456’ W; then running 44° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°15.723’ N, Long. 76°21.578’ W; then running 353° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°17.936’ N, Long. 76°21.913’ W; then running 269° True to a point on the shore at Cedar Point defined by Lat. 38°17.932’ N, Long. 76°22.384’ W; then running 76° True to a point at the intersection of the Saint Mary’s-Calvert-Dorchester county line, defined by Lat. 38°18.602’ N, Long. 76°19.088’ W; then running 171° True to a point on the Saint Mary’s-Dorchester county line, defined by Lat. 38°17.967’ N, Long. 76°18.967’ W; then running 158° True to a point on the Saint Mary’s-Dorchester county line, defined by Lat. 38°4.586’ N, Long. 76°11.983’ W; then running 189° True to a point on the Saint Mary’s-Somerset county line at the south jetty at Smith Point defined by Lat. 37°53.400’ N, Long. 76°14.167’ W; then running 247° True to the point of beginning; except the waters of Point Lookout Sanctuary which is described as: All of the waters of the area enclosed by a line beginning at a point defined by Lat. 38°2.169' N, Long. 76°18.358' W; then running 270° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°2.172' N, Long. 76°19.016' W; then running 358° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°3.018' N, Long. 76°19.056' W; then running 91° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°3.009' N, Long. 76°17.932' W; then running 202° True to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>St. Mary’s River. All of the waters of the State that lie in Saint Mary’s County, enclosed by a line beginning at a point Jurisdictional Marker PRM2A, defined by Lat. 38°6.360’ N, Long. 76°25.301’ W; then running 272° True to a point Jurisdictional Marker PRM2B, defined by Lat. 38°6.426’ N, Long. 76°27.899’ W; then running 272° True to a point on the shore at St. George’s Island, defined by Lat. 38°6.427’ N, Long. 76°27.937’ W; then running northeasterly along the shore to a point at the northeast end of a jetty, defined by Lat. 38°6.637’ N, Long. 76°27.750’ W; then running 269° True to a point on the shore of St. George’s Island, defined by Lat. 38°6.635’ N, Long. 76°27.966’ W; then running northwesterly along the shore to a point on the shore at Ball Point defined by Lat. 38°7.252’ N, Long. 76°28.377’ W; then running 30° True to a point on the shore at Cherryfield Point defined by Lat. 38°7.742’ N, Long. 76°28.022’ W; then running 111° True to a point at Natural Oyster Bar corner 27-16-2, defined by Lat. 38°7.685’ N, Long. 76°27.832’ W; then running 39° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°7.971’ N, Long. 76°27.534’ W; then running 353° True to a point at Natural Oyster Bar corner 27-16-4, defined by Lat. 38°8.371’ N, Long. 76°27.594’ W; then running 269° True to a point on the shore at Edmund Point defined by Lat. 38°8.370’ N, Long. 76°27.677’ W; then running northwesterly along the shore to a point defined by Lat. 38°8.934’ N, Long. 76°28.084’ W; then running 335° True to Josh Point defined by Lat. 38°9.178’ N, Long. 76°28.227’ W; then running northeasterly along the shore to a point on the shore south of Pagan Point defined by Lat. 38°11.279’ N, Long. 76°26.639’ W; then running 89° True to a point on the shore at Church Point defined by Lat. 38°11.286’ N, Long. 76°26.263’ W; then running southerly along the shore to a point on the shore at Rosecroft Point defined by Lat. 38°9.582’ N, Long. 76°26.256’ W; then running 141° True to a point on the south side of Saint Inigoes Creek, defined by Lat. 38°9.312’ N, Long. 76°25.981’ W; then running southerly along the shore to a point on the shore at Kitts Point defined by Lat. 38°6.365’ N, Long. 76°25.280’ W; then running 252° True to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Somerset County.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Kedges Straits. The power dredge zone consists of the waters of the State that lie within Somerset County beginning at a point at or near Fog Point, defined by Lat. 38°02.193' N, Long. 76°02.588' W, then running approximately 63° True to a point at or near Solomons Lump Lighthouse, defined by Lat. 38°02.883' N, Long. 76°00.883' W, then running approximately 3° True to a point at or near Sheepshead Point, defined by Lat. 38°04.283' N, Long.76°00.788 W; then running approximately 285° True to a point at or near the westerly entrance of Sheepshead Bay, defined by Lat. 38°04.533' N, Long. 76°01.975 W, then running northwesterly along the west side of South Marsh Island to a point at or near Sedgy Point defined by Lat. 38°05.484' N, Long. 76°03.352' W; then running approximately 306° True to a point at or near Pry Island defined by Lat. 38°05.705' N, Long. 76°03.734' W, then running approximately 203° to a point at or near the intersection of the Somerset-Dorchester county line and the line demarcating the waters contiguous to Somerset County depicted on Chart 32 of the Oyster Survey of 1906—1912 and amendments, defined by Lat. 38°04.783' N, Long. 76°04.182' W, then running approximately 150° True to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Contiguous Waters. All of the waters of the State that lie contiguous to Somerset County, enclosed by a line beginning at a point at Maryland-Virginia Boundary defined by Lat. 37°53.193’ N, Long. 76°14.198’ W; then running 7° True to a point on the shore on the north side of the north jetty at Smith Point defined by Lat. 37°53.401’ N, Long. 76°14.166’ W; then running 9° True to a point on the Somerset-Dorchester-Saint Mary’s county line, defined by Lat. 38°3.498’ N, Long. 76°12.198’ W; then running 88° True to a point on the Somerset-Dorchester county line, defined by Lat. 38°3.517’ N, Long. 76°11.532’ W; then running 162° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°59.798’ N, Long. 76°9.965’ W; then running 103° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°58.800’ N, Long. 76°4.680’ W; then running 351° True to a point on the Somerset-Dorchester county line, defined by Lat. 38°3.667’ N, Long. 76°5.636’ W; then running 88° True to a point on the Somerset-Dorchester County line, defined by Lat. 38°3.690’ N, Long. 76°4.707’ W; then running 21° True to a point on the intersection of the Somerset-Dorchester county line and the contiguous waters line, defined by Lat. 38°4.781’ N, Long. 76°4.181’ W; then running 161° True to a point on the shore at Fog Point defined by Lat. 38°1.984’ N, Long. 76°2.496’ W; then running southerly along the shore to a point on the shore at Channel Point defined by Lat. 38°0.585’ N, Long. 76°2.952’ W; then running 194° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°0.030’ N, Long. 76°3.129’ W; then running 175° True to the Maryland-Virginia line, defined by Lat. 37°57.212’ N, Long. 76°2.836’ W; then running 270° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°57.213’ N, Long. 76°3.119’ W; then running 245° True to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Great Rock. The power dredge zone consists of the waters of the State that lie within Somerset County beginning at a point defined by Lat. 37°57.707' N., Long. 75°55.834' W., then running approximately 81° True to a point at or near Janes Island Light, defined by Lat. 37°57.803' N., Long. 75°55.108' W., then running approximately 105° True to a point defined by Lat. 37°57.462' N., Long. 75°53.520' W., then running approximately 188° True to a point at or near the Maryland-Virginia state line, defined by Lat. 37°54.610' N., Long. 75°54.016' W., then running approximately 266° True to a point at or near the Maryland-Virginia state line, defined by Lat. 37°54.462' N., Long. 75°56.430' W., then running approximately 8° True to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Smith Island. The power dredge zone consists of the waters of the State that lie within Somerset County beginning at a point defined by Lat. 38°02.243' N., Long. 75°55.438' W., then running approximately 177° True to a point at or near Janes Island Light, defined by Lat. 37°57.803' N., Long. 75°55.108' W., then running approximately 260° True to a point near the corner of the Maryland-Virginia state line at Horse Hammock, defined by Lat. 37°57.221' N., Long. 75°59.478' W., then running approximately 19° True to a point near Terrapin Sands Point, defined by Lat. 38°00.247' N., Long. 75°58.181' W., then running approximately 331° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°01.424' N., Long. 75°58.993' W., then running approximately 307° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°02.211' N., Long. 76°00.305' W., then running approximately 34° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°02.992' N., Long. 75°59.637' W., then running approximately 103° True to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Manokin River. All of the waters of the State that lie within Somerset County enclosed by a line beginning at a point in the mouth of the Manokin River, defined by Lat. 38°2.243’ N, Long. 75°55.438’ W; then running 1° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°6.094’ N, Long. 75°55.389’ W; then running 126° True to a point on the shore at Hazard Point defined by Lat. 38°4.571’ N, Long. 75°52.694’ W; then running southeasterly along the shore to a point on the shore at Porpoise Point defined by Lat. 38°3.648’ N, Long. 75°52.422’ W; then running easterly along the shore to a point on the shore at Scott’s Point defined by Lat. 38°3.544’ N, Long. 75°48.794’ W; then running 134° True to a point on the shore at Long Point defined by Lat. 38°3.184’ N, Long. 75°48.326’ W; then running 252° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°2.802’ N, Long. 75°49.819’ W; then running 251° True to a point on the shore at Tenth Point defined by Lat. 38°2.303’ N, Long. 75°51.610’ W; then running southwesterly along the shore to a point on the shore at Flatcap Point defined by Lat. 38°2.147’ N, Long. 75°52.160’ W; then running 272° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°2.217’ N, Long. 75°54.349’ W; then running 44° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°2.500’ N, Long. 75°54.000’ W; then running 316° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°2.717’ N, Long. 75°54.267’ W; then running 224° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°2.433’ N, Long. 75°54.615’ W; then running 136° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°2.217’ N, Long. 75°54.349’ W; then running 272° True to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Pocomoke Sound. The power dredge zone consists of the waters of the State that lie within Somerset County beginning at a point at or near Maryland-Virginia Line Corner A in Pocomoke Sound, defined by Lat. 37°54.732' N. and Long. 75°48.063' W.; then running approximately 330° True to a point at or near the shore on Ware Point, defined by Lat. 37°56.345' N, Long. 75°49.247' W.; then running along the north shore of Pocomoke Sound, including Ape Hole Creek and East Creek then running along the shore to a point at or near Tulls Point at the west end of an existing Maryland Department of the Environment conditional line, defined by Lat. 37°57.775' N. and Long. 75°44.240' W., then running approximately 83° True to a point, defined by Lat. 37°57.865' N. and Long. 75°43.277' W.; then running approximately 85° True to a point, defined by Lat. 37°57.923' N. and Long. 75°42.440' W.; then running approximately 84° True to a point at or near the shore near the Handy Lodge, defined by Lat. 37°58.003' N. and Long. 75°41.420' W.; then running along the north shore of Pocomoke Sound to a point at or near the shore on the northeasterly entrance to Fair Island Channel, defined by Lat. 37°57.792' N. and Long. 75°39.328' W.; then running approximately 60° True to a point at or near Maryland-Virginia Line Corner N, defined by Lat. 37°57.985' N. and Long. 75°38.915' W.; then running approximately 179° True to a point at or near Maryland-Virginia Line Corner M, defined by Lat. 37°56.802' N. and Long. 75°38.893' W.; then running approximately 256° True to a point at or near Maryland-Virginia Line Corner L, defined by Lat. 37°56.710' N. and Long. 75°39.370' W.; then running approximately 298° True to a point at or near Maryland-Virginia Line Corner K, defined by Lat. 37°56.993' N. and Long. 75°40.043' W.; then running approximately 286° True to a point at or near Maryland-Virginia Line Corner J, defined by Lat. 37°57.318' N. and Long. 75°41.502' W.; then running approximately 266° True to a point or near Maryland-Virginia Line Corner H, defined by Lat. 37°57.272' N. and Long. 75°42.287' W.; then running approximately 254° True to a point at or near Maryland-Virginia Line Corner D, defined by Lat. 37°56.473' N. and Long. 75°45.705' W.; then running approximately 227° True to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Talbot County. All of the waters of the State that lie in Talbot County, enclosed by a line beginning at a point on the shore at Chlora Point defined by Lat. 38°38.225’ N, Long. 76°8.818’ W; then running 302° True to a point at Choptank River Lighthouse, defined by Lat. 38°39.344’ N, Long. 76°11.069’ W; then running 287° True to a point on the shore at Upper Bar Neck Point defined by Lat. 38°41.366’ N, Long. 76°19.333’ W; then running northwesterly along the shore to a point on the shore, defined by Lat. 38°42.240’ N, Long. 76°19.998’ W; then running 67° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°42.825’ N, Long. 76°18.214’ W; then running 193° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°42.667’ N, Long. 76°18.262’ W; then running 86° True to a point on the shore west of Nelson Point defined by Lat. 38°42.767’ N, Long. 76°16.527’ W; then running southeasterly along the shore to a point on the shore at Nelson Point defined by Lat. 38°42.549’ N, Long. 76°16.281’ W; then running 61° True to a point on the south side of Bridge Creek, defined by Lat. 38°43.440’ N, Long. 76°14.196’ W; then running southerly along the shore to a point on the shore at Holland Point defined by Lat. 38°41.879’ N, Long. 76°13.611’ W; then running 186° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°41.838’ N, Long. 76°13.617’ W; then running 92° True to a point on the shore at Lucy Point defined by Lat. 38°41.825’ N, Long. 76°13.178’ W; then running southeasterly to a point on the shore of Ferry Neck, defined by Lat. 38°40.354’ N, Long. 76°12.083’ W; then running 144° True to a point on the shore at Benoni Point defined by Lat. 38°40.249’ N, Long. 76°11.969’ W; then running 96° True to a point on the shore at the north side of Boone Creek, defined by Lat. 38°40.090’ N, Long. 76°10.138’ W; then running 118° True to a point on the shore at the south side of Boone Creek, defined by Lat. 38°40.011’ N, Long. 76°9.954’ W; then running then running southeasterly along the shore to a point on the shore at the north side of Island Creek, defined by Lat. 38°39.697’ N, Long. 76°9.699’ W; then running 120° True to a point on the shore at the south side of Island Creek, defined by Lat. 38°39.517’ N, Long. 76°9.300’ W; then running southeasterly along the shore to the point of beginning.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Power Dredge Study Areas. An individual may catch oysters only by power dredge in the areas listed in §C(1)—(3) of this regulation.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Queen Anne’s County Power Dredge Study Areas:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Eastern Bay enclosed by a line beginning at a point defined by Lat. 38°53.805’ N, Long. 76°15.450’ W; then running 274° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°53.831’ N, Long. 76°15.920’ W; then running 313° True to a point defined by Lat. 38° 54.060’ N, Long. 76° 16.230’ W; then running 53° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°54.482’ N, Long. 76°15.511’ W; then running 91° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°54.476’ N, Long. 76°15.059’ W; then running 199° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°54.130’ N, Long. 76°15.213’ W; then running 210° True to the point of beginning; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>All of the waters of Eastern Bay enclosed by a line beginning at a point defined by Lat. 38°52.672’ N, Long. 76°18.659’ W; then running 304° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°52.995’ N, Long. 76°19.265’ W; then running 36° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°53.465’ N, Long. 76°18.825’ W; then running 122° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°53.160’ N, Long. 76°18.211’ W; then running 216° True to the point of beginning.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Kent County Power Dredge Study Area. All of the waters of the Chesapeake Bay enclosed by a line beginning at a point defined by Lat. 39°7.690’ N, Long. 76°18.868’ W; then running 5° True to a point defined by Lat. 39°8.482’ N, Long. 76°18.772’ W; then running 111° True to a point defined by Lat. 39°8.258’ N, Long. 76°18.038’ W; then running 111° True to a point defined by Lat. 39°8.114’ N, Long. 76°17.546’ W; then running 170° True to a point defined by Lat. 39°7.603’ N, Long. 76°17.432’ W; then running 272° True to a point defined by Lat. 39°7.623’ N, Long. 76°18.167’ W; then running 277° True to the point of beginning.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Dorchester County Power Dredge Study Area. All of the waters of Holland Straits enclosed by a line beginning at a point defined by Lat. 38°6.359' N, Long. 76°3.752' W, then running 273° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°6.385' N, Long. 76°4.481' W, then running 2° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°6.840' N, Long. 76°4.463' W, then running 95° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°6.790' N, Long. 76°3.749' W, then running 180° True to the point of beginning.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Wild Grounds Study Area.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The study area consists of all of the waters of Eastern Bay enclosed by a line beginning at a point defined by Lat. 38°53.160' N, Long. 76°18.211' W; then running 302° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°53.465' N, Long. 76°18.825' W; then running 36° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°53.633' N, Long. 76°18.668' W; then running 124° True to a point defined by Lat. 38°53.320' N, Long. 76°18.063' W; then running 216° True to the point of beginning.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A commercial licensee may not harvest oysters with a power dredge in this area unless authorized by public notice in accordance with <cite path="08|02|04|.12|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Public Notice.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In order to evaluate the potential effects of power dredging, the Department may, by public notice:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Open or close portions of the areas defined in §§C(2) and D(1) of this regulation to the harvest of oysters; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Specify gear that may be used in portions of the area defined in <cite path="08|02|04|.12|D.|(1)">§D(1) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If it is determined necessary to maintain surface shell, the Department may by public notice establish the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Portions of the areas defined in §§C(2) and D(1) of this regulation in which maintenance is necessary;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Allowable gears for maintenance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A requirement to receive prior written permission by the Department to perform maintenance on the area;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Number of licensees who may perform maintenance on the area; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Dates and times during which the maintenance may be performed.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The public notice shall state its effective hour and date and shall be published on the Fisheries Service website at least 48 hours in advance of the effective hour and date.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Secretary shall make a reasonable effort to disseminate a public notice issued under this section through various other media so that an affected individual has a reasonable opportunity to be informed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A violation of the restrictions set by the Secretary in accordance with this section is a violation of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Repealed.</heading>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Repealed.</heading>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|02|04|.15">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Oyster Sanctuaries.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Oyster Sanctuaries of the Chesapeake Bay and Its Tidal Tributaries (September 2010) designates oyster sanctuaries in the Chesapeake Bay and its tidal tributaries and is hereby incorporated by reference.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Harvest from a Sanctuary.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may not harvest wild oysters from a sanctuary established in <cite path="08|02|04|.15|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="08|02|04|.15|B.|(3)">§B(3) of this regulation</cite>, a person may not harvest clams from a sanctuary designated in Section I of “Oyster Sanctuaries of the Chesapeake Bay and Its Tidal Tributaries (September 2010)” that is incorporated by reference in <cite path="08|02|04|.15|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person may harvest clams from the Chester ORA Zone A sanctuary.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Aquaculture in Sanctuaries.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="08|02|04|.15|C.|(2)">§C(2) of this regulation</cite>, a shellfish lease may not be located within 150 feet of a Yates Bar located in an oyster sanctuary established in <cite path="08|02|04|.15|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Until termination in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-11">Natural Resources Article, §4-11</cite>A-10, Annotated Code of Maryland or surrender in accordance with <cite path="08.02.23.03|J.">COMAR 08.02.23.03J</cite>, leased areas and all areas within 150 feet of the leased areas existing at the time of the enactment of Ch. 173, Acts of 2009 shall not be considered part of the sanctuaries as established in <cite path="08|02|04|.15|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A leaseholder under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-11">Natural Resources Article, §4-11</cite>A, Annotated Code of Maryland, or permit registrant under <cite path="08.02.23.04">COMAR 08.02.23.04</cite> shall notify the Department as specified on the Shellfish Aquaculture Harvester Permit 48 hours in advance of using a power dredge in areas described in §A or C(2) of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>No more than 10 percent of each oyster sanctuary established in <cite path="08|02|04|.15|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall be leased for shellfish aquaculture.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>St. Mary’s River Oyster Sanctuary.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Department shall, based on the results of the Maryland Geological Survey’s 2010 sonar survey, post on its website a map of the areas of restorable bottom in the St. Mary’s River Oyster Sanctuary.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A lease may only be issued in the St. Mary’s River Oyster Sanctuary if the results of a biological survey approved by the Department indicate the average oyster density is less than 15 oysters per square meter in:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The restorable bottom portion of the proposed lease area; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The remaining bottom in the proposed lease area.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>No more than 25 percent of the total restorable bottom in the St. Mary’s River Oyster Sanctuary shall be leased for shellfish aquaculture purposes.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Recording the Catching and Disposal of Oysters. —Repealed.</heading>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.17</num>
    <heading>Public Shellfish Fishery Area.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Public Shellfish Fishery Areas of the Chesapeake Bay and Its Tidal Tributaries (June 2023) designates public shellfish fishery areas in the Chesapeake Bay and its tidal tributaries and is hereby incorporated by reference.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Declassification.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person may petition the Department to declassify a portion of a public shellfish fishery area by submitting a lease application as described in <cite path="08.02.23.03|A.">COMAR 08.02.23.03A</cite> or B and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-11">Natural Resources Article, §4-11</cite>A-09, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The declassification of a public shellfish fishery area may be approved:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If the results of a biological survey conducted by the Department or a designated agent show that the average density of oysters per square meter is equal to or below the maximum threshold of one oyster that is 1 inch or greater per square meter;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>After commercial harvest activity and other quantitative data is considered by the Department;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If the lease application meets the requirements of <cite path="08.02.23.03">COMAR 08.02.23.03</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>If the lease application is approved in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr">Natural Resources Article, Title 4, Subtitle 11A, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Natural Resources Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-215">4-215</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-2">4-2</cite>A-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|03">03</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-701">4-701</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-1008">4-1008</cite>.1, 4-1009, 4-1009.1, 4-1012, 4-1013, 4-1015, 4-1015.1, 4-1018, 4-1019,<br/>4-1019.2, 4-1027, 4-1103, 4-1106, 4-11A-04, 4-11A-05, and 4-11A-12, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1975-07-23">Effective date: July 23, 1975 (2:16 Md. R. 1138)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-10-07"><cite path="|08|02|04|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective November 29, 2010 (37:24 Md. R. 1657); October 7, 2019 (46:20 Md. R. 843)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-10-05"><cite path="|08|02|04|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective October 5, 2020 (47:20 Md. R. 874)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-06-21"><cite path="|08|02|04|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective August 15, 1983 (10:16 Md. R. 1450); June 21, 1993 (20:12 Md. R. 996)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-12-28"><cite path="|08|02|04|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective September 14, 1998 (25:21 Md. R. 1570); amended permanently effective December 28, 1998 (25:26 Md. R. 1919)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-08-26"><cite path="|08|02|04|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective October 11, 2004 (31:20 Md. R. 1484); August 26, 2019 (46:17 Md. R. 725)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1987-09-14"><cite path="|08|02|04|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective September 14, 1987 (14:20 Md. R. 2138); emergency status expired January 11, 1988</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1988-09-15"><cite path="|08|02|04|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective September 15, 1988 (15:21 Md. R. 2465)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-09-15">Regulations .02B and .06 amended as an emergency provision effective September 15, 1989 (16:21 Md. R. 2254); emergency status expired March 31, 1990</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-09-15">Regulations .02B and .06 amended as an emergency provision effective September 15, 1990 (17:20 Md. R. 2420); emergency status expired March 31, 1991</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1991-09-15">Regulations .02 and .06 amended as an emergency provision effective September 15, 1991 (18:18 Md. R. 2000); emergency status expired March 31, 1992</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-09-15">Regulations .02 and .06 amended as an emergency provision effective September 15, 1992 (19:19 Md. R. 1700); emergency status expired March 31, 1993</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-09-15">Regulations .02B and .06 amended as an emergency provision effective September 15, 1993 (20:21 Md. R. 1649); emergency status expired March 31, 1994</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-10-01">Regulations .02B and .06 amended as an emergency provision effective October 1, 1994 (21:21 Md. R. 1809); emergency status expired April 1, 1995</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1996-02-27">Regulations .02B and .06 amended as an emergency provision effective October 5, 1995 (22:22 Md. R. 1653); Regulation .02B amended as an emergency provision effective February 27, 1996 (23:6 Md. R. 468); emergency status expired March 31, 1996</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1996-09-15">Regulations .02B and .06 amended as an emergency provision effective September 15, 1996 (23:19 Md. R. 1370); emergency status expired March 31, 1997</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1997-10-01">Regulations .02B and .06 amended as an emergency provision effective October 1, 1997 (24:22 Md. R. 1549); emergency status expired April 1, 1998</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-10-19"><cite path="|08|02|04|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective April 20, 2009 (36:8 Md. R. 595); October 19, 2009 (36:21 Md. R. 1590)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-07-31"><cite path="|08|02|04|.02|D.">Regulation .02D</cite> amended effective July 31, 1995 (22:15 Md. R. 1118)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1976-03-17"><cite path="|08|02|04|.02|F.">Regulation .02F</cite> adopted effective March 17, 1976 (3:6 Md. R. 358)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1983-08-15"><cite path="|08|02|04|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective August 15, 1983 (10:16 Md. R. 1450)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-12-28"><cite path="|08|02|04|.03">Regulation .03</cite> repealed and new Regulation .03 adopted as an emergency provision effective September 14, 1998 (25:21 Md. R. 1570); adopted permanently effective December 28, 1998 (25:26 Md. R. 1919)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-09-25"><cite path="|08|02|04|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective September 25, 2000 (27:20 Md. R. 1835); emergency status expired September 30, 2000</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-03-31"><cite path="|08|02|04|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective March 31, 2015 (42:8 Md. R. 605); emergency status expired April 30, 2015</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-08-26"><cite path="|08|02|04|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective August 26, 2019 (46:17 Md. R. 725)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-10-19"><cite path="|08|02|04|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite> amended effective April 20, 2009 (36:8 Md. R. 595); October 19, 2009 (36:21 Md. R. 1590)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1981-05-29"><cite path="|08|02|04|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite> amended effective May 29, 1981 (8:11 Md. R. 972)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-12-11"><cite path="|08|02|04|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective November 1, 2000 (27:20 Md. R. 1835); amended permanently effective December 11, 2000 (27:24 Md. R. 2199)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-10-11"><cite path="|08|02|04|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite> amended effective October 11, 2004 (31:20 Md. R. 1484)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-11-13"><cite path="|08|02|04|.03|C.">Regulation .03C</cite> amended effective November 5, 2007 (34:22 Md. R. 1976); November 13, 2023 (50:22 Md. R. 973)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-11-05"><cite path="|08|02|04|.03|D.">Regulation .03D</cite> adopted effective November 5, 2007 (34:22 Md. R. 1976)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-08-18"><cite path="|08|02|04|.03|E.">Regulation .03E</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective August 18, 2011 (38:19 Md. R. 1143); emergency status expired January 9, 2012</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-01-09"><cite path="|08|02|04|.03|E.">Regulation .03E</cite> adopted effective January 9, 2012 (38:27 Md. R. 1763)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-11-13"><cite path="|08|02|04|.03|E.">Regulation .03E</cite> amended effective November 13, 2023 (50:22 Md. R. 973)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-12-22"><cite path="|08|02|04|.03|F.">Regulation .03F</cite> adopted effective December 22, 2014 (41:25 Md. R. 1477)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-08-18"><cite path="|08|02|04|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective August 18, 2011 (38:19 Md. R. 1143); emergency status expired January 9, 2012</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-01-09"><cite path="|08|02|04|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective January 9, 2012 (38:27 Md. R. 1763)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-07-19"><cite path="|08|02|04|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 19, 2013 (40:16 Md. R. 1338); emergency provision expired December 23, 2013</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-04-01"><cite path="|08|02|04|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective December 23, 2013 (40:25 Md. R. 2067); April 1, 2024 (51:6 Md. R. 270)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1983-11-17"><cite path="|08|02|04|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective November 17, 1983 (9:26 Md. R. 2579); emergency provision expired March 17, 1984</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-08-05"><cite path="|08|02|04|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite> amended effective August 5, 2024 (51:15 Md. R. 706)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1983-04-25"><cite path="|08|02|04|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite>—C amended effective April 25, 1983 (10:8 Md. R. 725)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-12-31"><cite path="|08|02|04|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective March 29, 1982 (9:6 Md. R. 613); December 31, 2018 (45:26 Md. R. 1240)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1983-08-15"><cite path="|08|02|04|.05|A.">Regulation .05A</cite> amended effective August 15, 1983 (10:16 Md. R. 1450)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1987-09-14"><cite path="|08|02|04|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective September 14, 1987 (14:20 Md. R. 2138); emergency provision expired January 11, 1988</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1988-09-15"><cite path="|08|02|04|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective September 15, 1988 (15:21 Md. R. 2465)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-12-28"><cite path="|08|02|04|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective September 14, 1998 ((25:21 Md. R. 1570); amended permanently effective December 28, 1998 (25:26 Md. R. 1919)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-09-25"><cite path="|08|02|04|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective September 25, 2000 (27:20 Md. R. 1835); emergency provision expired September 30, 2000</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-12-11"><cite path="|08|02|04|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective November 1, 2000 (27:20 Md. R. 1835); amended permanently effective December 11, 2000 (27:24 Md. R. 2199)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-09-06"><cite path="|08|02|04|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective November 10, 2003 (30:22 Md. R. 1577); September 6, 2010 (37:18 Md. R. 1213)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-08-18"><cite path="|08|02|04|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective August 18, 2011 (38:19 Md. R. 1143); emergency status expired January 9, 2012</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-01-09"><cite path="|08|02|04|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective January 9, 2012 (38:27 Md. R. 1763)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-08-26"><cite path="|08|02|04|.06">Regulation .06</cite> repealed effective August 26, 2019 (46:17 Md. R. 725)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1983-08-15"><cite path="|08|02|04|.06|C.">Regulation .06C</cite> amended effective August 15, 1983 (10:16 Md. R. 1450)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1977-01-20"><cite path="|08|02|04|.06|D.">Regulation .06D</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective January 20, 1977 (4:4 Md. R. 278); emergency status expired January 30, 1977</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1983-08-15"><cite path="|08|02|04|.06|D.">Regulation .06D</cite> adopted effective August 15, 1983 (10:16 Md. R. 1450)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1975-09-03"><cite path="|08|02|04|.07">Regulation .07</cite> adopted effective September 3, 1975 (2:20 Md. R. 1300)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-10-12"><cite path="|08|02|04|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective April 14, 1976 (3:3 Md. R. 425); October 12, 2015 (42:20 Md. R. 1263)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1978-06-30"><cite path="|08|02|04|.07|B.">Regulation .07B</cite> amended effective June 30, 1978 (5:13 Md. R. 1042)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1979-10-04"><cite path="|08|02|04|.08">Regulation .08</cite>, Oyster Culling — Commercial, adopted as an emergency provision effective October 10, 1978 (5:21 Md. R. 1584), expired February 28, 1979; March 21, 1979 (6:7 Md. R. 575), expired August 4, 1979; October 4, 1979 (6:21 Md. R. 1705), expired March 31, 1980</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1982-03-29"><cite path="|08|02|04|.08">Regulation .08</cite> adopted effective March 29, 1982 (9:6 Md. R. 613)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-10-07"><cite path="|08|02|04|.08">Regulation .08</cite> amended effective November 29, 2010 (37:24 Md. R. 1657); October 7, 2019 (46:20 Md. R. 843)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1977-02-09"><cite path="|08|02|04|.09">Regulation .09</cite>, Handscraping for Oysters, adopted as an emergency provision effective February 9, 1977 (4:6 Md. R. 503), expired February 23, 1977</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1982-09-15"><cite path="|08|02|04|.09">Regulation .09</cite>, Power Assisted Hand Tonging, adopted as an emergency provision effective September 15, 1982 (9:21 Md. R. 2103), expired January 15, 1983</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1983-09-12"><cite path="|08|02|04|.09">Regulation .09</cite>, Areas Reserved for Hand Tonging, Exceptions, adopted effective September 12, 1983 (10:18 Md. R. 1607)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-11-29"><cite path="|08|02|04|.09">Regulation .09</cite> amended effective November 29, 2010 (37:24 Md. R. 1657)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-10-01"><cite path="|08|02|04|.09">Regulation .09</cite> amended effective October 1, 2012 (39:19 Md. R. 1236)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-09-29"><cite path="|08|02|04|.09">Regulation .09</cite> repealed and new Regulation .09 adopted effective September 29, 2014 (41:19 Md. R. 1076)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-10-25"><cite path="|08|02|04|.09|T.">Regulation .09T</cite> amended effective October 25, 1993 (20:21 Md. R. 1653)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1983-12-05"><cite path="|08|02|04|.09|X.">Regulation .09X</cite> and Y adopted as an emergency provision effective September 15, 1983 (10:20 Md. R. 1780); adopted permanently December 5, 1983 (10:24 Md. R. 2184)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1983-10-31"><cite path="|08|02|04|.10">Regulation .10</cite>, Prolonging the Season for Catching Oysters, adopted as an emergency provision effective March 15, 1977 (4:7 Md. R. 575), March 9, 1978 (5:6 Md. R. 448), October 30, 1978 (5:21 Md. R. 1584), March 6, 1979 (6:6 Md. R. 507), October 29, 1979 (6:21 Md. R. 1705); March 14, 1980 (7:7 Md. R. 704), expired March 26, 1980; March 16, 1981 (8:7 Md. R. 639), expired April 11, 1981; October 31, 1983 (10:23 Md. R. 2060), expired February 28, 1984</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-12-28"><cite path="|08|02|04|.10">Regulation .10</cite>, Dredging with an Auxiliary Yawl Boat, adopted as an emergency provision effective September 14, 1998 (25:21 Md. R. 1570); adopted permanently effective December 28, 1998 (25:26 Md. R. 1919)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-12-11"><cite path="|08|02|04|.10">Regulation .10</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective November 1, 2000 (27:20 Md. R. 1835); amended permanently effective December 11, 2000 (27:24 Md. R. 2199)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-09-06"><cite path="|08|02|04|.10|A.">Regulation .10A</cite> amended effective September 6, 2010 (37:18 Md. R. 1213)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-08-26"><cite path="|08|02|04|.10|A.">Regulation .10A</cite>, B amended effective August 26, 2019 (46:17 Md. R. 725)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1979-10-19"><cite path="|08|02|04|.11">Regulation .11</cite>, Hand Tonging in South River, adopted as an emergency provision effective October 19, 1979 (6:22 Md. R. 1774), expired March 31, 1980</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1980-03-28"><cite path="|08|02|04|.11">Regulation .11</cite>, Extending the Tonging Season for Catching Oysters, adopted as an emergency provision effective March 28, 1980 (7:8 Md. R. 769); expired April 5, 1980</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-12-28"><cite path="|08|02|04|.11">Regulation .11</cite>, General Provisions, adopted as an emergency provision effective September 14, 1998 (25:21 Md. R. 1570); adopted permanently effective December 28, 1998 (25:26 Md. R. 1919)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-08-26"><cite path="|08|02|04|.11">Regulation .11</cite> amended effective September 6, 2010 (37:18 Md. R. 1213); March 28, 2016 (43:6 Md. R. 404); August 26, 2019 (46:17 Md. R. 725)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-12-26"><cite path="|08|02|04|.11|A.">Regulation .11A</cite>, C amended effective December 26, 2022 (49:26 Md. R. 1078)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-10-11"><cite path="|08|02|04|.11|D.">Regulation .11D</cite>, E adopted effective October 11, 2004 (31:20 Md. R. 1484)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-07-10"><cite path="|08|02|04|.11|E.">Regulation .11E</cite>, G amended effective June 26, 2023 (50:12 Md. R. 475); July 10, 2023 (50:13 Md. R. 511)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-03-03"><cite path="|08|02|04|.11|F.">Regulation .11F</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective January 2, 2014 (41:2 Md. R. 88); amended permanently effective March 3, 2014 (41:4 Md. R. 299)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-09-24"><cite path="|08|02|04|.11|G.">Regulation .11G</cite>, H adopted effective September 24, 2007 (34:19 Md. R. 1649)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-03-24"><cite path="|08|02|04|.11|I.">Regulation .11I</cite> adopted effective March 24, 2008 (35:6 Md. R. 696)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-11-01"><cite path="|08|02|04|.12">Regulation .12</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective November 1, 1999 (26:24 Md. R. 1851); emergency status extended at 27:8 Md. R. 794; emergency status expired April 14, 2000</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-04-16"><cite path="|08|02|04|.12">Regulation .12</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective November 8, 2000 (27:24 Md. R. 2197); adopted permanently effective April 16, 2001 (28:7 Md. R. 688)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-09-29"><cite path="|08|02|04|.12">Regulation .12</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective January 27, 2003 (30:4 Md. R. 311); emergency status expired April 15, 2003; adopted permanently effective September 29, 2003 (30:19 Md. R. 1329)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-11-29"><cite path="|08|02|04|.12">Regulation .12</cite> amended effective November 10, 2003 (30:22 Md. R. 1577); October 11, 2004 (31:20 Md. R. 1484); October 23, 2006 (33:21 Md. R. 1674); November 29, 2010 (37:24 Md. R. 1657)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-11-10"><cite path="|08|02|04|.12">Regulation .12</cite> amended effective October 1, 2012 (39:19 Md. R. 1236); November 10, 2014 (41:22 Md. R. 1318)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-10-07"><cite path="|08|02|04|.12|B.">Regulation .12B</cite> amended effective October 7, 2019 (46:20 Md. R. 843)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-10-12"><cite path="|08|02|04|.12|C.">Regulation .12C</cite> amended effective October 12, 2015 (42:20 Md. R. 1263)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-03-21"><cite path="|08|02|04|.12|D.">Regulation .12D</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective December 15, 2010 (38:2 Md. R. 79); adopted permanently effective March 21, 2011 (38:6 Md. R. 393)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-04-02"><cite path="|08|02|04|.12|D.">Regulation .12D</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective January 19, 2012 (39:3 Md. R. 256); amended permanently effective April 2, 2012 (39:6 Md. R. 407)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-02-27"><cite path="|08|02|04|.12|E.">Regulation .12E</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective December 16, 2005 (33:1 Md. R. 33); adopted permanently effective February 27, 2006 (33:4 Md. R. 352)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-03-24"><cite path="|08|02|04|.12|E.">Regulation .12E</cite> repealed effective March 24, 2008 (35:6 Md. R. 696)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-11-10"><cite path="|08|02|04|.13">Regulation .13</cite> adopted effective November 10, 2003 (30:22 Md. R. 1577)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-10-11"><cite path="|08|02|04|.13">Regulation .13</cite> repealed and new Regulation .13 adopted effective October 11, 2004 (31:20 Md. R. 1484)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-09-05"><cite path="|08|02|04|.13">Regulation .13</cite> repealed effective September 5, 2022 (49:18 Md. R. 819)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-09-20"><cite path="|08|02|04|.13|B.">Regulation .13B</cite> amended effective October 23, 2006 (33:21 Md. R. 1674); August 13, 2007 (34:16 Md. R. 1431); October 6, 2008 (35:20 Md. R. 1773); September 21, 2009 (36:19 Md. R. 1435); September 20, 2010 (37:19 Md. R. 1283)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-01-20"><cite path="|08|02|04|.13|B.">Regulation .13B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective January 20, 2011 (38:4 Md. R. 262); emergency status expired March 31, 2011</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-01-07"><cite path="|08|02|04|.13|B.">Regulation .13B</cite> amended effective October 3, 2011 (38:20 Md. R. 1201); September 29, 2014 (41:19 Md. R. 1076); January 7, 2016 (42:26 Md. R. 1594)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-10-11"><cite path="|08|02|04|.14">Regulation .14</cite> adopted effective October 11, 2004 (31:20 Md. R. 1484)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-10-07"><cite path="|08|02|04|.14">Regulation .14</cite> amended effective October 7, 2019 (46:20 Md. R. 843)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-09-05"><cite path="|08|02|04|.14">Regulation .14</cite> repealed effective September 5, 2022 (49:18 Md. R. 819)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-10-23"><cite path="|08|02|04|.15">Regulation .15</cite> adopted effective October 23, 2006 (33:21 Md. R. 1674)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-09-06"><cite path="|08|02|04|.15">Regulation .15</cite> repealed and new Regulation .15 adopted effective September 6, 2010 (37:18 Md. R. 1213)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-01-29"><cite path="|08|02|04|.15|B.">Regulation .15B</cite> amended effective August 13, 2007 (34:16 Md. R. 1431); January 29, 2018 (45:2 Md. R. 68)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-01-09"><cite path="|08|02|04|.15|C.">Regulation .15C</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 20, 2011 (38:17 Md. R. 1011); amended permanently effective January 9, 2012 (38:27 Md. R. 1763)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2016-02-15"><cite path="|08|02|04|.15|C.">Regulation .15C</cite> amended effective December 23, 2013 (40:25 Md. R. 2067); February 15, 2016 (43:3 Md. R. 271)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-09-21"><cite path="|08|02|04|.15|D.">Regulation .15D</cite>, F, I amended effective September 21, 2009 (36:19 Md. R. 1435)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-11-05"><cite path="|08|02|04|.15|F.">Regulation .15F</cite>, G amended as an emergency provision effective November 5, 2007 (34:24 Md. R. 2153)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-03-24"><cite path="|08|02|04|.15|F.">Regulation .15F</cite>, G amended effective March 24, 2008 (35:6 Md. R. 696)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-09-24"><cite path="|08|02|04|.16">Regulation .16</cite> adopted effective September 24, 2007 (34:19 Md. R. 1649)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-08-18"><cite path="|08|02|04|.16">Regulation .16</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective August 18, 2011 (38:19 Md. R. 1143); emergency status expired January 9, 2012</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-01-09"><cite path="|08|02|04|.16">Regulation .16</cite> amended effective January 9, 2012 (38:27 Md. R. 1763)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-02-22"><cite path="|08|02|04|.16|E.">Regulation .16E</cite> adopted effective February 22, 2010 (37:4 Md. R. 338)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-11-13"><cite path="|08|02|04|.16">Regulation .16</cite> repealed effective November 13, 2023 (50:22 Md. R. 973)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-09-06"><cite path="|08|02|04|.17">Regulation .17</cite> adopted effective September 6, 2010 (37:18 Md. R. 1213)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-04-04"><cite path="|08|02|04|.17|A.">Regulation .17A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective January 20, 2011 (38:4 Md. R. 262); amended permanently effective April 4, 2011 (37:8 Md. R 429)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-03-19"><cite path="|08|02|04|.17|A.">Regulation .17A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective October 10, 2011 (38:23 Md. R 1416); amended permanently effective March 19, 2012 (39:5 Md. R. 381)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-10-30"><cite path="|08|02|04|.17|A.">Regulation .17A</cite> amended effective October 1, 2012 (39:19 Md. R. 1236); January 29, 2018 (45:2 Md. R. 68); February 11, 2019 (46:3 Md. R. 106); March 23, 2020 (47:6 Md. R. 340); October 30, 2023 (50:21 Md. R. 951)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-01-29"><cite path="|08|02|04|.17|B.">Regulation .17B</cite> amended effective January 29, 2018 (45:2 Md. R. 68)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
