<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>18</num>
  <heading>Fishing Guide Provisions</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter applies to an individual who is licensed in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-210">Natural Resources Article, §4-210 </cite>or 4-210.1, Annotated Code of Maryland, to accept direct or indirect consideration for providing services as a fishing guide to an individual fishing in the waters of the State. This chapter also applies to an individual under the guidance of the licensee.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Department" means the Department of Natural Resources.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Licensee" means an individual who holds a valid type NT, type NTT, or type L fishing guide license issued by the Department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Nonresident" means an individual who resides in a state other than Maryland on the date of application for or renewal of a fishing guide license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Resident.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Resident" means an individual who resides in this State on the date of application for or renewal of a fishing guide license.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Resident" includes a member of the armed forces of the United States who is:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>On active duty; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Stationed officially in this State.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Striped bass" means the species Morone saxatilis, also known as rockfish, and all hybrids of striped bass.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Fishing guide" means an individual who accepts direct or indirect consideration for providing instruction, direction, supervision, or transportation to an individual for the purpose of catching fish by angling.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Freshwater Fishing Guide License — Type NT.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A type NT freshwater fishing guide license, as authorized by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-210">Natural Resources Article, §4-210</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland, authorizes the licensee to provide fishing guide services only in the nontidal waters of the State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Striped Bass. An angler under the guidance of a licensee with a valid type NT license in nontidal waters of the State may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Hook striped bass and immediately release the striped bass unharmed to the water from which the striped bass was taken; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Harvest striped bass from the following areas:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Youghiogheny Reservoir;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Piney Run Reservoir;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Tridelphia Reservoir;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Loch Raven Reservoir;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Prettyboy Reservoir;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>T. Howard Duckett (Rocky Gorge) Reservoir;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Liberty Reservoir; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Conowingo Reservoir.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Fees. The fees for a type NT license are:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For a resident, $20; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For a nonresident, $50.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>General. Except in Deep Creek Lake, the maximum number of individuals present on a vessel which is operated by a licensee may not exceed four, including the licensee.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|02|18|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Freshwater Fishing Guide License — Type NTT.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A type NTT freshwater fishing guide license, as authorized by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-210">Natural Resources Article, §4-210</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland, authorizes the licensee to provide fishing guide services in nontidal waters and designated tidal waters of the State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Fishing Area. A type NTT license authorizes the licensee to provide fishing guide services in:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All nontidal waters of the State; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The following designated areas located in tidal waters of the State:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Chesapeake Bay upstream of a line from Sandy Point on Spesutie Island to Turkey Point;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Elk River upstream of a line from Turkey Point to the State launching ramp at Pearce Creek;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Pond Creek upstream of a line connecting the two unnamed points at the entrance to the creek;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Sassafras River upstream of a line from Grove Point to Howell Point;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Still Pond Creek upstream of a line from Meeks Point to Rocky Point;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Worton Creek upstream of a line from Copeland Point to Handys Point;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Fairlee Creek upstream of a line across the entrance of the creek;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Chester River upstream of a line from Spaniard Point to Nichols Point;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Corsica River, a tributary of the Chester River, upstream of a line from Spaniard Point to Holton Point;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Langford Creek, a tributary of the Chester River, upstream of a line from Nichols Point to Grays Inn Point;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Grays Inn Creek, a tributary of the Chester River, upstream from Grays Inn Point to Little Gum Point;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>Choptank River upstream of the Dover Bridge on Route 331;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>Blackwater River upstream of a line from the lower point of Snake Island to the southernmost point on the opposite shore;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(n)</num>
          <text>Transquaking River upstream of a line from Alabaster Point running magnetic north to the opposite shore;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(o)</num>
          <text>Nanticoke River upstream of a line from Long Point to Runaway Point;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(p)</num>
          <text>Wicomico River upstream of the Whitehaven ferry crossing;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(q)</num>
          <text>Pocomoke River upstream of the landing at Rehobeth;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(r)</num>
          <text>Maryland tributaries of the Potomac River above the Route 301 bridge;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(s)</num>
          <text>Wicomico River, a tributary of the Potomac River, upstream of a line from Mills Point in a westerly direction to the northernmost point at the entrance to Dolly Boarmans Creek;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(t)</num>
          <text>Patuxent River upstream of the overhead power lines north of Gods Grace Point;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(u)</num>
          <text>Swanson Creek, a tributary of the Patuxent River, upstream of a line from Teague Point to Chalk Point;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(v)</num>
          <text>Patapsco River upstream of the Hanover Street crossing parallel to the Potee Street crossing;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(w)</num>
          <text>Back River upstream of a line from Cuckhold Point to Rocky Point;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(x)</num>
          <text>Middle River upstream of a line from Booby Point to Bowley Bar Point;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(y)</num>
          <text>Seneca Creek upstream of a line from Bowley Bar Point to Lowen Point;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(z)</num>
          <text>Gunpowder River upstream of a line from Weir Point to Rickett Point; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(aa)</num>
          <text>Bush River upstream of a line from Abbey Point to Sandy Point.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Striped Bass.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notwithstanding <cite path="08.02.15.08">COMAR 08.02.15.08</cite>—.11, an angler under the guidance of a licensee with a valid type NTT license in tidal waters of the State may not possess the species of fish known as striped bass.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Notwithstanding <cite path="|08.02.15">COMAR 08.02.15</cite>, an angler under the guidance of a licensee with a valid type NTT license in tidal waters of the State may not catch or attempt to catch striped bass from waters of the State north of a line drawn from Abbey Point to Worton Point, from March 1 through May 31, inclusive.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An angler under the guidance of a licensee with a valid type NTT license in nontidal waters of the State may:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Hook striped bass and immediately release the striped bass unharmed to the water from which the striped bass was taken; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Harvest striped bass from the areas set forth in <cite path="|08|02|18|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Fees. The fees for a type NTT license are:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For a resident, $50; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For a nonresident, $100.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>License Allocations.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The number of type NTT licenses issued annually is limited to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>120 for residents; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>30 for nonresidents.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Department shall maintain separate waiting lists of qualified resident and nonresident individuals in chronological order who have applied for a type NTT license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A type NTT license that is revoked or voluntarily relinquished to the Department may be reallocated to an individual who meets all qualifications for a type NTT license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Department shall issue a type NTT license to the first individual on the appropriate waiting list described in <cite path="08|02|18|.04|D.|(2)">§D(2) of this regulation</cite> when a license is available.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>General. Except in Deep Creek Lake, the maximum number of individuals present on a vessel which is operated by a licensee may not exceed four, including the licensee.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Limited Fishing Guide License — Type L.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A type L limited fishing guide license, as authorized by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-210">Natural Resources Article, §4-210, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, authorizes the licensee to provide fishing guide services in all waters of the State.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Striped Bass.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notwithstanding <cite path="|08.02.15">COMAR 08.02.15</cite>, an angler under the guidance of a licensee with a valid type L license in tidal waters of the State may not catch or possess striped bass in the following areas:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Chesapeake Bay upstream of a line from Sandy Point on Spesutie Island to Turkey Point;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Elk River upstream of a line from Turkey Point to the State launching ramp at Pearce Creek;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Pond Creek upstream of a line connecting the two unnamed points at the entrance to the creek;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Sassafras River upstream of a line from Grove Point to Howell Point;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Still Pond Creek upstream of a line from Meeks Point to Rocky Point;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Worton Creek upstream of a line from Copeland's Point to Handys Point;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Fairlee Creek upstream of a line across the entrance of the creek;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Chester River upstream of a line from Spaniard Point to Nichols Point;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Corsica River, a tributary of the Chester River, upstream of a line from Spaniard Point to Holton Point;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Langford Creek, a tributary of the Chester River, upstream of a line from Nichols Point to Grays Inn Point;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Grays Inn Creek, a tributary of the Chester River, upstream from Grays Inn Point to Little Gum Point;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>Choptank River upstream of the Dover Bridge on Route 331;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>Blackwater River upstream of a line from the lower point of Snake Island to the southernmost point on the opposite shore;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(n)</num>
          <text>Transquaking River upstream of a line from Alabaster Point running magnetic north to the opposite shore;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(o)</num>
          <text>Nanticoke River upstream of a line from Long Point to Runaway Point;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(p)</num>
          <text>Wicomico River upstream of the Whitehaven ferry crossing;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(q)</num>
          <text>Pocomoke River upstream of the landing at Rehobeth;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(r)</num>
          <text>Wicomico River, a tributary of the Potomac River, upstream of a line from Mills Point in a westerly direction to the northernmost point at the entrance to Dolly Boarmans Creek;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(s)</num>
          <text>Patuxent River upstream of the overhead power lines north of Gods Grace Point;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(t)</num>
          <text>Swanson Creek, a tributary of the Patuxent River, upstream of a line from Teague Point to Chalk Point;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(u)</num>
          <text>Patapsco River upstream of the Hanover Street crossing parallel to the Potee Street crossing;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(v)</num>
          <text>Back River upstream of a line from Cuckhold Point to Rocky Point;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(w)</num>
          <text>Middle River upstream of a line from Booby Point to Bowley Bar Point;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(x)</num>
          <text>Seneca Creek upstream of a line from Bowley Bar Point to Lowen Point;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(y)</num>
          <text>Gunpowder River upstream of a line from Weir Point to Rickett Point;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(z)</num>
          <text>Bush River upstream of a line from Abbey Point to Sandy Point; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(aa)</num>
          <text>Maryland tributaries of the Potomac River above the Route 301 bridge.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Notwithstanding <cite path="|08.02.15">COMAR 08.02.15</cite>, an angler under the guidance of a licensee with a valid type L license in tidal waters of the State may not catch or attempt to catch striped bass from waters of the State north of a line drawn from Abbey Point to Worton Point, from March 1 through May 31, inclusive.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An angler under the guidance of a licensee with a valid type L license in nontidal waters of the State may:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Hook striped bass and immediately release the striped bass unharmed to the water from which the striped bass was taken; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Harvest striped bass from the areas set forth in <cite path="|08|02|18|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Fees. The fees for a type L license are:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For a resident, $50; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For a nonresident, $100.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>General. A type L licensee may guide:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Anglers in no more than three boats or vessels that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Have one or two occupants per boat; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Are propelled by human power;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Ten anglers on foot; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any number of anglers who are participating in an educational or recreational program sponsored by a State, local, or municipal government and who are fishing from shore or on foot in the water.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|02|18|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>General Provisions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Licensee Requirements. In addition to a type NT, NTT, or L license, a licensee shall possess, as applicable, the following when engaged in fishing guide activities:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A valid angler's license in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-604">Natural Resources Article, §4-604, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A valid Chesapeake Bay and coastal sport fishing license or registration in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-745">Natural Resources Article, §4-745, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any necessary stamps issued by the Department; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A valid license issued by the U. S. Coast Guard.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Safety Requirements. An applicant for a type NT, NTT, or L license shall provide a valid copy of the following documentation:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A cardiopulmonary resuscitation (CPR) certificate; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An American Red Cross First Aid Certification or equivalent.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Angler Requirements. An individual guided by a licensee shall possess, as applicable:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A valid angler's license in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-604">Natural Resources Article, §4-604, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A valid Chesapeake Bay and coastal sport fishing license or registration in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-745">Natural Resources Article, §4-745, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any necessary stamps issued by the Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Dividing Lines. The dividing lines for tidal and nontidal waters are designated in <cite path="08.02.01.09">COMAR 08.02.01.09</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A licensee may not possess fish for personal use while providing fishing guide services.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Term. A type NT, NTT, or L license is valid from the date of issuance through December 31 of each year following the date of issuance.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Renewal. A licensee may renew a type NT, NTT, or L license for an additional 1 year term if the licensee:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is otherwise entitled to hold the license;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provides a valid copy of the documents set forth in <cite path="08|02|18|.06|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Submits to the Department, by December 31:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A renewal application on the form that the Department requires; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The applicable annual fee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Reporting.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A licensee shall submit reports as required on forms provided by the Department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Any person who is licensed to guide fishing parties on tidal waters shall accurately record their catch on a commercial charter boat captain's daily log and submit the log in accordance with <cite path="08.02.13.06">COMAR 08.02.13.06</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Natural Resources Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-206">4-206</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-210">4-210</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-210">4-210</cite>.1, 4-215, 4-701, and 4-745, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-01-01">Effective date: January 1, 2000 (26:24 Md. R. 1857)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-03-03"><cite path="|08|02|18|.04|C.">Regulation .04C</cite> amended effective March 3, 2003 (30:4 Md. R. 315)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-08-28" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective August 28, 2006 (33:17 Md. R. 1436)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-12-28"><cite path="|08|02|18|.04|C.">Regulation .04C</cite> amended effective December 28, 2020 (47:26 Md. R. 1107)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-12-28"><cite path="|08|02|18|.05|B.">Regulation .05B</cite>, D amended effective December 28, 2020 (47:26 Md. R. 1107)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-04-04"><cite path="|08|02|18|.06|A.">Regulation .06A</cite>, C amended effective April 4, 2011 (38:7 Md. R. 429)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-12-28"><cite path="|08|02|18|.06|D.">Regulation .06D</cite>, E amended effective December 28, 2020 (47:26 Md. R. 1107)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-02-22"><cite path="|08|02|18|.06|H.">Regulation .06H</cite> amended effective February 22, 2010 (37:4 Md. R. 338)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
