<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>26</num>
  <heading>Shell Recycling Grant Program</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Aggregation site” means a location where shell donated for recycling is stored or aged prior to being replanted in State waters.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Authorized shell recycling collector” means a business entity authorized by the Department to collect shells and issue grants to shell recyclers.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Bushel” means an amount of oyster shells that will fill a 10-gallon container, or about 500 shells.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Business Entity.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Business entity” means:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A person conducting or operating a trade or business in Maryland; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>An organization operating in Maryland that is exempt from taxation under §501(c)(3) or (4) of the Internal Revenue Code.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Business entity” includes a person operating a landfill or solid waste acceptance facility permitted under <cite path="|26.04.07">COMAR 26.04.07</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Comptroller” means the Maryland Comptroller of the Treasury, or the Comptroller’s designee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Corporation” includes an association or joint-stock company.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Department” means the Maryland Department of Natural Resources.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Grant” means a payment to a shell recycler for donated shells.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“Person” includes the State, any county, municipal corporation, or other political subdivision of the State, or any of their units, or an individual, receiver, trustee, guardian, executor, administrator, fiduciary, or private corporation, or any other entity.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>“Restaurant” means a food service facility as defined in <cite path="|10.15.03">COMAR 10.15.03</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>“Seafood dealer or processor” means a person who is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Licensed as a seafood dealer in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-701">Natural Resources Article, §4-701, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or who is exempt from licensing as a seafood dealer under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-702">Natural Resources Article, §4-702, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Licensed or certified by the Maryland Department of Health in accordance with <cite path="|10.15.07">COMAR 10.15.07</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>“Shell recycler” means a nonprofit organization, community association, restaurant, seafood processor, or seafood dealer that donates shells to an authorized shell recycling collector and that has not received compensation for the shell donation from any source other than the Department or its agent.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Eligibility.</heading>
    <text>To be eligible for a State income tax credit under this chapter, a shell recycler shall:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Prior to donating shell, complete an online registration as specified by the Department that includes the shell recycler’s Tax Identification Number; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Donate shell for recycling to an authorized shell recycling collector.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="08|02|26|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Authorized Shell Recycling Collector.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Certification of a Collector.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A business entity may apply to the Department to be an authorized shell recycling collector.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An application shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be submitted on a form provided by the Department; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Include the applicant’s:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Name, address, and contact information;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Planned shell aggregation site; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Planned method of storing and aging the shell.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Upon receipt and review of an application for certification under this regulation, the Department may:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Approve the application and issue the applicant a certificate designating the applicant an authorized shell recycling collector; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Deny an application for reasonable cause.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A certification issued to an authorized shell recycling collector:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Shall be valid for 1 year beginning on the day of issuance; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>May be renewed for a new term upon the Department’s receipt of a renewal application submitted as specified by the Department.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A certified recycled shell collector shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Collect and process oyster shell from shell recyclers in accordance with the terms and conditions set out in the certification issued under <cite path="08|02|26|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, and all applicable federal, State and local laws and regulations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For each shell donation collected, submit an electronic report as specified by the Department verifying the location, date, and amount of the shell donation within 48 hours of collecting the donation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Allow the Department, or the Department’s designee, to inspect at reasonable hours the certified recycled shell collector’s shell aggregation site and collected recycled shell; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Notify the Department immediately of any changes to the authorized shell recycling collector’s aggregation site or contact information.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Issuance of Grants.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An authorized shell recycling collector shall issue grants to shell recyclers in the amounts described in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-1019">Natural Resources Article, §4-1019</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A shell recycler may only receive one grant per donation year, which shall be in the amount which reflects the total amount of shell that the recycler has donated over the course of that year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The donation year shall run from January 1 through December 31.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>By January 31 of each year, an authorized shell recycling collector shall submit all necessary recycling records to the Department to reflect the amount of shell collected from each shell recycler the previous year and the total amount of grants which are to be disbursed to the shell recyclers by the authorized shell recycling collector.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Within 30 days of receiving payment from the Department, an authorized shell recycling collector shall issue the appropriate grants to each shell recycler.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Once the authorized collector has received payment from the Department, the donated shell becomes the property of the State of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Limitations on Funding.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Grants issued under this chapter are subject to the amount of funds budgeted for the Shell Recycling Grant Program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In the event that shell recyclers donate more shells to the Shell Recycling Grant Program than the Department has budgeted for, the Department shall issue grants to authorized shell recycling collectors, and authorized shell recycling collectors shall disburse to shell recyclers grants in the order in which recycled shells were donated to the collectors.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Penalties.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Department may suspend or revoke a certification issued to a recycled shell collector for failure to comply with this chapter or the terms and conditions of the certification.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Within 15 days of receipt of the Department’s notice of a denial, suspension, or revocation of a certification issued under <cite path="08|02|26|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, the recycled shell collector may appeal the decision in writing to the Director of the Maryland Fisheries Service.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gnr|4-1019">Natural Resources, §4-1019</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-03-31">Regulations <cite path="|08|02|26|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|08|02|26|.06">.06</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective January 13, 2014 (41:3 Md. R. 199); adopted permanently effective March 31, 2014 (41:6 Md. R. 377)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-12-31"><cite path="|08|02|26|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite>, B amended effective December 31, 2018 (45:26 Md. R. 1240)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-09-02" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective September 2, 2024 (51:17 Md. R. 777)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
