<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>Regulations for Fairs and Shows</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>These regulations provide qualifications and guidelines for the allocation of Maryland Agricultural Fair Board funds to agricultural organizations or youth groups.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>"Activity" means an exhibition of agricultural products and events for the purpose of education and promotion, for example, fairs, field days, community shows, exhibits, youth contests.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>"Agricultural youth group" means an organization that educates youth in the production and promotion of food and fiber, for example, 4-H, FFA, FHA.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>"Board" means the Maryland Agricultural Fair Board, a unit of the Maryland Department of Agriculture.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>"Competitive department" means a category of agricultural or homemaking products or activities in which one entry is compared against another or a set of established standards to determine quality.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>"Premium" means a prize awarded in a competitive department.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Application.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board only shall give financial assistance to an agricultural youth group or an organization sponsoring an agricultural activity.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Procedure. An applicant shall submit the following to the Board:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An application on forms provided by the Board at least 1 month in advance of the Board's announced allocation meeting;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A financial statement of the activity for the previous year, if any; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An overview of significant changes from the previous year's activity.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Board Evaluation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board shall decide whether to approve a qualified applicant's application for funding based upon the proposed activity's ability to meet the following criteria:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Ability to meet community needs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Degree of agricultural promotion;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Financial need;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Growth and improvement of activity;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Involvement of community;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Organizational quality of activity;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Quality of display;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Size and scope of activity; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Strength and depth of management.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the Board approves an application for funding, it shall notify the applicant of the allocation. The applicant shall enter into an agreement with the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Funding Conditions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The agreement shall include a list of requirements which a successful applicant shall perform to receive Board funding.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>These requirements include the following submissions to the Board:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A list of its officers or committee leaders. The list shall include names, addresses, and telephone numbers.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A list of judges for all livestock shows at least 15 days in advance of the activity.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A final activity report within 45 days after the final day of the activity unless otherwise directed by the Board.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A draft, copy, or original current fair or show catalog listing premiums and a schedule of events in advance of the activity.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Special Conditions for Livestock Shows.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Livestock shall meet health requirements of the Maryland Department of Agriculture.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Judges in dairy, beef, sheep, swine, and dairy goats shall be selected from the current Maryland Official Judges List, compiled by the Board, or receive approval of the appropriate Maryland livestock association before any show.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Checking Registration and Identification.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In a purebred livestock show, the applicant shall check the registration papers for exhibit ownership and class qualification.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>In a non-purebred livestock show, the applicant shall check for appropriate identification to determine exhibit ownership and class qualification.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The applicant shall use funds received from the Board only for the payment of premiums, ribbons, and trophies in competitive departments unless otherwise authorized by the Board. Premium money is to be awarded on quality exhibits only.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An organization shall pay all premiums won by qualified exhibitors within 30 days after the final day of the activity.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>An organization or activity that conducts a livestock sale shall comply with the requirements of the Maryland Weights and Measures Law of the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag">Agriculture Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Allocation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Before an exhibition, the Board may advance a portion of the allocation to the applicant.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>After the exhibition, the applicant shall submit a final report of the expenditures. This report is subject to audit by the Department. Upon approval of the report, the Board shall authorize payment of the approved allocation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Non-Compliance.</heading>
    <text>If a person violates these regulations, the Board may deny a current or future fund allocation.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gag|10-303">Agriculture Article, §10-303(b), </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1971-11-15">Effective date: November 15, 1971</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1980-01-25"><cite path="|15|12|01|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite> amended effective January 25, 1980 (7:2 Md. R. 117)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1980-01-25"><cite path="|15|12|01|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite> adopted effective January 25, 1980 (7:2 Md. R. 117)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1984-02-27" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|15|12|01|.01">.01</cite>--<cite path="|15|12|01|.07">.07</cite> repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|15|12|01|.01">.01</cite>--<cite path="|15|12|01|.07">.07</cite> adopted effective February 27, 1984 (11:4 Md. R. 318)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1988-10-03"><cite path="|15|12|01|.05|A.">Regulation .05A</cite> amended effective October 3, 1988 (15:20 Md. R. 2335)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-04-06"><cite path="|15|12|01|.05|E.">Regulation .05E</cite> adopted effective April 6, 1986 (13:7 Md. R. 795)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
