<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>07</num>
  <heading>Maryland Seal of Biliteracy Program</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose and Scope.</heading>
    <text>Recognizing that high school graduates who can function in two or more languages are equipped with the knowledge and skills to participate successfully in college, careers, and a diverse 21st century society, the Maryland Seal of Biliteracy Program is established to recognize and reward excellence in language learning as measured by rigorous proficiency assessments across a range of language skills.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“American Council on the Teaching of Foreign Languages (ACTFL) Proficiency Guidelines” means the global descriptions of five levels of integrated performance in listening, speaking, reading and writing:  Novice, Intermediate, Advanced, Superior, and Distinguished.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“World language” means any natural language, including American Sign Language, native American languages, and languages no longer spoken (e.g., Latin and ancient Greek).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Local School System Participation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Participation in the program by a local public school system is voluntary.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An individual school may not opt out of participation in a local school system program.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Demonstrating Proficiency in English and World Languages.</heading>
    <text>To receive a Maryland Seal of Biliteracy:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The student must meet the assessment requirement as set forth in COMAR 13A.03.02.09 on the Maryland High School English Language Arts/Literacy assessment; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The student must select appropriate world language assessment instrument(s) from the Maryland State Department of Education’s approved list of assessments aligned to the ACTFL Proficiency Guidelines and attain an overall proficiency level of Intermediate High.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Awarding the Maryland Seal of Biliteracy.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The student shall provide official test results to the local school system.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The local school system shall validate the assessment results and affix the Seal of Biliteracy to the student’s diploma or transcript at graduation, at no cost to the student.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|7-208">Education Article, §7-208, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-02-13">Effective date: February 13, 2017 (44:3 Md. R. 189)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
