<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>06</num>
  <heading>Provider Requirements</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Minimum Age.</heading>
    <text>To be approved as a family child care provider, an individual shall be 18 years old or older.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|15|06|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Training Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Preservice Training. An individual who applies for an initial registration shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Hold a current certificate indicating successful completion of training in approved:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Basic first-aid through the American Red Cross, or a program with equivalent standards; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Cardiopulmonary resuscitation (CPR) through the American Heart Association, or a program with equivalent standards, appropriate for each age group approved for care in the home;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide documentation of having successfully completed:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Within 2 years before the application for initial registration is filed, at least 24 clock hours of approved training that includes 4 clock hours in each of the six core of knowledge competencies;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The 90 clock hour course, or its approved equivalent, that satisfies the preservice training requirement for a child care teacher or child care center director under COMAR 13A.16.06.05B(4), COMAR 13A.16.06.09A(3), or COMAR 13A.16.06.10B(1)(a), as applicable;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Department of Defense training modules for child care providers;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Child Development Associate Credential issued by the Council for Professional Recognition;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>An associate's degree that includes at least 15 semester hours of early childhood education or elementary education course work;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>A bachelor's or higher degree in early childhood education, elementary education, or other discipline approved by the office; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Other course work approved by the office;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Complete approved training on emergency and disaster planning;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Effective January 1, 2020, complete approved basic health and safety training within 90 days of initial registration; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Complete:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Approved training in supporting breastfeeding practices;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>3 clock hours of approved training in complying with the Americans with Disabilities Act; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Approved training in medication administration.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Continued Training. A provider shall successfully complete:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The health and safety training, as required by the office, by the end of each 12-month period measured each calendar year;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>During the first year of registration, 18 clock hours of approved training specified by the office; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>By the end of each 12-month period after the first full year of registration, a total of 12 clock hours of approved continued training that consists of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>At least 6 clock hours of core of knowledge training; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Not more than 6 clock hours of elective training.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Professional Development Plan.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The provider shall maintain a professional development plan.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Training completed by the provider under <cite path="13A|15|06|.02|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Consistent with the provider's professional development plan; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Documented by the provider on the professional development plan.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Current certification in approved basic first aid and CPR training as specified in §A(1)(a) and (b) of this regulation shall be maintained at all times by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The provider; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If applicable, the additional adult.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Infant-Toddler Training.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The office may not approve a request by an applicant or a provider for an infant-toddler capacity of more than two children younger than 2 years old unless the individual has completed 3 semester hours or 45 clock hours of approved training, or the equivalent, related to the care of children younger than 2 years old.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Sudden Infant Death Syndrome (SIDS) Training.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The office may not approve a request by an applicant or a provider to provide care for a child younger than 24 months old unless the applicant or provider presents evidence of having successfully completed, within 5 years before the date of the request, approved SIDS training.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>SIDS training may not be used to satisfy the continued training requirements set forth in <cite path="13A|15|06|.02|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The office may not approve an application for an initial registration or a continuing registration unless the applicant has completed:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Approved training in:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Supporting breastfeeding practices; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Medication administration; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>3 clock hours of approved training in complying with the Americans with Disabilities Act.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A currently registered provider shall have completed approved training as specified in <cite path="13A|15|06|.02|F.">§F of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Provider Substitute.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The provider shall designate at least one substitute who is available on short notice to care for the children at the provider’s registered family child care home.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Approval by Office.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An individual designated as a substitute may not be used in that capacity unless the office has approved the individual.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If information received by the office indicates that an individual designated as a substitute may present a risk to the health, safety, or welfare of children in care, the office may disapprove the use of that substitute.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The office shall notify the provider of its decision to approve or disapprove a substitute within 30 days of the request being submitted.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Use of Substitutes.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A provider may use a substitute to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Provide care for children during a temporary absence of the provider; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Assist in providing care while the provider is present.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Unless the office approves an additional number of days in advance, the use of substitutes to provide care in the provider's absence is limited to a total of not more than 20 working days in any 12-month period, counting only days on which substitute care is provided for more than 2 hours.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A substitute shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be 18 years old or older;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Be familiar with the requirements of this subtitle;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Complete, sign, and submit to the office the required forms for substitutes, including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A medical evaluation completed within the past 12 months; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Permission to examine records of abuse and neglect of children and adults;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Apply for a federal and State criminal background check at a designated law enforcement office in the State;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If residing or having resided in a state other than Maryland within 5 years before being hired as a substitute:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Apply for a state criminal background check to be performed by a duly authorized entity within that state; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Request the non-Maryland state entity performing the criminal background check to transmit the result of that background check directly to the Agency; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Present no risk to the health, safety, or welfare of children.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Before allowing a substitute to provide or to assist in providing care, the provider shall orient the substitute to child health and safety matters, including, but not limited to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The location of the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Telephone and emergency telephone numbers;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>First aid supplies; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Child emergency forms;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Medication administration information for each child authorized to receive medication;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Modified diet information for each child placed on a modified diet;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Emergency evacuation procedures;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Permissible and appropriate child discipline procedures;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Authorized child release procedures; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Procedures for documenting and reporting child injuries and accidents.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>During the provider's absence, a substitute is responsible for meeting the requirements of this subtitle regarding the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Supervision and protection of each child in care; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Operation of the family child care home.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|15|06|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Additional Adult.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as set forth in <cite path="13A|15|06|.04|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, before an individual may be used as an additional adult, the provider shall ensure that the individual:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is 18 years old or older;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Attends an information session presented by the office concerning the requirements of this subtitle for the care of children younger than 2 years old;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Files with the office:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A completed additional adult application form;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Signed and notarized release forms giving the office permission to examine records of abuse and neglect of children and adults for information about the applicant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Completed information, on a form supplied by the office, for each of the applicant's substitutes; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A medical report on the applicant based on a medical evaluation conducted within the previous 12 months by a practicing physician, certified nurse practitioner, or registered physician's assistant, and signed by the individual who conducted the evaluation;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Applies for a federal and State criminal background check at a designated office in the State;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If residing or having resided in a state other than Maryland within 5 years before being hired as an additional adult:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Applies for a state criminal background check to be performed by a duly authorized entity within that state; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Requests the non-Maryland state entity performing the criminal background check to transmit the result of that background check directly to the Agency;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Holds a current certificate indicating successful completion of approved basic first aid and CPR training applicable to children younger than 2 years old; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Presents evidence of having completed approved SIDS training within the previous 5 years.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A provider may not use an individual as an additional adult unless the office has approved the individual in that capacity.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Volunteers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Before permitting an individual to begin volunteer duties at the family child care home, the provider shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Ensure that the individual presents no risk to the health, safety, or welfare of children;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Conduct a child health and safety orientation for the individual that meets the requirements set forth in <cite path="|13A|15|06|.03|E.">Regulation .03E of this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Ensure that the individual has applied for a federal and State criminal background check at a designated office in the State; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Ensure that the individual, if residing or having resided in a state other than Maryland within 5 years before being hired as an additional adult:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Applies for a state criminal background check to be performed by a duly authorized entity within that state; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Requests the non-Maryland state entity performing the criminal background check to transmit the result of that background check directly to the Agency.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The provider, substitute, or additional adult shall accompany a volunteer whenever the volunteer is in the presence of an unrelated child in care.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A volunteer who is younger than 18 years old may not be permitted to work with a child in care who is younger than 2 years old.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Education Article, §§9.5-301—9.5-308, 9.5-310—9.5-312, 9.5-320, and 9.5-321;<br/><cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-333">General Provisions Article, §4-333</cite>; <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ghu|1-202">Human Services Article, §1-202</cite>; Annotated Code of Maryland<br/>Agency Note: Federal Statutory Reference — Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (42 U.S.C. §12101 et seq.);<br/>Pro-Children Act of 1994 (20 U.S.C. §6081 et seq.);<br/>Child Care Development Block Grant (45 CFR Parts 98 and 99 and 42 U.S.C. 9858 et seq.);<br/>Social Security Act §418 (42 U.S.C. 618)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-10-20">Effective date: October 20, 2008 (35:21 Md. R. 1826)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-01-13"><cite path="|13A|15|06|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective April 19, 2010 (37:8 Md. R. 618); January 13, 2020 (47:1 Md. R. 12)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-07-20"><cite path="|13A|15|06|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended effective July 20, 2015 (42:14 Md. R. 882)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-07-20"><cite path="|13A|15|06|.02|H.">Regulation .02H</cite> adopted effective July 20, 2015 (42:14 Md. R. 882)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-01-13"><cite path="|13A|15|06|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective January 13, 2020 (47:1 Md. R. 12)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-04-19"><cite path="|13A|15|06|.03|C.">Regulation .03C</cite>, D amended effective April 19, 2010 (37:8 Md. R. 618)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-04-19"><cite path="|13A|15|06|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective April 19, 2010 (37:8 Md. R. 618)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-01-13"><cite path="|13A|15|06|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite> amended effective January 13, 2020 (47:1 Md. R. 12)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-03-21"><cite path="|13A|15|06|.04|C.">Regulation .04C</cite> repealed effective March 21, 2011 (38:6 Md. R. 396)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-01-13"><cite path="|13A|15|06|.05|A.">Regulation .05A</cite> amended effective January 13, 2020 (47:1 Md. R. 12)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
