<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>General Regulations</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|81|01|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this subtitle, the following terms have the meanings indicated:</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Aesthetic site" means a site whose aesthetic nature is of general public interest as officially recognized by a local, state, or federal government agency charged with the responsibility to oversee the protection of the environment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Applicant" means the oil pipeline corporation making an application under the provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|5-404">Public Utilities Article, §5-404, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and this subtitle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Archeological Site".</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Archeological site" means a site or locality yielding artifacts, structural remains, or other evidence of occupation or use dating before 1900, and especially those before 1875.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The site may be either prehistoric (Indian), historic (colonial, industrial, and so forth), or both.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The designation of a site or locality having archeological interest as an archeological site will be made by the State Archeologist, Maryland Geological Survey, who will also act to coordinate subsequent field activities.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Commission" means the Public Service Commission of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Construction Site".</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Construction site" means a site having a portion or all of its real property within the proposed oil pipeline facility property acquisition.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Construction" includes any clearing of land, excavation, or other action that would affect the natural environment of the site or route of the oil pipeline facilities, but does not include changes needed for temporary use of sites or routes for non-pipeline purposes, or uses in securing geological or topographical data, including any necessary borings.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Cost" means the total estimated cost for the design, construction, and activation of the project, expressed in dollars for the year or years in which the expenditures are budgeted.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Historic site" means a site duly registered with the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Maryland Historic Trust;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>National Register of Historic Places;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>National Register of Natural Landmarks;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>National Trust for Historic Preservation; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Register of National Historic Landmarks.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Oil pipeline" means all fixed property and facilities used in the transportation of refined petroleum products.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Oil pipeline corporation" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|5-404">Public Utilities Article, §5-404(a)(2), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Project" means the proposed oil pipeline facility as defined in <cite path="20|81|01|.01|B.|(8)">§B(8) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|81|01|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Information and Documents To Be Included in Application.</heading>
    <text>The following information and documents shall be included in an application made under this subtitle:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The applicant's name and the address of its principal business office;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The name, title, and address of the person authorized to receive notices and communications with respect to the application;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The location or locations at which the public may inspect a map or maps showing in more detail the site and routing of the project, as required by <cite path="20|81|01|.02|R.">§R of this regulation</cite>;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A concise general description of the entire project, including pertinent design and operational features, provisions for aesthetic and environmental considerations, and the overall project schedule for engineering, construction, and activation;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The estimated cost of the project;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Tentative plans for financing the project;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A statement of the need for the project in meeting present and future demands for service, how the project will satisfy these requirements, the alternatives considered, and a concise description of the estimated specific consequences if the project is not installed or if schedule slippage occurs;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Regarding the land for the project—a description of the types of property conveyance and pertinent provisions, the extent and dates of any portions of the land privately acquired to date, and a brief description of any improvements which may have to be acquired for the project;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>A list of local, state, or federal government agencies having requirements which must be met in connection with the construction or operation of the project, and a statement that the necessary approval has been obtained from each of these agencies or an explanation why the approvals have not been obtained at the date the application is filed;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>A copy of every required franchise or a statement that no franchise is required;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>A copy of the applicant's corporate charter;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>A general description of the proposed route and the number of miles located in each county within the State;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>The rights-of-way widths and acreage included in them;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>The location and identification of conflicting aesthetic or historic sites, areas of environmental significance, or both, including wetlands as may be designated by the Department of Natural Resources;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>The location and identification of aesthetic or historic sites, institutional lands, parks, recreational areas, and wildlife management areas from which the project would be clearly and permanently visible;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>P.</num>
      <text>A summary of any studies which have been made of the environmental impact of the project, and the results of the studies as may be embodied in the project;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>Q.</num>
      <text>The location and description of any historic or prehistoric archeological sites that are within the right-of-way for the oil pipeline or that may be on or near unimproved access roads or other roads built or improved for construction or maintenance of the oil pipeline;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>R.</num>
      <text>A depiction on suitable topographic maps of the applicable information required by §§L—Q of this regulation (the topographical maps shall have a scale of 1 to 24,000 or larger).</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Form of Application.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The original application shall be signed by a person or persons having authority to make the application and having knowledge of the matters set forth in it, and shall be verified under oath.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Every application shall be printed or typewritten on sheets 8-1/2 by 11 inches in size, except that supporting exhibits such as maps, profiles, and other engineering material may be on paper not exceeding 28 by 40 inches in size.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Distribution of Application.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The applicant shall submit to the Commission the original and six copies of the application.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>At the time the application is filed with the Commission, the applicant shall mail a copy of it to the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The governing body, and the planning zone commission of each county in which any portion of the project will be located;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Maryland Department of Health;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Maryland Department of Transportation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Maryland Department of Natural Resources (six copies);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Department of Commerce;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Office of Planning;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Maryland State Highway Administration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The Regional Planning Council, the Maryland National Capital Park and Planning Commission, or both, if affected by the application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>United States Department of Interior; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>All other local, state, or federal agencies designated in Regulations .01B(1) and (7) and .02I of this chapter, if affected by the application.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A certificate of service showing the identity of those served shall be attached to the application.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Hearing on Application.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Commission shall hold a public hearing on the application as required by law and shall render its decision in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|5-404">Public Utilities Article, §5-404, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Advertisement.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The applicant shall advertise the public hearing in a newspaper of general circulation in the area or areas where the proposed project is to be constructed once in each of 2 successive weeks immediately before the hearing as a legal notice.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The applicant shall publish a display advertisement which includes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A brief description of the project which the general public can understand; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A map sufficient to indicate the proposed general location or route of the project, or both.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All advertisements shall contain a statement that a map showing in detail the routing of the proposed oil pipeline is available for public inspection at a specific location within the county in which any construction is proposed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Written Notice.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The applicant shall give written notice to every person under or over whose land the proposed oil pipeline is to be located.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The applicant shall send the notice by certified mail at least 30 days before the hearing to every owner or owners of the property as determined from the current tax assessment records of the political subdivision in which the property is located.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Other Notice.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In addition and if appropriate, the applicant shall publish any other notice that may be required by other Maryland law and regulations, relating to but not limited to matters involving private wetlands, the use and diversion of State waters, and the probable effect of the application on ambient air quality.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>This notice shall refer to these matters as being part of the proceedings and public hearings on the application.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The applicant under these circumstances shall obtain from the appropriate State agencies the proper form and content of public notice.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Proceedings under this subtitle shall be governed by the relevant provisions of the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu">Public Utilities Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and by the Commission's regulations.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Public Utilities Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-121">2-121</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|5-404">5-404</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1981-05-01">Effective date: May 1, 1981 (8:9 Md. R. 803)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
