<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>Nonresidential Customer Deposits</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Declaration of Public Policy.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Public Service Commission of Maryland, in these regulations referred to as the "Commission", declares that it is in the public interest for each utility to administer fairly and without discrimination a reasonable policy reflected by written regulations, in accordance with these regulations, which will permit an applicant for permanent nonresidential service to establish, or an existing nonresidential customer to reestablish, credit with the utility for the use of its service.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Commission further declares that when it is necessary for an applicant or customer to make a cash deposit to establish or reestablish credit in accordance with these regulations, the making of this deposit is in the public interest because it avoids, to the extent practicable, the creation of a burden arising from uncollectible bills which would have to be borne ultimately by all the utility's ratepayers.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Commission further declares that the essential ingredient in each utility's administration of its deposit policy, as expressed by these regulations, is the equitable and indiscriminate application of that policy to all applicants for service and customers throughout its service area without regard to the economic character of the area or any part of it, and that this deposit policy shall be predicated upon the credit risk of the applicant (or customer) without regard to the collective credit reputation of the area in which the applicant does business.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|30|01|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Establishment of Credit.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A utility may require each applicant for nonresidential service to establish credit in compliance with the methods and procedures listed in <cite path="20|30|01|.02|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Methods of Establishing Credit.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In order to establish credit, a utility may require an applicant for nonresidential service to demonstrate good paying habits by showing that the applicant:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Was a customer of a Maryland utility for at least 12 months within the preceding 2 years;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Does not currently owe any outstanding bills for utility service to a utility doing business in Maryland;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Did not have service discontinued for nonpayment of a utility bill during the last 12 months that service was provided; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Did not fail, on more than two occasions during the last 12 months that service was provided, to pay a utility bill when it became due.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In addition to demonstrating good paying habits under <cite path="20|30|01|.02|B.|(1)">§B(1) of this regulation</cite>, a utility may require an applicant for nonresidential service to satisfy any one of the following in order to establish credit:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Showing that the applicant has been actively engaging in its current business as a proprietorship, partnership, or corporation for a period of at least 4 years;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Demonstrating credit worthiness by showing that the applicant has made payment on credit accounts when due;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Furnishing a guaranty satisfactory to the utility, furnishing an irrevocable commercial letter of credit, or securing a bond drawn against an insurance company acceptable to the utility to secure payments of bills for the service requested in an amount not to exceed the amount of cash deposit prescribed in <cite path="|20|30|01|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Otherwise establishing the applicant's credit to the satisfaction of the utility in conformance with additional reasonable regulations which it may adopt.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A guaranty under <cite path="20|30|01|.02|B.|(2)|(c)">§B(2)(c) of this regulation</cite> shall be in writing and shall continue in effect for 4 years from the date issued or until the customer's credit is otherwise established.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Determination of credit worthiness under <cite path="20|30|01|.02|B.|(2)|(b)">§B(2)(b) of this regulation</cite>  shall be based upon information supplied through normal business credit reporting agencies, acceptable current financial statements, or other established accounts maintained in a satisfactory manner.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If an applicant for nonresidential service is unable to establish credit under the provisions of §B(1) and (2) of this regulation, a utility may require the applicant to establish credit by making a cash deposit to secure payment of a final bill for service under <cite path="|20|30|01|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>If a utility requests from an applicant credit or financial information under <cite path="20|30|01|.02|B.|(4)">§B(4) of this regulation</cite>, and the information is not provided by the applicant within a reasonable time, the utility may require a deposit from an applicant under <cite path="|20|30|01|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite> as a condition of providing service.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The establishment of credit under this regulation does not relieve the applicant or customer from compliance with the reasonable regulations of the utility as to prompt payment of bills, and does not relieve the customer from having service terminated for nonpayment of bills due from service furnished.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>A utility shall advise all applicants for service that a customer may be required to reestablish credit under this regulation, if the conditions of service or the basis on which credit was originally established materially change.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Reestablishment of Credit.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A utility may require an applicant for service who is a present or former nonresidential customer of that utility to reestablish credit under <cite path="|20|30|01|.02">Regulation .02 of this chapter</cite> at the time of application if one of the following exists:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Customer owes an outstanding bill for a prior nonresidential service;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Customer's nonresidential account has been terminated by the utility within the last 12 months of prior service for nonpayment of a bill;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Customer failed to pay a nonresidential bill when it became due on more than two occasions in the last 12 months of prior service;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Customer's nonresidential account is more than 1 month in arrears; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Conditions of service or the basis on which the customer's credit was originally established have materially changed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A nonresidential customer who has established credit and is receiving service but who fails to pay a bill by the expiration date of a termination of service notice, may be required by the utility to reestablish credit by depositing the amount prescribed in <cite path="|20|30|01|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>, in addition to paying the outstanding bill and a reasonable reconnection charge.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03-1</num>
    <heading>Denial of Service.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as prohibited by State or federal law, a utility may refuse to connect or may disconnect service for a former nonresidential customer unless the customer has paid or made satisfactory arrangements to pay any outstanding bill, or undisputed portion of a disputed bill, for prior nonresidential service.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A utility may not refuse service to a customer for nonpayment of an outstanding bill that is over 7 years old, unless the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Customer signed an agreement to pay the outstanding bill before the expiration of this period; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Outstanding bill is for service obtained by the customer in any manner described in <cite path="20.31.02.03|D.">COMAR 20.31.02.03D</cite> or <cite path="20.31.02.04|A.|(1)">COMAR 20.31.02.04A(1)</cite>—(4).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|30|01|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Deposit.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Amount of Deposit. The deposit required by the utility may not be less than $5, and it may not be more than the maximum estimated charge for service for two consecutive billing periods, or 90 days, whichever is less, or as may reasonably be required by the utility in cases involving service for short periods or special occasions.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Payment of Deposit. If requested by the applicant, the utility shall provide some means by which a deposit amount of $100 or more may be paid by the customer in installments over a period of at least 8 weeks. The customer shall be notified of this right at the time of the initial request for deposit. The provisions of this section do not apply to utilities providing telephone service.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Deposit Receipt. Each utility shall issue a receipt of deposit to each customer from whom a deposit is received, and shall provide means by which a depositor may establish his claim if his receipt is lost.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Interest on Deposits.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each utility shall pay simple per annum interest on a deposit from the date of receipt by the utility.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The rate of the interest in <cite path="20|30|01|.04|D.|(1)">§D(1) of this regulation</cite> shall be a weighted monthly average of calendar year rates appropriate to the holding period.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Calendar Year Rates.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The calendar year rates shall be established in December of each year to be effective January 1 of the following year.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The rate shall be equal to the average of the percent yields of 1-year treasury constant maturities for September, October, and November of the preceding year.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Payment of Interest. Interest shall be paid annually, if requested by the customer, or at the time the deposit is returned.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Cessation of Interest. The obligation to pay interest on a deposit shall cease upon:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The date it is returned;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The date service is terminated; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The date notice is sent to the customer's last known address that the deposit is no longer required.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Record of Deposit. Each utility shall keep records to show:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The name and address of each depositor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The amount and date of the deposit;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Each transaction concerning the deposit (a deposit waiver is not considered a transaction).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Record of Unclaimed Deposits. A record of each unclaimed deposit shall be maintained for at least 3 years, during which time the utility shall make reasonable efforts to return the deposit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Unclaimed Deposits. Unclaimed deposits, with accrued interest, shall be credited to an appropriate account, or shall otherwise be disposed of in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcl">Commercial Law Article, Title 17, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|30|01|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Refund of Deposit.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Discontinuance of Service. Upon discontinuance of service, the utility, within 45 days, shall automatically refund the customer's deposit plus accrued interest, or the balance, if any, in excess of the unpaid bills including any penalties assessed for service furnished by the utility. A transfer of service from one premises to another within the service area of the utility may not be deemed a discontinuance of service within the meaning of these regulations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Good Payment Record.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The utility shall promptly and automatically refund the deposit plus accrued interest under the following conditions:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The customer has paid bills for service for the first 4 years of service following payment of his deposit without having had service discontinued for nonpayment of bills within the last 2 years;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The customer has paid all bills without having had more than two occasions within the last 12 months in which a bill was not paid in a reasonable period after it became due;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The customer is not presently delinquent in the payment of his bills;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The customer has not presented a bad check in payment of his bills within the last 2 years; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Detrimental credit information has not been recorded against the customer within the last 2 years.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a customer does not meet the foregoing conditions, the utility shall thereafter review the account every 12 months, and shall promptly and automatically refund the deposit plus accrued interest when the customer has met these standards.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Establishment of Credit. The utility shall promptly return the deposit plus accrued interest at any time upon request if the customer's credit has been established in accordance with the methods specified in <cite path="|20|30|01|.02|B.">Regulation .02B of this chapter</cite>, provided the customer does not owe outstanding bills for the service and meets the criteria set forth in <cite path="20|30|01|.05|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Option of Utility. The utility may refund a deposit plus accrued interest, in whole or in part, earlier than the times prescribed in this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05-1</num>
    <heading>Use of Deposit.</heading>
    <text>A utility may apply a nonresidential customer deposit plus accrued interest, first against any unpaid balance due the utility for nonresidential service as determined by the final bill issued to the customer, and then against any unpaid balance due the utility on any other nonresidential account of that customer.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Appeal by Applicant or Customer.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Appeal to Utility Supervisory Personnel. Each utility shall direct its personnel engaged in initial contact with an applicant for service, or customer seeking to establish or reestablish credit under the provisions of these regulations, to refer the applicant or customer, at his request, to supervisory personnel for further consideration of his problem.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Appeal to Commission Personnel. Each utility shall further direct this supervisory personnel to inform the applicant or customer who expresses dissatisfaction with the decision of the supervisory personnel, of his right to have the problem reviewed by the Commission, and shall furnish him with the business address and telephone number of the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Information to Customers.</heading>
    <text>Each utility, upon request, shall furnish a copy of these regulations to the applicant for service or customer from whom a deposit is required. This copy shall contain the name, address, and telephone number of the Commission.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Public Utilities Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-113">2-113</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-121">2-121</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|4-503">4-503</cite>(a), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|5-101">5-101</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|5-105">5-105</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1979-01-26">Effective date: January 26, 1979 (6:2 Md. R. 75)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-11-18">Regulations .02 and .03 repealed effective November 18, 1985 (12:23 Md. R. 2221)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-11-18">Regulations .02, .03, .03-1, and .05-1 adopted effective November 18, 1985 (12:23 Md. R. 2221)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-05-10"><cite path="|20|30|01|.03-1">Regulation .03-1</cite> amended effective May 10, 1993 (20:9 Md. R. 779)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-03-01"><cite path="|20|30|01|.04|D.">Regulation .04D</cite> amended effective November 18, 1985 (12:23 Md. R. 2221); March 1, 1993 (20:4 Md. R. 372)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-11-18"><cite path="|20|30|01|.04|F.">Regulation .04F</cite> amended effective November 18, 1985 (12:23 Md. R. 2221)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-09-21"><cite path="|20|30|01|.04|I.">Regulation .04I</cite> amended effective September 21, 2009 (36:19 Md. R. 1438)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-11-18"><cite path="|20|30|01|.05|C.">Regulation .05C</cite> amended effective November 18, 1985 (12:23 Md. R. 2221)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
