<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>04</num>
  <heading>Revocation of Disabled Registration Plates and Parking Placards</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>The purpose of this chapter is to establish procedures for the revocation of disabled registration plates and parking placards issued by the Administration under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-616">Transportation Article, §13-616, </cite>13-616.1, or 13-616.2, Annotated Code of Maryland, if the Administration determines an individual has committed fraud, made any misrepresentation in applying for or using disabled registration plates or parking placard, or currently fails to meet the requirements for the issuance of disabled registration plates or parking placard.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Administration" means the Motor Vehicle Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Disabled registration plates" means special disabled registration plates issued by the Administration to individuals who meet the requirements under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-616">Transportation Article, §13-616, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Owner" means an individual issued disabled registration plates or a parking placard under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-616">Transportation Article, §13-616, </cite>13-616.1, or 13-616.2, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Parking placard" means a disabled parking placard issued by the Administration to individuals with disabilities who meet the requirements of Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-616">13-616</cite>.1 or 13-616.2, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Revoke" means to cancel and recall disabled registration plates or parking placards issued by the Administration under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-616">Transportation Article, §13-616, </cite>13-616.1, or 13-616.2, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Complaints.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Complaints made to the Administration regarding fraud or misrepresentation in applying for or using disabled registration plates or parking placards, or individuals with disabled registration plates or parking placards who do not meet the eligibility requirement shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Submitted in writing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Submitted on a form approved by the Administration; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Signed under penalties of perjury by the complainant.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall review the complaint and may conduct an investigation to determine if an individual with disabled registration plates or a parking placard:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Committed fraud in the application for the disabled registration plates or parking placard;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Made any misrepresentation in applying for or using the disabled registration plates or parking placard; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Does not currently meet the eligibility requirements for the issuance of the disabled registration plates or parking placard.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall maintain a record of all investigations conducted regarding fraud, misrepresentation, or ineligibility of individuals with disabled registration plates or parking placards issued by the Administration for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>1 year from the date the investigation is closed, if no administrative action was taken to revoke the disabled registration plates or parking placard; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>8 years from the date the disabled registration plates or parking placards were revoked.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Revocation of Disabled Registration Plates or Parking Placards.</heading>
    <text>The Administration may revoke an owner’s disabled registration plates or parking placard, if after an investigation, the Administration determines that the owner of the disabled registration plates or parking placard:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Committed fraud in the application for the disabled registration plates or parking placard;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Made any misrepresentation in applying for or using the disabled registration plates or parking placard; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Does not currently meet the eligibility requirements for the issuance of disabled registration plates or parking placard.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Notice of Revocation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall send a notice of the proposed revocation to the owner of disabled registration plates or parking placard, and that notice shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In writing; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Sent by U. S. mail to the individual at the address on record with the Administration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The notice shall advise the individual of the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The date the disabled registration plates or parking placard will be revoked;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The reason for the revocation of the disabled registration plates or parking placard;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>That an administrative hearing may be requested by sending a written request to the Administration within 15 days of the notice of revocation to appeal the decision to revoke the disabled registration plates or parking placard;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>That the effective date of the revocation will be stayed until a requested administrative hearing is conducted; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>That the individual may be represented by an attorney at the administrative hearing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Failure to appear for the scheduled administrative hearing shall result in the immediate revocation of the disabled registration plates or parking placard.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Surrender of Revoked Disabled Registration Plates or Parking Placards.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The owner shall surrender to the Administration all disabled registration plates or parking placards revoked by the Administration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Failure to surrender revoked disabled registration plates or parking placards will result in the Administration's issuance of an order to pick up the plates or placards.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall issue substitute registration plates to replace the surrendered disabled registration plates for the remainder of the registration period.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Reissue of Disabled Registration Plates or Parking Placard.</heading>
    <text>If an individual’s disabled registration plates or parking placard has been revoked, before the issuance of new disabled registration plates or parking placard, the individual shall submit an application for the disabled registration plates or parking placard for investigation to determine the validity of the individual’s information on the application.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|12-104">12-104</cite>(b), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-616">13-616</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|13-616">13-616</cite>.1, and 13-616.2, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-03-13">Effective date: March 13, 2006 (33:5 Md. R. 521)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-07-30"><cite path="|11|16|04|.04|D.">Regulation .04D</cite> repealed effective July 30, 2018 (45:15 Md. R. 726)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-07-30"><cite path="|11|16|04|.07">Regulation .07</cite> amended effective July 30, 2018 (45:15 Md. R. 726)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
