<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>11</num>
  <heading>Deanna Camille Green Rule — Contact Voltage Survey Requirement and Reporting</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>CVRZ, Voltage Survey Plan, and Voltage Survey Requirement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Within 60 days after the effective date of these regulations, each electric company shall file for Commission approval:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A list and location map for all CVRZs within its service territory, if applicable; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If no CVRZs are designated in its service territory, its voltage survey plan.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Within 30 days after the Commission approves a CVRZ or CVRZs within an electric company’s service territory, the electric company shall file its voltage survey plan for Commission approval.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Upon approval of the electric company’s voltage survey plan, the electric company shall conduct an initial contact voltage survey of each CVRZ within 1 year of the approval and shall conduct subsequent contact voltage surveys of each CVRZ as set forth in its voltage survey plan.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The electric company shall conduct its initial and each subsequent contact voltage survey within each Commission-approved CVRZ of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All publicly accessible electric distribution plant and electric company-owned or-maintained streetlights that are capable of conducting electricity;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Municipal-owned or governmental-owned streetlights and traffic signals that are publicly accessible and are capable of conducting electricity, if the consent of the municipal government or other appropriate governmental authority is received; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All objects and surfaces that are publicly accessible in public parks and playgrounds and that are capable of conducting electricity, if the consent of the municipal government or other appropriate governmental authority is received.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>At least 60 days prior to implementing any material change to its voltage survey plan, the electric company shall file for Commission approval.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>For areas within each electric company’s service territory which are not located in a CVRZ, the electric company shall perform an initial contact voltage survey within 3 years of the approval of the voltage survey plan on all publicly accessible electric distribution plant, except for wooden poles, and publicly accessible electric company-owned or-maintained streetlights that are capable of conducting electricity. Subsequent contact voltage surveys for all equipment capable of conducting electricity shall be conducted in accordance with the voltage survey plan.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Streetlights shall be tested for contact voltage after dark or when the light is illuminated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The Commission may increase or decrease the frequency or scope of any contact voltage survey requirement upon a showing of good cause.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Contact voltage readings shall be conducted in accordance with acceptable methods described in the Institute of Electrical and Electronic Engineers Standard 1695 — 2016.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Contact Voltage Survey Equipment.</heading>
    <text>Each electric company shall include in its voltage survey plan all equipment used for detecting contact voltage. The type of equipment shall be certified by an independent test laboratory as being able to reliably detect voltages of 6 to 600 volts and this certification shall be included with the electric company’s voltage survey plan filing.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|50|11|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Contact Voltage Survey Test Results.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each electric company shall make an area safe after detecting a potential contact voltage condition during its contact voltage survey until the potential condition can be confirmed under <cite path="20|50|11|.03|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Each electric company shall confirm and document all contact voltage detected in its contact voltage survey using a voltmeter and a 500 ohm shunt resistor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>For each contact voltage measurement under <cite path="20|50|11|.03|B.">§B of this regulation</cite> greater than or equal to one volt (60 Hertz Alternating Current), each electric company shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Perform a contact voltage survey on all objects and surfaces that are capable of conducting electricity and are publicly accessible within a minimum 30 foot radius of the location of the measured contact voltage;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When an electric distribution plant or an electric company-owned or-maintained streetlight is indicating contact voltage, immediately and continuously make the area safe, and use best efforts to make a permanent repair to mitigate the contact voltage as soon as possible, but not later than 45 days, however, a temporary measure to mitigate contact voltage may last longer than 45 days in extraordinary circumstances provided the area remains safe;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>When non-electric company property is indicating contact voltage, immediately use best efforts to make the area safe and immediately use best efforts to notify the customer or responsible person associated with the premises or the customer-owned facility of the unsafe condition and the need for the customer to make a permanent repair to mitigate contact voltage; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Maintain written records of its actions to make the area safe and to mitigate the contact voltage.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Compliance Reporting and Certification.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each electric company shall file, on a form approved by the Commission, an annual compliance report with the Commission:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Describing the results of its contact voltage surveys; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Summarizing each known contact voltage electric shock and each contact voltage electric shock complaint received from a member of the public, whether the shock affected a person or animal.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An initial compliance report shall be filed at the direction of the Commission and subsequent compliance reports shall be filed on or before April 1 of each year for the preceding calendar year.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Civil Penalty.</heading>
    <text>An electric company’s failure to comply with this subtitle may subject the company to civil penalties under the Public Utilities Article.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Waivers and Modifications.</heading>
    <text>The Commission may, in its discretion, waive or modify any provision of this subtitle and may also impose additional requirements as circumstances warrant.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Public Utilities Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-113">2-113</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-121">2-121</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|5-101">5-101</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|5-303">5-303</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-11-28">Effective date: November 28, 2011 (38:24 Md. R. 1503)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-08-21"><cite path="|20|50|11|.01|I.">Regulation .01I</cite> adopted effective August 21, 2023 (50:16 Md. R. 728)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
