<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>Definitions</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this subtitle, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Advanced life support (ALS)" means the level of care which may be rendered by an individual licensed under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|13-516">Education Article, §13-516, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, as an:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Emergency medical technician-paramedic; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Cardiac rescue technician licensed.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Automated external defibrillator (AED)" means a medical heart monitor and defibrillator device that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is cleared for market by the federal Food and Drug Administration;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Recognizes the presence or absence of ventricular fibrillation or rapid ventricular tachycardia;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Determines, without intervention by the operator, whether defibrillation should be performed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>On determining that defibrillation should be performed, automatically charges; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Either:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Requires operator intervention to deliver the electrical impulse; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Automatically continues with delivery of electrical impulse.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Advanced life support (ALS) education program" means an individual, agency, corporation, association, or other entity that prepares individuals for Maryland emergency medical services (EMS) licensure at the ALS level.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Basic life support (BLS)” means the level of care which may be rendered by an individual certified under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|13-516">Education Article, §13-516, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, as:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An emergency medical technician (EMT); or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An emergency medical responder.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Basic life support (BLS) education program" means an individual, agency, corporation, association, or other entity that prepares individuals for Maryland EMS certification at the BLS level.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"BLS instructor" means an individual who meets the requirements of <cite path="30.04.03.09|A.">COMAR 30.04.03.09A</cite> or .11.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“CAPCE” means the Commission on Accreditation for Pre-Hospital Continuing Education, which is a national organization designed to approve continuing education.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"CoAEMSP" means the Committee on Accreditation of Educational Programs for the Emergency Medical Services Professions which is a national committee that accredits programs instructing EMS curricula.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Commercial ambulance service" means a commercial ambulance service required to be licensed under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|13-515">Education Article, §13-515, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Continuing education" means education used for renewal of EMS licensure or certification.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Continuing education program" means a program offering continuing education courses for EMS providers in conjunction with and through an EMS operational program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>"Curriculum" means the required educational content of an EMS course approved by the EMS Board for licensure or certification as an EMS provider under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|13-516">Education Article, §13-516(a), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>"Distance education" means a method of acquiring knowledge and skills through mediated information and instruction, encompassing all technologies and other forms of learning at a distance.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>"Emergency medical dispatcher (EMD)" means an individual licensed by the EMS Board as an emergency medical dispatcher.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>"EMD education program" means an individual, agency, corporation, association, or other entity that prepares individuals for licensure as a Maryland EMD.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>"EMD instructor" means an individual who is currently approved by MIEMSS to teach an approved EMD education program and approved continuing education.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>“Emergency medical responder instructor” means an individual who is currently approved by MIEMSS to teach FR courses and approved continuing education.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>“Emergency medical services (EMS) operational program” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A jurisdictional EMS operational program; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An institution, agency, corporation, or other entity that is licensed by MIEMSS as a commercial service.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>“Emergency medical technician instructor” means an individual who can teach emergency medical technician or EMR courses and meets the requirements of <cite path="30.04.03.09|A.">COMAR 30.04.03.09A</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>"FR instructor" means an individual who is currently approved by MIEMSS to teach FR courses and approved continuing education.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>"JCAHO" means the Joint Commission on Accreditation of Healthcare Organizations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>"MDH" means the Maryland Department of Health.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>"MFRI" means the Maryland Fire and Rescue Institute, University of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(24)</num>
        <text>"MICRB" means the Maryland Instructor Certification Review Board as defined in COMAR 13B.03.01.02B(6).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(25)</num>
        <text>"Nationally recognized EMD education program" means an individual, agency, corporation, association, or other entity which conducts EMD education courses and has:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Nationally recognized expertise and resources to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Set minimum standards for EMD instruction; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Provide adequate quality assurance of its instruction and instructors; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A valid and reliable instrument for the evaluation of EMD students.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(26)</num>
        <text>"NHTSA" means the National Highway Transportation Safety Administration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(27)</num>
        <text>"Proprietary education program" means an individual, agency, corporation, association, or other entity which conducts EMS education and has:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The expertise and resources to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Set minimum standards for the instruction of EMS content; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Provide adequate quality assurance of its instruction and instructors; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A valid and reliable instrument for the evaluation of participants.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(28)</num>
        <text>"Person" includes an individual, agency, corporation, association, or other entity.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(29)</num>
        <text>"Refresher course" means a continuing education course which provides continuing education requirements required for renewal of an EMS license or certificate under <cite path="|30.02.07">COMAR 30.02.07</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(30)</num>
        <text>"Skills course" means a continuing education course which fulfills the skills requirements required for renewal of an EMS license or certificate under <cite path="|30.02.07">COMAR 30.02.07</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(31)</num>
        <text>"Specialty care transport" has the meaning stated in <cite path="30.09.01.02|B.|(1)">COMAR 30.09.01.02B(1)</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|13-516">Education Article, §13-516(d), </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-10-15">Effective date: October 15, 2001 (28:20 Md. R. 1784)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-04-09"><cite path="|30|04|01|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective September 27, 2004 (31:19 Md. R. 1434); December 12, 2013 (40:24 Md. R. 2017); April 9, 2018 (45:7 Md. R. 347)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-01-15"><cite path="|30|04|01|.10|B.">Regulation .10B</cite> amended effective January 15, 2005 (32:16 Md. R. 1866)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
