<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>04</num>
  <heading>Emergency Medical Dispatcher Education Programs</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter governs EMD education programs and EMD courses approved by the EMS Board.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Operational Policies.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each EMD education program shall have written criteria for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Admission;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Frequent evaluation of each student during the course of study including evaluation of competency in providing patient care;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Student requirements for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Attendance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Educational performance including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Attitudes;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Knowledge; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Skills; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Behavior;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Student access to program information including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Fees;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Requirements;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Policies;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Procedures; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Support services;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Selection of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A medical director;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A program coordinator;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Faculty; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Other necessary personnel;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Nondiscrimination and fair practices with regard to students, faculty and program personnel; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Review and improvement of the effectiveness of student evaluation techniques.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Organizational Chart.</heading>
    <text>An EMD education program shall maintain an organizational chart that shows the relationship among students, the program coordinator, the medical director, and the instructors for each EMD course.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Records and Reports.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each EMD education program shall maintain accurate and appropriate records of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Students;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Faculty; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Courses including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Course statistics; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Demographics of applicants.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Records shall be maintained for at least 5 years following course completion in a manner to prevent loss, destruction, or unauthorized use.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Content.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each EMD education program shall teach the appropriate EMD curriculum.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Distance Education. A training program may utilize distance education for cognitive components of initial training leading to EMS licensure if the program:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Demonstrates the methods of distance education utilized are educationally and technically appropriate for the content and audience; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Ensures the quality of the distance education method including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Learning and teaching considerations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Communication;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Educational and technology design; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Program and system management.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Human Resources—General.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>There shall be written agreements and position descriptions stating the roles and responsibilities of the following program positions:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Medical director;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Program coordinator;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Instructor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>All education programs shall have adequate clerical and support staffing to provide for the program needs.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Human Resources—Medical Director.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each EMD education program shall have a medical director who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is a physician licensed to practice medicine in Maryland;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Has current working knowledge and experience in emergency medical care of acutely ill or injured patients;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Has working knowledge of the Maryland EMS system;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Has working knowledge of the Maryland Medical Protocols for Emergency Medical Services Providers; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Has current working knowledge of EMD operations.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The medical director is responsible for oversight of the medical educational content of the EMD education program curriculum.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Human Resources—Program Coordinator.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each EMD education program shall have a program coordinator with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At least 3 years public safety call taking and call allocating experience;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Experience in EMD education programs; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An EMD license.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The program coordinator shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Have overall responsibility for the success of the EMD education program including quality review and improvement; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Assist the medical director with the recruitment and selection of instructors.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Human Resources—Instructor.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each EMD course shall be taught by an EMD instructor, or an interim instructor under the supervision of an EMD instructor, who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Satisfies all of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is certified as an MICRB Level II emergency services instructor who has successfully:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Completed one didactic and one practical teaching session evaluated by an EMD instructor approved as an MICRB evaluator; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Taught one EMD course as an interim instructor and been twice successfully evaluated by an EMD instructor approved as an MICRB evaluator;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Has at least 3 years of public safety call taking and call allocating experience; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Is licensed as a Maryland EMD and ALS provider; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is approved by a nationally recognized EMD education program approved by the EMS Board or the equivalent.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An EMD instructor is responsible for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The education program instruction; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Any interim or additional EMD instructors assisting with the course.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The EMD instructor approval period shall be concurrent with the MICRB emergency services certification or the instructor approval period of a nationally recognized EMD education program approved by the EMS Board or the equivalent.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>EMD Instructor Renewal. An EMD instructor shall remain current by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Satisfying all of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Completing requirements as an MICRB instructor including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Receiving a satisfactory EMD course teaching evaluation and no subsequent unsatisfactory evaluations from an EMD instructor who is also an approved MICRB evaluator; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Instructing at least 16 hours in an EMD course or, if a training supervisor, at least 4 hours in an EMD course; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Maintaining a Maryland EMD and ALS license; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Maintaining instructor approval by a nationally recognized EMD education program approved by the EMS Board or the equivalent.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If qualified, the EMD instructor may also function as the EMD program coordinator.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Physical Resources.</heading>
    <text>Each EMD education program shall have adequate space at instructional facilities to accommodate the program.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Financial Resources.</heading>
    <text>Each EMD education program shall have sufficient financial resources to ensure complete EMD course delivery for all enrolled students.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Special Needs.</heading>
    <text>Each EMD education program shall advise MIEMSS in writing of any students requiring accommodations for documented disabilities at least 5 days before a scheduled licensure examination.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Program Evaluation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each EMD education program shall have a written policy and procedure for evaluation of the EMD courses.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The evaluation shall be annually and provide written evidence the program is meeting its objectives and changing needs of EMS care.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The evaluation plan shall include methods for gathering and analyzing data on the effectiveness of the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Instruction;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Resources;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Responsiveness to recommendations for change;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>EMD instructors; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Students' ability to function as entry-level providers upon successful completion of the EMD education program.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The results of the evaluations shall provide the basis for continuous quality improvement and future direction of the EMD courses.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Annual Report. Each EMD education program shall submit an annual report to MIEMSS in an approved format.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Curriculum and Education.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The EMS Board shall establish standard curricula and learning objectives for the EMD education programs.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Each EMD course shall prepare the student for entry-level practice.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The amount of time devoted to the delivery of the EMD course may vary depending on the students' ability to demonstrate proficiency in the educational objectives utilizing:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Written examinations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Oral examinations; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Practical examinations.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>EMD Education Program Approval.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An EMD education program shall apply for approval by submitting a MEIMSS-approved application and a copy of the course curriculum to MIEMSS, Office of Education, Licensure, and Certification, EMD Program, 653 West Pratt Street, Baltimore, Maryland 21201-1528.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An EMD education program providing EMD courses on the effective date of this regulation may continue to offer EMD courses for not more than 3 years from that date unless the program is approved under this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Site Visit.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>After a completed application is accepted by MIEMSS, a site visit shall be scheduled at a mutually convenient time.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The site review team shall be selected by MIEMSS and consist of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A system medical director or an EMD education program medical director;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A BLS instructor or EMD program director;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>MIEMSS representative; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Others as necessary.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If an applicant can demonstrate a reasonable basis for concern, MIEMSS shall consider allegations that conflicts of interest exist between a site reviewer and an applicant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The site review team shall send a written report to MIEMSS within 30 days after the site visit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The site review team and MIEMSS shall finalize the site visit and report and MIEMSS shall submit a recommendation to the EMS Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>EMS Board Action.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Five-Year Approval. If the EMS Board determines that the applicant meets the requirements of this chapter, the EMS Board shall grant the applicant a 5-year approval as an EMD education program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>To maintain approval the EMD education program shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Comply with <cite path="|30.04.04">COMAR 30.04.04</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Advise MIEMSS in writing within 30 days of any changes in:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Program personnel other than instructors;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Organizational changes; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Programmatic changes;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Maintain a process of continuous quality improvement; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Conduct at least one full length EMD course every 2 years.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Provisional Approval.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If the EMS Board determines that the application and the site visit indicate limitations in meeting requirements for full approval, it may approve the application provisionally on the conditions and for the provisional period, including any extensions, which the EMS Board deems appropriate.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An applicant receiving provisional approval shall submit written progress reports to MIEMSS as required by the EMS Board.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>MIEMSS may conduct one or more additional site visits to verify the resolution of limitations.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Before any additional site visit, the applicant shall prepare a revised report that includes changes made since the prior site visit.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Upon satisfactory resolution of limitations, or at the end of the provisional period, including any extensions, the EMS Board shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Confer approval for the remainder of the 5-year period if the applicant has satisfied all requirements for approval; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Deny or revoke approval.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Denial or Revocation of Approval. The EMS Board may deny or revoke program approval if an EMD education program is not in compliance with this chapter. The program shall be notified by mail of the EMS Board's decision. If the decision is other than a 5-year approval, the notice shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>State the reasons for the decision;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Advise the EMD education program of appeal rights; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Otherwise comply with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-207">State Government Article, §10-207, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>MIEMSS personnel may attend course sessions for quality assurance.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Renewal.</heading>
    <text>EMD education programs shall make application for renewal of approval at least 6 months before the expiration of current approval.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.17</num>
    <heading>Course Number.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each EMD course shall have a number assigned by MIEMSS.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An EMD education program approved under this chapter shall apply for EMD course approval and a course number for each course it proposes to provide by submitting a MIEMSS-approved application at least 20 days before the first class to MIEMSS, Office of Education, Licensure, and Certification, EMD Programs, 653 West Pratt Street, Baltimore, Maryland 21201-1528.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Requests for approval of EMD courses shall be signed by the program director.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>ALS and BLS Education Programs.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>EMS Board approved ALS and BLS education programs may offer EMD education courses in accordance with this chapter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The ALS or BLS education program shall request MIEMSS approval of an EMD course and request a course number at least 20 days before the first class of each course which the program purposes to provide.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Sections of the course application that parallel the ALS or BLS education program approval process may be waived if the ALS or BLS education program complies with <cite path="|30.04.04">COMAR 30.04.04</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>ALS or BLS education program requests for EMD course approval and a course number shall be signed by the program director and sent to MIEMSS in a MIEMSS-approved format.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Nationally Recognized Programs.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An EMS Board approved nationally recognized EMD education program or the equivalent as determined by the EMS Board may offer EMD education courses.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The nationally recognized EMD education program or equivalent shall request an EMD course number at least 20 days before the first class of each course it proposes to provide.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The request shall be filed with MIEMSS in a format approved by MIEMSS.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.18</num>
    <heading>No Effect on Other Laws.</heading>
    <text>This chapter does not relieve the EMD education program from the requirements of any statute or regulation which would otherwise apply.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|13-516">Education Article, §13-516(d), </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-10-15">Effective date: October 15, 2001 (28:20 Md. R. 1784)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-10-03"><cite path="|30|04|04|.15|D.">Regulation .15D</cite> amended effective October 3, 2011 (38:20 Md. R. 1205)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
