<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Continuing Education</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter governs MIEMSS-approved continuing education courses for renewal of licensure or certification for Maryland EMS providers.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="30|04|05|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Continuing Education Courses Eligible for Credit under COMAR 30.02.02.07.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Skills and full refresher courses eligible for credit under <cite path="30.02.02.07">COMAR 30.02.02.07</cite> shall be provided under the requirements of this chapter by EMS Board approved:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>ALS education programs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>BLS education programs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>EMD education programs; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Programs listed in <cite path="30.04.05.02|C.">COMAR 30.04.05.02C</cite> which:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Complete an application approved by MIEMSS;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Have policies and procedures in place which address:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Student attendance;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Nondiscrimination and fair practices with regard to students, faculty, and program personnel;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Selection of a medical director, coordinator, and faculty;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Evaluation of the courses and evidence to demonstrate continuous quality improvement; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Record maintenance for at least 5 years following course completion in a manner to prevent loss, destruction, or unauthorized use;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Have adequate physical resources to effectively deliver courses including necessary equipment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Have sufficient financial resources to ensure complete course delivery for all enrolled students;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Have faculty or instructors approved by the medial director;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Utilize only emergency medical technician refresher or skills courses instructors who meet the requirements under <cite path="30.04.03.09">COMAR 30.04.03.09</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Submit an annual report to MIEMSS in an approved format.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The period for which EMS Board approval for programs offering skills and full refresher courses is valid:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Coincides with the program approval for approved ALS, BLS, or EMD education programs; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is 5 years for other programs.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Other continuing education courses eligible for credit under <cite path="30.02.02.07">COMAR 30.02.02.07</cite> shall be provided by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>EMS operational programs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Hospitals accredited by the Joint Commission on Accreditation of Healthcare Organizations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>EMS Board approved proprietary education programs;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Entities accredited by the Emergency Numbers Systems Board; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Education programs listed in <cite path="30|04|05|.02|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Distance Education.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Scope. Training programs may use distance education for cognitive components of continuing education leading to EMS relicensure or recertification if the program:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Demonstrates the methods of distance education used are educationally and technically appropriate for the content and audience; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Ensures the quality of the distance education method including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Learning and teaching considerations;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Communication;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Educational and technology design; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Program and system management.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Distance education programs may apply for a course number and approval as outlined in <cite path="|30|04|05|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Records and Reports.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each continuing education program shall maintain accurate and appropriate records including:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Student attendance records;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Names of instructors;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Presentation outlines;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Objectives;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Handouts; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>An evaluation mechanism.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Records shall be securely maintained to prevent loss, destruction, or unauthorized use for at least 5 years following course completion.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Instructors.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>All non-distance education continuing education courses shall be taught by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An ALS faculty member of an ALS education program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An EMS Board approved proprietary education program instructor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An EMS operational program medical director or designee who has experience or knowledge with the topic to be presented;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>An EMD, emergency medical technician, or EMR instructor; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A certified MICRB emergency services instructor.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The following continuing education instructors shall teach skills at the level for which they are approved:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>EMD instructors may only teach EMD material;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>EMR instructors may only teach EMR material;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Emergency medical technician instructors may only teach BLS material;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>ALS faculty may only teach material they are approved to teach in their ALS education program; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>MICRB-certified instructors may only teach the material they are approved to teach with their education program.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="30|04|05|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Approval and Course Number.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each continuing education course shall have a number assigned by MIEMSS.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="30|04|05|.05|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>, each person shall apply for approval of each continuing education course they propose to offer, and for a course number, by submitting a MIEMSS-approved application at least 14 days before the course begins to MIEMSS, Office of Education, Licensure, and Certification, Continuing Education, 653 West Pratt Street, Baltimore, Maryland 21201-1528.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If MIEMSS determines that the continuing education course is in compliance with this chapter, MIEMSS shall assign:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The course's continuing education category;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The number of credit hours which can be obtained from the course; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A course number.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Continuing education courses that are statewide or nationally recognized may be assigned a permanent course number by MIEMSS. A course with a permanent number may be offered without further approval from MIEMSS if it continues to meet the requirements of this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Continuing education courses developed, designed, and used at or within an EMS operational program shall be coordinated through that EMS operational program. The request for MIEMSS approval of these courses shall be reviewed by the EMS operational program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>MIEMSS may deny or revoke course approval if a continuing education course is not in compliance with this chapter. The continuing education course shall be notified by mail of MIEMSS' decision. The notice shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>State the reasons for the decision;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Advise the continuing education course of appeal rights; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Otherwise comply with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-207">State Government Article, §10-207, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>MIEMSS personnel may attend course sessions for quality assurance.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Other Courses.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Requests for approval of credit for continuing education courses for other courses attended shall be submitted to MIEMSS accompanied by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Documentation of successful completion; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Course content.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>CAPCE-approved continuing education shall be submitted to MIEMSS for approval.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|13-516">Education Article, §13-516(d), </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-10-15">Effective date: October 15, 2001 (28:20 Md. R. 1784)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-09-27"><cite path="|30|04|05|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective September 27, 2007 (31:19 Md. R. 1434)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-12-12"><cite path="|30|04|05|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended effective December 12, 2013 (40:24 Md. R. 2017)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-12-12"><cite path="|30|04|05|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective December 12, 2013 (40:24 Md. R. 2017)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-04-09"><cite path="|30|04|05|.06|B.">Regulation .06B</cite> amended effective April 9, 2018 (45:7 Md. R. 347)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
