<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>09</num>
  <heading>Maryland Child Care Credential Program</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter governs the operation of the Maryland Child Care Credential Program and sets forth the:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Requirements for participation in the program;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Process for application into the program;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Basis and procedure for making determinations and awards; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Penalties for providing false information in order to obtain an award.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Accreditation” means the assessment of a child care facility by an accreditation organization approved by the Office, such as, but not limited to, the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Maryland State Department of Education;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>National Association for the Education of Young Children;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>National Association for Family Child Care; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>National Early Childhood Professional Accreditation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Annual family income" means the combined annual adjusted gross income, as reported for federal tax purposes, of all members of the applicant's household.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Applicant" means an individual applying for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Participation in the credential program;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Funding through training vouchers; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Funding through the Child Care Career and Professional Development Fund.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Approved course work" means approved courses taken for credit from a regionally accredited college or university that includes at least one course in each of the following topic areas:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Child development;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Early childhood materials and methods;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Special education;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Administration and management of a child care program;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Infants and toddlers;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>School-age children;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Health, safety, and nutrition; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Language and literacy.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Approved degree program" means a program of college courses leading to a degree in:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Early childhood education;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Child development;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Elementary education; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A related field as approved by the Office.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Approved setting" means a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Licensed child care center;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Registered family child care home, including a large family child care home;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Nursery school;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Public or private school;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Parks and recreation program; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Similar program recognized by the Office of Child Care.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Approved trainer" means an individual or organization that has been evaluated and approved by the Office to offer training to child care providers.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Award" means any payment of money, or the issuance of a training voucher, by the Office under this chapter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Benefits" means one or more employer incentives available to child care program staff that include, but are not limited to, health coverage, 401K plan, profit sharing, paid vacation leave, sick leave, holiday leave, and release time for training.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Child care professional activity" means an activity or group of activities related to the child care profession, such as:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Professional association membership;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Work with State or national accreditation organizations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Peer mentoring; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Conducting training.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>“Child care facility” means a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Registered family child care home, including a large family child care home;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Licensed child care center;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Letter of compliance facility; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Child care program authorized by the U.S. Department of Defense.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>"Child care professional activity unit" means the amount of credit given to an individual professional activity for the purpose of determining a credential level.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>"Clock hour" means 1 hour (60 minutes) on the clock.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>"College" means an accredited college or university that is approved by the Office.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>“Continued training” means approved training that is taken on an annual or continuing basis to fulfill the requirements of this chapter and of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>COMAR 13A.15;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>COMAR 13A.16;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>COMAR 13A.17; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>COMAR 13A.18.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>"Core of knowledge" means the competencies, which include child development, curriculum, special needs, professionalism, community and health, safety, and nutrition, that are identified by the Office as essential for all individuals working in the child care delivery system.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>“Core of knowledge training” means training that has been evaluated and approved by the Office as meeting the standards for the core of knowledge and the requirements of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>COMAR 13A.15;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>COMAR 13A.16;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>COMAR 13A.17; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>COMAR 13A.18.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>"Credential" means the credential from the Maryland Child Care Credential Program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>"Credential level" means a level of the Maryland Child Care Credential program that designates achievement of a predetermined amount of professional education, experience, and activity.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>“Credential achievement bonus” means a cash payment awarded to a program participant who achieves, or renews program participation at, a specified credential level.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>"Degree" means the completion of a course of study from an accredited college or university located in:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The United States;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A United States territory; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A foreign country, if the degree has been:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Translated into English; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Determined to meet standards equivalent to a degree issued in the United States.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>“Experience” means working directly with children in a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Child care facility; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Supervised program, such as a:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Nursery school;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Public or private school;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Parks and recreation program; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Similar program recognized by the Office of Child Care.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>"Fund" means the Child Care Career and Professional Development Fund.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(24)</num>
        <text>"Grantee" means an individual who has received an award under this chapter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(25)</num>
        <text>“Lead staff” means the director of a child care facility or a child care facility staff member designated to be in charge of the facility or a classroom of children at a given time during the facility’s approved hours of operation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(26)</num>
        <text>"Office" means the Office of Credentialing under the Office of Child Care, State Department of Education</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(27)</num>
        <text>“One year of college” means the successful completion of 30 college credit hours.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(28)</num>
        <text>“One year of college course work” means not less than 30 college credit hours from a regionally accredited college or university that have been successfully completed for credit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(29)</num>
        <text>"One year of experience" means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>1,800 clock hours of experience working with children from birth through 5 years old; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>400 clock hours of experience working with children 6 years old through 16 years old.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(30)</num>
        <text>"Participant" means an individual who participates in the Maryland Child Care Credential program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(31)</num>
        <text>"Points" means the numerical value assigned to a specified activity or accomplishment that may be counted toward qualification for a specified credential level.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(32)</num>
        <text>"Pre-service training" means training that is received:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Through a college or university; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>To meet initial employment qualification requirements established for registered family child care homes, licensed child care centers, or letter of compliance facilities.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(33)</num>
        <text>“Provider” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A registered family child care provider or co-provider;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An approved additional adult in a registered family child care home;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The director of a child care facility; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A staff member in a child care facility.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(34)</num>
        <text>“Related discipline” means the completion of at least 15 college credit hours of approved core of knowledge coursework.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(35)</num>
        <text>“Staff member” means an individual, other than a volunteer or a substitute, who is assigned responsibility for child care in a child care facility and, if applicable, whose assignment helps to maintain required staff/child ratios.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(36)</num>
        <text>“Successful completion” means meeting the requirements of a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Workshop, training, or seminar for which a certificate of completion is received; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>College course taken for credit in which a grade of “C” or higher is earned.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(37)</num>
        <text>"Training" means a workshop, seminar, or other course, whether completed for credit or noncredit, that is offered by a college, university, or approved trainer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(38)</num>
        <text>“Training voucher” means a coupon given by the Office to a participant to purchase pre-service or conference training from an approved training source.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(39)</num>
        <text>“Transcript” means an official statement from a college or university which identifies the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Student;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Institution;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Primary course of study;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Dates of attendance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Courses taken;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Grades received;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Number of credits completed; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Degree awarded, if applicable, and the date of the award.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>General Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>To qualify at each credential level, an applicant shall meet the requirements for that level.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Eligibility for Participation.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Participation in the credential program is limited to providers, as defined at <cite path="|13A|14|09|.02|B.|(33)">Regulation .02B(33) of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The following individuals who are employed or serve in a child care facility are not eligible to participate in the credential program:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Substitutes;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Volunteers;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Support staff, such as clerical workers and van drivers, who do not have child care responsibilities and, if applicable, whose assignment does not help to maintain required staff/child ratios;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A family child care provider, child care center operator, or letter of compliance facility operator whose registration certificate, center license, or letter of compliance is the subject of suspension or revocation action; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>A provider who has a documented history of confirmed complaints involving serious harm to a child in care including but not limited to child abuse, child neglect, injurious treatment of a child, or child supervision.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Upon applying to participate in the credential program, an applicant shall agree to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Continue working in a child care setting for not less than 1 year from the date of acceptance into the credentialing program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Complete continued training for the applicable credential level under <cite path="|13A|14|09|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Pursuant to <cite path="|13A|14|09|.04">Regulation .04 of this chapter</cite>, complete the appropriate number of child care professional activity units for the applicable credential level.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Term and Renewal of Credential. At each credential level, a credential:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is issued for a 12-month period; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>May be renewed annually under <cite path="|13A|14|09|.05|D.">Regulation .05D of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|14|09|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Child Care Credential Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Staff Credential 1. The only qualification for a level 1 credential shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Current registration as a family child care provider or co-provider; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Qualification by the Office as a child care facility:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Director; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Staff member.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Staff Credential 2. Qualification for a level 2 credential requires:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Successful completion of 45 clock hours of core of knowledge training, of which 20 clock hours shall be in child development; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Completion of one child care professional activity unit within the 12 months before applying for participation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Staff Credential 3. Qualification for a level 3 credential requires:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Successful completion of 90 clock hours of core of knowledge training, of which a minimum of 20 clock hours each shall be in child development and in curriculum development;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Completion of two child care professional activity units within the 12 months before applying for participation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Completion of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>1 year of experience working directly with children in an approved setting;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>1 year of college; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A combination of experience and college equal to 1 year.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Staff Credential 4. Qualification for a level 4 credential requires:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Successful completion of 135 clock hours of core of knowledge training, consisting of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>45 clock hours in child development;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>30 clock hours in curriculum development;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>20 clock hours in health, safety, and nutrition;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>15 clock hours in special needs;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>15 clock hours in professionalism; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>10 clock hours in community issues;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Completion of three child care professional activity units within the 12 months before applying for participation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Completion of 2 years of experience working directly with children in an approved setting.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Staff Credential 4 Plus. Qualification for a level 4 plus credential requires a participant to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Successfully complete 135 clock hours of core of knowledge training as specified at <cite path="13A|14|09|.04|D.|(1)">§D(1) of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Take part in at least four child care professional activity units within the 12 months before applying for participation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Complete a minimum of 2 years of experience working directly with children in an approved setting; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Meet one of the following requirements:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Hold current accreditation as a family child care provider;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Complete at least:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>15 college credit hours of approved course work that includes courses in child development and curriculum planning; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>7 additional years of experience working with children in an approved setting; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Enroll in an approved degree program that includes at least one early childhood course and accumulate 55 points by earning 5 points for completing each additional:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Early childhood course for credit; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Year of experience working with children in an approved setting.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Staff Credential 5. Qualification for a level 5 credential requires a participant to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Complete a minimum of 2 years of experience working directly with children in an approved setting;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Take part in four child care professional activity units; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Complete one of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An associate degree with 15 college credit hours of approved course work that includes courses in child development and curriculum planning;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>30 college credit hours of approved course work that includes at least one course in each of the following areas:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Child development;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Curriculum planning;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Health and safety;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Special needs;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Working with school-age children;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Working with infant and toddler-age children;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Language and literacy; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Administration of child care programs; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>15 college credit hours of approved course work, enrolled in an approved degree program, and accumulate 45 points by earning 5 points for completing each additional:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Early childhood course for credit; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Year of experience working with children in an approved setting.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Staff Credential 6. Qualification for a level 6 credential requires a participant to complete:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At least 2 years of experience working directly with children in an approved setting;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>At least 5 child care professional activity units within the 12 months before applying for participation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>One of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A bachelor's, master's, or doctoral degree from an accredited college or university in:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Early childhood education;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Elementary education;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Special education;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Family studies;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Child development; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>A related discipline; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>At least one course in:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Child development; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Curriculum development; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Complete:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A bachelor's, master's, or doctoral degree in a nonrelated field; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>30 semester hours of approved course work that includes courses in child development and curriculum planning; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Complete an associate or higher degree with 15 semester hours of approved course work, enroll in an approved degree program, and accumulate 45 points by earning 5 points for each additional:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Early childhood course for credit; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Year of experience working with children in an approved setting.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Administrator Credential 1. Qualification for a level 1 credential requires completion of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>2 years of experience working directly with children in an approved setting;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Four child care professional activity units within the 12 months before applying for participation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>240 clock hours of core of knowledge training, consisting of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>45 clock hours in child development;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>45 clock hours in curriculum development;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>45 clock hours in health, safety, and nutrition;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>45 clock hours in special needs;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>45 clock hours in professionalism; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>15 clock hours in community issues.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Administrator Credential 2. Qualification for a level 2 credential requires completion of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>2 years of experience working directly with children in an approved setting;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Five child care professional activity units within the 12 months before applying for participation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>240 clock hours of core of knowledge training consisting of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>45 clock hours in child development;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>45 clock hours in curriculum development;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>45 clock hours in health, safety, and nutrition;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>45 clock hours in special needs;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>45 clock hours in professionalism; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>15 clock hours in community issues; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Either:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The National Administrator's Credential; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>At least 30 semester hours of college course work in an approved course of study.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Administrator Credential 3. Qualification for a level 3 credential requires completion of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>4 years of experience working directly with children in an approved setting;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Five child care professional activity units within the 12 months before applying for participation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An associate degree from an accredited college that includes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>15 college credit hours of course work related to business management or administration; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>One course for credit in each of the following areas:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Child development;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Curriculum development; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Administration of child care programs.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Administrator Credential 4. Qualification for a level 4 credential requires completion of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>5 years of experience working directly with children in an approved setting;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Six child care professional activity units within the 12 months before applying for participation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>45 clock hours of training in the area of mentoring and coaching staff;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A bachelor's, master's, or doctoral degree from an accredited college or university in:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Business administration;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Public administration and management;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Public school administration;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A degree as specified at <cite path="13A|14|09|.04|G.|(3)">§G(3) of this regulation</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>A related discipline; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>One course for credit in each of the following areas:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Child development;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Curriculum development; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Administration of child care programs.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|14|09|.05">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Application for Credential.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A separate application is required for each level of a Staff Credential or an Administrator Credential.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Application for Participation.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Office shall accept applications only from individuals.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>To participate, each applicant shall submit to the Office a complete application, which includes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An application form, supplied by the Office, which is completed and signed by the applicant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Documentation of all:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Workshops, conferences, and seminars completed within 5 years before the date of application;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>College course work for credit, preservice course work, Child Development Associate certification, or military child development training regardless of date completed; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Documentation of participation in child care professional activities which includes but is not limited to a membership card, letter of participation, or certificate of recognition.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An applicant for a Staff Credential or Administrator Credential at level 2 or higher shall submit:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All documentation specified in <cite path="13A|14|09|.05|B.|(2)">§B(2) of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Documentation of experience, which shall consist of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A letter from each employer that states the dates of employment, position held, and age group of children worked with;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A copy of the applicant's college transcript indicating 1 year of college course work; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A copy of the applicant’s current family child care registration certificate with at least one child attendance sheet completed during the past 12 months.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>An applicant for a Staff Credential 5, Staff Credential 6, Administrator Credential 3, or Administrator Credential 4 shall submit:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All documentation specified in §B(2) and (3) of this regulation; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Documentation of the applicant's college degree, which shall consist of a copy of the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Awarded diploma; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>College transcript.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Office may not accept a foreign diploma or academic transcript for credential application purposes unless it has been translated and evaluated by an approved evaluation organization.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Notification to Applicant. Within 60 days of receiving an application, the Office shall notify the applicant of the status of the application.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Renewal. Within 30 days after the credential expires, a participant who wants to renew shall submit to the Office:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A completed application for renewal; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Documentation that each of the following has occurred, as required, during the 12-month period for which the credential was issued:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Continued employment; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Completion of the following continuing training and child care professional activity unit requirements applicable to the participant's credential level:</text>
          <text>
            <table class="layout-table">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th/>
                  <th colspan="2">Continued Child Care Professional</th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <th>Level</th>
                  <th>Training</th>
                  <th>Activity Units</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td>Staff Credential 2</td>
                  <td>12</td>
                  <td>1</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Staff Credential 3</td>
                  <td>18</td>
                  <td>2</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Staff Credential 4</td>
                  <td>24</td>
                  <td>3</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Staff Credential 4 Plus 24</td>
                  <td>4</td>
                  <td/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Staff Credential 5</td>
                  <td>24</td>
                  <td>4</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Staff Credential 6</td>
                  <td>24</td>
                  <td>5</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Administrator Credential 1</td>
                  <td>24</td>
                  <td>4</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Administrator Credential 2</td>
                  <td>30</td>
                  <td>5</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Administrator Credential 3</td>
                  <td>30</td>
                  <td>5</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Administrator Credential 4 30</td>
                  <td>6</td>
                  <td/>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Credential Achievement Bonus.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A credential program participant shall receive an achievement bonus upon:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Initial entry into the credential program at Staff Credential or Administrator Credential level 2 or higher; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Achievement thereafter of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Each successively higher credential level; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Annual approval at:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Staff Credential levels 4 Plus through 6; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Administrator Credential levels 2 through 4.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An achievement bonus shall be awarded:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>One time only at:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Staff Credential levels 2 through 4; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Administrator Credential level 1; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Annually for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Staff Credential levels 4 Plus through 6; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Administrator Credential levels 2 through 4.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>To receive an achievement bonus, a participant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Meet the requirements for Staff Credential or Administrator Credential level 2 or higher as set forth at Regulation .04B or I, as applicable, of this chapter; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>File an application pursuant to <cite path="|13A|14|09|.05|E.">Regulation .05E of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Upon verification by the Office that the participant has met the requirements for an achievement bonus, the Office shall award a bonus of at least the amount set forth in the following schedule:</text>
      <text>
        <table class="layout-table">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Level</th>
              <th>Achievement Bonus</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>Staff Credential 1</td>
              <td>No Award</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Staff Credential 2</td>
              <td>$200</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Staff Credential 3</td>
              <td>$300</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Staff Credential 4</td>
              <td>$500</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Staff Credential 4 Plus</td>
              <td>$600</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Staff Credential 5</td>
              <td>$750</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Staff Credential 6</td>
              <td>$1,000</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Administrator Credential 1</td>
              <td>$600</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Administrator Credential 2</td>
              <td>$750</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Administrator Credential 3</td>
              <td>$1,000</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Administrator Credential 4</td>
              <td>$1,500</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Training Vouchers and Reimbursement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Eligibility for a training voucher or reimbursement is limited to individuals participating in the credential program at level two or higher.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>During the 12-month credential period, a participant may receive not more than $400 in training vouchers and reimbursements to pay for the cost of approved core of knowledge training.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Application for Training Vouchers.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An application for a training voucher shall be accepted only for a pre-service training, a Statewide conference, or a national conference.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Office shall accept an application for a training voucher only from an individual.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Not less than 60 days before the date of the training for which the voucher will be used, the individual shall submit to the Office a complete application, which includes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An application form, supplied by the Office, that is completed and signed by the participant; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Documentation of the training for which the voucher will be used, which shall include a copy of the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Course catalog description;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Registration form; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Conference training advertisement.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Subject to funding availability, the Office shall, within 30 days of the receipt of the application, approve an applicant to receive a training voucher if the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Application is received not less than 60 days before the training date;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Application is complete;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Amount requested does not exceed $400; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Applicant is eligible to receive a voucher.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Application for Training Reimbursement.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An individual may request and receive reimbursement for training if the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Training meets the requirements of the core of knowledge;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Training has been successfully completed not more than 180 days before the date of the request; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Individual has not received more than $400 in training vouchers or reimbursements within the individual’s current credentialing period.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Not more than 180 days after the successful completion of the training for which the reimbursement is sought, the individual shall submit to the Office a complete application, which includes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An application form, supplied by the Office, that is completed and signed by the participant; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Documentation of the training for which the reimbursement is sought, which shall include a copy of the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Course catalog description or training advertisement;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Grade slip, transcript, or certificate of completion; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Receipt for payment indicating the amount paid.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Subject to funding availability, the Office shall approve an applicant to receive training reimbursement if the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Application is received not later than 180 days after the completion of training;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Application is complete;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Amount requested does not exceed $400; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Applicant is eligible to receive a reimbursement.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If the applicant is eligible, the Office shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Award a training voucher to the applicant for the training and the amount specified on the application; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Issue instructions for payment of training reimbursement.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>If the applicant is found ineligible for an award, the Office shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provide written notification to the applicant of the determination of ineligibility; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Return to the applicant all application materials submitted.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Assignment of Awards.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Funding for training vouchers and reimbursement is provided to the Office on an annual basis.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Awards are assigned according to the incomes of all applicants who are eligible for an award, with higher priority given to lower income applicants.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Applicants whose annual family income does not exceed the current Maryland median income for their family size shall be given priority to receive training vouchers or reimbursement during that month.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Office shall make training voucher and reimbursement awards according to assigned award priority until:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An award has been made to each eligible applicant; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The funding allocation is exhausted.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Upon successful completion of the workshop, seminar, or other course for which a training voucher was issued and used, the participant shall provide to the Office a copy of the:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Transcript;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Grade slip;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Certificate; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Documentation given by the instructor that indicates successful completion of the training.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|14|09|.08">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Child Care Career and Professional Development Fund.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Fund Uses and Limitations. An award under the Fund:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Applied toward the cost of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Tuition;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>College fees; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Course-required textbooks; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Used by a grantee only for the actual expense of college course work incurred subsequent to an award toward completion of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A college degree in early childhood education or a related field; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Developmental course work needed to meet prerequisites for a degree program in early childhood education or a related field.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>May not be used to pay for fees or costs, including tuition costs, previously incurred for college enrollment or attendance purposes.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Eligibility to submit an application is limited to individuals who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Are participating in the credential program at level 2 or higher;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Have at least 1 year of documented experience working with groups of children in an approved setting; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Have been accepted by an accredited college or university for enrollment in one or more college courses for credit toward a degree in early childhood education or a related field.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Applications.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Office shall accept an application only from a provider, as defined at <cite path="|13A|14|09|.02">Regulation .02 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>To apply for the Fund, the applicant shall submit to the Office a complete application, which includes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An application form, supplied by the Office, which is completed and signed by the applicant; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>All documentation required by the application form supplied by the Office.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Priority for an award shall be given to applicants who have not completed any college courses for credit from an accredited college or university.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Subject to funding availability, the Office shall approve an applicant to receive an award if the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Application is complete;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>College has been approved to participate in the Fund; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Applicant is eligible to receive an award.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Upon determination by the Office that an applicant is eligible to receive an award and that funding is available:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The applicant shall receive an award; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An award letter shall be issued to the applicant.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>If an eligible applicant is denied an award due to insufficient award funds, the individual may reapply to be considered for a future award.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>If an applicant is found ineligible for an award, the Office shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Provide written notification to the applicant of the determination of ineligibility; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Return to the applicant all application materials submitted.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Assignment of Awards.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Funding for the Child Care Career and Professional Development Fund awards is provided to the Office on an annual basis.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Office shall make awards annually until:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>An award has been made to each eligible applicant who has submitted a complete application; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The funding allocation is exhausted.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Continuation and Service Requirement. Upon receipt of a Child Care Career and Professional Development Fund award, a grantee shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be eligible for continued funding as long as:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An academic grade-point average of 2.5 or higher is maintained in all course work pursued in satisfaction of award requirements;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The grantee is employed at least 10 hours per week as a provider in an approved child care facility;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The grantee successfully completes at least two courses during each 12-month period of the grantee’s award; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The approved course of study is pursued;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In relation to the number of college credits, or equivalent, completed or the degree earned due in part or in whole to receipt of a Fund award, commit to continuing employment at least 10 hours per week as a provider for a period of time which is the shortest of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>1 month for each college credit successfully completed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>2 years for a completed associate degree; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>4 years for a completed bachelor's degree;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the grantee’s academic grade-point average falls below 2.5, agree to a plan of action established by the Office and the college in order to continue participation in the Fund; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the grantee does not comply with the plan of action specified in <cite path="13A|14|09|.08|D.|(3)">§D(3) of this regulation</cite>, be ineligible to receive a future Fund award.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|14|09|.09">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Tiered Reimbursement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Application for Participation.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Office shall accept an application to participate in the tiered reimbursement program only from:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A registered family day care provider who is currently providing child care for at least one unrelated child; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An operator of a licensed child care center or letter of compliance facility.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An applicant for tiered program participation shall make application in a form and format approved by the Office.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Office may not consider an application for approval until the applicant has met all requirements set forth in §§B—E of this regulation as applicable.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Applicant Requirements—General. An applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be currently registered or licensed by the Office of Child Care, Division of Early Childhood Development;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Hold a family child care registration, child care center license, or letter of compliance that is not the subject of suspension or revocation action;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Possess the appropriate level of credential for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A family child care provider; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A minimum of 60 percent of lead staff, if the applicant is the operator of a child care center or a letter of compliance facility;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Certify that at least 15 minutes are spent daily on reading time with the children in care; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If applicable, certify that a policy is in place that bases child care staff salaries on training, experience, and staff evaluation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Applicants for Tiered Reimbursement, Level 2—Special Requirements. An applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Comply with the requirements in <cite path="13A|14|09|.09|A.|(2)">§A(2) of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Initiate a program of accreditation self-study through the Maryland State Department of Education or a nationally recognized child care accreditation organization approved by the Office of Child Care, Division of Early Childhood Development;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Be approved at Credential Level 2;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Certify that parents are involved in the program in at least two ways; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Certify that a nationally recognized rating scale approved by the Office of Child Care, Division of Early Childhood Development, that is appropriate to the setting and age of the children in care has been self-administered.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Applicants for Tiered Reimbursement, Level 3—Special Requirements. An applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Comply with requirements in <cite path="13A|14|09|.09|A.|(2)">§A(2) of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Complete a program of accreditation self-study through the Maryland State Department of Education or a nationally recognized child care accreditation organization approved by the Office of Child Care, Division of Early Childhood Development;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Be approved at Credential Level 3;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Certify that parents are involved in the program in at least four ways; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>As administered by an Office of Child Care, Division of Early Childhood Development, approved evaluator, achieve a rating of four on a nationally recognized rating scale that is appropriate to the setting and ages of the children in care.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Applicants for Tiered Reimbursement, Level 4—Special Requirements. An applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Comply with requirements in <cite path="13A|14|09|.09|A.|(2)">§A(2) of this regulation</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Achieve program accreditation through the Maryland State Department of Education or a nationally recognized child care accreditation organization approved by the Office of Child Care, Division of Early Childhood Development;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Be approved at Credential Level 4;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Certify that parents are involved in the program in at least six ways;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Except if the program received accreditation during the previous 12-month period, and as administered by an Office of Child Care, Division of Early Childhood Development, approved evaluator, achieve a rating of five on a nationally recognized rating scale that is appropriate to the setting and age of the children in care; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>If applicable, certify that a policy is in place that offers child care staff benefits based on training, experience, and staff evaluation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A family child care provider or the operator of a child care center or letter of compliance facility may reapply annually under <cite path="13A|14|09|.09|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Denial of Application for Participation.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Office may deny an application for participation in the tiered reimbursement program. Notice of the denial shall include the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Reason for the denial;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Regulatory basis for the denial; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Procedures for appealing the decision.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A family child care provider or the operator of a child care center or letter of compliance facility who is denied participation in the tiered reimbursement program by the Office may request an appeal of the decision to the Office's Training Review Committee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An applicant may appeal a denial of program participation by submitting to the Office a written appeal, on a form supplied by the Office, within 30 days of the date of application denial.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Office's Training Review Committee shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Reach a decision regarding the appeal within 30 days of receiving the appeal; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Notify the appellant in writing within 30 days after the appeal decision has been reached.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If a denial of an application for tiered reimbursement program participation is overturned on appeal to the Training Review Committee, the Office shall approve the application retroactively to the initial application date.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|14|09|.10">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Prohibitions and Penalties.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant, participant, or grantee may not knowingly make or cause to be made any false statement or report:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In an application or documentation furnished to the Office under the requirements of this chapter; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For the purpose of influencing the action of the Office on any matter related to an award, either before or after an award has been made.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Violation of <cite path="13A|14|09|.10|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> shall result in:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Forfeiture of any claim to a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Training voucher;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Bonus award; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Child Care Career and Professional Development Fund award; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Denial of initial or continued participation, as applicable, in the credential program.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If a participant uses a training voucher and, without good cause, fails to comply with the requirements of <cite path="|13A|14|09|.07|I.">Regulation .07I of this chapter</cite>, the participant shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Ineligible to receive further training vouchers; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Required to repay the amount of the training voucher to the Office.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If a participant receives an award through the Fund and, without good cause, fails to comply with the requirements of <cite path="|13A|14|09|.08|D.">Regulation .08D of this chapter</cite>, the participant shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Ineligible to receive a future award; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Required to repay the amount of the award to the Office in proportion to the remaining employment commitment set forth at <cite path="|13A|14|09|.08|D.|(2)">Regulation .08D(2) of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Family Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|5-551">5-551</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfl|5-573">5-573</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-07-01">Effective date: July 1, 2001 (28:12 Md. R. 1104)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-08-15">Chapter revised effective August 15, 2005 (32:16 Md. R. 1391)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2006-01-01" discontinuity="true">Transferred from <cite path="|07.04.09">COMAR 07.04.09</cite> to 13A.14.09 effective January 1, 2006</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-09-10" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective September 10, 2007 (34:18 Md. R. 1581)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-01-04"><cite path="|13A|14|09|.02|B.">Regulation .02B</cite> amended effective April 6, 2009 (36:7 Md. R. 526); January 4, 2010 (36:26 Md. R. 1998)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-01-04"><cite path="|13A|14|09|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite> amended effective January 4, 2010 (36:26 Md. R. 1998)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-04-06"><cite path="|13A|14|09|.08|B.">Regulation .08B</cite>, D amended effective April 6, 2009 (36:7 Md. R. 526)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-06-27"><cite path="|13A|14|09|.08">Regulation .08</cite> amended effective June 27, 2011 (38:13 Md. R. 756)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-01-04"><cite path="|13A|14|09|.09">Regulation .09</cite> adopted effective January 4, 2010 (36:26 Md. R. 1998)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-01-04"><cite path="|13A|14|09|.09">Regulation .09</cite> amended and recodified to be Regulation .10 effective January 4, 2010 (36:26 Md. R. 1998)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2015-03-30" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective March 30, 2015 (42:6 Md. R. 513)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
