<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>Definitions; General Provisions</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this subtitle, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Absentee ballot bag” means the bag designated by the State Administrator for the collection of absentee ballots at an early voting center or polling place.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Absent uniformed services voter” has the meaning stated in 42 U.S.C. §1973ff-6.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Authorized agent” means an individual who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is 18 years old or older;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is not a candidate on the voter's ballot; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Has been authorized in writing, signed by the voter under penalty of perjury, to act on the voter's behalf.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Common access card” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|3-202">Election Law Article, §3-202</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Electronic transmission” means transmission by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Email;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Internet; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Facsimile.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Federal post card application” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|3-202">Election Law Article, §3-202</cite>.1, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Federal Write-in Absentee Ballot” means a write-in absentee ballot for use in elections conducted under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel">Election Law Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, by an absent uniformed services voter or an overseas voter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Overseas voter” has the meaning stated in 42 U.S.C. §1973ff-6.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“Return envelope” means the envelope used by the voter to return a voted absentee ballot.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>“Uniformed services” has the meaning stated in 42 U.S.C. §1973ff-6.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Emergency Procedures.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Scope. This regulation applies if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A national or local emergency arises, such as a natural disaster or an armed conflict; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The emergency makes it impossible or unreasonable to comply fully with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>This subtitle; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Uniformed and Overseas Citizens Absentee Voting Act.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Emergency Procedures Authorized. The State Board may issue special procedures or requirements as appropriate to facilitate absentee voting by all those who might be affected by the emergency and are otherwise eligible to vote.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Limitations. A special procedure issued under this regulation may not waive any requirement expressly set by statute.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Designated Means of Electronic Communications for Certain Voters.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>As required by federal law, the State Board designates the agency's general email address, website, and facsimile number as the means of electronic communication for voters authorized to vote under the Uniformed and Overseas Citizens Absentee Voting Act.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The designated means of electronic communication shall be used to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Request a formal application;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Send or obtain the appropriate formal application; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Provide voting, balloting, and election information.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="33|11|01|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Ballot Drop Boxes.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Considerations for Ballot Drop Box Locations. A local board shall consider the following factors when determining the location of a ballot drop box:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Accessibility of the ballot drop box to historically disenfranchised communities, including voters with disabilities, cultural groups, ethnic groups, and minority groups;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Proximity of the ballot drop box to dense concentrations of voters;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Accessibility of the ballot drop box by public transportation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Ensuring equitable distribution of ballot drop boxes throughout the county; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Maximizing voter participation, including through the use of community centers and public gathering places.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Requirements for Ballot Drop Boxes Locations.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each ballot drop box location shall have security cameras to monitor the box at all times.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The images from each security camera shall be made available to the local board immediately or within a reasonable amount of time of a request from the State Administrator or local board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Approval Process for Ballot Drop Box Locations.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The State Administrator shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Prescribe a form for a local board to use to provide information about a proposed ballot drop box; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Provide each local board with the form at least 7 months before a primary election.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The form shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Include questions related to whether the proposed ballot drop box meets the considerations and requirements defined in §§A and B of this regulation; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If a proposed ballot drop box does not satisfy all of the considerations defined in <cite path="33|11|01|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, allow the local board to list other locations that were considered and why they were not proposed and describe the factors that mitigate the fact that the proposed ballot drop box location does not meet the considerations defined in <cite path="33|11|01|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>At least 6 months before a primary election, the local board shall submit to the State Administrator:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A form for each proposed ballot drop box; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Forms for all proposed ballot drop boxes at the same time.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The State Administrator shall approve a proposed location that meets the considerations defined in <cite path="33|11|01|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>If the State Administrator determines that a proposed ballot drop box location does not meet the considerations defined in <cite path="33|11|01|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Within 2 days of making the determination, the State Administrator shall provide the local board with a detailed explanation of why the proposed location does not meet the factors;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The State Administrator shall require that the local board reconsider the proposed location for one or more ballot drop boxes and propose one or more other locations that meet the considerations defined in <cite path="33|11|01|.04|A.">§A of this Regulation</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Within 7 days of receiving the State Administrator's detailed explanation, the local board shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Propose one or more locations that meet the considerations defined in <cite path="33|11|01|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Explain why a location that meets the considerations defined in <cite path="33|11|01|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite> cannot be proposed and propose the location of an additional ballot drop box.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The State Administrator may add additional ballot drop box locations if the State Administrator determines that the proposed ballot box location does not meet the considerations defined in <cite path="33|11|01|.04|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Electioneering Boundary.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The local board shall post signs delineating an area around each ballot box where a person may not electioneer. A local board is not required to delineate this area with a physical line on the ground.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="33|11|01|.04|D.|(3)">§D(3) of this regulation</cite>, the line shall be located as near as practicable to 50 feet from the ballot box after consideration of the placement of the ballot box and the effect of placement on public safety and the flow of pedestrian and vehicular traffic.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the ballot box is placed within the electioneering boundary of a polling place, the line for the ballot box shall be the electioneering boundary of the polling place.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The signs shall contain the words “No Electioneering Beyond this Point.”</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Electioneering Activities.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The following activities are not permitted within the electioneering boundary set forth in <cite path="33|11|01|.04|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Electioneering by individuals; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Observing or recording voter activities by a group of affiliated individuals.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An individual observing a ballot box or recording activities within the electioneering boundary set forth in <cite path="33|11|01|.04|D.">§D of this regulation</cite> is not electioneering if the person is not communicating with, questioning, or otherwise interfering with voters dropping off materials at a ballot box.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Other Activities.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in <cite path="33|11|01|.04|F.|(2)">§F(2) of this regulation</cite>, an individual may not visibly possess, visibly carry, or brandish a firearm within the electioneering boundary set forth in <cite path="33|11|01|.04|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A law enforcement officer or security guard who is on duty or traveling to or from duty may enter the electioneering boundary set forth in <cite path="33|11|01|.04|D.">§D of this regulation</cite> to drop off materials at a ballot box.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person may observe an election official remove materials from the ballot box if the person does not interfere with the process.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Absent Uniformed Services Voters and Overseas Voters in Special Elections.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The State Board shall provide notice to absent uniformed services voters and overseas voters concerning a special election as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In a vote by mail special election under COMAR §33.21.01—.08, by sending an absentee ballot to all absent uniformed service voters and overseas voters; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In a special election that is not conducted as a vote by mail election, by providing notice to a major news outlet and social media.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Absent uniform service voters and overseas voters may request an absentee ballot as provided in COMAR §<cite path="33.11.02.01">33.11.02.01</cite>—.04.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Absent uniform service voters and overseas voters may request delivery of an absentee ballot for a special election using any of the following methods to ensure timely return:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>By mail, including a postage paid return envelope;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>By email; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>By fax.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation app="2025-09-29" doc="Maryland Register, Volume 52, Issue 19" eff="2025-09-29" path="regulations|final|25-111-F" type="History" display="false"/>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Election Law Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|2-102">2-102</cite>(b)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|4">4</cite>), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|2-202">2-202</cite>(b), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|2-304">2-304</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|2-305">2-305</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gel|3-202">3-202</cite>.1, 9-303, 9-305, 9-306, 11-301, 11-302, and 11-30, and 11-304, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-04-17">Regulations .01, .02 adopted as an emergency provision effective February 1, 2000 (27:6 Md. R. 637); adopted permanently effective April 17, 2000 (27:7 Md. R. 709)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-12-13"><cite path="|33|11|01|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective May 31, 2010 (37:11 Md. R. 768); August 19, 2013 (40:16 Md. R. 1346); September 16, 2013 (40:18 Md. R. 1480); January 13, 2020 (47:1 Md. R. 19); December 13, 2021 (48:25 Md. R. 1081)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-05-31"><cite path="|33|11|01|.03">Regulation .03</cite> adopted effective May 31, 2010 (37:11 Md. R. 768)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-04-04"><cite path="|33|11|01|.04">Regulation .04</cite> adopted effective April 4, 2022 (49:7 Md. R. 469)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-04-15"><cite path="|33|11|01|.04|D.">Regulation .04D</cite>— F adopted effective April 15, 2024 (51:7 Md. R. 335)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-29"><cite path="|33|11|01|.05">Regulation .05</cite> adopted effective September 29, 2025 (52:19 Md. R. 957)</annotation>
    <annotation app="2025-09-29" doc="Maryland Register, Volume 52, Issue 19" eff="2025-09-29" path="regulations|final|25-111-F" type="History" display="false"/>
  </annotations>
</container>
