<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>Board of Boiler Rules</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In these regulations, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“ASME Code” means the “ASME Boiler and Pressure Vessel Code” of the American Society of Mechanical Engineers with revisions, amendments, and interpretations adopted by the Board of Boiler Rules.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Antique boiler” means a boiler that is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Fabricated and stamped:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>In accordance with the ASME Code or another nationally recognized boiler construction standard; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>More than 30 years before the date of the inspection;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Operated primarily for demonstration, exhibition, or instructional purposes and not for profit; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Constructed, inspected, and stamped in accordance with the ASME Code and registered with the National Board of Boiler and Pressure Vessels Inspectors to replace a historical boiler.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Approved” means approved by the Board of Boiler Rules.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Authorized Inspection Agency” means an entity that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is accredited in accordance with the National Board of Boiler and Pressure Vessel Inspectors NB-369, Qualifications and Duties for Authorized Inspection Agencies Performing Inservice Inspection Activities and Qualifications for Inspectors of Boilers and Pressure Vessels;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is accredited in accordance with the National Board of Boiler and Pressure Vessel Inspectors NB-371, Accreditation of Owner-User Inspection Organizations (OUIO); or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Meets the qualifications and definition of the National Board of Boiler and Pressure Vessel Inspectors NB-360, Criteria for Acceptance of Authorized Inspection Agencies for New Construction.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Authorized Insurer” means an authorized inspection agency licensed to insure boilers and pressure vessels in Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Board” means the Board of Boiler Rules.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Boiler external piping” means piping which:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Begins where the boiler proper terminates at the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>First circumferential joint for welded end connections;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Face of the first flange in bolted flanged connections; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>First threaded joint in threaded connections; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Extends up to and including the valve or valves required by Section I or Section IV of the ASME Code.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Certificate of Competency” means a certificate issued by the Chief Boiler Inspector indicating the suitability and fitness of an individual to inspect boilers and pressure vessels in Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“Certificate inspection” means an inspection the report of which is used by the Chief Boiler Inspector to determine whether to issue a certificate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>“Certificate of inspection for repair or alteration” means the certificate inspection performed after a repair or alteration to determine suitability of the object for return to service.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>“Commissioner” means the Commissioner of Labor and Industry.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>“Condemned boiler or pressure vessel” means a boiler or pressure vessel that has been inspected and declared unsafe or declared disqualified under legal requirements by an inspector who is authorized to take such action and who has applied a stamp or mark designating condemnation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>“Electric boiler” means a boiler in which the source of heat is electricity.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>“Existing boiler or pressure vessel installation” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A boiler constructed, installed, placed in operation, or contracted for before July 1, 1969, excluding antique boilers, historical boilers or model steam boilers; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A pressure vessel constructed, installed, placed in operation, or contracted for before January 1, 1974, excluding antique boilers, historical boilers or model steam boilers.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>“External inspection” means an inspection made when a boiler or pressure vessel is in operation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>“Follow up inspection” means an inspection performed after a boiler or pressure vessel has been determined to be nonconforming with applicable laws and regulations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>Heating Boiler.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Heating boiler” means:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A steam boiler that operates at pressures not exceeding 15 PSIG; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A hot water boiler operated at pressures not exceeding 160PSIG or temperatures not exceeding 250°F at or near the boiler outlet.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Heating boiler” includes a vessel used in connection with it as an expansion tank.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>“High-pressure, high-temperature water boiler” means a water boiler that operates at pressures exceeding 160 PSIG or temperatures exceeding 250°F at or near the boiler outlet.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>“Historical boiler” means a boiler that is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Riveted and/or welded construction;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Not under the jurisdiction of the Federal Railroad Administration;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Not used for profit; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>An antique boiler, steam tractor, traction engine, hobby steam boiler, or portable steam boiler that is preserved, restored, and maintained for demonstration, viewing, or educational purposes.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>“Hobby steam boiler” means a model steam boiler.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(21)</num>
        <text>“Hot water heating boiler” means a heating boiler furnishing hot water circulated to return to itself.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(22)</num>
        <text>“Hot water supply boiler” means a heating boiler furnishing hot water for use external to itself.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(23)</num>
        <text>“Individually fabricated” means constructed, inspected, and stamped in accordance with the ASME Code, or other standard accepted by the Chief Boiler Inspector.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(24)</num>
        <text>“Inspector” means the chief boiler inspector, a deputy boiler inspector, or a special inspector.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(25)</num>
        <text>"Installer” means an individual, firm, association, corporation, or other entity that installs or constructs boilers or pressure vessels.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(26)</num>
        <text>“Internal inspection” means an examination as complete as possible of the internal and external surfaces of a boiler or pressure vessel conducted while it is not in operation, and with all manhole plates, hand hole plates, and other coverings of inspection openings removed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(27)</num>
        <text>“Kitchen” means an area used for the preparation or processing of food for human consumption.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(28)</num>
        <text>“Kitchen equipment boiler” means a boiler located in a kitchen, and used for cooking or related purposes.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(29)</num>
        <text>“Lap-seam crack” means a crack in a lap-seam of a boiler or pressure vessel parallel to a longitudinal joint, either between or adjacent to rivet holes.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(30)</num>
        <text>“Maryland inspection report form” means the form submitted by an inspector and available on the Department’s website.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(31)</num>
        <text>“Miniature boiler” means a boiler when none of the following limitations are exceeded:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>16 inches inside diameter of shell;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>20 square feet heating surface, except for an electric boiler;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>5 cubic feet gross volume, exclusive of casing and insulation; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>100 psig maximum allowable working pressure.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(32)</num>
        <text>“Model steam boiler” means a boiler that is individually fabricated for non-commercial use and that is used primarily for demonstration, exhibition, or educational purposes, and not used for profit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(33)</num>
        <text>“Maximum allowable operating pressure” means the maximum pressure at which a boiler or pressure vessel is permitted to operate as determined by an inspector after an inspection and which is equal to or less than the maximum allowable working pressure.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(34)</num>
        <text>“Maximum allowable working pressure” means the maximum pressure at which a boiler or pressure vessel is designed to operate as determined by the manufacturer in accordance with the construction code.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(35)</num>
        <text>“Modular boiler system” means a series of boiler units specifically designed to be used singularly or together in sequential operation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(36)</num>
        <text>“National Board” means the National Board of Boiler and Pressure Vessel Inspectors.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(37)</num>
        <text>“NBIC” means the National Board Inspection Code.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(38)</num>
        <text>“New boiler or pressure vessel installation” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A boiler constructed, installed, placed in operation, or contracted for after July 1, 1969; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A pressure vessel constructed, installed, placed in operation, or contracted for after January 1, 1974.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(39)</num>
        <text>“Nonstandard boiler or pressure vessel” means a boiler or pressure vessel that does not bear the stamp of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Maryland;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Another jurisdiction which has adopted a standard of construction equivalent to that required by the Board of Boiler Rules;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The ASME; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The National Board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(40)</num>
        <text>"Owner" means a person, firm, or corporation owning or operating a boiler or pressure vessel within Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(41)</num>
        <text>“Owner-user inspection service” means an owner of a boiler or pressure vessel in Maryland, who maintains a regularly established inspection department whose inspection procedures meet the applicable requirements of the National Board of Boiler and Pressure Vessel Inspectors and are acceptable to the Board.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(42)</num>
        <text>“Person” means an installer, owner, or operator of a boiler or pressure vessel, a repair organization, or a company licensed to insure or inspect boilers and pressure vessels in the State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(43)</num>
        <text>“Portable boiler or pressure vessel” means a boiler or pressure vessel that is not historical but meets the following requirements:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is set on a frame, platform or trailer; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is designed to be moved to different locations for use.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(44)</num>
        <text>“Portable steam boiler” means a historical boiler that is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Not self-propelled;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Set on a frame, platform, or trailer; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Designed to be moved to different locations for use.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(45)</num>
        <text>“Power boiler” means a boiler in which steam or other vapor is generated at a pressure of more than 15 PSIG, and includes a high-pressure, high-temperature water boiler.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(46)</num>
        <text>“PSIG” means pounds per square inch gauge.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(47)</num>
        <text>“Standard boiler or pressure vessel” means a boiler or pressure vessel that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Bears the stamp of Maryland;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Bears the stamp of another jurisdiction which has adopted a standard of construction equivalent to that required by the Board of Boiler Rules;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Bears the stamps of both ASME and the National Board; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Is of equivalent safe construction acceptable to the Board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(48)</num>
        <text>“Used boiler or pressure vessel” means a boiler or pressure vessel which has been removed from its original setting and reinstalled at the same or different location.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(49)</num>
        <text>“Water heater” means a closed vessel with openings through which water may flow and includes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An apparatus by which heat is generated;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Controls necessary to prevent pressures greater than 160 psig and water temperatures greater than 210 degrees F; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Potable water that is withdrawn for external use.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(50)</num>
        <text>“Workday” means a day that is not a Saturday, a Sunday, or a State holiday.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|12|01|.01-1">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01-1</num>
    <heading>Incorporation by Reference.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The following documents are incorporated by reference to the extent that they are referenced in this chapter:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>ASME 2019 Boiler and Pressure Vessel Code, an International Code; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>National Board Inspection Code — NBIC, 2019 Edition.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The following documents are incorporated by reference in their entirety:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>ASME B31.1 — 2018 Edition, Power Piping (American Society of Mechanical Engineers);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>ASME B31.3 — 2018 Edition, Process Piping (American Society of Mechanical Engineers);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>ASME CSD-1 — 2018 Edition, Controls and Safety Devices for Automatically Fired Boilers (American Society of Mechanical Engineers) as amended in <cite path="09|12|01|.01-1|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>NFPA 85, Boiler and Combustion Systems Hazards Code — 2019 Edition (National Fire Protection Association).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Controls and Safety Devices for Automatically Fired Boilers (CSD-1) (American Society of Mechanical Engineers).</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The requirements of ASME CSD-1 in effect at the time a boiler is installed apply to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Power boilers regardless of fuel input;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Other boilers with a fuel input of greater than 2,500,000 Btu per hour and less than 12,500,000 Btu per hour; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Other boilers with a fuel input of 2,500,000 Btu per hour or less, except that Section CF of CSD-1 does not apply to these boilers.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The following are exempt from the requirements of ASME CSD-1:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Water heaters stamped either “H” or “HLW” and used as potable water heaters, if the water temperature is less than 210°F and the water pressure is less than 160 PSIG;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Miniature boilers, except as required in <cite path="|09|12|01|.37">Regulation .37 of this chapter</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Kitchen equipment boilers, except as required in <cite path="|09|12|01|.38">Regulation .38 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Historical boilers.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01-2</num>
    <heading>Compliance.</heading>
    <text>In the event of a conflict between a regulation in this chapter and a code section incorporated by reference, the provisions of this chapter control.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|12|01|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Access and Egress.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Clearance.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except for a water heater or a modular boiler system, a new or replacement boiler installed in a new or existing building shall be installed consistent with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Or exceeding, the manufacturer's recommendations for clearance; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The space requirements of <cite path="09|12|01|.02|A.|(6)">§A(6) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In the event manufacturer recommendations for clearance are not provided, a new or replacement boiler installed in a new or existing building, shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Have at least 3 feet between:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The top of the boiler and the ceiling, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Each side of the boiler and the adjacent wall or other structure; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Comply with the conditions of <cite path="09|12|01|.02|A.|(6)">§A(6) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The distance between or around a new or replacement boiler in a modular boiler system installed in a new or existing building shall be in accordance with the manufacturer's recommendations while ensuring:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>There are 3 feet between each side of the perimeter of the boiler system and the adjacent wall or structure; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The conditions in <cite path="09|12|01|.02|A.|(6)">§A(6) of this regulation</cite> are met.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The distance between or around a water heater installed in a new or existing building shall be in accordance with the manufacturer's recommendations while ensuring the conditions of <cite path="09|12|01|.02|A.|(6)">§A(6) of this regulation</cite> are met.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A boiler or pressure vessel having a manhole shall have 5 feet clearance from the manhole opening to any wall, ceiling, or piping that prevents entrance through the manhole.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A boiler or pressure vessel shall be located to provide adequate space for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Proper operation of the boiler or pressure vessel and its appurtenances;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Inspection of all surfaces, tubes, water-walls, economizers, piping, valves, and other equipment; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Required maintenance and the repair and replacement of tubes.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Ladders and Runways.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>When necessary to afford safe access, a steel runway or platform of standard construction shall be installed across the tops of adjacent boilers or pressure vessels, or at another convenient level.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When a valve or appurtenance requiring frequent manipulation cannot be reached or operated from the floor, a platform or other safe means of operation shall be provided.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A platform or runway shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be at least 24 inches wide;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Have standard handrails and toe boards; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Provide at least 7 feet, 6 inches overhead clearance.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A runway shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Have at least two means of exit, located remotely from each other; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Be connected to floor level by:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A permanent stairway, or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>An inclined ladder.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Each elevation in a boiler room shall have at least two exits, located remotely from each other, if the room:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Exceeds 500 square feet floor area; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Contains one or more boilers having a fuel-burning capacity of 1,000,000 Btu per hour, or equivalent electrical heat input.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Air and Ventilation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A boiler room shall have a permanent source of outside air to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Permit satisfactory combustion of fuel; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide proper ventilation of the boiler under normal operating conditions.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Louvered area.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The total requirements of all burners for all fired pressure vessels in a boiler room shall be used to determine the louver sizes, whether the pressure vessels are fired by coal, oil, or gas.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The minimum net free louvered area shall be at least 1 square foot.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The minimum dimension of air openings may not be less than 3 inches.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Ducts, when used, shall be of the same cross-sectional area as the free area of the openings to which they connect.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The following configurations shall be used:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Two permanent openings:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>One opening shall start within 12 inches of the ceiling, and one opening shall start within 12 inches of the floor;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The openings shall connect directly, or by ducts, with the outdoors or with crawl or attic spaces that freely connect with the outdoors;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Where directly connecting with the outdoors or where connecting to the outdoors through vertical ducts, each opening shall have a minimum free area of 1 square inch per 4,000 Btu per hour of total input rating, or total relieving capacity, of all fired pressure vessels, whichever is greater; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Where connecting to the outdoors through horizontal ducts, each opening shall have a minimum free area of 1 square inch per 2,000 Btu per hour of total input rating, or total relieving capacity, of all fired pressure vessels, whichever is greater; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>One permanent opening:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The opening shall start within 12 inches of the ceiling;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The opening shall directly connect with the outdoors, or shall connect through a vertical or horizontal duct to the outdoors or with crawl or attic spaces that freely connect to the outdoors; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The opening shall have a free open area of 1 square inch per 3,000 Btu per hour of total input rating, or total relieving capacity, of all fired pressure vessels, whichever is greater.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The following table shall be used to determine the net louvered area in square feet:</text>
        <text>
          <table class="layout-table">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th>Input Btu per Hour</th>
                <th>Required Air CFM</th>
                <th>Vertical Ducts Minimum Net Louvered Area Sq. Ft. per Opening</th>
                <th>Horizontal Ducts Minimum Net Louvered Area Sq. Ft. per Opening</th>
                <th>Single Opening</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td>100,000</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">50</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">0.50</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">0.50</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">1.00</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>200,000</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">100</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">0.50</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">0.69</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">1.00</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>300,000</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">150</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">0.50</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">1.04</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">1.00</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>400,000</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">200</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">0.69</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">1.39</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">1.00</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>500,000</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">250</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">0.87</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">1.74</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">1.16</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>750,000</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">375</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">1.30</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">2.60</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">1.74</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>1,000,000</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">500</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">1.74</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">3.47</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">2.31</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>1,250,000</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">625</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">2.17</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">4.34</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">2.89</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>1,500,000</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">750</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">2.60</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">5.21</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">3.47</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>1,750,000</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">875</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">3.04</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">6.08</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">4.05</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>2,000,000</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">1000</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">3.47</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">6.94</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">4.63</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>2,500,000</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">1250</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">4.34</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">8.68</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">5.79</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>3,000,000</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">1500</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">5.21</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">10.42</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">6.94</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>3,500,000</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">1750</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">6.08</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">12.15</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">8.10</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>4,000,000</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">2000</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">6.94</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">13.89</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">9.26</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>4,500,000</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">2250</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">7.81</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">15.63</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">10.42</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>5,000,000</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">2500</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">8.68</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">17.36</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">11.57</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>6,000,000</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">3000</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">10.42</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">20.83</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">13.89</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>7,000,000</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">3500</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">12.15</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">24.31</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">16.20</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>8,000,000</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">4000</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">13.89</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">27.78</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">18.52</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>9,000,000</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">4500</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">15.63</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">31.25</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">20.83</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>10,000,000</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">5000</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">17.36</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">34.72</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">23.15</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>11,000,000</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">5500</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">19.10</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">38.19</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">25.46</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>12,000,000</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">6000</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">20.83</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">41.67</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">27.78</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>12,500,000</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">6250</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">21.70</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">43.40</td>
                <td data-text-align="center">28.94</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Mechanical Combustion and Ventilation.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Mechanical ventilation may be used to supply combustion air or ventilation air, or both, to a boiler room.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When mechanical ventilation is used:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The firing device shall be interlocked with the fan so that the firing device cannot operate without proven airflow;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The velocity of the air passing through the louvers cannot exceed 500 feet per minute; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The total air delivered shall be equal to or exceed 0.5 CFM per 1,000 Btu per hour of total input rating or total required relieving capacity, whichever is greater.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Water Heater Combustion Air Ventilation Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Hot water heaters in excess of 200,000 Btu per hour up to but not including 1,000,000 Btu per hour, that are located in their own equipment room, shall have at least:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>1 permanent source of outside air; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>1 square foot of total net free louvered air space.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Hot water heaters of 1,000,000 Btu per hour or greater shall follow manufacturer's requirements.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Hot water heaters with inputs and required relieving capacities less than 200,000 Btu per hour are not covered by this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Equipment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Automatic Low Water Fuel Cutoff or Water Feeding Device.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An automatically fired steam or vapor system boiler shall have a low water fuel cutoff that automatically cuts off the fuel supply when the water surface falls to the lowest safe level. The following apply:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A water feeding device shall be:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Constructed so that the water inlet valve cannot feed water into the boiler through the float chamber, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Located to supply the necessary feedwater;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The lowest safe water line shall be not lower than the lowest visible part of the water glass.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A fuel or feedwater control device may be attached:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Directly to a boiler; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>To the tapped openings provided to attach a water glass directly to a boiler, provided that for low-pressure boilers:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Connections from the boiler are made with nonferrous tees or Y's at least 1/2 inch pipe size between the boiler and the water glass, so that the water glass is attached directly and as close as possible to the boiler,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Straightaway tapping of the Y or tee takes the water glass fittings, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The side outlet of the Y or tee takes the fuel cutoff or water feeding device.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The ends of all nipples shall be reamed to full-size diameter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A design using a float and float bowl shall have a vertical straightway valve drain pipe located at the lowest point in the water-equalizing pipe connections by which the bowl and equalizing pipe can be flushed and the device tested.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Blowoff Equipment.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Blowdown from a boiler that enters a sanitary sewer system, or blowdown that is a hazard to life or property, shall pass through blowoff equipment to ensure that the maximum:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Temperature of water leaving the equipment is 150°F; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Pressure of blowdown leaving the equipment is 5 PSIG.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Blowoff equipment shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Use piping and fittings between the boiler and the blowoff tank that comply with the ASME Code, Section I, paragraph PG-59;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Be fabricated of material that complies with the ASME Code, Section II;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Be fitted with openings that facilitate cleaning and inspection; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Conform to the rules for boiler blowoff equipment established by the National Board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Discharge of safety valves, blowoff pipes, and other outlets shall be located to prevent injury to personnel.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Boiler-Door Latches.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Firing Doors.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The firing doors on a watertube boiler shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Open inward;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Be equipped with effective fastening devices; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Be constructed to prevent the doors from being blown open by pressure on the furnace side.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Except for coal openings on a downdraft or similar furnace:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Door fastenings shall be positive self-locking; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Friction contacts, latches, or bolts actuated by springs may not be used.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An explosion door, if used and located in a setting wall within 7 feet of a firing floor or operating platform, shall have substantial deflectors to divert a blast.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Except for an explosion door, a door not used during boiler firing may be equipped with bolts or fastenings.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Pressure-Reducing Valve.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>When a pressure-reducing valve is used:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If the piping or equipment on the low-pressure side of the reducing valve does not meet the requirements for full initial pressure, at least one relief or safety valve shall be installed on the low-pressure side of the reducing valve;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The relief or safety valves shall adjoin or be as close as possible to the reducing valve;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>When a relief or safety valve is vented to the atmosphere, proper protection shall be provided to prevent escaping fluid from causing injury or damage;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The combined discharge capacity of relief or safety valves shall be such that the pressure rating of the lowest pressure piping or equipment cannot be exceeded if the reducing valve sticks open.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Bypass Around Reducing Valves.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A hand-controlled bypass around a reducing valve may be used.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If a bypass is used around a reducing valve, the safety valve on the low-pressure side shall have sufficient relief capacity to prevent overpressuring the low-pressure side.</text>
        </para>
        <aftertext>(3 ) A pressure gage shall be installed on the low-pressure side of a reducing valve.</aftertext>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A boiler or pressure vessel shall have masonry or structural supports of sufficient strength and rigidity to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Safely support the boiler or pressure vessel and its contents; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Prevent excessive vibration of the boiler, pressure vessel, or connecting piping.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Factor of Safety--Increase for Existing Installation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An inspector may increase the factor of safety of an existing installation if the condition of the boiler or pressure vessel warrants the increase.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Appeal Procedure.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An owner may appeal an increase in a factor of safety to the Board.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Upon appeal, the Board may request that the chief boiler inspector and a deputy boiler inspector or special inspector conduct a joint inspection.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Each inspector shall submit a report to the Board.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Based on the reports submitted, the Board shall make a final determination of the appropriate factor of safety.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Fired Jacketed Steam Kettle.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A fired jacketed steam kettle may be installed if it is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Constructed and stamped in accordance with the ASME Code, Section I, IV, or VIII, Division 1; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Registered with the National Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A gas-fired jacketed steam kettle may be constructed in accordance with the ASME Code, Section VIII, Division 1, provided that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Welded joints having contact with products of combustion are Type No. 1 of Table UW-12;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The minimum thickness of a part subject to pressure is, for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Carbon steel, 1/4 inch, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Stainless steel or nonferrous pressure parts, as specified in the ASME Code, Section VIII, Division 1, Subsection C;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A part having contact with products of combustion is, for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Carbon steel, pressure vessel quality, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Austenitic stainless steel, either extra-low carbon or stabilized grade;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Structural grade carbon steel is not used for any pressure part;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The operating pressure of the jacket does not exceed 50 PSI;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A vessel constructed in accordance with this regulation:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Is inspected by an authorized inspector, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is not marked with the UM symbol;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Steam or water is not withdrawn from the jacket for use external to the vessel;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The capacity of the safety valve in pounds of steam per hour is at least equal to the BTU rating of the burner divided by 1,000; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>The jacket has:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A pressure gage,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A water gage glass,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A separate connection, fitted with a check valve and stop valve, for adding water to the jacket while the vessel is not under pressure,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>An automatic gas valve controlled by pressure or temperature to maintain the steam pressure in the jacket below the safety valve setting,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>A low water cutoff to stop the flow of fuel to the burner if the water in the jacket drops below the lowest permissible water level as established by the manufacturer, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>A safety pilot control to stop the flow of fuel to both the main burner and the pilot burner in case of pilot flame failure.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Gas-Fired Installations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A burner in a gas-fired installation shall be tested and certified by the American Gas Association.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A gas-fired boiler shall have a vent or flue that terminates at an acceptable location outside the building.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The size of the vent or flue shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>That recommended by the boiler manufacturer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>At least 4 inches in diameter or equivalent area; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the horizontal run exceeds 10 feet, at least 6 inches in diameter or equivalent area.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Hazardous Condition.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A special inspector who finds a hazardous condition affecting the safety of a boiler or pressure vessel shall notify the chief boiler inspector in accordance with <cite path="|09|12|01|.28">Regulation .28 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If a special inspector determines that a boiler or pressure vessel is unsafe for operation:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The inspector shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Notify the owner promptly;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Specify the repair or corrective measure required to achieve compliance with regulations; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>If the owner does not agree to take the required action promptly, notify the chief boiler inspector immediately;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Until the required repair or corrective measure is completed:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Use of the boiler or pressure vessel is prohibited; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The chief boiler inspector shall suspend the inspection certificate, if any.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If, upon inspection, the chief boiler inspector or a deputy boiler inspector declares a boiler or pressure vessel unsafe:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The boiler or pressure vessel shall be condemned and stamped in accordance with <cite path="|09|12|01|.30">Regulation .30 of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Use or operation of the condemned boiler or pressure vessel shall subject the owner to the penalties provided by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|12-915">Public Safety Article, §12-915, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Hearings.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A hearing shall be held in accordance with the requirements of the Administrative Procedure Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">Title 10, Subtitle 2, State Government Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner delegates the authority to issue a proposed decision on a citation or penalty to the Office of Administrative Hearings.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A proposed decision of the Office of Administrative Hearings becomes a final order of the Commissioner 20 days after the date it is issued, unless:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The person found to have violated <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps">Public Safety Article, Title 12, Subtitle 9, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or a regulation or order issued to carry out this law, requests a review; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Commissioner orders review.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Review of Proceedings Before the Commissioner.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A request for review by a person found to have violated <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps">Public Safety Article, Title 12, Subtitle 9, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or a regulation or order issued to carry out this law, shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Be in writing;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Contain a concise statement identifying each portion of the determination for which a review is requested;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Be filed with the Commissioner within 20 days after the date the determination is issued; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Be mailed by the requesting party to all other parties to the proceeding.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Affected parties have the opportunity to present argument to the Commissioner based on the record before the Office of Administrative Hearings.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Order of the Commissioner.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>After review of the proceedings, with or without a hearing, the Commissioner shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Issue an order based on findings of fact; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Mail copies of the order to all affected parties.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Commissioner’s order shall affirm, modify, or vacate the citation or proposed penalty, or direct other appropriate relief.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Hearings Before the Board of Boiler Rules.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A hearing before the Board of Boiler Rules shall be held before at least four members of the Board.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A request for postponement of a hearing may not be considered unless the presiding officer receives a request:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In writing;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>At least 5 days before the scheduled hearing date; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Setting forth the reasons for the request.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Presiding Officer.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>At a hearing before the Board, the chairman of the Board or, in the chairman’s absence, the chairman’s designee, shall be the presiding officer.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A presiding officer may:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Administer oaths and affirmations;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Rule on offers of proof and procedural matters;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Regulate the course of the hearing, including the conduct of parties and counsel;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Receive relevant evidence;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Examine a witness; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Take other action authorized by statute or regulation.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A hearing shall be recorded verbatim.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Hearing Procedure.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The presiding officer shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Call the title of the case;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Briefly explain the purpose and nature of the hearing;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Recite any charges, complaints, or other matters involved;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Administer the oath to all persons who are to testify; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Receive any stipulation entered into by the parties.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Counsel or a party may address any preliminary matter, exception, or motion.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The following exhibits shall be introduced:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A copy of the petition, complaint, or other matter involved in the hearing; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A copy of the notice of hearing.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>In a hearing on an application for variance, the applicant shall proceed first and present evidence to demonstrate either that the subject regulation is unreasonable or that it imposes an undue burden on the applicant, and that equivalent safety can be maintained. The presenter of evidence shall then present information obtained as a result of the agency’s investigation of the application.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Subject to statutes and rules governing the practice of law, a party or counsel representing a party may:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Call witnesses;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Offer evidence, including rebuttal evidence;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Cross-examine a witness called by another party or the agency; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Present argument and summation.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Any member of the Board may examine a witness.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>The Board may permit or require a party to file a written memorandum, which may include proposed findings of fact and conclusions of law.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Board shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Issue a written determination which includes findings of fact and conclusions of law, and an order disposing of the proceedings; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Promptly serve a copy of the determination on each party or the party's counsel of record.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A party aggrieved by a final order issued pursuant to this regulation may obtain judicial review by filing a written petition with the appropriate circuit court within 30 days of issuance of the final order.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Heating Boiler — Existing Installation: Maximum Allowable Working Pressure</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The maximum allowable working pressure on a standard boiler may not exceed the pressure stamped or cast by the manufacturer on:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The boiler; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A plate secured to the boiler.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The maximum allowable working pressure on:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The shell of a nonstandard riveted heating boiler shall be determined in accordance with <cite path="|09|12|01|.22">Regulation .22 of this chapter</cite>, except that the maximum allowable working pressure on a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Steam heating boiler may not exceed 15 PSIG; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Hot water boiler may not exceed:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>160 PSIG, or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>250°F.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A nonstandard steel or wrought iron heating boiler of welded construction:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>May not exceed 15 PSIG for steam; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For service other than steam, shall be calculated in accordance with the ASME Code, Section IV.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A nonstandard boiler composed principally of cast iron, or having a cast iron shell or heads and steel or wrought iron tubes, may not exceed:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>15 PSIG for steam service; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>30 PSIG for hot water service.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Heating Boiler — Existing Installation: Safety Valve.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A steam boiler shall have at least one safety valve which is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Officially rated;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Of the spring pop type; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Adjusted and sealed to discharge at a pressure not greater than 15 PSI.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A seal shall be attached in a manner to prevent the valve from being disassembled without breaking the seal.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A safety valve shall be arranged so that it cannot be reset to relieve at a pressure higher than the maximum allowable working pressure of the boiler.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Body Drain.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The manufacturer shall provide a body drain connection below seat level.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A body drain may not be plugged during or after field installation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If a valve exceeds 2 inch pipe size, the drain hole shall be tapped at least 3/8 inch pipe size.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A valve less than 2 inches pipe size shall have a drain hole at least 1/4 inch in diameter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Valve Size.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A safety valve for a steam boiler shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>At least 3/4 inches, unless the boiler and radiating surfaces are a self-contained unit; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Not larger than 4 1/2 inches.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An inlet opening shall have an inside diameter at least equal to the seat diameter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The minimum relief capacity of a valve or valves is governed by the capacity marking on the boiler.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Valve Capacity.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Subject to the requirements of §H, below, the minimum valve capacity in pounds per hour is the greater of the capacity determined:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>By dividing the maximum BTU output at the boiler nozzle, obtained by firing any fuel for which the unit is installed, by 1,000; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>In accordance with the following table:</text>
          <text>
            <table>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th colspan="3">Minimum Pounds of Steam Per Hour <br/>Per Square Foot of Heating Surface*</th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <th>Boiler Heating Surface</th>
                  <th>Firetube Boilers</th>
                  <th>Watertube Boilers</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td>Hand-fired</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">5</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">6</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Stoker-fired</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">7</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">8</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Oil, gas, or pulverized fuel-fired</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">8</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">10</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>
                    <em>Waterwall Heating Surface</em>
                  </td>
                  <td/>
                  <td/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Hand-fired</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">8</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">8</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Stoker-fired</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">10</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">12</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Oil, gas, or pulverized fuel-fired</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">14</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">16</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </text>
          <text><sup>*</sup>1. When a boiler is fired only by a gas having a heat value of 200 BTU or less per cubic foot, the minimum safety valve or safety reliefvalve relief capacity may be determined by the value given forhand-fired boilers, above.</text>
          <text><sup>*</sup>2. Heating surface shall be determined in accordance with the ASME Code, Section IV, Paragraph HG-403.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The minimum safety valve or safety relief valve relief capacity for an electric boiler shall be 3-1/2 pounds per hour per kilowatt input.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>The safety valve capacity for a steam boiler shall be sufficient to ensure that when fuel burning equipment is operated at maximum capacity, the pressure cannot exceed the maximum allowable working pressure by more than 5 PSI.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>When operating conditions change, or additional boiler heating surface is installed:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Valve capacity shall be increased, if necessary, to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Meet the new conditions, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Comply with the requirements of this regulation;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provided there is no intervening valve, any additional valves required because of changed conditions may be installed on the outlet piping.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>If there is any doubt as to the capacity of a safety valve, an accumulation test shall be conducted in accordance with the ASME Code, Section VI, Recommended Rules for the Care and Operation of Heating Boilers.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>A valve of any type may not be placed:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Between a safety valve and a boiler; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>On a discharge pipe between a safety valve and the atmosphere.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Discharge Pipe.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A discharge pipe shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>At least full-size; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Fitted with an open drain to prevent water from lodging in the upper part of a safety valve or in the discharge pipe.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a safety valve discharge pipe has an elbow, the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Elbow shall be located near the safety valve outlet; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Discharge pipe shall be securely anchored and supported.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>Safety valve discharges shall be located or piped so as not to endanger workers.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Heating Boiler — Existing Installation: Miscellaneous.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Feedwater Connection.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Feedwater, make-up water, or water treatment:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Shall be introduced into a boiler through:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The return piping system, or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>An independent feedwater connection that does not discharge against a part of the boiler exposed to direct radiant heat from the fire;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>May not be introduced through an opening or connection provided for:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Inspection or cleaning,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Safety valve,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Safety relief valve,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Surface blowoff,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Water column,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Water gage glass,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Pressure gage, or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Temperature gage.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Feedwater pipe shall have a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Check valve near the boiler; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Stop valve or cock between the check valve and the boiler or return pipe system.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Pressure or Altitude Gage.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A hot water boiler shall have a pressure or altitude gage connected to the boiler or its flow connection so that it cannot be shut off from the boiler except by a cock with a tee or lever handle:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Placed on the pipe near the gage; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>With the handle parallel to the pipe in which it is located, when the cock is open.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The scale on the dial of a pressure or altitude gage shall be graduated to indicate pressures from 1-1/2 to 3 times the maximum allowable working pressure.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Piping or tubing for a pressure or altitude gage connection smaller than 1 inch pipe size shall be of nonferrous metal.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Steam Gage.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A steam boiler shall have a steam gage connected to its steam space, water column, or steam connection by a siphon or equivalent device on the exterior of the boiler.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A siphon shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Of sufficient capacity to keep the gage tube filled with water; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Arranged so that the gage can be shut off from the boiler only by a cock with a tee or lever handle:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Placed in the pipe near the gage, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>With the handle parallel to the pipe in which it is located, when the cock is open.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Scale.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The scale on the dial of a steam gage shall be graduated to at least 30 PSIG.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The gage shall have effective stops for the indicating pointer at the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Zero point; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Maximum pressure point.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The travel of the pointer from zero to 30 PSIG shall be at least 3 inches.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Stop Valve and Check Valve.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A boiler which can be closed off from the heating system by closing a steam stop valve shall have a check valve in the condensate return line between the boiler and the system.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Any part of a heating system that can be closed off from the remainder of the system by closing a steam stop valve shall have a check valve in the condensate return pipe from that part of the system.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A hot water boiler shall have a thermometer located and connected so that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person observing the water pressure or altitude gage can read the thermometer easily; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The thermometer at all times indicates the temperature, in degrees Fahrenheit, of the water in the boiler at or near the outlet.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Water Gage Glass.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A steam boiler shall have at least one water gage glass attached to the water column or boiler by valved fittings.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The lower fitting shall have a straightway drain valve with an opening at least 1/4 inch diameter to facilitate cleaning.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Gage glass replacement shall be possible while the boiler is under pressure.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Transparent material other than glass may be used for a water gage if the material is suitable for the pressure, temperature, and corrosive conditions encountered in service.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>When practicable, a boiler equipped with a condensate return pump shall have a water level control that automatically maintains the water level in the boiler within the range of the gage glass.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Repairs and replacements of fittings or appliances shall comply with the ASME Code for new construction, Section IV.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>The ASME Code, Section VI, Recommended Rules for the Care and Operation of Heating Boilers is recommended as a guide for proper and safe operating practices.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>It is recommended that a return water connection to a low-pressure steam heating boiler supplying a gravity return heating system be arranged to form a return pipe loop connection, so that water cannot be forced out of the boiler below the safe water level, as shown in Section IV, Figure HG-703.1 of the ASME Heating Boiler Code.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|12|01|.13">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Hot Water Boiler—Existing Installation: Safety Relief Valve.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Number of Valves.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A hot water heating boiler shall have at least one safety relief valve which is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Officially rated; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Set to relieve at or below the maximum allowable working pressure of the boiler.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A hot water supply boiler shall have at least one safety relief valve which is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Officially rated;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Automatically reseating; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Set to relieve at or below the maximum allowable working pressure of the boiler.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A safety relief valve with an officially rated capacity shall have pop action when tested by steam.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>When more than one safety relief valve is used on a hot water heating or hot water supply boiler, each additional valve shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Officially rated; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Set at a maximum of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>6 PSI above the maximum allowable working pressure of the boiler, for a boiler having a maximum allowable working pressure of 60 PSI or less, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>10 percent above the maximum allowable working pressure, for a boiler having a maximum allowable working pressure exceeding 60 PSI.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A safety relief valve shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Spring loaded; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Arranged so that it cannot be reset at a pressure higher than the maximum permitted by this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A material that can fail because of deterioration or vulcanization when subject to saturated steam temperature corresponding to capacity test pressure may not be used for any part.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Size.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as otherwise provided by this regulation, the standard pipe size of a safety relief valve may not be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Smaller than 3/4 inch; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Larger than 4-1/2 inches.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A boiler having a heat input of 15,000 BTU per hour or less may have a rated safety relief valve of 1/2 inch standard pipe size.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An inlet opening shall have an inside diameter approximately equal to, or greater than, the seat diameter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The minimum opening through any part of a valve shall be at least 1/2 inch in diameter or the equivalent area.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Subject to the requirements of <cite path="09|12|01|.13|I.">§I of this regulation</cite>, the minimum steam relief capacity of a pressure relief device on a boiler, in pounds per hour, shall be the greater of the capacity determined:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>By dividing by 1,000 the maximum BTU output at the boiler nozzle, obtained by firing any fuel for which the unit is installed; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In accordance with Table <cite path="09.12.01.11|G.">09.12.01.11G</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>When operating conditions change or additional boiler heating surface is installed:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Valve capacity shall be increased, if necessary, to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Meet the new conditions, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Comply with this regulation; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If there is no intervening valve, any additional valves required because of changed conditions may be installed on the outlet piping.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>The safety relief valve capacity for a boiler shall be sufficient to ensure that, with fuel burning equipment operated at maximum capacity, pressure cannot exceed:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>6 PSI above the maximum allowable working pressure of the boiler, for a boiler having a maximum allowable working pressure of 60 PSI or less; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>10 percent above the maximum allowable working pressure, for a boiler having a maximum allowable working pressure greater than 60 PSI.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>If there is any doubt as to the capacity of a safety relief valve, an accumulation test shall be conducted in accordance with the ASME Code, Section VI, Recommended Rules for the Care and Operation of Heating Boilers.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>A valve of any type may not be placed:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Between a safety relief valve and a boiler; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>On a discharge pipe between a safety relief valve and the atmosphere.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Discharge Pipe.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A discharge pipe shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>At least full-size; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Fitted with an open drain to prevent water from lodging in the upper part of a safety relief valve or in the discharge pipe.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a safety relief valve discharge pipe has an elbow, the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Elbow shall be located near the safety relief valve outlet; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Discharge pipe shall be securely anchored and supported.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>Safety relief valve discharges shall be located or piped so as not to endanger workers.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|12|01|.14">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Inspection Intervals.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Boilers and pressure vessels subject to this regulation do not include power boilers, or high pressure or high temperature water boilers.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="09|12|01|.14|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, boilers and pressure vessels shall receive a certificate inspection biennially.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A boiler or pressure vessel that is part of an amusement attraction, as defined by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gbr|3-101">Business Regulation Article, §3-101(b), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, shall receive a certificate inspection annually.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A historical boiler shall be inspected at intervals specified in <cite path="|09|12|01|.34">Regulation .34 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|12|01|.14-1">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14-1</num>
    <heading>Inspection.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Internal Inspection.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Unless an internal inspection is required by law or by an inspector at the inspector's discretion, a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Hot water boiler requires only an external inspection for certificate purposes; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Pressure vessel requires only an external inspection for certificate purposes.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>At least 7 days before an internal inspection, the inspector shall notify the owner of the inspection date.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The owner of a boiler shall prepare the boiler for internal inspection and hydrostatic test, if necessary, by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Drawing off water and washing the boiler thoroughly;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Removing manhole and handhole plates, washout plugs, and inspection plugs in water column connections;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Cooling and thoroughly cleaning furnace and combustion chambers;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Removing all grates of internally fired boilers;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Removing the pressure gage for testing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Disconnecting the pipe or valve at the most convenient point to prevent leakage of steam or hot water into the boiler;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Performing the following procedures before opening a manhole or handhole cover and entering any part of a steam-generating unit connected to a common header with other boilers:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Close, tag, and preferably padlock:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Non return and steam stop valves; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Feed and check valves;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Open drain valves or cocks between:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Non return and steam stop valves; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Feed and check valves; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>After draining the boiler:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Close and padlock the blowoff valves;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Where practicable, disconnect blowoff lines at a point between pressure parts and valves; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Open all drains and vent lines.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The owner of a pressure vessel shall prepare the pressure vessel for inspection to the extent required by the inspector, using the applicable procedures set out in <cite path="09|12|01|.14-1|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Removal of Covering During Inspection.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At each annual inspection, brickwork shall be removed, as required by the inspector, to determine the condition of the boiler, headers, furnace, supports, or other parts.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Unless the information can be obtained by other means, if boiler or pressure vessel jacketing conceals the longitudinal seams of a shell, drum, or dome, sufficient jacketing, setting wall, or other casing or housing shall be removed to permit:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Reasonable inspection of the seams; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Determination of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The size and pitch of the rivets; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Other data necessary to ascertain the safety of the boiler or pressure vessel.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>When an external inspection discloses evidence of a leak or crack:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Sufficient covering shall be removed from the boiler or pressure vessel to permit the inspector to make a safety determination; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If the covering cannot be removed during the inspection, the inspector may order use of the boiler or pressure vessel discontinued until:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The covering can be removed; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Proper inspection can be made.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Hydrostatic Pressure Test.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A hydrostatic pressure test of a boiler or pressure vessel may not exceed:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>1-1/2 times the maximum allowable working pressure; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The required test pressure by more than 2 percent.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>During a hydrostatic test:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Each safety valve shall be removed; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Each valve disk shall be held to its seat by a testing clamp, and not by tightening the compression screw on the spring.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Water used to apply a hydrostatic test shall have a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Recommended minimum temperature of 70°F; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Maximum temperature of 140°F.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>When a hydrostatic test is applied to an existing installation to determine:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Tightness, test pressure shall equal the release pressure of the safety valve having the lowest release setting; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Safety, test pressure shall equal 1-1/2 times the maximum allowable working pressure.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If a boiler or pressure vessel is not properly prepared for internal inspection, or if the owner fails to comply with the requirements for a hydrostatic test as set out in this regulation:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The inspector may refuse to conduct the inspection or test; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the inspector refuses, the chief boiler inspector shall withhold the inspection certificate until the owner complies with the requirements.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>An inspector is authorized to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Conduct inspections in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|12-909">Public Safety Article, §12-909, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Review and verify records required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps">Public Safety Article, Title 12, Subtitle 9, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and by Codes referenced in <cite path="|09|12|01|.01-1">Regulation .01-1 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Inspection Certificate.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Revocation or Suspension.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Emergency Action.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The chief boiler inspector or an authorized representative may order an inspection certificate suspended summarily if, in his opinion, public safety imperatively requires emergency action.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If an inspection certificate is summarily suspended, the chief boiler inspector shall promptly give the owner of the boiler or pressure vessel for which the inspection certificate was issued:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Written notice of the suspension, including the reason and facts that warrant the suspension; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>An opportunity to be heard.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>General.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The chief boiler inspector shall suspend an inspection certificate if:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>An inspector determines that the condition of the boiler or pressure vessel makes continued operation unsafe;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A special inspector notifies the chief boiler inspector that an owner refuses to make promptly the repairs necessary to bring an unsafe boiler or pressure vessel into compliance with these regulations;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The owner refuses to permit inspection of a boiler or pressure vessel; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>The owner refuses to pay a fee required by the Boiler and Pressure Vessel Safety Act.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The chief boiler inspector or an authorized representative may suspend or revoke an inspection certificate if the boiler or pressure vessel for which it was issued:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Cannot be operated consistent with public safety; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Does not comply with applicable law or regulations.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Except as otherwise provided by this regulation, before suspending or revoking an inspection certificate, the chief boiler inspector shall give the owner of the boiler or pressure vessel:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Written notice of the suspension or revocation which states the reasons and facts warranting the suspension or revocation; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>An opportunity to be heard.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An inspection certificate becomes invalid:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>On its expiration date; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When the boiler or pressure vessel for which it was issued ceases to be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Insured by an authorized insurer; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Owned by an owner-user inspection service.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|12|01|.16">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16</num>
    <heading>Inspector.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An inspector:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>May not engage in the sale of boilers, pressure vessels, or any related item; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shall be employed regularly in inspection work.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>To be eligible to take the examination for a Certificate of Competency as an inspector, an applicant shall have:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A degree in mechanical engineering plus 1 year of experience in the design, construction, operation, or inspection of high pressure vessels;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A degree in another branch of engineering, plus 2 years of experience in the design, construction, operation, or inspection of high pressure boilers and pressure vessels; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The equivalent of a high school education plus 3 years of experience:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In high pressure boiler and pressure vessel construction or repair;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>As an operating engineer in charge of a high pressure boiler operation; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>As an inspector of high pressure boilers and pressure vessels.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Application Procedure for Certificate of Competency.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An applicant shall apply to take an examination:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>On the form furnished by the Chief Boiler Inspector; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>At least 30 days before the examination date.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The applicant shall provide:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A description of the applicant's education;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A list of the applicant's past and present employers;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The dates of the applicant's employment with each employer;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The position the applicant held with each employer; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Upon approval of the application by the Chief Boiler Inspector, a $50 examination fee, payable to the Division of Labor and Industry.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An individual applying for a Certificate of Competency as a special inspector on the basis of a commission issued by the National Board of Boiler and Pressure Vessel Inspectors shall submit an application:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>On the form furnished by the Chief Boiler Inspector; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Accompanied by a copy of the commission and valid identification card issued by the National Board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>An application containing false information shall be rejected.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The examination for Certificate of Competency shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be written;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Cover the construction, installation, operation, maintenance, and repair of boilers and pressure vessels and their appurtenances;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Be offered:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>At the office of the Board of Boiler Rules, or any other location that the Board selects; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>On the first Wednesday of March, June, September, and December.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The chief boiler inspector shall issue a Certificate of Competency to an applicant who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Passes the examination or a subsequent re-examination; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is a full-time employee of an authorized inspection agency.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Special Inspector Commission Application Procedure.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An authorized inspection agency or an owner-user inspection service employing an individual applying for a special inspector commission shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Submit a completed application form to the chief boiler inspector, setting forth the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The applicant's name;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A description of the applicant's education;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A list of the applicant's past and present employers;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>The dates of the applicant’s employment with each employer; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>The position the applicant held with each employer.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Submit with the application for an individual who holds a commission or certificate of competency from a state with an equivalent examination or a commission issued by the National Board, a copy of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The commission or certificate; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Any valid identification card issued by a state or the National Board.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An application containing false information shall be rejected.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Upon approval of the special inspector commission by the chief boiler inspector, the authorized inspection agency or owner-user inspection service shall pay a $50 special inspector commission fee, payable to the Division of Labor and Industry.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Unless the authorized inspection agency or owner-user inspection service complies with the renewal provisions of <cite path="09|12|01|.16|H.">§H of this regulation</cite>, a special inspector commission expires:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>On the second March 1 after June 1, 2001, for special inspector commissions that were issued before June 1, 2001;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>On March 1 of the next odd number year after the initial issuance of the special inspector commission; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>On March 1 of the next odd number year after renewal of the special inspector commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>To renew a special inspector commission, the authorized inspection agency or the owner-user inspection service employing the special inspector shall, at least 30 days before the special inspector commission is scheduled to expire, provide documentation that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The special inspector continues to be certified as a special inspector by the National Board;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The special inspector has maintained sufficient proficiency during the past year by experience and training to qualify for renewal of the commission; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The special inspector remains in the employ of the authorized inspection agency or the owner-user inspection service.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Suspension of Special Inspector Commission.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>After due investigation and recommendation by the Board of Boiler Rules, the Commissioner may suspend a special inspector commission for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Incompetence;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Untrustworthiness; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Willful falsification of information provided:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>On the application; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>In an inspection report.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Commissioner shall give the inspector and the inspector's employer written notice within 10 days of the suspension.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An inspector whose special inspector commission is suspended may:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Appeal the suspension to the Board of Boiler Rules; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Be present or be represented by counsel at any hearing of the appeal.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>An applicant who fails an examination may take another examination:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>After 90 days; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>At the next regularly scheduled examination date.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.16-1</num>
    <heading>Authorized Inspection Agency Insurance Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An authorized inspection agency shall have general liability insurance and professional liability insurance to cover its inspection activities.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An insurance policy required by this section shall be issued by an insurance company authorized to do business in Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The insurance policy shall be in the amount of at least $500,000 for injury or death for any number of individuals in any single occurrence, and $100,000 for property damage in any single occurrence.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The authorized inspection agency shall notify the Commissioner of any alterations or cancellations within 5 business days.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|12|01|.17">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.17</num>
    <heading>Installation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A new or used boiler, pressure vessel, or piping installation or reinstallation shall be installed in accordance with this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Notice of Installation.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At least 30 days before installing or reinstalling a boiler or pressure vessel, the installer shall file with the chief boiler inspector written notice of the installation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The notice of installation shall contain the following information for each boiler or pressure vessel to be installed:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Installer’s name, company name, contact person, address, telephone number, fax number, and email address;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Owner’s name, company name, contact person, street address, telephone numbers, fax number, and email address;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>User’s name, company name, contact person, street address, telephone numbers, fax number, and email address;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Name of the location where the boiler or pressure vessel is installed, company name, contact person, street address, telephone numbers, fax number, and email address;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Type and use of boiler or pressure vessel;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>If a boiler, the type of fuel;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>If a pressure vessel, the pressurized fluid;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>The minimum required safety valve capacity;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>If the boiler or pressure vessel is greater than 30 boiler horsepower input or 1,000,000 Btu/hr minimum required safety valve capacity, and operates at greater than 15 psig, the name and Maryland license number of the stationary engineer responsible for the boiler or pressure vessel;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Manufacturer, date of manufacture, National Board number, and manufacturer’s serial number;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Construction code and section and stamp;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>Name and contact information of the authorized inspection agency for the installation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>Planned date of installation, and planned date of startup; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(n)</num>
          <text>Whether a waiver of the 30 day notice requirement under <cite path="09|12|01|.17|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> is requested, with a detailed explanation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Waiver of 30-day Notice Requirement.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If emergency or unusual circumstances are established by the installer, the chief boiler inspector shall waive the 30-day notice requirement.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>To obtain a waiver, the installer shall file a written waiver request with the Chief Boiler Inspector as soon as the emergency or unusual circumstances arise; and give a detailed explanation of the emergency or unusual circumstances.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the Chief Boiler Inspector grants a waiver under this section, the Chief Boiler Inspector shall also advise the installer of when the notice is due.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Except for an existing boiler or pressure vessel being reinstalled, or as otherwise provided by this regulation, a boiler or pressure vessel may not be installed unless:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The boiler or pressure vessel has been constructed, inspected and stamped in accordance with the ASME Code and registered with the National Board;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The boiler or pressure vessel has been:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Constructed, inspected and stamped in accordance with the ASME Code;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Inspected and the inspector recommends acceptance; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Chief Boiler Inspector accepts the inspector’s recommendation; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The boiler or pressure vessel has been constructed equal to or greater than Maryland standards and:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The person intending to construct or install the boiler or pressure vessel:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Applies to the Chief Boiler Inspector for approval prior to installation; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Together with the application files the manufacturer’s data report covering construction of the boiler or pressure vessel;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An inspector inspects the boiler or pressure vessel during construction and approves the design, materials, fabrication, welding, welding specification, welder’s qualifications, processes and workmanship; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Chief Boiler Inspector approves the boiler or pressure vessel and its installation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Reinstallation.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A used boiler or pressure vessel not moved to another state for use, or repair, or alteration may be reinstalled if the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Owner applies to the Chief Boiler Inspector for permission;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Owner submits documents required by the Chief Boiler Inspector; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Chief Boiler Inspector approves the reinstallation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A used standard boiler or pressure vessel, if moved outside the state for use, repair, or alteration, may be reinstalled if the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Owner applies to the Chief Boiler Inspector for permission;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Owner submits documents required by the Chief Boiler Inspector; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Chief Boiler Inspector approves the reinstallation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A used nonstandard boiler or pressure vessel, if moved outside the State for use, repair or alteration, may be reinstalled in Maryland if the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Owner applies to the Chief Boiler Inspector and the Board for permission;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Owner submits documents required by the Chief Boiler Inspector and the Board; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Board of Boiler Rules approves the reinstallation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Fittings and appliances of a stationary boiler or pressure vessel which is moved and reinstalled shall comply with the requirements for new installations.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.18</num>
    <heading>Lap-Seam Crack.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If a boiler or pressure vessel has a lap-seam crack along a longitudinal riveted joint, use of the shell or drum shall be discontinued immediately.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If the boiler is not more than 15 years old, a complete new course of the original thickness may be installed upon:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Recommendation by the inspector; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Approval of the chief boiler inspector.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Patching a lap seam crack is prohibited.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.19</num>
    <heading>Portable Boilers and Pressure Vessels.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The installer and owner of a portable boiler or pressure vessel shall comply with all requirements of this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>While a portable boiler or pressure vessel is being moved, it shall not be operated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A portable boiler or pressure vessel shall receive an internal and external certificate inspection:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Annually; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>After it has been moved to a different location and installed before use.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.20</num>
    <heading>Power Boiler — Existing Installation: Age Limit.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Nonstandard Construction.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as otherwise provided in this regulation, the age limit of a boiler of nonstandard construction installed before the Act became effective shall be 30 years.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A boiler of nonstandard construction installed before the Act became effective, not having a lap-riveted longitudinal joint, may continue to operate for more than 30 years without reduction in working pressure after a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Thorough internal and external inspection; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Hydrostatic pressure test at 1-1/2 times the allowable working pressure, held for a period of at least 30 minutes, during which no distress or leakage develops.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A boiler having a lap-riveted longitudinal joint, which operates at a pressure greater than 50 PSI, has an age limit of 20 years.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The chief boiler inspector may authorize a reasonable time for replacement, not to exceed 1 year.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Standard Construction.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The age limit of a boiler of standard construction installed before July 1, 1969 shall be determined by a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Thorough internal and external inspection; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Hydrostatic pressure test conducted at 1-1/2 times the maximum allowable working pressure, with water temperature between 70°F and 140°F and not less than the nil ductility temperature of the material.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A boiler that exhibits no distress or leakage under test conditions may continue in operation at the same working pressure.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The shell or drum of a boiler having a lap-seam crack along a longitudinal riveted joint in either a butt seam or a lap joint may not be used under steam pressure.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.21</num>
    <heading>Power Boiler — Existing Installation: Boiler Feed System.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A boiler shall have a feed supply which permits it to be fed at any time while under pressure.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A boiler having more than 500 square feet of water-heating surface shall have at least two means of feeding, as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>One means shall be an approved feed pump, injector, or inspirator;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The other source may be directly from a water main, at a pressure 6 percent greater than the set pressure of the safety valve having the highest setting.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A boiler conforming to the ASME Code, PG-61.1, and fired by gaseous, liquid, or solid fuel in suspension may have a single feed supply provided that means are furnished for the immediate shutoff of heat input if the water feed is interrupted.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Feedwater shall be fed into a boiler so that it will not be introduced:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Near a riveted joint of a shell or furnace sheet; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Directly against a surface exposed to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A product of combustion, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Direct radiation from the fire.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Feed Pipe.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Feed pipe shall have a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Check valve near the boiler; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Valve or cock between the check valve and the boiler.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When two or more boilers are fed from a common source, the branch to each boiler shall have a valve between the check valve and source of supply.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The inlet of a globe valve on a feed pipe shall be under the disc of the valve.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Returns.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>When a return is fed back to a boiler by gravity, each return line shall have, as close as practicable to the boiler, a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Check valve; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Stop valve placed between the boiler and the check valve.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>It is recommended that no stop valve be placed in the supply and return pipe connection of a single boiler installation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Deaerating Heater. When a deaerating heater is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Not used, the recommended minimum temperature for feedwater is 120°F to avoid creating localized stress.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Used, the recommended minimum feedwater temperature is 215°F, so that dissolved gases can be released completely.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.22</num>
    <heading>Power Boiler — Existing Installation: Maximum Allowable Working Pressure.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The maximum allowable working pressure on a standard boiler shall be determined in accordance with the ASME Code under which it was constructed and stamped.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The maximum allowable working pressure on the shell of a nonstandard boiler shall be determined by the strength of the weakest section of the structure computed by multiplying TS by t and E and dividing the product by R multiplied by FS:</text>
      <text>(TS x t x E) / (R x FS) = maximum allowable working pressure, PSIG, where:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>TS = ultimate tensile strength of the shell plate, PSI, which, if unknown, shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>55,000 PSI for steel; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>45,000 PSI for wrought iron;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>t = minimum thickness of the shell plate of the weakest course, in inches;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>E = efficiency of the longitudinal joint, which is, for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Tube ligaments and riveted construction, established by Section I of the ASME Code for power boilers; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Seamless construction, 100 percent;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>R = inside radius of the weakest course of the shell, in inches;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>FS = factor of safety required by this regulation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The resistance to crushing of mild steel is assumed to be 95,000 PSI of cross-sectional area;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>When computing the ultimate strength of rivets in shear, the following values, in pounds per square inch, of the cross-sectional area of the rivet shank shall be used:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Iron rivets in single shear 38,000 PSI;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Iron rivets in double shear 76,000 PSI;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Steel rivets in single shear 44,000 PSI; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Steel rivets in double shear 88,000 PSI;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>When the diameter of a rivet hole in a longitudinal joint of a boiler is not known, the diameter and cross-sectional area of the rivet, after driving, shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Ascertained by cutting out one rivet in the body of the joint; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>As indicated in the following table:</text>
          <text>
            <table>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th colspan="2">Rivet Size</th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <th>Plate Thickness <br/>in Inches</th>
                  <th>Rivet Diameter</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">1/4</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">11/16</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">9/32</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">11/16</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">5/16</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">3/4</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">11/32</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">3/4</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">3/8</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">13/16</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">13/32</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">13/16</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">7/16</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">15/16</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">15/32</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">15/16</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">1/2</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">15/16</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">9/16</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">1-1/16</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">5/8</td>
                  <td data-text-align="center" data-vertical-align="middle">1-1/16</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The maximum allowable working pressure on a:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Water-tube boiler having tubes secured to cast iron or malleable-iron headers, or having cast-iron mud drums, shall be 160 PSIG;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Cast-iron boiler, except a hot-water boiler, shall be 15 PSIG;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Boiler having lap-riveted longitudinal joints, operated at a pressure greater than 50 PSI, when removed from an existing setting and reinstalled, shall be 15 PSIG; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Reinstalled horizontal-return tubular boiler having a continuous longitudinal lap seam more than 12 feet long, shall be 15 PSIG.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Except as otherwise provided by this regulation, the lowest factor of safety shall be, for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An existing installation: 4.5;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A horizontal-return tubular boiler having continuous longitudinal lap seams more than 12 feet long: 8;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A reinstalled or secondhand boiler having longitudinal seams of lap-riveted construction: 6; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A reinstalled or secondhand boiler with longitudinal seams of butt and double-strap construction: 5.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.23</num>
    <heading>Power Boiler — Existing Installation: Other Equipment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Blowoff Connection.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A boiler shall have a blowoff pipe, fitted with a valve or cock, connected directly to the lowest water space. The following apply:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A cock shall be of the gland or guard type, suitable for the pressure allowed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A globe valve may not be used.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Settings.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The setting around a blowoff pipe shall permit free expansion and contraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>To the maximum extent practicable, setting openings shall be sealed without restricting the movement of the blowoff piping.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Blowoff piping exposed to furnace heat shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Protected by firebrick or other heat-resisting material; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Constructed so that the piping can be inspected readily.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>When the maximum allowable working pressure exceeds 100 PSIG:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A blowoff pipe shall have two valves or a valve and cock of at least extra-heavy type;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Blowoff piping shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Be at least extra-heavy non-galvanized steel, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Run full size without reducers or bushings.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A fitting between the boiler and a blowoff valve shall be steel.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A replacement blowoff pipe or fitting shall be installed in accordance with the ASME Code requirements for new installations.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Steam Gage.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A steam boiler shall have a steam gage which:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Has a dial range of at least 1-1/2 times the maximum allowable working pressure;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is connected to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The steam space or steam connection to the water column, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A siphon or equivalent device of sufficient capacity to keep the gage tube filled with water;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Is arranged so that the gage can be shut off from the boiler only by a cock with a tee or lever handle:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Placed near the gage, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>With the handle parallel to the pipe in which it is located, when the cock is open.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When a steam gage connection longer than 8 feet is necessary, a shutoff valve near the boiler may be used if the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Valve is:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The outside-screw-and-yolk type, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Locked open; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Line is:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Of ample size, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Permits free blowing.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A boiler shall have a 1/4 inch nipple and globe valve:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Connected to the steam space; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Used only to attach a test gage while the boiler is in operation, to measure the accuracy of the boiler steam gage.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Stop Valves.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except for safety valve and water column connections, each steam outlet from a boiler shall have a stop valve as near as practicable to the boiler.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Drainage.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>When a stop valve is located so water can accumulate, ample drains shall be provided.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Drainage shall be piped to a safe location and may not be discharged on the top of the boiler or its setting.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Common Steam Mains.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>When boilers having manholes are connected to a common steam main, the steam connection from each boiler shall be fitted with two stop valves having an ample free blow drain between them.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The discharge of the drain shall be:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Visible to the operator while manipulating the valves; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Piped clear of the boiler setting.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A stop valve arrangement having one automatic non-return valve beside the boiler, and a second valve of the outside-screw-and-yoke-type, is recommended.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Water Level Indicator.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except for a damper regulator, feedwater regulator, low-water fuel cutout, drain, steam gage, or other apparatus that does not permit the escape of an appreciable amount of steam or water, no outlet connection shall be placed on piping that connects a water column to a boiler.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A water column shall have a valved drain of at least 3/4 inch pipe size.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The drain shall be piped to a safe location.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Gage Cocks.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Except as otherwise provided by this regulation, a boiler shall have at least three gage cocks within the visible length of the water glass.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A boiler shall have at least two gage cocks if the boiler:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Has two water glasses on the same horizontal line; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Is 36 inches or less in diameter, and has a heating surface of 100 square feet or less.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>When a water gage glass is more than 30 feet above the boiler operating floor, remote water-level indicating or recording gages installed above the operating floor at eye level are recommended.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.24</num>
    <heading>Power Boiler — Existing Installation: Safety Valve.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A weighted-lever safety valve or a safety valve having a cast iron seat or disc:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>May not be used after October 15, 1975; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shall be replaced by a direct, spring-loaded, pop-type valve that complies with the requirements of the ASME Code, Section I.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A boiler shall have at least one safety valve.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A boiler shall have at least two safety valves if the boiler has:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>More than 500 square feet of water-heating surface; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An electric power input of more than 500 kw.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A safety valve shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Connected to the boiler, independent of any other steam connection;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Attached:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>As close as possible to the boiler, without unnecessary intervening pipe or fittings; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>With no valve of any type between the safety valve and the boiler; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Installed in a manner that protects walkways and platforms from discharges.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>If an escape pipe is used:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>There may not be a valve of any type between a safety valve and the atmosphere;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>It shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>At least the full size of the safety valve discharge; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Fitted with an open drain to prevent water from lodging in the upper part of a safety valve or escape pipe;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If a safety valve escape pipe has an elbow, the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Elbow shall be located near the safety valve outlet; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Escape pipe shall be anchored and supported securely.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A boiler shall have sufficient safety valve capacity to discharge all steam the boiler can generate without allowing pressure to rise more than:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>6 percent above the highest pressure to which any valve is set; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>6 percent above the maximum allowable working pressure.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Settings.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At least one safety valve on a boiler shall be set at or below the maximum allowable working pressure.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Additional valves shall be set not more than 3 percent above the maximum allowable working pressure.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The range of settings of all safety valves on a boiler may not exceed 10 percent of the highest pressure to which any valve is set.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>When two or more boilers, operating at different pressures and safety valve settings, are interconnected, the lower pressure boilers or interconnected piping shall have safety valves of sufficient capacity to prevent over-pressure, considering the maximum generating capacity of all boilers.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>A boiler supplied with feedwater directly from a water main without the use of feeding apparatus other than a return trap, may not have a safety valve set at a pressure greater than 94 percent of the lowest pressure obtained in the supply main feeding the boiler.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Relief Capacity.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The relief capacity of a safety valve shall be tested by one of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An accumulation test (unless the valve is located on a boiler having a superheater or reheater), performed by shutting off all other steam-discharge outlets from the boiler and forcing fires to the maximum. The safety valve relief capacity shall be sufficient to prevent increased pressure in excess of 6 percent of the maximum allowable working pressure.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Measuring the maximum amount of fuel that can be burned, and computing the corresponding evaporative capacity on the basis of the heating value of the fuel, as outlined in the appendix of the ASME Code, Section I.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Measuring the maximum amount of feedwater that can be evaporated.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When either method in §J(1)(b) or (c) is used, the sum of the safety valve capacities shall equal or exceed the maximum evaporative capacity of the boiler.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If relief capacity is insufficient, additional valves shall be provided.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.25</num>
    <heading>Power Boiler — Existing Installation: Miscellaneous.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Repair or replacement of a fitting or appliance shall comply with the ASME Code.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The ASME Code, Section VII, Recommended Guidelines for the Care of Power Boilers, is recommended as a guide for safe operating practices.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A condition not specifically covered by this regulation:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall be treated as a new installation; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>May be referred to the chief boiler inspector for information about the requirements.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.26</num>
    <heading>Pressure Vessel — Existing Installation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The maximum allowable working pressure for a standard pressure vessel:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Shall be determined in accordance with the ASME Code under which it was constructed and stamped; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>May not exceed the pressure shown on the manufacturer's name plate stamp and data report.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Nonstandard Pressure Vessel—Maximum Allowable Working Pressure.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The maximum allowable working pressure on the shell of a nonstandard pressure vessel shall be determined by the strength of the weakest course computed by multiplying TS by t and E and dividing the product by R multiplied by FS:</text>
        <text>(TS x t x E)/(R x FS) = maximum allowable working pressure, PSIG, where:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>TS = ultimate tensile strength of the shell plate, PSI, which, if unknown, shall be 55,000 PSI for steel, for temperatures not exceeding 700°F;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>t = minimum thickness of the shell plate of the weakest course, in inches;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>E = efficiency of the longitudinal joint, which is, for:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Riveted joints, the calculated riveted efficiency, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Fusion-welded and brazed joints:</text>
            <text>Single lap weld ... 40 percent</text>
            <text>Double lap weld ... 60 percent</text>
            <text>Single butt weld ... 60 percent</text>
            <text>Double butt weld ... 75 percent</text>
            <text>Forge weld ... 70 percent</text>
            <text>Brazed steel ... 80 percent</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>R = radius of the weakest course of the shell, in inches, using the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Inside radius, if the thickness is 10 percent or less of the radius, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Outside radius, if the thickness is greater than 10 percent of the radius;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>FS = factor of safety required by this regulation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The maximum allowable working pressure for a cylindrical nonstandard pressure vessel subjected to external or collapsing pressure shall be determined by the ASME Code, Section VIII, paragraphs UG-28 and UG-29.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Factor of Safety.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>For an existing installation, the minimum factor of safety shall be at least four.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>When necessary to ensure safe operation, the inspector may increase the factor of safety based on the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Condition of the vessel; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Specific service to which it is subject.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The maximum allowable working pressure for formed heads under pressure shall be determined by the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Appropriate formulas from the ASME Code, Section VIII, Division 1, Paragraphs UG-32, UG-33, and UG-35; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Tensile strength and factors of safety set out in this regulation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the inspector determines, because of conditions disclosed during an inspection, that the interior or exterior lining, covering, or brickwork should be removed to expose parts of the vessel not normally visible, the owner shall remove the material to permit:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Proper inspection; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Drilling any part of the vessel where necessary to ascertain thickness.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Safety Appliances.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To ensure safe operation, a pressure vessel shall have:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Safety and relief valves; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Indicating and controlling devices.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Safety appliances shall be constructed, located, and installed so that they cannot readily be rendered inoperative.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The relief capacity of a safety valve shall be sufficient to prevent pressure in the vessel from rising more than 10 percent above the maximum allowable working pressure, with static head pressure factored into the calculation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Safety valve discharge shall be carried to a safe place.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Repairs and replacements of fittings and appliances shall comply with the requirements for new installations.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.27</num>
    <heading>Repair.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>All repairs and alterations of boilers and pressure vessels shall conform to the requirements of the NBIC.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The person performing repairs and alterations on a boiler or pressure vessel shall provide the chief boiler inspector with reports related to the repair as required by <cite path="|09|12|01|.28">Regulation .28 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The person certifying that the repair or alteration is complete and in accordance with the NBIC shall be a special inspector, deputy boiler, or Chief Boiler Inspector.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|12|01|.28">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.28</num>
    <heading>Reporting Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Accident or Explosion Report.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>After an accident or explosion the owner or operator shall notify the chief boiler inspector within 24 hours by email and by telephone.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Notification under <cite path="09|12|01|.28|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite> shall contain the following information regarding the accident or explosion:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Name, address, telephone number, and other contact information of the individual reporting the incident;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Location and address of the incident;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Date and time of the incident;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Description of the incident;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Maryland registration number and National Board registration number;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Manufacturer, year of manufacture, and serial number;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Type of boiler or pressure vessel and maximum allowable working pressure;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Injuries including fatalities; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Property damage.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A special inspector, immediately upon receiving a report of an accident or explosion, shall notify the chief boiler inspector.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Unless necessary to save human life, the owner or operator, or both, shall ensure that the boiler, pressure vessel, or any part of the boiler or pressure vessel is not removed or disturbed before the inspector conducts an inspection.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An inspector shall file a report of a hazardous condition that affects the safe operation of a boiler or pressure vessel with the Chief Boiler Inspector within 24 hours by email.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An authorized insurer shall file a report with the Chief Boiler Inspector by email within 24 hours if the insurance policy is cancelled, not renewed, or suspended due to an unsafe condition.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An authorized insurer shall file a report with the Chief Boiler Inspector by email within 24 hours where the insurance coverage is denied as a result of an inspector’s first inspection.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Inspection Report.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within 30 days of the inspection date, an authorized inspection agency shall submit to the Chief Boiler Inspector:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A report of each certificate inspection; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A report of each inspection of a boiler or pressure vessel that did not have a valid certificate at the time of the inspection.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The inspection report shall include at least the following information:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Date of the inspection;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Maryland registration number;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Owner’s identification number;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Manufacturer, year of manufacture, National Board registration number, manufacturer’s serial number;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Year of installation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Location and address of the boiler or pressure vessel;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Name and address of the owner of the boiler or pressure vessel;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Name and address of the primary contact of the boiler or pressure vessel;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Name and address of the person to whom a certificate should be sent;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Name and address of the person to whom an invoice should be sent;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Specific location in the plant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>Type and use of the boiler or pressure vessel;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>Whether a variance has been granted and if so, the terms of the variance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(n)</num>
          <text>ASME symbol stamped on the boiler or pressure vessel;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(o)</num>
          <text>If a boiler, the fuel, the fuel train code, and the firing method;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(p)</num>
          <text>If a pressure vessel, the pressurized fluid;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(q)</num>
          <text>The stamped maximum allowable working pressure and the maximum allowable operating pressure and the set pressure of the pressure relief device;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(r)</num>
          <text>The minimum required capacity of the pressure relief device, and the total installed pressure relief capacity;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(s)</num>
          <text>The status of the boiler or pressure vessel;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(t)</num>
          <text>The inspection type;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(u)</num>
          <text>Whether a certificate is posted;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(v)</num>
          <text>Whether the pressure gage was tested;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(w)</num>
          <text>Whether the inspector recommends that a certificate be issued;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(x)</num>
          <text>Whether a hydrostatic pressure test was performed, and if so, at what pressure;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(y)</num>
          <text>Complete nameplate information or a photograph or rubbing of the nameplate;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(z)</num>
          <text>A statement of the condition of the boiler or pressure vessel, in general and specifically as needed, including violations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(aa)</num>
          <text>If violations were noted, the recommended corrective action to take;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(bb)</num>
          <text>The name of the owner or owner’s representative to whom the report was explained, with contact information;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(cc)</num>
          <text>The name of the authorized inspection agency; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(dd)</num>
          <text>The name of the inspector, the inspector’s National Board commission number, and the inspector’s Maryland commission number.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An inspection of a historical boiler shall be reported on:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>National Board Form C-1; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A Maryland inspection report form.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Method of Filing an Inspection Report.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A report shall be submitted electronically in the format required by the Chief Boiler Inspector, unless to do so would create an undue burden.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If a report is not submitted electronically in the format required by the Chief Boiler Inspector it shall be:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Submitted on the Maryland inspection report form; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Subject to a filing fee, payable by the authorized inspection agency.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>An authorized insurer shall file a report of insurance change with the Chief Boiler Inspector within 30 days after an insurance policy is issued, cancelled, not renewed, or suspended for any reason.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A manufacturer shall file a manufacturer’s data report with the Chief Boiler Inspector through the National Board for each of its boilers and pressure vessels to be operated in Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Repair and Alteration Reports.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person performing repairs or alterations on a boiler or pressure vessel shall provide the Chief Boiler Inspector and the owner with a written report of each repair or alteration within 30 days of the completion of the repair or alteration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The repair or alteration report shall include at least the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Name and address of the company performing the repair or alteration;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Owner and location, including the address of the boiler or pressure vessel;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Maryland registration number and National Board registration number;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Manufacturer and serial number;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Description of the repair or alteration; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Completion of certificate of compliance and certificate inspection.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Inventory Report.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within 3 days of the first day of each month, each authorized insurer shall submit to the Chief Boiler Inspector an inventory report of each boiler and pressure vessel that it insures.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Within 3 days of the first day of each month, each owner-user inspection service shall submit to the Chief Boiler Inspector an inventory report of each boiler and pressure vessel it owns.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The inventory report shall contain at least the following information about each boiler and pressure vessel:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Maryland registration number;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Name of the manufacturer, year of manufacture, and National Board number;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Manufacturer’s serial number;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Owner’s identifying number;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Type of boiler or pressure vessel;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Location and address of the boiler or pressure vessel; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Name and address of the owner of the boiler or pressure vessel.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Method of Filing an Inventory Report.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An inventory report shall be submitted electronically in the format required by the Chief Boiler Inspector, unless to do so would create an undue burden.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If an inventory report is not submitted electronically in the format required by the Chief Boiler Inspector it shall be subject to a filing fee, payable by the authorized inspection agency.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.28-1</num>
    <heading>Record Keeping.</heading>
    <text>An owner or user of a boiler or pressure vessel shall maintain a legible copy of inspection, maintenance, repair, and alteration records.</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>At a readily accessible central location in the building where the boiler or pressure vessel is located; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>For the life of the boiler or pressure vessel.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|12|01|.28-2">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.28-2</num>
    <heading>Database Report of Boilers and Pressure Vessels.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An authorized insurer shall develop a database report of boilers and pressure vessels that it insures.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An owner-user inspection service shall develop a database report of the boilers and pressure vessels it owns.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The database report required by §§A and B of this regulation shall contain the following information about each boiler and pressure vessel:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Maryland registration number and National Board registration number;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Name and address of the owner of the boiler or pressure vessel;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Location and address of the boiler or pressure vessel;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Type of boiler or pressure vessel;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Name of the manufacturer and serial number;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Date or dates the certificate inspection was completed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Name of the special inspector conducting the inspection; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Last inspection date.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Submission of Database Report.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A copy of the database report required by §§A and B of this regulation shall be submitted to the chief boiler inspector by September 1, 2001.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>After September 1, 2001, the database report and annual updates to the database report shall be submitted to the chief boiler inspector by January 15 of each year.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Database reports submitted by an authorized insurer pursuant to <cite path="09|12|01|.28-2|D.">§D of this regulation</cite> shall reflect all boilers and pressure vessels that the company insures including:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each certificate inspection; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Each time that the authorized insurer adds or drops a boiler or pressure vessel from coverage.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Filing Reports.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Database reports shall be filed by an authorized insurer or owner-user inspection service in an electronic format that is acceptable to the chief boiler inspector.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The chief boiler inspector shall notify authorized insurers and owner-user inspection services of the acceptable electronic formats.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Database reports not submitted electronically by an authorized insurer or owner-user inspection service shall be submitted on the form provided by the chief boiler inspector.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Database reports not submitted electronically by an authorized insurer are subject to the filing fee provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|12-910">Public Safety Article, §12-910(a)(3), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.28-3</num>
    <heading>Quality Assurance Program.</heading>
    <text>Each authorized inspection agency shall make available for review by the Chief Boiler Inspector, the quality assurance program documents that were submitted to the National Board for accreditation as an authorized inspection agency.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.29</num>
    <heading>Safety Appliance Removal.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>When a boiler or pressure vessel is operating, a person may not remove, modify, alter, or repair a safety appliance required by these regulations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>When a boiler or pressure vessel is not operating and a safety appliance is removed for modification, alteration, or repair the appliance shall be reinstalled in proper working order before the boiler or pressure vessel resumes operation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A safety valve may not be loaded to maintain a working pressure greater than the maximum allowable operating pressure.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.30</num>
    <heading>Stamping.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>At the first post-installation internal or certificate inspection, the inspector shall assign to a boiler or pressure vessel a Maryland serial number that is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At least 5/16 of an inch in height;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Configured as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>For power boilers	&lt;MD&gt;	MD 0000;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For heating boilers	&lt;MD&gt;	MD 0000H;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>For pressure vessels	&lt;MD&gt;	MD 0000V;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>For nuclear vessels	&lt;MD&gt;	MD 0000N; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Stamped on:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The boiler or pressure vessel, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A metal tag at least 1 inch in height, securely attached to the front of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A low pressure heating boiler constructed of cast iron, or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A pressure vessel constructed of cast iron or other material of a thickness that should not be stamped.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Unless a record is kept showing the location of stamping so that the stamping can be uncovered readily, stamping:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>May not be concealed by lagging or paint; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Shall be exposed at all times.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>When a boiler or pressure vessel stamp is indistinct:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An inspector shall direct the owner to have the boiler or pressure vessel restamped;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The owner shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Request from the chief boiler inspector permission to restamp, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Submit with the request, proof of the original stamp; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the chief boiler inspector authorizes restamping, an inspector shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Observe the restamping, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>File with the chief boiler inspector notice of the restamping, and a facsimile of the stamp applied.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A condemned boiler or pressure vessel shall be stamped with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Letters 5/16 of an inch in height; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The configuration XXX MD XXX.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.31</num>
    <heading>Variance from Regulation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A person who believes that a regulation is unreasonable or imposes an undue burden on an owner may request the Board of Boiler Rules to grant a variance from that regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An application for variance shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be in writing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Specify the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Name and address of the applicant,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Regulation from which the applicant seeks a variance,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Location, equipment, and practices involved;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>State:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In detail, the reasons why the applicant requests the variance, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The steps the applicant has taken and will take, with specific dates when appropriate, to protect employees and the public against the hazard covered by the regulation;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Certify that the applicant has given appropriate notice of the application to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The applicant's employees affected by the variance,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>All authorized representatives of the affected employees, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Other persons affected by the condition for which a variance is sought;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Include a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Copy or description of the required notice, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>List of the names and addresses of persons entitled to notice.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Order of Variance.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>After an investigation and such hearing as it may direct, the Board of Boiler Rules may grant a variance from a regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An order of variance may impose special conditions necessary to ensure equivalent safety.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>When there is reason to believe, or when a complaint is received, that a variance does not provide safety equivalent to the regulation, the Board of Boiler Rules may continue, suspend, revoke, or modify the conditions specified in a variance order after:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notice to the owner and to the complainant, if any; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Such investigation and hearing as the Board of Boiler Rules may direct.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>A declaration, act, or omission of the Board of Boiler Rules, the chief boiler inspector, a deputy boiler inspector, or a special inspector, other than a written order authorizing a variance in accordance with this regulation, may not exempt an owner from full compliance with this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.32</num>
    <heading>Vacant</heading>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|12|01|.33">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.33</num>
    <heading>Model Steam Boilers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Model steam boilers are subject to the requirements of Regulations .01, .01-1, .05, .08, .09, .14—.16, .19, and .27—.31 of this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Repealed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A model steam boiler may not be operated in Maryland unless it has a valid:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Maryland inspection certificate; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Inspection or operating certificate issued by another state having standards equivalent to the requirements of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Inspection Certificate.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Unless sooner suspended or revoked, an inspection certificate expires 1 year from date of issuance.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An inspection certificate shall specify the maximum operating pressure of the model steam boiler, determined in accordance with this regulation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Initial Test.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Before an initial test of a model steam boiler:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An owner shall provide the inspector with:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Construction drawings,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Material specifications,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Welding and brazing information,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Stress calculations, in accordance with <cite path="09|12|01|.33|H.">§H of this regulation</cite>,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>The calculated factor of safety,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Requested maximum operating pressure,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>The name and qualifications of the manufacturer and assembler, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>The name and qualifications of the designer, if available; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An inspector shall verify that the design of the model steam boiler is in accordance with the documents provided.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Before being put into operation, a new model steam boiler shall be tested hydrostatically to a pressure of at least two times the maximum operating pressure.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Inspection.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A model steam boiler shall be tested:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Annually; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>After repair or modification.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An owner requesting an inspection of a model steam boiler shall supply test equipment, including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Water source, pump, pressure lines, and master test gage; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Plugs, gags, or caps to replace safety valves or other appurtenances, if needed to prevent damage by the required test pressure.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An inspector:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Shall conduct an external inspection and, to the extent possible, an internal inspection, to ascertain the physical condition of the model steam boiler before the hydrostatic test is conducted;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Shall witness the hydrostatic test;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>May require that:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A model steam boiler be placed in operation so the inspector can make further observations and check safety valve operation, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>An accumulation test be conducted in accordance with <cite path="|09|12|01|.24|J.|(1)|(a)">Regulation .24J(1)(a) of this chapter</cite>; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>If the test is completed successfully, shall sign the test report and file it with the chief boiler inspector.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A hydrostatic test:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Except as otherwise provided by this regulation, shall be applied at 1-1/2 times the maximum operating pressure;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>May be conducted using a model steam boiler's feed pump and pressure gage, if the:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Range of the gage is sufficient, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Gage has been calibrated in accordance with this regulation; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>May not be approved if the model steam boiler:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Shows leakage, bulging or displacement of a sheet, firebox, barrel, or other surface exposed to pressure, or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>While pressure is being increased or is at the maximum level, experiences a serious leak, unusual sound, or sudden drop in pressure.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Equipment.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Safety Valve.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A model steam boiler shall have two or more safety valves.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Each safety valve shall be set at or below the maximum operating pressure.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A model steam boiler shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Have sufficient safety valve capacity to discharge all steam the model steam boiler can generate, without allowing pressure to rise more than 6 percent above the maximum operating pressure; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Comply with the requirements of the ASME Code, Section I, Paragraph PG-70.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Steam Gage. If a steam gage:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Has sufficient range:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>It may be left in place during a test,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A record shall be made of its readings and compared with the master test gage, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>If test readings conflict, the steam gage shall be recalibrated or replaced;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Does not have sufficient range for test pressure:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The steam gage shall be removed and calibrated with the test gage or with a dead weight tester, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A test gage shall be used to conduct the test.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Maximum operating pressure, as designated on the inspection certificate:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For a model steam boiler on a locomotive, shall be that necessary to move the locomotive, considering cylinder dimension and weight on driving wheels;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For other model steam boilers, shall be that necessary for optimum operation of the engine; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>May not exceed the maximum allowable working pressure.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Maximum Allowable Working Pressure.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Maximum allowable working pressure on:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The shell of a model steam boiler shall be computed by the formula: (s X t X c)/r = maximum allowable working pressure, PSIG, where:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>s = maximum allowable material stress, PSI,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>t = minimum thickness of the shell wall, in inches,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>c = constant, which for a seamless shell shall be 1.0, and for a welded shell shall be 0.8, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>r = outside radius of the shell, in inches;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A stayed surface shall be computed by the formula: (t squared X s X c)/p squared = Maximum allowable working pressure, PSIG, where:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>c = constant, which for welded or silver soldered stay bolts without heads shall be 2.1, and for welded or silver soldered stay bolts with heads shall be 2.8,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>p = stay bolt pitch, in inches, using the largest dimension if the spacing is not square,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>s = maximum allowable material stress, PSI, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>t = minimum thickness of the wall, in inches;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A stay bolt shall be computed by the formula: (a X s)/(h X v) = maximum allowable working pressure, PSIG, where:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>a = cross sectional area of stay bolt, root of thread, if threaded, in square inches,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>h = stay bolt horizontal spacing, in inches,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>s = maximum allowable material stress, PSI, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>v = stay bolt vertical spacing, in inches.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The calculated factor of safety shall be computed by the formula: ((maximum allowable ASME Code calculated working pressure, PSIG)/(maximum operation pressure, PSIG)) X (ASME Code factor of safety) = calculated factor of safety</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The maximum allowable material stress shall be, for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Carbon steel:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Ultimate tensile strength: 50,000 PSI;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>ASME Code factor of safety: 4;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Allowable working stress: 12,500 PSI; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>A temperature allowance is not required for pressures up to 250 PSI. Allowable stress values for pressures above 250 PSI shall comply with the requirements of the ASME Code, Section I, Part PG-23.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Copper:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Ultimate tensile strength: 30,000 PSI;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>ASME Code factor of safety: 5; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Allowable working stress, with temperature allowance:</text>
            <text>Atmospheric, 40° to 100°F ... 6,000 PSI</text>
            <text>80 PSIG, 324°F ... 4,400 PSI</text>
            <text>90 PSIG, 331°F ... 4,300 PSI</text>
            <text>100 PSIG, 338°F ... 4,200 PSI</text>
            <text>110 PSIG, 344°F ... 4,100 PSI</text>
            <text>120 PSIG, 350°F ... 4,000 PSI</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.34</num>
    <heading>Historic Boilers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as provided for in this regulation, a historical boiler shall be installed, inspected, operated, repaired, or altered in accordance with the NBIC.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Inspection.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An initial inspection shall be conducted:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>To determine baseline criteria needed for the operating life of the boiler;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>In accordance with the requirements outlined in the NBIC;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>On any boiler not previously inspected in Maryland; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>On any boiler which has not received a certificate inspection in Maryland in the previous 2 years.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in this subsection, a historical boiler shall be inspected at the inspection intervals of the NBIC:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An internal inspection shall be conducted annually;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An external inspection shall be conducted annually;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>After a repair or alteration, a historical boiler shall be inspected before operation; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>If an inspection detects a condition warranting further investigation, an inspector may require further investigation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Before an inspection, an owner shall, upon request, provide the inspector with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Stress calculations in accordance with this regulation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The calculated factor of safety;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Requested maximum allowable operating pressure;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The two most recent ultrasonic thickness examination maps; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Any other documentation required by the NBIC.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>During an inspection, an inspector may:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Examine all documents pertaining to the qualifications of the operator; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Assess an operator’s demonstrated understanding of the operational requirements of the historical boiler.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Hydrostatic Pressure Test.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A historical boiler shall be hydrostatically tested to a pressure of not less than the maximum allowable operating pressure but no more than 1-1/4 times the maximum allowable operating pressure.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>After a repair or alteration, a historical boiler shall be tested hydrostatically to a pressure of not less than 1¼ times the maximum allowable operating pressure but no more than 1½ times the maximum allowable operating pressure.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An owner shall supply the necessary test equipment required by the inspector for the hydrostatic test including:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Water source, pump, pressure lines, and calibrated test gauge; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Plugs, gags, or caps to replace safety valves or other appurtenances if needed to prevent damage from the required test pressure.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Maximum Allowable Operating Pressure.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The maximum allowable operating pressure shall be determined by the inspector in accordance with the NBIC and ASME Code.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The maximum allowable operating pressure for objects containing wrought iron will be determined by considering the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>For pressures up to 250 psi a temperature allowance is not required; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>For pressures above 250 psi the allowable stress values shall comply with the requirements of the ASME Code, Section I, Part PG-23.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The maximum allowable operating pressure for objects containing materials other than carbon steel or wrought iron shall be determined in accordance with the ASME Code.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Training.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person who operates a historical boiler shall retain a written record of their training.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Upon request, a person who operates a historical boiler shall provide the Chief Boiler Inspector with a copy of their training record.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Historical boilers with a certificate of inspection issued by another jurisdiction may operate in Maryland under the following circumstances:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An owner of a historical boiler may request that the Chief Boiler Inspector recognize a certificate of inspection issued by another jurisdiction;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In evaluating a request for recognition of a certification of inspection by the other jurisdiction, the Chief Boiler Inspector may conduct an inspection of a historical boiler to verify:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Compliance with the NBIC; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Satisfaction of safety requirements that are equal to or greater than Maryland’s requirements;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the Chief Boiler Inspector conducts an inspection to evaluate a historical boiler with a certificate of inspection from the other jurisdiction, the Chief Boiler Inspector shall examine the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Verification and validation of the certificate of inspection from the other jurisdiction;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Examination of all documents required by this regulation and by the NBIC;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Examination of all documents pertaining to the qualifications of the operator;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Demonstrated understanding of the operational requirements by the operator of the historical boiler; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Other tests at the discretion of the inspector including but not limited to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>An external inspection;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A determination of the maximum allowable operating pressure in Maryland; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Operation at the maximum allowable operating pressure in Maryland; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>If the Chief Boiler Inspector determines that a historical boiler with a certificate of inspection issued by another jurisdiction is in compliance with safety requirements that are equal to or greater than Maryland, the Chief Boiler Inspector shall issue a certificate of inspection.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>A historical portable steam boiler shall not be operated at a pressure greater than:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>15 psig when being moved at a speed of 5 miles per hour or less; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Zero psig when being moved at a speed greater than 5 miles per hour.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|12|01|.35">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.35</num>
    <heading>Citations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>If, after an inspection or investigation, the Commissioner finds that, within the immediately preceding 6 months, a person has violated <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps">Public Safety Article, Title 12, Subtitle 9, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or a regulation or order issued to carry out this law, the Commissioner shall issue a citation to the person.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Each citation shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be in writing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Describe, in detail, the nature of the alleged violation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Cite the provision or provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps">Public Safety Article, Title 12, Subtitle 9, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, regulation, or order that the person is alleged to have violated;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Set a reasonable time for correction of the alleged violation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>State the proposed civil penalty, if any, that the Commissioner intends to impose; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Inform the person of the right to a hearing under <cite path="09|12|01|.35|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner shall serve the citation on each named person by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Certified mail, return receipt requested; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Personal delivery, if the person serving the document certifies to the manner and date of service.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A person who receives a citation shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Upon receipt of the citation, post the citation, or an unedited copy, conspicuously at or near each place where the citation alleges that a violation occurred;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Post the citation, or an unedited copy, conspicuously at its place of business where:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Notices to employees are usually posted; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Notices to the public are usually posted;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Ensure that the posted citation is not:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Removed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Altered;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Defaced; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Covered; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Ensure that the citation remains posted for the later of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The time the violation described in the citation is corrected; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>3 workdays.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Within 15 workdays after a person receives notice of a citation under <cite path="09|12|01|.35|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>, the person may submit to the Commissioner a written request for a hearing on the citation or proposed civil penalty.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Unless a person requests a hearing as provided in <cite path="09|12|01|.35|E.">§E of this regulation</cite>, a citation, including a notice of a proposed civil penalty, is considered a final order.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner, or the Commissioner’s designee, shall give notice of a hearing and hold the hearing under <cite path="09|12|01|.35|E.">§E of this regulation</cite> in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 10, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, as supplemented by <cite path="|09|12|01|.09">Regulation .09 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>A person shall correct each violation for which the Commissioner issues a citation within the time set for correction in the citation or a final order under this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.36</num>
    <heading>Penalties.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner may impose a civil penalty, not exceeding $1,000 for each violation, against a person who violates <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps">Public Safety Article, Title 12, Subtitle 9, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or a regulation or order issued to carry out this law, if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The violation involves recordkeeping, notice, filing, access, or posting requirements;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An inspection is not conducted on time; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Commissioner finds that the violation is less than serious.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner may impose a civil penalty, not exceeding $2,500 for each violation, against a person who violates <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps">Public Safety Article, Title 12, Subtitle 9, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or a regulation or order issued to carry out this law, if a substantial probability of death, serious physical injury, or serious damage to property exists because of the violation, unless the person did not know and with reasonable diligence could not have known of the violation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner may impose a civil penalty, not exceeding $5,000 for each violation, against a person who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Operates a boiler or pressure vessel without a certificate of inspection from the Commissioner;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Operates a boiler or pressure vessel that has been prohibited from use; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Willfully or repeatedly violates <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps">Public Safety Article, Title 12, Subtitle 9, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, or a regulation or order issued to carry out this law.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Before the Commissioner imposes a civil penalty, the Commissioner shall consider the appropriateness of the penalty in relation to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The size of the business of the person against whom the penalty is to be imposed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The nature or gravity of the violation for which the penalty is to be imposed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The good faith of the person; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Any previous violations by the person.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner may impose a civil penalty, not exceeding $1,000 for each day a violation continues, against a person who fails to correct the violation in the time set for its correction.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Each civil penalty shall be paid into the General Fund of the State.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.37</num>
    <heading>Miniature Boilers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Miniature boilers are exempt from the requirements of CSD-1, except that they shall have:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An emergency shut-off switch located outside of the main point of access and egress to the boiler room, unless the installer can establish that this location would allow access by the general public that could be detrimental to the operation of the boiler; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A lockable service disconnect.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Control and safety devices for miniature boilers shall comply with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The code under which they were constructed and stamped; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The recommendations and requirements in the manufacturer's installation manual.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If a conflict between §B(1) and (2) of this regulation occurs, the code under which they were constructed and stamped shall be followed.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.38</num>
    <heading>Kitchen Equipment Boilers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Kitchen equipment boilers are exempt from the requirements of CSD-1, except that they shall have:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An emergency shut-off switch located outside of the main point of access and egress to the kitchen, unless the installer can establish that this location would allow access by the general public that could be detrimental to the operation of the boiler; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A lockable service disconnect.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Control and safety devices for kitchen equipment boilers shall comply with:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The code under which they were constructed and stamped; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The recommendations and requirements in the manufacturer's installation manual.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If a conflict between §B(1) and (2) of this regulation occurs, the code under which they were constructed and stamped shall be followed.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Public Safety Article, Title 12, Annotated Code of Maryland<br/>Ch. 351, Acts of 2004</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1975-10-15">Effective date: October 15, 1975 (2:23 Md. R. 1414)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1982-06-01"><cite path="|09|12|01|.02|C.">Regulation .02C</cite>C amended and .02DD repealed effective June 1, 1982 (9:8 Md. R. 821)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-11-04"><cite path="|09|12|01|.02|P.">Regulation .02P</cite>P amended effective November 4, 1985 (12:22 Md. R. 2103)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-11-04">Regulations <cite path="|09|12|01|.07">.07</cite>—<cite path="|09|12|01|.08">.08</cite> adopted effective November 4, 1985 (12:22 Md. R. 2103)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-06-01" discontinuity="true">Regulations <cite path="|09|12|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|09|12|01|.08">.08</cite> repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|09|12|01|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|09|12|01|.32">.32</cite> adopted effective June 1, 1989 (16:10 Md. R. 1106)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1997-06-30"><cite path="|09|12|01|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective September 1, 1989 (16:16 Md. R. 1749); April 16, 1990 (17:7 Md. R. 848); October 7, 1996 (23:20 Md. R. 1422); June 30, 1997 (24:13 Md. R. 930)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-10-04"><cite path="|09|12|01|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 14, 1999 (26:16 Md. R. 1237); amended permanently effective October 4, 1999 (26:20 Md. R. 1545)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2000-07-10"><cite path="|09|12|01|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective July 10, 2000 (27:13 Md. R. 1211)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-02-19"><cite path="|09|12|01|.01-1">Regulation .01-1</cite> amended effective January 31, 1994 (21:2 Md. R. 98); July 18, 1994 (12:14 Md. R. 1228); November 20, 1994 (21:25 Md. R. 1933); July 3, 1995 (22:13 Md. R. 966); January 15, 1996 (23:1 Md. R. 23); April 22, 1996 (23:8 Md. R. 604); August 12, 1996 (23:16 Md. R. 1175); June 30, 1997 (24:13 Md. R. 930); November 3, 1997 (24:22 Md. R. 1551); July 10, 2000 (27:13 Md. R. 1211); February 19, 2001 (28:3 Md. R. 205)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-10-04"><cite path="|09|12|01|.01-1A">Regulation .01-1A(1)</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 14, 1999 (26:16 Md. R. 1236); amended permanently effective October 4, 1999 (26:20 Md. R. 1545)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-10-11"><cite path="|09|12|01|.01-2">Regulation .01-2</cite> adopted effective October 11, 1993 (20:20 Md. R. 1569)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1997-06-30"><cite path="|09|12|01|.01-2">Regulation .01-2</cite> amended effective June 30, 1997 (24:13 Md. R. 930)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-02-19"><cite path="|09|12|01|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended effective October 7, 1996 (23:20 Md. R. 1422); July 10, 2000 (27:13 Md. R. 1211); February 19, 2001 (28:3 Md. R. 205)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-07-03"><cite path="|09|12|01|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite> amended effective July 3, 1995 (22:13 Md. R. 966)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-03-05"><cite path="|09|12|01|.09">Regulation .09</cite> amended effective March 5, 1990 (17:4 Md. R. 496)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-10-11"><cite path="|09|12|01|.14|G.">Regulation .14G</cite> adopted effective October 11, 1993 (20:20 Md. R. 1569)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-09-03"><cite path="|09|12|01|.15">Regulation .15</cite> amended effective September 3, 1990 (17:17 Md. R. 2078)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-10-11"><cite path="|09|12|01|.17|A.">Regulation .17A</cite> amended effective October 11, 1993 (20:20 Md. R. 1569)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-10-04"><cite path="|09|12|01|.17|A.">Regulation .17A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 14. 1999 (26:16 Md. R. 1237); amended permanently effective October 4, 1999 (26:20 Md. R. 1545)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-09-01"><cite path="|09|12|01|.17|E.">Regulation .17E</cite> amended effective September 1, 1989 (16:16 Md. R. 1749)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-07-03"><cite path="|09|12|01|.22|B.">Regulation .22B</cite> amended effective July 3, 1995 (22:13 Md. R. 966)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-10-04"><cite path="|09|12|01|.25|B.">Regulation .25B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 14, 1999 (26:16 Md. R. 1237); amended permanently effective October 4, 1999 (26:20 Md. R. 1545)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-07-03"><cite path="|09|12|01|.26|B.">Regulation .26B</cite> amended effective July 3, 1995 (22:13 Md. R. 966)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-10-04"><cite path="|09|12|01|.27">Regulation .27</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective July 14, 1999 (26:16 Md. R. 1237); amended permanently effective October 4, 1999 (26:20 Md. R. 1545)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-11-20"><cite path="|09|12|01|.27|B.">Regulation .27B</cite> amended effective August 5, 1991 (18:15 Md. R. 1725); November 20, 1994 (21:23 Md. R. 1933)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1991-08-05"><cite path="|09|12|01|.27|C.">Regulation .27C</cite> adopted effective August 5, 1991 (18:15 Md. R. 1725)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-10-11"><cite path="|09|12|01|.27|C.">Regulation .27C</cite> amended effective October 11, 1993 (20:20 Md. R. 1569)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1997-06-30"><cite path="|09|12|01|.28|A.">Regulation .28A</cite> amended effective June 30, 1997 (24:13 Md. R. 930)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-11-20"><cite path="|09|12|01|.31|D.">Regulation .31D</cite> amended effective November 20, 1994 (21:23 Md. R. 1933)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-10-11"><cite path="|09|12|01|.32">Regulation .32</cite> amended and recodified to Regulation .01-1 effective October 11, 1993 (20:20 Md. R. 1569)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-04-16"><cite path="|09|12|01|.32|A.">Regulation .32A</cite> amended effective April 16, 1990 (17:7 Md. R. 848)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-09-01"><cite path="|09|12|01|.33">Regulation .33</cite> adopted effective September 1, 1989 (16:16 Md. R. 1749)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1997-06-30"><cite path="|09|12|01|.33|A.">Regulation .33A</cite> amended, B repealed effective June 30, 1997 (24:13 Md. R. 930)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1997-06-30"><cite path="|09|12|01|.34">Regulation .34</cite> adopted effective June 30, 1997 (24:13 Md. R. 930)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-11-12" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised as an emergency provision effective August 10, 2001 (28:17 Md. R. 1551); revised permanently effective November 12, 2001 (28:22 Md. R. 1936)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-04-23"><cite path="|09|12|01|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective December 12, 2002 (29:24 Md. R. 1919); April 23, 2018 (45:8 Md. R. 419)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-04-19"><cite path="|09|12|01|.01-1">Regulation .01-1</cite> amended effective April 19, 2021 (48:8 Md. R. 308)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-03-17"><cite path="|09|12|01|.01-1A">Regulation .01-1A</cite> amended effective September 29, 2003 (30:19 Md. R. 1331); March 17, 2014 (41:5 Md. R. 342)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-09-02"><cite path="|09|12|01|.01-1A">Regulation .01-1A</cite>, B amended effective September 2, 2002 (29:17 Md. R. 1380)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-04-23"><cite path="|09|12|01|.01-1A">Regulation .01-1A</cite>, C amended effective April 23, 2018 (45:8 Md. R. 419)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-12-12"><cite path="|09|12|01|.01-1B">Regulation .01-1B</cite>, C amended effective December 12, 2002 (29:24 Md. R. 1919)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-04-23"><cite path="|09|12|01|.01-2">Regulation .01-2</cite> amended effective December 12, 2002 (29:24 Md. R. 1919); April 23, 2018 (45:8 Md. R. 419)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-09-30"><cite path="|09|12|01|.03|B.">Regulation .03B</cite>, C amended and D adopted effective September 30, 2002 (29:19 Md. R. 1523)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-04-23"><cite path="|09|12|01|.08">Regulation .08</cite> amended effective April 23, 2018 (45:8 Md. R. 419)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-04-23"><cite path="|09|12|01|.09">Regulation .09</cite> amended effective April 23, 2018 (45:8 Md. R. 419)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-09-27"><cite path="|09|12|01|.14">Regulation .14</cite> recodified to Regulation .14-1 and new Regulation .14 adopted as an emergency provision effective July 9, 2004 (31:18 Md. R. 1348); adopted permanently effective September 27, 2004 (31:19 Md. R. 1431)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-04-23"><cite path="|09|12|01|.14|C.">Regulation .14C</cite> amended effective April 23, 2018 (45:8 Md. R. 419)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-04-23"><cite path="|09|12|01|.14|D.">Regulation .14D</cite> adopted effective April 23, 2018 (45:8 Md. R. 419)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-04-23"><cite path="|09|12|01|.14-1G">Regulation .14-1G</cite> amended effective April 23, 2018 (45:8 Md. R. 419)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-04-23"><cite path="|09|12|01|.15|B.">Regulation .15B</cite> amended effective April 23, 2018 (45:8 Md. R. 419)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-12-22"><cite path="|09|12|01|.16">Regulation .16</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective December 22, 2008 (36:2 Md. R. 96); emergency status extended at 36:17 Md. R. 1310; emergency status expired November 19, 2009</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-04-23"><cite path="|09|12|01|.16">Regulation .16</cite> amended effective April 23, 2018 (45:8 Md. R. 419)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-12-22"><cite path="|09|12|01|.16-1">Regulation .16-1</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective December 22, 2008 (36:2 Md. R. 96); emergency status extended at 36:17 Md. R. 1310; emergency status expired November 19, 2009</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-12-26"><cite path="|09|12|01|.16-1">Regulation .16-1</cite> adopted effective December 26, 2011 (38:26 Md. R. 1696)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-04-23"><cite path="|09|12|01|.16-1">Regulation .16-1</cite> amended effective April 23, 2018 (45:8 Md. R. 419)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-04-23"><cite path="|09|12|01|.17">Regulation .17</cite> amended effective April 23, 2018 (45:8 Md. R. 419)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-12-12"><cite path="|09|12|01|.17|C.">Regulation .17C</cite> amended effective December 12, 2002 (29:24 Md. R. 1919)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-04-23"><cite path="|09|12|01|.19">Regulation .19</cite> repealed and new Regulation .19 adopted effective April 23, 2018 (45:8 Md. R. 419)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-04-23"><cite path="|09|12|01|.27|A.">Regulation .27A</cite> amended effective September 29, 2003 (30:19 Md. R. 1331); April 23, 2018 (45:8 Md. R. 419)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-04-23"><cite path="|09|12|01|.27|C.">Regulation .27C</cite> adopted effective April 23, 2018 (45:8 Md. R. 419)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-04-23"><cite path="|09|12|01|.28">Regulation .28</cite> amended effective April 23, 2018 (45:8 Md. R. 419)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-07-16"><cite path="|09|12|01|.28|G.">Regulation .28G</cite> amended effective July 16, 2020 (47:14 Md. R. 675)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-04-23"><cite path="|09|12|01|.28-1">Regulation .28-1</cite> amended effective April 23, 2018 (45:8 Md. R. 419)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-04-23"><cite path="|09|12|01|.28-2B">Regulation .28-2B</cite>, F amended effective April 23, 2018 (45:8 Md. R. 419)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-04-23"><cite path="|09|12|01|.28-3">Regulation .28-3</cite> amended effective April 23, 2018 (45:8 Md. R. 419)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-04-23"><cite path="|09|12|01|.29">Regulation .29</cite> amended effective April 23, 2018 (45:8 Md. R. 419)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-04-23"><cite path="|09|12|01|.34">Regulation .34</cite> amended effective April 23, 2018 (45:8 Md. R. 419)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-04-23"><cite path="|09|12|01|.35">Regulation .35</cite> amended effective April 23, 2018 (45:8 Md. R. 419)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-12-12"><cite path="|09|12|01|.37">Regulation .37</cite> adopted effective December 12, 2002 (29:24 Md. R. 1919)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-12-12"><cite path="|09|12|01|.38">Regulation .38</cite> adopted effective December 12, 2002 (29:24 Md. R. 1919)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
