<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>56</num>
  <heading>Maryland Swimming Pool and Spa Standards ​</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>The purpose of this chapter is to adopt the International Swimming Pool and Spa Code (ISPSC).</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|12|56|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="09|12|56|.02|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>, the Standards shall apply to all swimming pools and spas for which an application for a building permit is received by a local jurisdiction on or after December 31, 2023.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Standards adopted under this chapter do not apply to a swimming pool or spa built and in operation before December 31, 2023, unless there is an alteration or repair that results in a substantial and material structural change to the swimming pool or spa that occurs on or after December 31, 2023.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If there is an alteration or repair to a swimming pool or spa built and in operation before December 31, 2023, that results in a substantial or material structural change, the alteration or repair shall conform to the Standards.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Incorporation by Reference.</heading>
    <text>The 2021 International Swimming Pool and Spa Code (ISPSC), International Code Council, is incorporated by reference.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <text>“Substantial and material structural change” means an alteration or repair that:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Increases the volume of the swimming pool or spa by 15 percent or more; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Decreases the flow capacity of the swimming pool or spa by 15 percent or more.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Amendments.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Chapter 3. Rename Section 305.2 to “Applicability” and replace the text with the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A public swimming pool or spa shall be surrounded by a barrier that complies with Sections 305.2.1 through 305.7, except that the top of the barrier where measured on the side of the barrier that faces away from the swimming pool or spa shall be not less than:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>72 inches (1828mm) above grade for a Class A, B, or D swimming pool or spa;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>60 inches (1524mm) above grade for a Class C or E swimming pool or spa; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>36 inches (914.4mm) above grade for a wading pool.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Non-public outdoor swimming pools and spas and indoor swimming pools shall be surrounded by a barrier that complies with Sections 305.2.1 through 305.7.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In Section 307.1.4, where “International Building Code” appears, substitute “Maryland Accessibility Code” and, where “ICC A117.1” appears, substitute “Maryland Accessibility Code”.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>In Section 324.7.1, where “International Fire Code” appears, substitute “Maryland State Fire Prevention Code.”</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Public Safety Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|12-1203">12-1203</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|12-1207">12-1207</cite>(a)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|2">2</cite>), Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2024-01-22">Effective date: January 22, 2024 (51:1 Md. R. 16)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
