<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>81</num>
  <heading>Elevator, Escalator, and Chairlift Safety</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Safety Code for Elevators and Escalators.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Scope.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The following sections set out the dates on which ANSI/ASME codes and supplements as required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|12-805">Public Safety Article, §12-805, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, became effective.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The applicable adopted safety code will be contingent upon the date the contract to install an elevator unit is signed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Documentation verifying the contract date shall be provided as part of the registration process.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The elevator unit shall undergo a final acceptance inspection within 3 years of the contract date or the next subsequent adopted safety code shall be applied.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Requirements prescribed at the time of the initial elevator certification remain in effect.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Frequency of inspection requirements set forth in ANSI Code shall be performed annually, according to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|12-812">Public Safety Article, §12-812, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The American Standard Safety Code for Elevators, Dumbwaiters, Escalators, and Moving Walks, ANSI A17.1—1971 and its supplements, are effective on the dates indicated:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>ANSI A17.1—1971 is effective March 7, 1973;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>ANSI A17.1a—1972 is effective May 23, 1974;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>ANSI A17.1b—1973 is effective January 1, 1975;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>ANSI A17.1c—1974 is effective January 1, 1975;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>ANSI A17.1d—1975 is effective October 31, 1975;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>ANSI A17.1e—1975 is effective October 31, 1975;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>ANSI A17.1f—1975 is effective October 31, 1975;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>ANSI A17.1g—1976 is effective November 30, 1976.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The American Standard Safety Code for Elevators, Dumbwaiters, Escalators, and Moving Walks, ANSI A17.1—1978 and its supplements, are effective on the dates indicated:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>ANSI A17.1—1978 is effective September 15, 1978;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>ANSI A17.1a—1979 is effective June 30, 1979;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>ANSI A17.1b—1980 is effective August 15, 1980.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The ANSI/ASME A17.1 Safety Code for Elevators and Escalators, ANSI/ASME A17.1—1981 and its supplements, are effective on the dates indicated:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>ANSI/ASME A17.1—1981 is effective April 22, 1982;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>ANSI/ASME A17.1a—1982 is effective May 30, 1983;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>ANSI/ASME A17.1b—1983 is effective June 23, 1984.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The ANSI/ASME A17.1 Safety Code for Elevators and Escalators, ANSI/ASME A17.1—1984 and its supplements, are effective on the dates indicated:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>ANSI/ASME A17.1—1984 is effective March 16, 1985;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>ANSI/ASME A17.1a—1985 is effective October 15, 1985;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>ANSI/ASME A17.1b—1985 is effective April 15, 1986;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>ANSI/ASME A17.1c—1986 is effective October 31, 1986;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>ANSI/ASME A17.1d—1986 is effective May 31, 1987;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>ANSI/ASME A17.1e—1987 is effective October 30, 1987.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The ASME/ANSI A17.1 Safety Code for Elevators and Escalators, ASME/ANSI A17.1—1987 and its supplements, are effective on the dates indicated:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>ASME/ANSI A17.1—1987 is effective July 16, 1988;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>ASME/ANSI A17.1a—1988 is effective May 16, 1989;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>ASME/ANSI A17.1b—1989 is effective May 31, 1990.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>ASME A17.1-1990 Safety Code for Elevators and Escalators and Supplements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The ASME A17.1-1990 Safety Code for Elevators and Escalators, excluding Parts V, XXI, and XXIII, is incorporated by reference and is effective October 14, 1991, with the following changes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>On page 87, delete the text under Rule 211.3b Smoke Detectors, and insert in its place the following:</text>
          <include>
            <text>211.3b Smoke Detectors. Smoke detectors shall be installed in each elevator lobby at each landing and associated machine room in accordance with NFPA 72E, Chapter 4. Smoke detectors are not required in elevator lobbies at unenclosed landings. Smoke detectors may be installed in any hoistway and shall be installed in hoistways which are sprinklered (see Rule 102.2).</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>The activation of a smoke detector in any elevator lobby, other than at the designated level, shall cause all cars that serve that lobby to return nonstop to the designated level. The activation of a smoke detector in any elevator machine room shall cause all elevators having any equipment located in that machine room, and any associated elevators of a group automatic operation, to return nonstop to the designated level. The activation of a smoke detector in any elevator hoistway shall cause all elevators having any equipment located in the hoistway, and any associated elevators of a group automatic operation, to return nonstop to the designated level. The operation shall conform to the requirements of Rule 211.3a.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>If the smoke detector at the designated level is activated, the operation shall conform to the requirements of Rule 211.3a, except that the cars shall return to an alternate level approved by the enforcing authority, unless the designated-level three-position Phase I switch (Rule 211.3a) is in the "ON" position.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>If required by the fire authority having jurisdiction, Phase I recall may be initiated by a local protective signaling system (ANSI/NFPA 72A) rather than by the means specified in Rule 211.3b(1) and (2).</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Elevators shall only react to the first smoke detector zone which is activated for that group.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>Phase I operation, when initiated by a smoke detector, shall be maintained until cancelled by moving the Phase I Switch to the "BYPASS" position (also see Rule 211.3a(10)). Smoke detectors and/or smoke detector systems shall not be self-resetting.</text>
              <text>NOTE (Rule 211.3b): In buildings with fire alarm systems, see NFPA 72A for additional information.</text>
            </para>
          </include>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>On page 163, delete the text under Rule 1000.1 Persons Authorized to Make Inspections and Tests, and insert in its place the following:</text>
          <include>
            <text>The inspector shall meet the qualification requirements of the ASME QEI-1.</text>
          </include>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>On page 163, delete the text under Rule 1000.1b(1) and (2) Periodic Inspection and Tests, and insert in its place the following:</text>
          <include>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Periodic inspections and tests shall be witnessed by an inspector employed by the authority having jurisdiction or by a person authorized by the authority having jurisdiction, except as specified in Rule 1000.1b(3).</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>The owner or his authorized agent shall have all of the tests required by §§1002, 1005, 1008, and 1010 made by a person qualified to perform such service in the presence of an inspector employed by the authority having jurisdiction or by a person authorized by the authority having jurisdiction, except as specified in Rule 1000.1b(3).</text>
            </para>
          </include>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>On page 164, delete the text under Rule 1001.1 Inspection and Test Periods, and insert in its place the following:</text>
          <include>
            <text>The routine inspection and tests of passenger and freight electric elevators shall be made at intervals not longer than 1 year.</text>
            <text>NOTE: See Rule 1010.2 for private residence elevators.</text>
          </include>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>On page 169, delete the text under Rule 1004.1 Inspection and Test Periods, and insert in its place the following:</text>
          <include>
            <text>The routine inspection and tests of passenger and freight hydraulic elevators shall be made at intervals not longer than 1 year.</text>
            <text>NOTE: See Rule 1010.2 for private residence elevators.</text>
          </include>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>On page 171, delete the text under Rule 1007.1 Inspections and Test Periods, and insert in its place the following:</text>
          <include>
            <text>Routine inspections and tests of escalators and moving walks shall be made at intervals not longer than 1 year.</text>
          </include>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>On page 264, delete the text under Rule 2000.10b(2) Attendant Operation, and insert in its place the following:</text>
          <include>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>The attendant shall operate the lift by means of a continuous-pressure key switch so located that the attendant has full view of the floor area under the lift and full view of the lift throughout its travel. A manually reset emergency stop switch shall also be provided at that location.</text>
            </para>
          </include>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>On page 264, delete the text under Rule 2001.1b Clearances, and insert in its place the following:</text>
          <include>
            <text>Clearances between the platform and adjacent surfaces shall not be less than 3/4 inch (19 mm). At no point in its travel shall the edge of the platform facing the upper landing be more than 12 inches (305 mm) above a step or landing as measured vertically.</text>
          </include>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>On pages 266 and 267, delete the text under Rule 2001.6c(1) Platform Guarding, and insert in its place the following:</text>
          <include>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>The platform shall be equipped with a self-closing door at least 42 inches (1,067 mm) high on the sides of access to the upper and lower landings. The self-closing door shall be of solid construction and provided with a combination mechanical lock and electric contact and shall only be operable within 2 inches (51 mm) of the upper and lower landings. It may permit the platform to move if the door or gate is in the closed position, but not locked, provided the device will stop the platform if the door or gate fails to lock before the platform has moved more than 2 inches (51 mm) away from the landing.</text>
              <text>The platform side guards on the sides not used for access or exit shall be of smooth construction to a height of 42 inches (1,067 mm) above the platform with no openings, other than those necessary for operation. Openings necessary for operation shall reject a ball 1/2 inches (13 mm) in diameter. A grab rail extending the full length of either side guard shall be provided at a height of 36 inches (914 mm). The running clearance between the side guards and the enclosure shall be not less than 2 inches (51 mm) nor more than 3 inches (76 mm).</text>
            </para>
          </include>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>On page 268, delete the text under Rule 2001.10b(2) Attendant Operation, and insert in its place the following:</text>
          <include>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>The attendant shall operate the lift by means of a continuous-pressure key switch located in a control box on the free end of a detachable, flexible cord not more than 5 feet (1,524 mm) in length. A manually reset emergency stop switch shall also be provided in the control box.</text>
            </para>
          </include>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>On page 268, delete the text under Rule 2001.10b(4) Attendant Operation, and insert in its place the following:</text>
          <include>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>When the equipment operates on a straight flight of stairs, and the platform is within sight during its entire travel, the attendant shall operate the unit from the bottom of the stairs.</text>
            </para>
          </include>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>On page 270, delete the text under Rule 2002.6d Footrest Clearance, and insert in its place the following:</text>
          <include>
            <text>At no point in its travel shall the edge of the footrest facing the upper landing be more than 12 inches (305 mm) above the step or landing as measured vertically.</text>
          </include>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>On pages 289—293, delete the text under Part XXIII, Rooftop Elevators, and insert in its place the following:</text>
          <include>
            <text>A rooftop elevator shall be inspected, tested, and maintained in accordance with the applicable provisions of the A17.1 Code.</text>
          </include>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>ASME A17.1a—1991, the Addenda to ASME A17.1—1990 Safety Code for Elevators and Escalators, is incorporated by reference and is effective August 29, 1992.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>ASME A17.1b—1992, the Addenda to ASME A17.1—1990 Safety Code for Elevators and Escalators.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>ASME A17.1b—1992 is incorporated by reference and is effective July 5, 1993.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Errata to ASME A17.1b—1992 is incorporated by reference and is effective October 11, 1993.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>ASME A17.1—1993—Safety Code for Elevators and Escalators and Supplements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The ASME A17.1—1993 Safety Code for Elevators and Escalators, excluding Parts V, XXI, and XXIII, is incorporated by reference and is effective July 18, 1994, with the following changes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>On page 27, delete the text under Rule 106.1b(3) Design and Construction of Pits and insert in its place the following:</text>
          <include>
            <text>Drains connected directly to sewers may not be installed in elevator pits. Sumps, with or without pumps, may be installed. Where the accumulation of water is reasonably likely and a drain is not installed, a sump pump shall be provided.</text>
          </include>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>On page 87, delete the text under Rule 211.3b Smoke Detectors, and insert in its place the following:</text>
          <include>
            <text>211.3b Smoke Detectors. Smoke detectors shall be installed in each elevator lobby at each landing and associated machine room in accordance with NFPA 72, Chapter 5-3. Smoke detectors are not required in elevator lobbies at unenclosed landings. Smoke detectors may be installed in any hoistway and shall be installed in hoistways which are sprinklered (see Rule 102.2).</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>The activation of a smoke detector in any elevator lobby, other than at the designated level, shall cause all cars that serve that lobby to return nonstop to the designated level. The activation of a smoke detector in any elevator machine room shall cause all elevators having any equipment located in that machine room, and any associated elevators of a group automatic operation, to return nonstop to the designated level. The activation of a smoke detector in any elevator hoistway shall cause all elevators having any equipment located in the hoistway, and any associated elevators of a group automatic operation, to return nonstop to the designated level, except that smoke detectors in hoistways installed at or below the lowest landing of recall, when activated, shall cause the car to be sent to the upper level of recall. The operation shall conform to the requirements of Rule 211.3a.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>If the smoke detector at the designated level is activated, the operation shall conform to the requirements of Rule 211.3a, except that the cars shall return to an alternate level approved by the enforcing authority, unless the designated level three-position Phase I switch (Rule 211.3a) is in the "ON" position.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>If required by the fire authority having jurisdiction, Phase I recall may be initiated by a local protective signaling system (ANSI/NFPA 72A) rather than by the means specified in Rule 211.3b(1) and (2).</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Elevators shall only react to the first smoke detector zone which is activated for that group.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>Phase I operation, when initiated by a smoke detector, shall be maintained until cancelled by moving the Phase I Switch to the "BYPASS" position (also see Rule 211.3a(10)). Smoke detectors and/or smoke detector systems, shall not be self-resetting.</text>
              <text>NOTE (Rule 211.3b): In buildings with fire alarm systems, see NFPA 72A for additional information.</text>
            </para>
          </include>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b-1)</num>
          <text>On page 148, delete the text under Rule 802.3f Skirt Panels and insert in its place the following:</text>
          <include>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>The height of the skirt above the tread nose line shall be at least 1 in. (25mm) measured vertically.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>The skirt panel shall not deflect more than 1/16 in. (1.6mm) under a force of 150 lbf (667 N).</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>The exposed surfaces of the skirt panels adjacent to the steps shall be smooth except where a brush safety strip or similar device approved by the Commissioner of Labor and Industry is used and shall be made from a low friction material or treated with a friction reducing material.</text>
            </para>
          </include>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>On page 165, delete the text under Rule 1000.1 Persons Authorized to Make Inspections and Tests, and insert in its place the following:</text>
          <include>
            <text>The inspector shall meet the qualification requirements of the ASME QEI-1.</text>
          </include>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>On page 165, delete the text under Rule 1000.1b(1) and (2) Periodic Inspection and Tests, and insert in its place the following:</text>
          <include>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Periodic inspections and tests shall be witnessed by an inspector employed by the authority having jurisdiction or by a person authorized by the authority having jurisdiction, except as specified in Rule 1000.1b(3).</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>The owner or the owner's authorized agent shall have all of the tests required by §§1002, 1005, 1008, and 1010 made by a person qualified to perform the service in the presence of an inspector employed by the authority having jurisdiction or by a person authorized by the authority having jurisdiction, except as specified in Rule 1000.1b(3).</text>
            </para>
          </include>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>On page 166, delete the text under Rule 1001.1 Inspection and Test Periods, and insert in its place the following:</text>
          <include>
            <text>The routine inspection and tests of passenger and freight electric elevators shall be made at intervals not longer than 1 year.</text>
            <text>NOTE: See Rule 1010.2 for private residence elevators.</text>
          </include>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>On page 172, delete the text under Rule 1004.1 Inspection and Test Periods, and insert in its place the following:</text>
          <text>The routine inspection and tests of passenger and freight hydraulic elevators shall be made at intervals not longer than 1 year.</text>
          <text>NOTE: See Rule 1010.2 for private residence elevators.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>On page 174, delete the text under Rule 1007.1 Inspections and Test Periods, and insert in its place the following:</text>
          <include>
            <text>Routine inspections and tests of escalators and moving walks shall be made at intervals not longer than 1 year.</text>
          </include>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>On page 177, delete the text under Rule 1010.10 Wheelchair Lifts, and insert in its place the following:</text>
          <include>
            <text>Vertical wheelchair lifts, inclined wheelchair lifts, and inclined stairway chairlifts shall be subject to the applicable routine, periodic, and acceptance inspections and tests specified in §§1000—1006. Routine inspections and tests shall be performed at intervals not longer than 1 year.</text>
            <text>The inspection and test requirements shall apply to the corresponding requirements of Part XX. Any additional requirements for this equipment shall also be checked during these inspections and tests.</text>
          </include>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>On page 208, delete the text under §1217 Rooftop Elevators, and insert in its place the following:</text>
          <include>
            <text>Where any alteration is made to a rooftop elevator, the entire installation shall comply with the applicable provisions of the A17.1 Code.</text>
          </include>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>On page 270, delete the text under Rule 2000.10b(2) Attendant Operation, and insert in its place the following:</text>
          <include>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>The attendant shall operate the lift by means of a continuous-pressure key switch so located that the attendant has full view of the floor area under the lift and full view of the lift throughout its travel. A manually reset emergency stop switch shall also be provided at that location.</text>
            </para>
          </include>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>On page 271, delete the text under Rule 2001.1b Clearances, and insert in its place the following:</text>
          <include>
            <text>Clearances between the platform and adjacent surfaces may not be less than 3/4 inches (19 mm). At no point in its travel shall the edge of the platform facing the upper landing be more than 12 inches (305 mm) above a step or landing as measured vertically.</text>
          </include>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>On pages 272 and 273, delete the text under Rule 2001.6c(1) Platform Guarding, and insert in its place the following:</text>
          <include>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>The platform shall be equipped with a self-closing door at least 42 inches (1,067 mm) high on the sides of access to the upper and lower landings. The self-closing door shall be of solid construction and provided with a combination mechanical lock and electric contact and shall only be operable within 2 inches (51 mm) of the upper and lower landings. It may permit the platform to move if the door or gate is in the closed position, but not locked, provided the device will stop the platform if the door or gate fails to lock before the platform has moved more than 2 inches (51 mm) away from the landing. The platform side guards on the sides not used for access or exit shall be of smooth construction to a height of 42 inches (1,067 mm) above the platform with no openings, other than those necessary for operation. Openings necessary for operation shall reject a ball 1/2 inch (13 mm) in diameter. A grab rail extending the full length of either side guard shall be provided at a height of 36 inches (914 mm). The running clearance between the side guards and the enclosure shall be not less than 2 inches (51 mm) nor more than 3 inches (76 mm).</text>
            </para>
          </include>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>On page 274, delete the text under Rule 2001.10b(2) Attendant Operation, and insert in its place the following:</text>
          <include>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>The attendant shall operate the lift by means of a continuous-pressure key switch located in a control box on the free end of a detachable, flexible cord not more than 5 feet (1,524 mm) in length. A manually reset emergency stop switch shall also be provided in the control box.</text>
            </para>
          </include>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(n)</num>
          <text>On page 274, delete the text under Rule 2001.10b(4) Attendant Operation, and insert in its place the following:</text>
          <include>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>When the equipment operates on a straight flight of stairs, and the platform is within sight during its entire travel, the attendant shall operate the unit from the bottom of the stairs.</text>
            </para>
          </include>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(o)</num>
          <text>On page 276, delete the text under Rule 2002.6d Footrest Clearance, and insert in its place the following:</text>
          <include>
            <text>At no point in its travel shall the edge of the footrest facing the upper landing be more than 12 inches (305 mm) above the step or landing as measured vertically.</text>
          </include>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(p)</num>
          <text>On pages 295—299, delete the text under Part XXIII, Rooftop Elevators, and insert in its place the following:</text>
          <include>
            <text>A rooftop elevator shall be inspected, tested, and maintained in accordance with the applicable provisions of the A17.1 Code.</text>
          </include>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>ASME A17.1a-1994 Addenda to ASME A17.1-1993 Safety Code for Elevators and Escalators, excluding Part V, is incorporated by reference and is effective August 24, 1995.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The ASME A17.1b-1995 Addenda to ASME A17.1-1993 Safety Code for Elevators and Escalators, excluding Parts V and XXI, is incorporated by reference and is effective March 24, 1997, with the following changes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>On page 87, insert the following under Rule 211.3b:</text>
          <include>
            <para>
              <num>(6)</num>
              <text>If required by the fire authority having jurisdiction, Phase I recall may be initiated by a local protective signaling system (NFPA 72), within the zone in which the elevator is located, in addition to the means specified in Rule 211.3b(1) and (2).</text>
            </para>
          </include>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>On page 166, delete the text under Rule 1001.1 Inspection and Test Periods, and insert in its place the following:</text>
          <include>
            <text>The routine inspection and tests of passenger and freight electric elevators shall be made at intervals not longer than 1 year. All references to Items are to Items in A17.2.1, Inspectors' Manual for Electric Elevators.</text>
          </include>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>On page 174.1, delete the text under Rule 1007.1 Inspections and Test Periods, and insert in its place the following:</text>
          <include>
            <text>Routine inspections and tests of escalators and moving walks shall be made at intervals not longer than 1 year. All references to Items are to Items in A17.2.3, Inspectors' Manual for Escalators and Moving Walks.</text>
          </include>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>On page 324.5, delete the text under Rule 2501.12(a).</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>ASME A17.1-1996—Safety Code for Elevators and Escalators and Supplements. The ASME A17.1-1996 Safety Code for Elevators and Escalators, excluding Parts V, XXI, and XXIII, is incorporated by reference and is effective April 6, 1998, with the following changes:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>On page 31, delete the text under Rule 106.1b(3) Design and Construction of Pits, and insert in its place the following:</text>
        <include>
          <text>Drains connected directly to sewers may not be installed in elevator pits. Sumps, with or without pumps, may be installed. Where the accumulation of water is reasonably likely and a drain is not installed, a sump pump shall be provided.</text>
        </include>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>On page 90, under Rule 210.14 Inspection Operation With Hoistway-Door Electric Contact or Car-Door Electric Contact Open, before the NOTE, insert the following paragraph:</text>
        <include>
          <text>A warning device, either audible or visual, mounted on the elevator controller must be activated when the switches are in the "bypass" position.</text>
        </include>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>On page 92, insert the following under Rule 211.3b Smoke Detectors:</text>
        <include>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>If required by the fire authority having jurisdiction, Phase I recall shall be initiated by a local protective signaling system (NFPA 72) within the zone in which the elevator is located, in addition to the means specified in Rule 211.3b(1) and (2).</text>
          </para>
        </include>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>On page 158, delete the text under Rule 802.3f Skirt Panels, and insert in its place the following:</text>
        <include>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The height of the skirt above the tread nose line shall be at least 1 inch (25mm) measured vertically.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The skirt panel may not deflect more than 1/16 inch (1.6mm) under a force of 150 lbf (667 N).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>The exposed surfaces of the skirt panels adjacent to the steps shall be smooth, except where a brush safety strip or similar device approved by the Commissioner of Labor and Industry is used, and shall be made from a low friction material or treated with a friction reducing material.</text>
          </para>
        </include>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>On page 177, delete the text under Rule 1000.1 Persons Authorized to Make Inspections and Tests, and insert in its place the following:</text>
        <include>
          <text>The inspector shall meet the qualification requirements of the ASME QEI-1.</text>
        </include>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>On page 177, delete the text under Rule 1000.1b(1) and (2) Periodic Inspection and Tests, and insert in its place the following:</text>
        <include>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Periodic inspections and tests shall be witnessed by an inspector employed by the authority having jurisdiction or by a person authorized by the authority having jurisdiction, except as specified in Rule 1000.1b(3).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The owner or the owner's authorized agent shall have all of the tests required by §§1002, 1005, 1008, and 1010 made by a person qualified to perform that service in the presence of an inspector employed by the authority having jurisdiction or by a person authorized by the authority having jurisdiction, except as specified in Rule 1001.b(3).</text>
          </para>
        </include>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>On page 178, delete the text under Rule 1001.1 Inspection and Test Periods, and insert in its place the following:</text>
        <include>
          <text>The routine inspection and tests of passenger and freight electric elevators shall be made at intervals not longer than 1 year.</text>
          <text>NOTE: See Rule 1010.2 for private residence elevators.</text>
        </include>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>On page 184, delete the text under Rule 1004.1 Inspection and Test Periods, and insert in its place the following:</text>
        <include>
          <text>The routine inspection and tests of passenger and freight hydraulic elevators shall be made at intervals not longer than 1 year.</text>
          <text>NOTE: See Rule 1010.2 for private residence elevators.</text>
        </include>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>On page 187, delete the text under Rule 1007.1 Inspections and Test Periods, and insert in its place the following:</text>
        <include>
          <text>Routine inspections and tests of escalators and moving walks shall be made at intervals not longer than 1 year.</text>
        </include>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>On page 191, delete the text under Rule 1010.10 Wheelchair Lifts, and insert in its place the following:</text>
        <include>
          <text>Vertical wheelchair lifts, inclined wheelchair lifts, and inclined stairway chairlifts shall be subject to the applicable routine, periodic, and acceptance inspections and tests specified in §§1000—1006. Routine inspections and tests shall be performed at intervals not longer than 1 year.</text>
          <text>The inspection and test requirements shall apply to the corresponding requirements of Part XX. Any additional requirements for this equipment shall also be checked during these inspections and tests.</text>
        </include>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>On page 223, delete the text under §1217 Rooftop Elevators, and insert in its place the following:</text>
        <include>
          <text>Where any alteration is made to a rooftop elevator, the entire installation shall comply with the applicable provisions of the A17.1 Code.</text>
        </include>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>On page 284, delete the text under Rule 2000.10b(2) Attendant Operation, and insert in its place the following:</text>
        <include>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The attendant shall operate the lift by means of a key-activated continuous-pressure switch so located that the attendant has full view of the floor area under the lift and full view of the lift throughout its travel. A manually reset emergency stop switch shall also be provided at that location.</text>
          </para>
        </include>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>On page 285, delete the text under Rule 2001.1b Clearances, and insert in its place the following:</text>
        <include>
          <text>Clearances between the platform and adjacent surfaces may not be less than 3/4 inches (19 mm). At no point in its travel shall the edge of the platform facing the upper landing be more than 12 inches (305 mm) above a step or landing as measured vertically.</text>
        </include>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>On page 287, delete the text under Rule 2001.6c(1) Platform Guarding, and insert in its place the following:</text>
        <include>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The platform shall be equipped with a self-closing door at least 42 inches (1067 mm) high on the sides of access to the upper and lower landings. The self-closing door shall be of solid construction and provided with a combination mechanical lock and electric contact and shall only be operable within 2 inches (51 mm) of the upper and lower landings. It may permit the platform to move if the door or gate is in the closed position, but not locked, provided the device will stop the platform if the door or gate fails to lock before the platform has moved more than 2 inches (51 mm) away from the landing. The platform side guards on the sides not used for access or exit shall be of smooth construction to a height of 42 inches (1,067 mm) above the platform with no openings, other than those necessary for operation. Openings necessary for operation shall reject a ball 1/2 inch (13 mm) in diameter. A grab rail extending the full length of either side guard shall be provided at a height of 36 inches (914 mm). The running clearance between the side guards and the enclosure shall be not less than 2 inches (51 mm).</text>
          </para>
        </include>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>On page 289, delete the text under Rule 2001.10b(2) Attendant Operation, and insert in its place the following:</text>
        <include>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The attendant shall operate the lift by means of a key-activated continuous-pressure switch located in a control box on the free end of a detachable, flexible cord not more than 5 feet (1,524 mm) in length. A manually reset emergency stop switch shall also be provided in the control box.</text>
          </para>
        </include>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>On page 289, delete the text under Rule 2001.10b(4) Attendant Operation, and insert in its place the following:</text>
        <include>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Where the equipment operates on a straight flight of stairs, and the platform is within sight during its entire travel, the attendant shall operate the unit from the bottom of the stairs.</text>
          </para>
        </include>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>On page 291, delete the text under Rule 2002.6d Footrest Clearance, and insert in its place the following:</text>
        <include>
          <text>At no point in its travel shall the edge of the footrest facing the upper landing be more than 12 inches (305 mm) above the step or landing as measured vertically.</text>
        </include>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>On pages 309 through 313, delete the text under Part XXIII, Rooftop Elevators, and insert in its place the following:</text>
        <include>
          <text>A rooftop elevator shall be inspected, tested, and maintained in accordance with the applicable provisions of the A17.1 Code.</text>
        </include>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>On page 341, delete the text under Rule 2501.12(a).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>ASME A17.1a-1997 Addenda to ASME A17.1-1996 Safety Code for Elevators and Escalators, excluding Part V, is incorporated by reference and is effective December 28, 1998.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>ASME A17.1b-1998 Addenda to ASME A17.1-1996 Safety Code for Elevators and Escalators is incorporated by reference and is effective August 23, 1999.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>ASME A17.1c-1999 Addenda to ASME A17.1-1996 Safety Code for Elevators and Escalators is incorporated by reference and is effective April 1, 2002.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>ASME A17.1d-2000 Addenda to ASME A17.1-1996 Safety Code for Elevators and Escalators is incorporated by reference and is effective April 1, 2002.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>ASME A17.1-2000 Safety Code for Elevators and Escalators. The ASME A17.1-2000 Safety Code for Elevators and Escalators, excluding Sections 5.3, 5.4, 5.6, and 5.8, is incorporated by reference with the following change: On page 374, delete the text under Rule 8.11.1.3 Periodic Inspection and Test Frequency, and insert in its place the following: Periodic inspections and tests shall be made at intervals not longer than 1 year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>O.</num>
      <text>ASME A17.1a-2002 Addenda to ASME A17.1-2000 Safety Code for Elevators and Escalators is incorporated by reference.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>P.</num>
      <text>ASME A17.1b-2003 Addenda to ASME A17.1-2000 Safety Code for Elevators and Escalators is incorporated by reference.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>Q.</num>
      <text>ASME A17.1-2004 Safety Code for Elevators and Escalators. The ASME A17.1-2004 Safety Code for Elevators and Escalators, excluding Sections 5.3, 5.4, 5.6, 5.8, and 5.9, is incorporated by reference.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>R.</num>
      <text>ASME A17.1a-2005 Addenda to ASME A17.1-2004 Safety Code for Elevators and Escalators, excluding Sections 5.3, 5.4, 5.6, 5.8, and 5.9, is incorporated by reference.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>S.</num>
      <text>ASME A17.1S-2005 Supplement to ASME A17.1-2004 Safety Code for Elevators and Escalators is incorporated by reference.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>T.</num>
      <text>The ASME A17.1-2007/CSA B44-07 Safety Code for Elevators and Escalators, excluding Sections 5.6, 5.8, and 5.9, is incorporated by reference.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>U.</num>
      <text>ASME A17.1a-2008/CSA B44a-08 Addenda to ASME A17.1-2007/CSA B44-07 Safety Code for Elevators and Escalators is incorporated by reference.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>V.</num>
      <text>ASME A17.1b-2009/CSA B44b-09 Addenda to ASME A17.1-2007/CSA B44-07 Safety Code for Elevators and Escalators is incorporated by reference.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>W.</num>
      <text>ASME A17.1-2010/CSA B44-10 (Revision of ASME A17.1-2007 and CSA B44-07) Safety Code for Elevators and Escalators, excluding Sections 5.6, 5.8, and 5.9, is incorporated by reference.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>X.</num>
      <text>Repealed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>Y.</num>
      <text>Repealed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>Z.</num>
      <text>ASME A17.1-2013/CSA B44-13 (Revision of ASME A17.1-2010/CSA B44-10) Safety Code for Elevators and Escalators is incorporated by reference.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>AA.</num>
      <text>ASME A17.1-2016/CSA B44-16 (Revision of ASME A17.1-2013 and CSA B44-13) Safety Code for Elevators and Escalators is incorporated by reference.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>BB.</num>
      <text>ASME A17.8-2016/CSA B44.8-16 Standard for wind turbine tower elevators is incorporated by reference.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>CC.</num>
      <text>Article 620 Elevators, Dumbwaiters, Escalators, Moving Walks, Platform Lifts, and Stairway Chairlifts of the National Electric Code (NFPA 70), which is incorporated by reference in <cite path="09.12.50.02">COMAR 09.12.50.02</cite>-1B(3).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>DD.</num>
      <text>ASME A17.1-2019/CSA B44-19 (Revision of ASME A17.1-2016 and CSA B44-16) Safety Code for Elevators and Escalators is incorporated by reference.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01-1</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"First aid" has the meaning stated in 29 CFR §1904.7(b)(5)(ii).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Incident" means an event that results in significant property damage or a major operational malfunction that is not consistent with manufacturer specifications.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Incident report" means a completed Division of Labor and Industry incident record form.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Inclined platform lift" means a hoisting and lowering mechanism equipped with a platform and seat that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Moves in guides in a diagonal plane from one level to another with limited travel, operating speed, and platform area; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is intended for transportation of mobility-impaired persons.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Inspection report" means a completed Division of Labor and Industry inspection report form.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Passenger elevator" means an elevator used primarily to carry persons other than the operator and persons necessary for loading and unloading.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Qualified" means a person who, by possession of a recognized degree in an applicable field or certificate of professional standing, or who, by extensive knowledge, training, and experience, has successfully demonstrated the ability to solve problems relating to elevator safety.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Safety Code" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|12-801">Public Safety Article, §12-801, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"Serious injury" means an injury that requires medical treatment by a physician other than one-time first aid, which other treatment does not include diagnostic procedures such as x-ray after the one time treatment, even if provided by a physician.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Serious injury record" means a completed Division of Labor and Industry serious injury record form.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>"Test report" means a completed Division of Labor and Industry test report form.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>"Third-Party Qualified Elevator Inspector Report and Checklist" means a completed Division of Labor and Industry Third-Party Qualified Elevator Inspector Report and Checklist form.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>"Vertical platform lift" means a hoisting and lowering mechanism equipped with a partially enclosed platform that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Moves in guides in a substantially vertical direction with limited travel, operating speed, and platform area; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is intended for transportation of mobility-impaired persons.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>"Witness", as it appears in the Safety Code, means to observe or to verify that testing has been performed by a qualified individual in accordance with the Safety Code.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|12|81|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Safety Standard for Platform Lifts and Stairway Chairlifts.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Scope.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The following sections set out the dates on which ANSI/ASME codes and supplements for platform lifts and stairway chairlifts, as required by <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|12-805">Public Safety Article, §12-805, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, became effective.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Requirements prescribed at the time of the initial platform lift and stairway chairlift certification remain in effect.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>ASME A18.1-1999 Safety Standard for Platform Lifts and Stairway Chairlifts is incorporated by reference and is effective April 1, 2002.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>ASME A18.1a-2001 Addenda to ASME A18.1-1999 Safety Standard for Platform Lifts and Stairway Chairlifts is incorporated by reference, as amended, and is effective March 4, 2013.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>ASME A18.1b-2001 Addenda to ASME A18.1-1999 Safety Standard for Platform Lifts and Stairway Chairlifts is incorporated by reference, as amended, and is effective March 4, 2013.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>ASME A18.1-2003 (Revision of ASME A18.1-1999) Safety Standard for Platform Lifts and Stairway Chairlifts is incorporated by reference, as amended, and is effective March 4, 2013.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>ASME A18.1-2005 (Revision of ASME A18.1-2003) Safety Standard for Platform Lifts and Stairway Chairlifts is incorporated by reference, as amended, and is effective March 4, 2013.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>ASME A18.1-2008 (Revision of ASME A18.1-2005) Safety Standard for Platform Lifts and Stairway Chairlifts is incorporated by reference, as amended, and is effective March 4, 2013.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>ASME A18.1-2011 (Revision of ASME A18.1-2008) Safety Standard for Platform Lifts and Stairway Chairlifts is incorporated by reference.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>ASME A18.1-2014 (Revision of ASME A18.1-2011) Safety Standard for Platform Lifts and Stairway Chairlifts is incorporated by reference.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>ASME A18.1-2017 (Revision of ASME A18.1-2014) Safety Standard for Platform Lifts and Stairway Chairlifts is incorporated by reference.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>ASME A18.1-2020 (Revision of ASME A18.1-2017) Safety Standard for Platform Lifts and Stairway Chairlifts is incorporated by reference.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>In addition to the requirements of Part XX, Inclined Stairway Chairlifts and Inclined and Vertical Wheelchair Lifts, of the A17.1-Safety Code for Elevators, and the requirements of ASME A18.1-1999 Safety Standard for Platform Lifts and Stairway Chairlifts, and all subsequent amendments, §<cite path="09|12|81|.02|F.">§CF of this regulation</cite> apply.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>General Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Vertical and inclined wheelchair lifts and inclined stairway chairlifts may be used only by physically handicapped individuals, and may not be modified from their intended use.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A sign, indicating that the lift is for use by the physically handicapped only, shall be posted at the top and bottom landings of the lift runway.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Disconnecting Device.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A main line disconnecting device lockable only in the "OFF" position shall be provided.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The disconnecting device shall be located within view of the lift motor.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Vertical Wheelchair Lift.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Adequate car illumination shall be provided during lift operation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An attendant-operated lift shall be operated by a key-activated continuous-pressure switch.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Inclined Wheelchair Lift.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The edge of the lift's foot rest, facing the upper landing, may not extend more than 12 inches above a step or landing as measured vertically.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Self-Closing Door.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The platform shall be equipped with a self-closing door on the sides of access to the upper and lower landings.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The self-closing door shall be operable within 2 inches of the upper and lower landings.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A lift shall be provided with a permanently attached folding seat and seatbelt to accommodate a person not in a wheelchair.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Attendant Operation.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An attendant-operated lift shall be operated by a key-activated continuous-pressure switch.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>When the equipment operates on a straight flight of stairs and the platform is within sight during its entire travel, the attendant shall operate the unit from the bottom of the stairs.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Inclined Stairway Chairlift. The edge of the lift's foot rest, facing the upper landing, may not extend more than 12 inches above a step or landing as measured vertically.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|12|81|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Notice of Planned Completion.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>At least 60 days before the planned completion of an elevator, dumbwaiter, escalator, or moving walk, an owner or lessee shall provide the Commissioner with written notice of the planned completion, which shall contain the following information:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Contractor name, contact person, address, telephone number, and fax number;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Site name, address, and telephone number;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Type of elevator, dumbwaiter, escalator, or moving walk;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Date of planned completion;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Name of manufacturer; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Tentative date of use.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Waiver of 60-Day Notice Requirement.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If emergency or unusual circumstances are established by the owner or lessee, the Commissioner shall waive the 60-day notice requirement of <cite path="09|12|81|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>To obtain a waiver, the owner or lessee shall file a written waiver request with the Commissioner:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>As soon as the emergency or unusual circumstances arise; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Containing a detailed explanation of the emergency or unusual circumstances.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>If the Commissioner grants a waiver under this section, the Commissioner shall also advise the owner or lessee of when the Notice is due.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Final Acceptance Inspection.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A final acceptance inspection by the Commissioner is required before the Commissioner may issue a certificate of registration and inspection on all new or modified elevator units.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A contractor shall request a final acceptance inspection at least 30 days before the date the contractor requests for the final acceptance inspection to be conducted.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A contractor may cancel a scheduled inspection under this regulation by written notice to the Commissioner at least 24 hours before the scheduled inspection.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|12|81|.04-1">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04-1</num>
    <heading>Third-Party Qualified Elevator Inspectors.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Qualifications.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A third-party qualified elevator inspector shall have a valid qualified elevator inspector certification issued by an organization accredited by the American Society of Mechanical Engineers.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A third-party qualified elevator inspector shall be:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An independent elevator consultant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Employed by an independent inspection agency; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Employed by the insurer of the elevator unit.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A third-party qualified elevator inspector shall be registered with the Commissioner before performing inspections pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|12-809">Public Safety Article, §12-809(d), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A third-party qualified elevator inspector, who meets the qualifications set forth in §A(1) and (3) of this regulation, but does not meet the qualifications set forth in <cite path="09|12|81|.04-1|A.|(2)">§A(2) of this regulation</cite>, is authorized to conduct only pre-final inspections under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|12-810">Public Safety Article, §12-810(c)(2), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Insurance Requirements.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A third-party qualified elevator inspector authorized to conduct periodic no-load elevator inspections shall provide the Commissioner with a certified copy of an insurance policy covering liability related to the third-party qualified elevator inspector performing inspections on elevator units in Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The insurance policy shall be issued by an insurance company authorized to do business in Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The insurance policy shall be in the amount of at least $500,000 for injury or death for any number of individuals in any single occurrence, and $100,000 for property damage in any single occurrence.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The insurance policy shall identify the Commissioner as the certificate holder.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A third-party qualified elevator inspector shall notify the Commissioner of any material insurance policy alterations or cancellations within 5 business days of receiving notice of the alteration or cancellation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A third-party qualified elevator inspector who conducts only inspections pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|12-810">Public Safety Article, §12-810(c), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, is not required to have insurance under this provision.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Registration and Renewal.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To register initially, a third-party qualified elevator inspector shall submit to the Commissioner a registration fee of $250 and a completed registration form setting forth the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The applicant's name and address of record;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A description of the applicant's education;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A list of the applicant's past and present employers;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The dates of the applicant's employment with each employer;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The position the applicant held with each employer;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Proof of certification required by <cite path="09|12|81|.04-1|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Proof of insurance required by <cite path="09|12|81|.04-1|B.">§B of this regulation</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A third-party qualified elevator inspector shall renew the registration on an annual basis and submit to the Commissioner the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A copy of the current qualified elevator inspector certification;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A completed renewal application form; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A renewal fee of $250.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Suspension, Revocation, or Cancellation of Registration for Third-Party Qualified Elevator Inspectors.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Suspension of Registration.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>After investigation, the Commissioner may suspend the registration of a third-party qualified elevator inspector for the following reasons:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Incompetence of the third-party qualified elevator inspector;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Untrustworthiness of the third-party qualified elevator inspector;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Willful falsification of any matter or statement contained in the registration or renewal form; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Willful falsification of any matter or statement contained in a report or checklist of an inspection made by the third-party qualified elevator inspector.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Within 10 days after suspending the registration of a third-party qualified elevator inspector, the Commissioner shall give written notice of the suspension to the third-party qualified elevator inspector.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>An individual whose third-party qualified elevator inspector registration has been suspended may apply for reinstatement after 120 days following the date of the suspension.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Revocation of Registration.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Following a suspension of registration under this section, if the Commissioner has reason to believe that a third-party qualified elevator inspector is no longer qualified to hold a registration, the Commissioner may hold a hearing to consider revocation of the third-party qualified elevator inspector's registration.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Commissioner shall give at least 10 days written notice of the hearing to the third-party qualified elevator inspector.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>At the hearing, the third-party qualified elevator inspector shall be present and may be represented by counsel.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The Commissioner shall hold a hearing in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 10, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>If, after the hearing, the Commissioner determines that the third-party qualified elevator inspector is no longer qualified to hold a registration, the Commissioner shall immediately revoke the third-party qualified elevator inspector's registration.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Cancellation of Registration. A third-party qualified elevator inspector shall be automatically cancelled if the insurance or QEI certification lapses for any reason.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Inspections by State Inspector.</heading>
    <text>An inspection by the Commissioner as provided for in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|12-809">Public Safety Article, §12-809(a), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite> is required before a certification of registration and inspection is issued.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|12|81|.06">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Record Keeping and Filing.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Record Keeping.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>At a readily accessible central location in the building where the elevator unit is located, a contractor, owner, or lessee shall maintain:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A legible hard copy of maintenance, repair, test, and inspection records; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An electronic copy of maintenance, repair, test, and inspection records in an electronic format approved by the Commissioner for that location.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A contractor, owner, or lessee shall retain the records according to <cite path="09|12|81|.06|A.|(1)">§A(1) of this regulation</cite> for the life of the elevator unit.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The records required to be filed with the Commissioner shall be filed pursuant to the following time intervals:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Incident reports shall be filed within 5 business days of the contractor, owner, or lessee having knowledge of the incident; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Serious injury records shall be filed within 24 hours of the contractor, owner, or lessee having knowledge of the occurrence.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>When the Commissioner requires records to be filed electronically, they shall be filed in comma delimited or tab delimited format, except when to do so would pose an undue burden.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|12|81|.07">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Owner Inspection Responsibilities.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An owner shall hire a third-party qualified elevator inspector who is registered and authorized to perform periodic annual inspections under <cite path="|09|12|81|.04-1">Regulation .04-1 of this chapter</cite> to conduct inspections under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|12-809">Public Safety Article, §12-809(d), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An inspection by a third-party qualified elevator inspector as provided for under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|12-809">Public Safety Article, §12-809(d), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, is required before a certification of registration and inspection is issued.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Commissioner may not issue a certificate of registration and inspection to an owner until the third-party qualified elevator inspector has filed an inspection report certifying compliance with the Safety Code and regulations adopted by the Commissioner.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>An owner shall ensure that an elevator unit suspended by wire ropes, belts, chains, or a similar suspension or an elevator with rack and pinion drive has a comprehensive 5-year inspection.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Comprehensive 5-Year Inspection.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A comprehensive 5-year inspection under <cite path="09|12|81|.07|D.">§D of this regulation</cite> is a periodic annual inspection and a full load test performed on an elevator unit as defined in the Safety Code as a Category 5 Periodic Test.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For a comprehensive 5-year inspection:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Commissioner shall establish the 5-year inspection anniversary date for each unit;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An owner shall ensure that each unit is tested by persons qualified to perform such testing as provided in the Safety Code;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>An owner shall coordinate with the Commissioner the date and time of the inspection by filing an inspection request with the Commissioner at least 60 days prior to the inspection; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>If an owner provides the Commissioner with less than 60 days notice of the inspection request, the Commissioner shall schedule the inspection at the convenience of the State, subject to the availability of State resources.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>This regulation does not preclude an owner from having an elevator unit inspected more frequently than required by this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Third-Party Qualified Elevator Inspections.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A Level I inspector is a third-party qualified elevator inspector who may perform pre-final inspections and periodic annual inspections if the individual:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Possesses and maintains a valid third-party qualified elevator inspector certification;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Is employed as an independent consultant or by an independent inspection agency or is employed by the insurer of the elevator unit; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Possesses and maintains insurance as required by <cite path="|09|12|81|.04-1">Regulation .04-1 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A Level II inspector is a third-party qualified elevator inspector who may perform only pre-final inspections if the individual possesses and maintains a valid qualified elevator inspector certification.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A third-party qualified elevator inspector is authorized to perform only pre-final inspections on a personnel hoist under the ANSI A10.4 Code if approved by the Commissioner after submission of the following information:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Documentation detailing experience, manufacturer's training, and knowledge of personnel hoists, safety codes, maintenance, and testing; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Any additional information requested by the Commissioner.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A third-party qualified elevator inspector shall ensure that inspections and tests are performed consistent with the ASME A17.2 Guide for Inspection of Elevators, Escalators, and Moving Walks and the Safety Code.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Within 30 days of the completion of the periodic annual inspection, the third-party qualified elevator inspector shall submit to the Commissioner the Third-Party Elevator Inspector Report and Checklist form detailing the inspection findings and certifying whether the elevator unit is in compliance with the Safety Code and regulations adopted by the Commissioner.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>If, during the course of a periodic annual inspection of an elevator unit, a third-party qualified elevator inspector finds a potential violation of the Safety Code or any regulation adopted by the Commissioner, the third-party qualified elevator inspector shall provide the owner with the opportunity to abate and correct the alleged violation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>When an inspection by a third-party qualified elevator inspector discloses that an elevator unit is in an unsafe condition so that its continued operation is likely to expose a passenger on an elevator unit to the threat of serious injury, the third-party qualified elevator inspector shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Advise the owner to cease operation of the elevator unit; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Notify the Commissioner immediately.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Public Safety Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|12-805">12-805</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|12-806">12-806</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|12-809">12-809</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container">Effective date:</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1979-07-13"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01|A.">Regulation .01A</cite> adopted effective July 13, 1979 (6:14 Md. R. 1207)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1980-02-01"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> adopted effective February 1, 1980 (7:2 Md. R. 114)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1982-08-16"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01|C.">Regulation .01C</cite> adopted effective August 16, 1982 (9:16 Md. R. 1605)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1982-09-01"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01|D.">Regulation .01D</cite> adopted effective September 1, 1982 (9:16 Md. R. 1605)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1983-11-01"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01|E.">Regulation .01E</cite> adopted effective November 1, 1983 (10:21 Md. R. 1900)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1984-12-17"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01|F.">Regulation .01F</cite> adopted effective December 17, 1984 (11:25 Md. R. 2133)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-09-26"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01|F.">Regulation .01F</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective September 26, 1986 (13:21 Md. R. 2311) (Emergency provisions are temporary and not printed in COMAR)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1985-01-28"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01|G.">Regulation .01G</cite> adopted effective January 28, 1985 (12:2 Md. R. 137)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-09-26"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01|H.">Regulation .01H</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective September 26, 1986 (13:21 Md. R. 2311) (Emergency provisions are temporary and not printed in COMAR)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1987-11-02" discontinuity="true">Chapter revised effective November 2, 1987 (14:22 Md. R. 2339)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-08-04"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01|A.">Regulation .01A</cite> amended effective April 28, 2003 (30:8 Md. R. 540); August 4, 2014 (41:15 Md. R. 890)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1988-01-25"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01|E.">Regulation .01E</cite> amended effective January 25, 1988 (15:2 Md. R. 120)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1988-12-26"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01|F.">Regulation .01F</cite> adopted effective December 26, 1988 (15:26 Md. R. 2981)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-11-12"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01|F.">Regulation .01F</cite> amended effective October 10, 1989 (16:19 Md. R. 2104); November 12, 1990 (17:22 Md. R. 2655)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1991-10-14"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01|G.">Regulation .01G</cite> adopted effective October 14, 1991 (18:20 Md. R. 2198)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-10-11"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01|G.">Regulation .01G</cite> amended effective March 2, 1992 (19:4 Md. R. 473); August 29, 1992 (19:16 Md. R. 1473); July 5, 1993 (20:13 Md. R. 1048); October 11, 1993 (20:20 Md. R. 1569)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-07-18"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01|H.">Regulation .01H</cite> adopted effective July 18, 1994 (21:14 Md. R. 1229)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-08-28"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01|H.">Regulation .01H</cite> amended effective August 28, 1995 (22:17 Md. R. 1317)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1996-04-25"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01|H.">Regulation .01H</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective April 25, 1996 (23:10 Md. R. 727); emergency status expired October 25, 1996</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1997-03-24"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01|H.">Regulation .01H</cite> amended effective November 18, 1996 (23:23 Md. R. 1556); March 24, 1997 (24:6 Md. R. 484)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-04-06"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01|I.">Regulation .01I</cite> adopted effective April 6, 1998 (25:7 Md. R. 526)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1998-12-28"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01|J.">Regulation .01J</cite> adopted effective December 28, 1998 (25:26 Md. R. 1921)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-10-04"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01|K.">Regulation .01K</cite> adopted effective October 4, 1999 (26:20 Md. R. 1545)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-04-01"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01|L.">Regulation .01L</cite>, M adopted effective April 1, 2002 (29:6 Md. R. 567)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-04-28"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01|N.">Regulation .01N</cite> adopted effective April 28, 2003 (30:8 Md. R. 540)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2003-09-29"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01|O.">Regulation .01O</cite> adopted effective September 29, 2003 (30:19 Md. R. 1331)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2005-03-14"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01|P.">Regulation .01P</cite> adopted effective March 14, 2005 (32:5 Md. R. 580)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-04-07"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01|Q.">Regulation .01Q</cite>, R, S adopted effective April 7, 2008 (35:7 Md. R. 748)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-11-16"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01|T.">Regulation .01T</cite>, U adopted as an emergency provision effective August 21, 2009 (36:19 Md. R. 143); adopted permanently effective November 16, 2009 (36:23 Md. R. 1816)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-07-25"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01|T.">Regulation .01T</cite> amended effective July 25, 2011 (38:15 Md. R. 899)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2011-12-26"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01|U.">Regulation .01U</cite>—W amended effective December 26, 2011 (38:26 Md. R. 1696)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-07-08"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01|W.">Regulation .01W</cite>—Y amended effective July 8, 2013 (40:13 Md. R. 1073)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-07-16"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01|W.">Regulation .01W</cite> amended effective July 16, 2018 (45:14 Md. R. 695)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-07-16"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01|X.">Regulation .01X</cite>, Y repealed effective July 16, 2018 (45:14 Md. R. 695)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-07-16"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01|Z.">Regulation .01Z</cite>, AA adopted effective July 16, 2018 (45:14 Md. R. 695)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-07-16"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite>B, CC adopted effective July 16, 2020 (47:14 Md. R. 675)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2022-10-22"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01|D.">Regulation .01D</cite>D adopted effective October 22, 2022 (49:9 Md. R. 531)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-01-29"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01-1">Regulation .01-1</cite> adopted effective January 29, 2007 (34:2 Md. R. 137)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-02-25"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01-1B">Regulation .01-1B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective October 15, 2007 (34:23 Md. R. 2019); amended permanently effective February 25, 2008 (35:4 Md. R. 514)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-11-16"><cite path="|09|12|81|.01-1B">Regulation .01-1B</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective August 21, 2009 (36:19 Md. R. 1433); amended permanently effective November 16, 2009 (36:23 Md. R. 1816)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2002-04-01"><cite path="|09|12|81|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective August 28, 1995 (22:17 Md. R. 1317); April 6, 1998 (25:7 Md. R. 526); April 1, 2002 (29:6 Md. R. 567)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-07-24"><cite path="|09|12|81|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite> amended effective July 16, 2020 (47:14 Md. R. 675); July 24, 2023 (Md. R. 50:14 592)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2013-03-04"><cite path="|09|12|81|.02|A.">Regulation .02A</cite>, B amended effective March 4, 2013 (40:4 Md. R. 345)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-10-01">Regulations <cite path="|09|12|81|.03">.03</cite>—<cite path="|09|12|81|.06">.06</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective July 5, 2001 (28:15 Md. R. 1394); adopted permanently effective October 1, 2001 (28:19 Md. R. 1684)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-02-25"><cite path="|09|12|81|.04|A.">Regulation .04A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective October 15, 2007 (34:23 Md. R. 2019); amended permanently effective February 25, 2008 (35:4 Md. R. 514)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-02-25"><cite path="|09|12|81|.04-1">Regulation .04-1</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective October 15, 2007 (34:23 Md. R. 2019); adopted permanently effective February 25, 2008 (35:4 Md. R. 514)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-11-16"><cite path="|09|12|81|.04-1A">Regulation .04-1A</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective August 21, 2009 (36:19 Md. R. 1433); amended permanently effective November 16, 2009 (36:23 Md. R. 1816)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-01-11"><cite path="|09|12|81|.04-1C">Regulation .04-1C</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective January 11, 2008 (35:3 Md. R. 285); emergency status expired June 9, 2008</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-01-29"><cite path="|09|12|81|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended effective January 29, 2007 (34:2 Md. R. 137)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-02-25"><cite path="|09|12|81|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective October 15, 2007 (34:23 Md. R. 2019); amended permanently effective February 25, 2008 (35:4 Md. R. 514)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-11-16"><cite path="|09|12|81|.05">Regulation .05</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective August 21, 2009 (36:19 Md. R. 1433); amended permanently effective November 16, 2009 (36:23 Md. R. 1816)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2007-01-29"><cite path="|09|12|81|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective January 29, 2007 (34:2 Md. R. 137)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2008-02-25"><cite path="|09|12|81|.06|B.">Regulation .06B</cite>, C amended as an emergency provision effective October 15, 2007 (34:23 Md. R. 2019); amended permanently effective February 25, 2008 (35:4 Md. R. 514)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-11-16"><cite path="|09|12|81|.07">Regulation .07</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective August 21, 2009 (36:19 Md. R. 1433); adopted permanently effective November 16, 2009 (36:23 Md. R. 1816)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2009-11-16"><cite path="|09|12|81|.08">Regulation .08</cite> adopted as an emergency provision effective August 21, 2009 (36:19 Md. R. 1433); adopted permanently effective November 16, 2009 (36:23 Md. R. 1816)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
