<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>83</num>
  <heading>Safety Requirements for Personnel Hoists</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Incorporation by Reference.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Purpose. These regulations establish safety standards for the design, construction, installation, operation, inspection, and maintenance of personnel hoists.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The American National Standard Safety Requirements for Personnel Hoists and Employee Elevators for Construction and Demolition Operations, ANSI A10.4—1990, is incorporated by reference, with the following changes:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>On page 1, under Section 2.1, Related American National Standards, delete reference to ANSI/ASME A17.1—1987 and insert in its place the following: American National Standard Safety Code for Elevators, Dumbwaiters, Escalators, and Moving Walks, ASME A17.1, as adopted by the Commissioner of Labor and Industry.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>On page 2, under Section 2.3, Referenced Standards, delete reference to ANSI/ASME A17.1—1988 and insert in its place the following: American National Standard Safety Code for Elevators, Dumbwaiters, Escalators, and Moving Walks, ASME A17.1, as adopted by the Commissioner of Labor and Industry.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>On pages 8 and 9, delete the following definitions:</text>
        <include>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Automatic Operation;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Car-Switch Automatic Floor-Stop Operation;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Nonselective Collective Automatic Operation;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Selective Collective Automatic Operation;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>Single Automatic Operation; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <text>Single Operation.</text>
          </para>
        </include>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>On page 11, delete the text under Section 4, Temporary Use of Permanent Elevators for Carrying Workers or Materials, and insert in its place the following: Section 4. Permanent passenger or freight elevators installed in buildings under construction, modification, or demolition may be used for carrying workers or materials, or both, provided the elevators are approved for such use and a temporary permit therefore is issued for the class of service for which approval is granted by the department having jurisdiction. Elevators for handling personnel during construction that operate in permanent hoistways on the permanent guide rails shall conform to the requirements of the current edition of the American National Standard Safety Code for Elevators, Dumbwaiters, Escalators, and Moving Walks, ASME A17.1, as adopted by the Commissioner of Labor and Industry, that apply to this type of operation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>On page 24, delete the text under Section 14.3.1 and insert the following: When oil buffers are used they shall comply with Part II, Section 201, Rule 201.4 of ASME A17.1, as adopted by the Commissioner of Labor and Industry.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>On page 45, delete Section 24.1.2.1 Automatic Operating Devices.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>On page 45, delete Section 24.1.2.2.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>On page 46, delete the text under Section 24.1.3, Top-of-Car Operation During Inspection, and insert the following:</text>
        <include>
          <text>Means shall be provided to operate the elevator from on top of the car during adjustment, inspection, maintenance, and repair. The operating means shall conform to the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>It shall be of the continuous-pressure type;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>It shall operate the car at a speed not exceeding 150ft/min(0.76m/s);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>It may be of the portable type provided the extension cord is permanently attached inside the car with enough cord to safely access the entire car top;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Except as provided in Rule 210.1d(8) of ASME A17.1, it shall be so arranged and connected that when operative, the movement of the car shall be solely under the control of this device and power door operating devices shall be inoperative, fail safe;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>The means for transferring the control of the elevator shall be:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>An inspection control device maintained inside the car; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>Of the manually closed type and be positively opened mechanically, and their opening shall not be solely dependent on springs. When opened, this switch shall prevent automatic operation;</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>The device shall be used only for the purpose of adjustment, inspection, maintenance, and repair of the elevator or hoistway equipment; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text>Separate additional means of the continuous-pressure type may also be provided to make power-door operating devices and automatic car-leveling devices operative from the top of the car for testing purposes.</text>
          </para>
        </include>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>On page 46, delete Section 24.1.4. Wireless Control.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>On page 46, delete Section 24.1.5 Design Principle for Wireless Control.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>On page 56, delete the text under Section 26.3, Acceptance Tests of Buffers for Car and Counterweight, and insert the following: No acceptance test shall be required for spring-type buffers. Oil buffers shall be tested in the field in accordance with Part X, Section 1000, Rule 1000.3 of ASME A17.1, as adopted by the Commissioner of Labor and Industry.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>On page 57, delete the text under Section 26.6 Operation and insert the following: Except for requirements relating to automatic operation and wireless control, hoists shall be operated in compliance with the manufacturing specifications, rules, and recommendations, and the same of the governing authority. This shall consist of items, functions and criteria pertaining to the hoist use and shall be a part of an operational maintenance and inspection log.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>On page 57, delete Section 26.6.1.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>On page 59, delete the text under Section 29 Posting of Operating Permits and insert the following: Permits shall be posted in accordance with <cite path="|09|12|83|.02">Regulation .02 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>American National Standard ANSI/ASSE A10.4 — 2007 Personnel Hoists and Employee Elevators on Construction and Demolition Sites, is incorporated by reference.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>American National Standard ANSI/ASSE A10.4 — 2016 Safety Requirements for Personnel Hoists and Employee Elevators on Construction and Demolition Sites, is incorporated by reference.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Article 620 Elevators, Dumbwaiters, Escalators, Moving Walks, Platform Lifts, and Stairway Chairlifts of the National Electric Code (NFPA 70), which is incorporated by reference in <cite path="09.12.50.02">COMAR 09.12.50.02</cite>-1B(3).</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Identification Plate and Certificate of Inspection.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A person may not operate a personnel hoist unless the Commissioner has issued:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An identification plate; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A certificate of inspection.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>State of Maryland Identification Plate.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Commissioner shall issue a State identification plate which the owner shall affix in a conspicuous location on the driving unit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If an identification plate is no longer legible, the owner shall notify the Commissioner, who shall issue a replacement.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Certificate of Inspection.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A certificate of inspection may not be issued unless the hoist is in full compliance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps">Public Safety Article, Title 12, Subtitle 8, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, and all applicable regulations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Application for a certificate of inspection shall be made on forms furnished by the Commissioner.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A certificate of inspection shall be posted on the personnel hoist for which it is issued.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A certificate of inspection is valid for not more than 90 days from the date of issuance.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|12-805">Public Safety Article, §12-805, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1988-04-18">Effective date: April 18, 1988 (15:8 Md. R. 1009)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-07-16"><cite path="|09|12|83|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective July 15, 1996 (23:14 Md. R. 1008); July 16, 2020 (47:14 Md. R. 675)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2018-07-16"><cite path="|09|12|83|.01|C.">Regulation .01C</cite>, D adopted effective July 16, 2018 (45:14 Md. R. 695)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
