<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Engineering</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Authorization for Construction.</heading>
    <text>An individual, corporation, firm, partnership, association, company, cooperative, joint stock company or association, or any other form of business enterprise, may not commence any construction of a water system for public use without the prior authorization of the Commission, which shall be granted only upon a finding by the Commission that to do so is in the public interest.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Good Engineering Practice.</heading>
    <text>The water plant of the utility shall be constructed, installed, maintained, and operated in accordance with accepted good engineering practice in the water industry to assure, as far as reasonably possible, continuity of service, uniformity in the quality of service furnished, and the safety of persons and property.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Design and Construction Requirements.</heading>
    <text>The design and construction of the water plant shall conform to the requirements of the Department of the Environment.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Inspection of Water Plant.</heading>
    <text>Each utility shall adopt a program of inspection of its water plant in order to determine the necessity for replacement and repair. The frequency of the various inspections shall be based on the utility's experience and accepted good practice. Each utility shall keep sufficient records to give evidence of compliance with its inspection program.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Mains.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Depth of Mains. Water mains should be installed below the frost line or be otherwise protected to minimize the possibility of freezing and shall have not less than 30 inches of cover except where this depth is not feasible due to underground obstructions or rocky or hardpan conditions.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Dead Ends. The utility should design its distribution system so as to avoid dead ends in its mains. When dead ends cannot be avoided, the mains shall be flushed as often as necessary to maintain the proper quality of the water.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Segmentation of System. Valves shall be provided at reasonable intervals in distribution mains so that, in case of breaks or repairs, a minimum number of customers will be affected. When feasible, valves shall be provided in the mains at intervals not to exceed one continuous block or 500 feet, whichever is greater, except where a dead end run is not intended to serve any intervening customers.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Grid Systems. The distribution system should be laid out in a properly segmented grid so that, in case of breaks or repairs, a minimum number of customers will be affected.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Minimum Pipe Sizes. The distribution system shall be of adequate size and designed to maintain the pressures within the range required by <cite path="20.70.07.02">COMAR 20.70.07.02</cite>. The pipe used in the system should be at least 6 inches in size. In special cases pipes of the sizes listed below may be installed. However, the maximum length from any connecting main at least 6 inches in size should not exceed the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>1-inch ------------------ 150 feet;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>1-1/2-inch --------------300 feet;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>2-inch ------------------ 500 feet.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Service Pipe.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Utility's Service Pipe. The utility shall furnish, install, and maintain the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Corporation stop;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Service pipe from main to curb stop or outlet of outdoor meter setting;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Curb stop; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Curb box.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Curb Stop. Curb stops are for the exclusive use of the utility for control of the water supply to individual customers and should not be located on the customer's property. The control of the water supply by the customer shall be by means of a separate valve, located just inside the building wall.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Customer's Service Pipe. The customer shall be responsible for furnishing, installing, and maintaining the service pipe from the curb stop or outlet of outdoor meter setting to the place of consumption on his premises.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Construction Standards. The service pipe shall be constructed of approved materials and shall be installed and maintained in accordance with accepted good practice and in conformance with applicable codes or governmental regulations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Cover and Size. All service pipes should be installed below the frost line or be otherwise protected to minimize the possibility of freezing and shall have at least 3 feet of cover. All service pipes shall be at least 3/4 inch inside diameter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Proximity to Sewer Pipe. A water service pipe may not be laid in the same trench with sewer pipe.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Valve Required. Every service pipe shall be provided with a valve and waste cock on the inside of the foundation wall adjacent to the location where the pipe passes through it, easily accessible, and fully protected from freezing. All pipes in the building shall be laid in such a way that they can be fully drained by the waste cock.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Inspection. If a governmental agency requires an inspection of the customer's plumbing then the utility may not connect the service until it receives a notice from the inspecting agency certifying that the customer's plumbing is satisfactory.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Meters.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Meter Installation. The utility shall furnish, install, and maintain all meters. Utilities should make available to customer's plumbers sketches of standard meter installations which show the way in which the customer's portion of the installation should be made.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Meter Location. The meter shall be set at a location designated by the utility on the delivery side of the curb stop, and may be inside the building or it may be outside, near the property line, in an appropriate box or vault. If the customer desires any change in the location or position of the meter, meter box, or vault, after they have been installed, the change in location shall be made by the utility at the expense of the customer.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Fire Protection.</heading>
    <text>Specifications, location, installation, maintenance, and ownership of fire hydrants, mains, and other fire protection facilities are subject to negotiation between the utility and the applicant. Fire hydrants for public fire protection should not be connected to mains smaller than 6 inches.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Temporary Service.</heading>
    <text>When the utility renders temporary service to a customer, it may require that the customer bear all the cost of installing and removing the service in excess of any salvage realized.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Main Extensions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Applications. Applications for extensions of water mains shall be made in writing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Ownership of Extensions. Any facilities installed in connection with the extension of mains shall become the property of the utility.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Construction Specifications. The size, type, quality of materials, and their location shall be specified by the utility and the actual construction shall be done by the utility or by a constructing agency acceptable to it.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Calculating Length of Extension. In arriving at the length of main extension necessary to render service at any point, the distance from the point to the nearest main shall be considered along lines of proper construction, due consideration being given to the general layout of the system.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Electing Alternate Route. When the property of the applicant is located adjacent to a street or highway exceeding 70 feet in width, or a freeway, waterway, or railroad right-of-way, the utility may elect to install a main extension on the same side thereof as the property of the applicant, and the estimated cost in the case may be based on such an extension.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Established Grades Required. The utility may not be required to make extensions where grades have not been brought to those established by public authority.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Requirements of Public Authorities. When an extension must comply with an ordinance, regulation, or specification of a public authority, the estimated cost of the extension shall be based upon the facilities needed to comply with the requirements.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Utility's Portion of Extension. The utility shall extend its water mains to serve new customers, other than subdivisions, housing projects, industrial developments, etc., at its own expense, when the cost of the required total length of main extension is not in excess of three times the estimated annual revenue to be derived from the extension, which amount shall be designated the "allowance."</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Estimated Annual Revenue. For the purpose of these regulations, the estimated annual revenue for residential service shall be the utility's average annual revenue per residential customer for the prior calendar year, this average to be effective on April 1st and used until the following April 1st. In unusual cases and for other classes of service, the utility may estimate the annual revenue to be derived in each case.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Customer's Portion of Extension. If the estimated cost of the required total length of main extension is in excess of the "allowance" for the service connections applied for, the applicant for the service shall be required to advance to the utility before construction is commenced that portion of the estimated cost of the extension over and above the "allowance." The amount of the advance to the utility may not include any costs of increasing the size or capacity of the utility's existing mains or any other facilities used or necessary in connection with the proposed extension, except as provided in §L, of this regulation. If the actual cost of the extension is less than the estimated cost, the utility shall promptly refund to the applicant any overpayment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Division of Customer's Portion of Extension. When more than one applicant is involved and an advance is required in payment for a main extension in excess of the "allowance," the amount of the advance shall be divided equally among the applicants, except that some different allocation may be approved by the utility under special conditions.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>L.</num>
      <text>Extensions to New Subdivisions and other Developments. An applicant for a main extension to serve a new subdivision, tract, housing project, or industrial development shall be required to advance to the utility before construction is commenced the estimated reasonable cost of installation of the mains, from the nearest existing main at least equal in size to the main required to serve the development, including necessary service stubs or service pipelines, fittings, valves, and housings therefor, and including fire hydrants when requested by the applicant or when required by public authority, exclusive of meters. If additional facilities are required specifically to provide supply, storage, or pressure exclusively for the service requested, the cost of the facilities may be included in the advance upon approval by the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>M.</num>
      <text>Basis For Refunds. For each new customer connected to an extension on which the utility holds refundable deposits, the utility shall refund three times the estimated annual revenue to be derived from the customer. Refunds shall be made within 90 days after the new customer's service is connected and shall be made to the depositors who advanced the money for the extension. If more than one depositor is entitled to receive a refund, the total amount shall be divided in proportion to the amount of the unrefunded advance of each depositor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>N.</num>
      <text>Disposition of Advances. Advances which may be required from applicants in payment for extensions will be held by the utility without interest. Refunds shall be made in accordance with these regulations and no depositor will have refunded to him an amount in excess of the amount of his advance. Any amount remaining unrefunded at the end of 10 years from the date the advance was received by the utility shall be retained by the utility and transferred to the Contributions in Aid of Construction account.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Public Utilities Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-121">2-121</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|5-101">5-101</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|5-303">5-303</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1968-07-01">Effective date: July 1, 1968 (Order No. 57171)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-05-14"><cite path="|20|70|02|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective May 14, 2001 (28:9 Md. R. 889)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
