<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>04</num>
  <heading>Customer Relations</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Applications For Service.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Applications. All applications for water service should be made in writing.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Application Constitutes Contract. The accepted application shall constitute a contract between the company and the applicant, obligating the applicant to pay for water service in accordance with the utility's tariff currently on file with the Commission, and to comply with this subtitle.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Termination of Service. When a customer desires to have his service terminated, he shall notify the utility and the notification should be in writing.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Information For Customers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>System Maps or Records. Each utility shall maintain up-to-date maps, plans, or records of its entire transmission and distribution systems, with such other information as may be necessary to enable the utility to advise prospective customers and others entitled to the information, as to the facilities available for serving customers within its service area.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Selecting Rate Schedule. Each utility shall assist the customer or prospective customer in selecting the most economical rate schedule.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Notifying Customers. Each utility shall notify customers affected by a change in rates or schedule classification.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Tariff Notice. Each utility shall post a notice in a conspicuous place in each office of the utility where applications for service are received, informing the public that a copy of its tariff, as filed with the Commission, is available for inspection.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Meter Reading Instruction. Upon request, each utility shall inform its customers as to the method of reading meters.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Other Information. Each utility shall furnish such additional information as the customer may reasonably request.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Customer Deposits.</heading>
    <text>Each utility may require from a customer a deposit to be applied against any unpaid balance due the utility for service at the time service is terminated, in accordance with the provisions of <cite path="|20.30">COMAR 20.30</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Bill Forms.</heading>
    <text>The bill forms shall show:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Meter Reading. The reading of the meter at the end of the period for which the bill is rendered.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Meter Reading Date. The date on which the meter was read.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Units Used. The number and kind of units metered.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Rate Schedule. The applicable rate schedule, or identification of the applicable rate schedule. If the actual rates are not shown, the bill shall carry a statement to the effect that, on request, the applicable rate schedule will be made available for examination.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Amount. The gross or net amount, or both, of the bill.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Payment Date. The date by which the customer must pay the bill in order to benefit from a discount or to avoid any penalty.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Estimated Bill. A distinct marking to identify an estimated bill.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Additional Billing Information. Any conversions from meter reading units to billing units or any calculations to determine billing units from recording or other devices, or any other factors used in determining the bill. In lieu of this information on the bill, a statement shall be on the bill advising that the information can be obtained by contacting the utility's principal office.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Billing Records.</heading>
    <text>The utility shall retain customer billing records for the length of time necessary to permit the utility to comply with <cite path="|20|70|04|.06">Regulation .06 of this chapter</cite>, but not less than 3 years.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Adjustment of Bills.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Fast Meters. If a meter is tested and found to have over-registered more than 2 percent, the utility shall recalculate the bills for service of the last customer of record receiving service through the meter and shall make a refund if the amount of the adjustment exceeds $1. The refund shall be for the period that the customer received service through the meter, but for not more than the periods established below:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Known Date of Error. If the date on which the error first developed or occurred can be established, the bills for service shall be recalculated from that time.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Unknown Date of Error. If the time at which the error first developed or occurred cannot be established, it shall be assumed that the over-registration existed for a period of 3 years or a period equal to one-half of the time since the meter was last tested, whichever is less.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Slow Meters. Whenever a meter is found to be more than 2 percent slow, the utility may bill the customer one-half of the unbilled error for a period of 12 months, unless the meter has been tested within that 12-month period, in which event the utility may bill the customer one-half the unbilled error for the period since the meter was last tested. If the amount of under-registration is less than $5, the utility may not adjust the bill.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Accuracy Calculations. Billing adjustments due to fast or slow meters shall be calculated on the basis that the meter should be 100 percent accurate. For the purpose of billing adjustment, the error in registration of the meter shall be calculated and applied as specified in <cite path="20.70.06.04">COMAR 20.70.06.04</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Overcharge Adjustment. When a customer has been overcharged as a result of incorrect reading of the meter, incorrect application of the rate schedule, incorrect connection of the meter, or other similar reasons, the amount of the overcharge shall be refunded or credited to the customer, except for an overcharge resulting from an incorrect reading of the meter where the amount will automatically be corrected in a subsequent billing based on a correct meter reading.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Undercharge Adjustment. When a customer has been undercharged as a result of an incorrect reading of the meter, incorrect application of the rate schedule, incorrect connection of the meter, stopped meter, or other similar reasons, the amount of the undercharge may be billed to the customer. However, the utility may deny service for non-payment only for that portion of the undercharge applicable to the 4 months immediately before the discovery of the error, unless otherwise authorized by the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Denial of Service Without Notice.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The utility may discontinue service without notice for any of the following reasons, and service may not be restored until the cause for the disconnection has been corrected:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Hazardous Condition. For a condition on the customer's premises determined by the utility to be hazardous.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Adverse Effect on Service. Customer's use of equipment in such a manner as to adversely affect the utility's equipment or the utility's service to others.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Tampering with Utility Property. Customer's tampering with equipment furnished and owned by the utility.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Unauthorized Use of Service. Customer's unauthorized use of service by any method, including diversion of water around a meter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A reasonable charge may be made for restoring service disconnected under this regulation, and customers who have been disconnected for unauthorized use of water or for damaging the utility's equipment may be charged the actual cost of reconnecting the service.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Denial of Service Requiring Notice.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The utility may deny service for any of the following reasons provided it has notified the customer of its intent to deny service and has allowed the customer a reasonable time in which to remove the cause for denial:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Non-Compliance with Regulations. For violation of or non-compliance with this subtitle, or for violation of or non-compliance with the utility's rules on file with the Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Failure on Contractual Obligations. For failure of the customer to fulfill his contractual obligations for service or facilities subject to regulation by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Refusal of Access. For failure of the customer to permit the utility to have reasonable access to its equipment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Non-Payment of Bill. For non-payment of a bill for service, provided that the utility has made a reasonable attempt to effect collection and has given the customer written notice that he has at least 5 days, excluding Sundays and holidays, in which to make settlement on his account or have his service denied. Except in cases where a prior attempt to gain access has been unsuccessful or where a prior promise to pay has not been kept, the utility may not deny service on the day preceding any day on which it is not prepared to accept payment of the amount due and to reconnect service.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Failure to Provide Deposit. For failure of the customer to provide the utility with a deposit as authorized in <cite path="|20|70|04|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Failure to Comply with Service Conditions. For failure of the customer to furnish any service equipment, permits, certificates, or rights-of-way, as shall have been specified by the utility as a condition to obtaining service, or if the equipment or permissions are withdrawn or terminated.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Waste of Water. For willful waste of water by the customer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Restrictions on Use of Water. For failure of the customer to comply with reasonable restrictions on the use of water, as imposed under <cite path="20.70.07.05">COMAR 20.70.07.05</cite>, provided that notice has been given to the customer and that written notice has been furnished to the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>When water has been turned off for any of the reasons specified in this regulation, a charge may be made for restoring service. This reconnection charge may not exceed $2 for restoring service to a residential or commercial customer, unless the utility has filed a different charge with the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Insufficient Reasons for Denial of Service.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The following may not constitute sufficient cause for refusal of service to a present or prospective customer:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Failure of a prior customer to pay for service at the premises to be served;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Failure to pay for merchandise purchased from the utility;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Failure to pay for a public utility service other than water service;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Failure to pay for a different class of service;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Failure to pay the bill of another customer as guarantor of the customer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Failure to pay the undercharge for the period in excess of 4 months as described in <cite path="|20|70|04|.06|E.">Regulation .06E of this chapter</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Failure to pay an outstanding bill that is over 7 years old, unless the:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Customer signed an agreement to pay the outstanding bill before the expiration of this period;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Outstanding bill is for service obtained by the customer by means of tampering with equipment furnished and owned by the utility or by unauthorized use of service by any method; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Outstanding bill is for service obtained by the customer by means of an application made:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>In a fictitious name,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>In the name of an individual who is not an occupant of the dwelling unit, without disclosure of the individual's actual address,</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>In the name of a third party without disclosing that fact or without bona fide authority from the third party, or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Without disclosure of a material fact or by misrepresentation of a material fact.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This regulation applies to both residential and nonresidential classes of service.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Right of Access.</heading>
    <text>The authorized agents of the utility shall have the right of access to the premises supplied with water, at reasonable hours, for the purpose of reading meters, examining fixtures and pipes, observing the manner of using water, and for any other purpose which is proper and necessary in the conduct of the utility's business.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Waste of Water.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Leakage Control. The customer should maintain his service pipe and all piping and fixtures on or in the building so that any loss of water through leakage is kept to a reasonably small amount. If the leakage becomes excessive, it may be treated as a willful waste of water.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Willful Waste. Unnecessary or excessive use of water may be treated as a willful waste of water.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Investigation of Complaints.</heading>
    <text>The utility shall investigate promptly and thoroughly any complaint concerning its charges, practices, facilities, or service.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Records of Complaints.</heading>
    <text>The utility shall keep such records of customer complaints as will enable it to review and analyze its procedures and actions as an aid in rendering improved service.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Identification of Employees.</heading>
    <text>Every employee, whose duties require him to enter the customer's premises, should wear a distinguishing uniform, or other insignia identifying him as an employee of the utility. The minimum requirement shall be a badge or identification card, carried on his person, certifying him as an employee of the utility authorized to enter the premises to perform necessary inspections or work.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Public Utilities Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-113">2-113</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-121">2-121</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|5-101">5-101</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1968-07-01">Effective date: July 1, 1968 (Order No. 57171)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1981-01-23">Regulations .03 and .06A amended effective January 23, 1981 (8:2 Md. R. 117)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-05-10"><cite path="|20|70|04|.09">Regulation .09</cite> amended effective May 10, 1993 (20:9 Md. R. 780)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
