<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>07</num>
  <heading>Quality of Service</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Quality of Water.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General. Each utility shall provide water that is potable, and, insofar as practicable, free from objectionable odors, taste, color, and turbidity. Each utility shall have a permit as required by the health laws of the State, and shall comply with the laws and regulations of the Department of the Environment and local departments of health.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Water Supply. The source of supply shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Free from pollution, unless the water is subsequently purified by treatment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Reasonably adequate to provide a continuous supply of water; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Of such quality as to meet the standards of the Department of the Environment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Operation of Supply System.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Free of Sanitary Defects. The water supply system, including the source of supply plant, pumping plant, water treatment plant, transmission plant, and distribution plant, shall be free from sanitary defects.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Cross Connections Restricted. Any physical connection between the distribution system of a public water supply and that of any other water supply shall comply with the regulations of the Department of the Environment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Disinfection of Facilities. All new mains, pumps, tanks, wells, and other facilities for handling potable water, and insofar as practicable, repaired mains and other facilities, shall be thoroughly disinfected before being connected to the system. The method of disinfection shall be as approved by the Department of the Environment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Testing of Water. Each utility shall cooperate with the Department of the Environment in the conduct of its water quality sampling program.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Pressure Limits.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Allowable Pressures. Under normal conditions of use of water, the pressure at a customer's service connection shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Not less than 25 psig; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Not more than 125 psig.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Exceptions to Pressure Requirements. Pressure outside the limits specified will not be considered a violation when the variations:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Arise from the action of the elements;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Are infrequent fluctuations not exceeding 5 minutes' duration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Arise from service interruptions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Are from causes beyond the control of the utility; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Arise from variations in service elevations which are local and which can be controlled in a satisfactory manner.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="20|70|07|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Pressure Surveys and Records.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Pressure Gauge. Each utility having more than 100 customers shall have at least one portable recording pressure gauge.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Point of Measurement. Pressure measurements should be made at the customer's service connection. If no outlet is available at this point, the measurement may be made at the nearest available outlet, making due allowance for any pressure differential between the point of customer's service connection (usually the curb or property line) and the point of measurement.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Survey by Utility. Each utility shall make a sufficient number of pressure measurements in order to determine if pressures throughout the system are in compliance with the requirements of Regulation .02.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Survey Records. Pressure records obtained under <cite path="20|70|07|.03|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> shall be retained by the utility for at least 2 years and shall be available for inspection by the Commission's representatives at all times. Notation of each pressure record shall indicate the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The location where the pressure was taken; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The time and date of the test.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Interruption of Service.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Endeavor to Avoid Interruptions. Each utility shall make reasonable efforts to avoid interruptions of service but when interruptions occur, service shall be re-established within the shortest time practicable that is consistent with safety.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Notification to Commission. Each utility shall notify the Commission by telephone or telegraph of any interruption to the service of a major portion of its distribution system when the interruption lasts for more than 6 hours.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Notification to Public Officials. If an interruption affects the service to any public fire protection device, the utility shall immediately notify the public official responsible for fire protection.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Standby Pumping Equipment. When the system pressure is provided through mechanical means, emergency standby pumping equipment or other adequate facilities shall be available to maintain pressure in the mains in the event of a failure of the primary pumping facilities.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Planned Interruptions. Planned interruptions shall be made at a time that will not cause unreasonable inconvenience to customers and shall be preceded, if feasible, by adequate notice to those who will be affected.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Record of Interruptions. Each utility shall keep records of interruptions of service on its system and shall make an analysis of the records for the purpose of determining steps to be taken to prevent recurrence of the interruptions. The records should include the following information concerning the interruptions:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Cause;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Date and time; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Duration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Restrictions on the Use of Water.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Restrictions on Outdoor Use. The utility may impose reasonable restrictions on the outdoor use of water during periods of shortage of supply, excessive demand, or other difficulty which jeopardizes the supply of water to any group of customers.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Restrictions on Large Use Customers. The utility may impose reasonable restrictions on the use of water by customers who use large quantities of water and thereby create conditions which prevent the company from supplying satisfactory service to that customer, or to other customers.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Notification. If a utility finds that it is necessary to restrict the use of water, it shall notify its customers, and give the Commission written notice, before the restriction becomes effective. The notifications shall specify:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The reason for the restriction;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The nature and extent of the restriction (for example, on outdoor use of water, use by certain classes of customers, and so on);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The date the restriction is to go into effect; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The probable date of termination of the restriction.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Public Utilities Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-121">2-121</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|5-101">5-101</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|5-303">5-303</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1968-07-01">Effective date: July 1, 1968 (Order No. 57171)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2001-05-14"><cite path="|20|70|07|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective May 14, 2001 (28:9 Md. R. 889)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
