<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Camps</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>It is the purpose and intent of these regulations to establish minimum</text>
    <text>standards of layout, operation, construction, and maintenance of camps to</text>
    <text>protect and promote the health, safety, and general welfare of the public.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01-1</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"Approving Authority" means the Secretary of Health or his designee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Camp" means a property consisting of a tract of land and all tents, vehicles, buildings, or other structures pertaining to it used as living quarters or shelter, which is operated gratuitously or for compensation, during any portion of any 5 or more days per annum, and which accommodates five or more persons at any time. However, this definition may not apply to a camp to be used by one family on its own premises, motels, motor courts, migrant labor camps, and mobile home parks.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Camping Vehicle.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"Camping vehicle" means a vehicular unit which is:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Designed for temporary dwelling or sleeping;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Designed without a permanent foundation;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Built or mounted on a vehicle or chassis; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Driven under its own motive power or mounted on or towed by another vehicle.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>"Camping vehicle" does not include a mobile home as defined in <cite path="10.16.02.01">COMAR 10.16.02.01</cite>-1.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Garbage" means all animal and vegetable wastes resulting from the handling, preparing, cooking, and serving of food, exclusive of recognized industrial by-products and human and animal excreta.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"Permit" means a written permit issued by the Approving Authority according to these regulations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Person" means a person, persons, individual, partnership, firm, corporation, company, or association having charge, care, custody, ownership, or control of a camp or part of a camp.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Refuse" means all putrescible, nonputrescible, combustible, noncombustible, and solid waste materials, including garbage, rubbish, and ashes, but not including sewage.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Service building" means a building housing toilet, bathing, laundry, and other sanitary facilities.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Permits.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General Requirements. It shall be unlawful for any person to operate a camp without an annual permit issued by the Approving Authority. Application for this permit shall be made in writing on a form and in a manner prescribed by the Approving Authority at least 30 days before the opening of the camp, and in the case of a new camp, or camp to be materially altered, enlarged, or added to, shall include plans and specifications for the proposed camp alterations, enlargements, or additions. Permits shall be nontransferable and shall be posted in a conspicuous place. A separate permit shall be required for each camp.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Issuance or Denial of a Permit. When, upon review of the application and following complete inspection of the premises, the Approving Authority is satisfied that the camp meets the sanitation requirements (Regulations <cite path="|10|16|03|.04">.04</cite> — <cite path="|10|16|03|.12">.12</cite>) of these regulations, a written permit to operate shall be issued. If the camp does not meet the sanitation requirements, the permit shall be denied in writing, setting forth the reason for this action.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Suspension or Revocation of Permits. A permit may be temporarily suspended by the Approving Authority after due notification regarding the violation by any person of any of the items outlined under the general sanitation requirements in these regulations, or revoked after a hearing by the Approving Authority upon repeated violation. Any person shall have the right of appeal to the Secretary of Health, and, after that, may appeal to the Circuit Court of the Counties or Baltimore City.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Inspections.</heading>
    <text>The Approving Authority shall have the right of entry at reasonable times upon any private or public property for the purpose of inspecting and investigating conditions relative to the enforcement of these regulations.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Location, Space, and General Layout.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Site Location. A camp may not be located in swamps or marshes or adjacent to them, or in areas not properly drained. Measures shall be taken for the eradication or control of poison ivy, poison oak, noxious weeds, mosquitoes, flies, rodents, and poisonous reptiles in the immediate camp area. Adequate guards, signs, or area restrictions shall be provided to reduce accident potential.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Location. The principal camp area in which food is prepared and served and where sleeping quarters are located shall be at least 500 feet from any area in which livestock is kept.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Swimming Pools and Bathing Areas.</heading>
    <text>A swimming pool or bathing area may not be installed, altered, improved, or used without compliance with applicable regulations. A bathing area may not be used without the written permission of the Approving Authority.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Service Buildings.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Requirements. In camps using service buildings, the following facilities</text>
      <text>shall be regarded as minimum:</text>
      <text>Number           Male     Female</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Toilets                    1    per          20           15</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Urinals                   1    per          30</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Lavatories              1    per          20           20</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>*Showers               1    per          20           20</text>
        <text>------</text>
        <text>*This shall apply to overnight camping facilities and/or where swimming or</text>
        <text>bathing is provided.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Compliance. All toilet, shower, lavatory, and laundry facilities shall be provided and maintained in a clean, sanitary condition and kept in good repair at all times. Separate toilet facilities shall be provided for each sex. Facilities shall be easily accessible and conveniently located. All toilet, shower, lavatory, and laundry room facilities shall be acceptable to the Secretary of the Environment or his designee and shall be in conformity with the State Plumbing Code.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Buildings. All service buildings and buildings used for sleeping of living quarters shall have windows or openings for the admission of light and shall be capable of adjustment for purposes of ventilation. All the openings, including doors, shall be properly screened, unless other effective means are provided to control flies and insects. All buildings used for sleeping or living purposes shall be provided with floors which are easily cleaned and in good repair. There shall be at least 3 feet between beds. The beds shall be arranged for head-to-foot or foot-to-foot sleeping.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.07</num>
    <heading>Water Supply.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Requirements. A safe, adequate, and conveniently located water supply shall be provided for each camp in compliance with applicable regulations. The water supply may not be installed, altered, or used without the written permission of the Secretary of the Environment or his designee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Drinking Fountains. Drinking fountains shall be of an approved type and in locations acceptable to the Secretary of the Environment or his designee. Faucets may not be used as drinking fountains. Areas around faucets or drinking fountains shall be drained in a manner acceptable to the Secretary of the Environment or his designee.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.08</num>
    <heading>Sewage Disposal.</heading>
    <text>Requirements. Approved, adequate, and conveniently located toilet facilities shall be provided for each camp in compliance with applicable regulations. A method of sewage disposal may not be installed, altered, or used without the written permission of the Approving Authority.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.09</num>
    <heading>Garbage and Refuse Disposal.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Storage, Collection, and Disposal. The storage, collection, and disposal of garbage and refuse shall be managed so as not to create health hazards, rodent harborage, insect-breeding areas, accidents, fire hazards, or air pollution.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Containers. All refuse shall be stored in conveniently located, leak-proof, rodent-proof containers with tight-fitting lids. Containers shall be provided in sufficient number and capacity for proper storage of all refuse.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Storage Racks or Platforms. Racks or concrete platforms shall be provided on which to store containers for refuse. These container racks or platforms shall be designed so as to prevent tipping, to minimize spillage and container deterioration, and to facilitate cleaning.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Collection. All refuse shall be collected at least twice weekly, or more often if the need is indicated. Where suitable collection service is not available from municipal or private agencies, the camp operator shall provide this service. All refuse shall be collected and transported in covered vehicles or covered containers to an approved disposal site.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.10</num>
    <heading>Insect and Rodent Control Measures.</heading>
    <text>Insect and rodent control measures to safeguard the public health and comfort shall be used in the camp as required by the Approving Authority.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.11</num>
    <heading>Electrical Service.</heading>
    <text>Where electrical service is used, the installation and use of these facilities shall conform with all applicable codes.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.12</num>
    <heading>Food Service.</heading>
    <text>Equipment and operation of kitchen, dining halls, and storage room facilities shall comply with the standards administered by the Approving Authority. Refrigeration and storage of food, food handling methods, dishwashing and storage of dishes by procedures meeting the requirements of the standards of the Secretary of Health.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.13</num>
    <heading>Emergency Medical Care and Hospitalization.</heading>
    <text>A person qualified to render emergency aid shall be available at all times. A registered nurse or physician licensed to practice in the State should be on the camp staff and available for emergency treatment of illness and accident. The nurse or physician need not be a resident, but should be on call and able to reach the camp within a short period of time. Transportation shall be available at all times for use in case of emergency.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.14</num>
    <heading>Penalties.</heading>
    <text>Any person who violates any of the provisions set forth in these regulations shall be guilty of a misdemeanor and upon conviction of it shall be fined not less than $25 or more than $100 for each offense and other penalties as provided by law. Each day's failure to comply with any provision shall constitute a separate violation.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.15</num>
    <heading>Severability.</heading>
    <text>If any section, subsection, paragraph, sentence, clause, or phrase of these regulations should be declared invalid for any reason whatsoever, the decision may not affect the remaining portions of these regulations, which shall remain in full force and effect, and to this end the provisions of these regulations are hereby declared to be severable.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health-General Article, § 2-104, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1965-05-15">Effective date: May 15, 1965</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1970-12-01">Amended effective June 8, 1965; April 1, 1967; December 1, 1970</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-03-14">Preface codified as Regulation .01 and Regulation .01 amended and recodified to Regulation .01-1 effective March 14, 1994 (21:5 Md. R. 404)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
