<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>General Provisions</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this subtitle, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Act” means the Public Information Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp">General Provisions Article, Title 4, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Applicant” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-101">General Provisions Article, §4-101(b), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Custodian” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-101">General Provisions Article, §4-101(d), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Dispute” means a point of contention between an applicant and a custodian arising from a request for public records under the Act, including those matters stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-1">General Provisions Article, §4-1</cite>B-04(a), Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Exemption” means a denial of inspection of a public record or part of a public record pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp">General Provisions Article, Title 4, Subtitle 3, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Final determination” means the written document issued by the Public Access Ombudsman pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-1">General Provisions Article, §4-1</cite>B-04(b), Annotated Code of Maryland, stating that a specific dispute has been resolved or partially resolved or not resolved, or other disposition as provided in Regulations .06, .07, and .09 of this chapter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Identifying information” means any information that identifies a party or other person.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“Mediation” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcj|3-1801">Courts and Judicial Proceedings Article, §3-1801(b), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“Mediation communication” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcj|3-1801">Courts and Judicial Proceedings Article, §3-1801(c), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>“Mediation Confidentiality Act” means the Maryland Mediation Confidentiality Act, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcj">Courts and Judicial Proceedings Article, Title 3, Subtitle 18, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>“Mediation information” means all information made and received as part of the Ombudsman’s mediation process and the decision to participate in mediation, including documentary materials and mediation communications.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>“Mediator” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gcj|3-1801">Courts and Judicial Proceedings Article, §3-1801(d), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>“Office” means the Office of the Public Access Ombudsman.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>“Ombudsman” means the person appointed to the position of the Public Access Ombudsman pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-1">General Provisions Article, §4-1</cite>B-03, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>“Party” means a participant or potential participant in the Ombudsman’s mediation process, including an applicant and a custodian.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>“Public record” has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-101">General Provisions Article, §4-101(k), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>“Sociological information” means any of the following information concerning a person that may be contained in a record of the Ombudsman:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Social security number;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Driver’s license number;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Personal mailing address;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Personal phone number;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Personal email address; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Date of birth.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>“Standards of Conduct for Mediators” means the Maryland Standards of Conduct for Mediators, Arbitrators and Other ADR Practitioners adopted by the Maryland Judiciary’s Mediation and Conflict Resolution Office.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(19)</num>
        <text>“Written guidance” means nonbinding guidance that advises parties on the interpretation of the Act and the application of the Act to specific facts.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(20)</num>
        <text>“Written mediation agreement” means a written agreement between the Ombudsman and the parties to a mediation that provides the specific terms under which that particular mediation will proceed.</text>
        <text>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Objective.</heading>
    <text>The objective of the Office of the Public Access Ombudsman is to make reasonable attempts, including mediation, to resolve disputes between applicants and custodians relating to requests for public records under the Act.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">General Provisions Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|4-1">4-1</cite>B-<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ggp|01">01</cite>—4-1B-04, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-06-17">Effective date: June 17, 2019 (46:12 Md. R. 547)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-09-18"><cite path="|14|37|01|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective September 18, 2023 (50:18 Md. R. 800)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
