<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>Definitions</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this subtitle, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>"American Board of Medical Specialties (ABMS)" means the umbrella organization for the 24 approved medical specialty boards in the United States.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>"Commercial Ambulance Service Advisory Council" means the advisory committee to the EMS Board on commercial ambulance service matters.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>"Credentialing" means the process by which an EMS operational program medical director and EMS operational program review and evaluate the qualifications and skills of an EMS provider in the course of delegating aspects of the practice of medicine to the EMS provider.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>"Direct supervision" means oversight exercised by a supervising physician who is close enough to the individual being supervised that the supervising physician can hear, see, and intervene as necessary.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4-1)</num>
        <text>"EMS provider-in-charge" means the highest medically certified or licensed EMS provider who assesses or provides care to a patient.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>"House officer" means an individual in a  postgraduate medical training program who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Has completed at least the first year of that program;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Is authorized to practice medicine without a license under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|14-302">Health Occupations Article, §14-302, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Is functioning as a resident in a residency program at a hospital that has a base station.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>"Jurisdictional Advisory Committee" means the advisory committee to the EMS Board on jurisdictional EMS operational program matters.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>"Licensed physician" means a physician licensed or otherwise authorized to practice medicine by the State Board of Physicians or its predecessor under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho">Health Occupations Article, Title 14, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>"Medical direction" has the meaning stated in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|13-516">Education Article, §13-516(a)(12), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>"MIEMSS Institutional Review Board" means the group of individuals designated by the EMS Board in compliance with 45 CFR 46, to review the use of human subjects in proposed research.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>"Off-line medical direction" means prospective and retrospective medical oversight of an EMS operational program by a medical director including credentialing, quality assurance, education, and planning.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>On-Line Medical Direction.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>"On-line medical direction" means oversight and orders by licensed physicians at base stations to EMS providers or members of the transport team providing patient care at an advanced life support (ALS) or basic life support (BLS) level.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“On-line medical direction” includes medical orders and oversight by a licensed practitioner at a specialty care unit at a hospital to a registered nurse during a specialty care transport provided the licensed practitioner is permitted by the facility to provide these services and the services are within the scope of the individual’s license.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>"Pediatric Emergency Medical Advisory Group" means the advisory committee to the EMS Board on pediatric matters.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>"Privileges" means the ability of an EMS provider to provide EMS under the delegated authority of an EMS operational program medical director.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>"Quality assurance (QA)" means an organized method of auditing and evaluating care provided within an EMS system.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>"Specialty care transport" has the meaning defined in <cite path="30.09.01.02|B.|(40)">COMAR 30.09.01.02B(40)</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>"System medical director" means any of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The Executive Director of MIEMSS;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The State EMS Medical Director;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The Associate State Medical Director for Pediatrics;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The regional medical directors;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The associate regional pediatric medical directors;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The EMS operational program medical directors; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>The assistant EMS operational program medical directors.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|13-509">13-509</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|13-510">13-510</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|13-516">13-516</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1999-12-15">Effective date: December 15, 1999 (26:24 Md. R. 1859)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-09-01"><cite path="|30|03|01|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective July 1, 2002 (29:12 Md. R. 931); January 15, 2005 (31:26 Md. R. 1866); December 19, 2005 (32:25 Md. R. 1945); November 1, 2010 (37:21 Md. R. 1437); September 1, 2014 (41:17 Md. R. 971)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
