<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Conditions Upon Approval</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>General.</heading>
    <text>The provisions set forth in this chapter shall be complied with by any person applying to the Commission under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|5-204">Public Utilities Article, §5-204, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, when the application is approved by the Commission.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Compliance With the Law.</heading>
    <text>Applicants, if granted authorization to begin construction of a water or sewage disposal system, shall comply with all provisions of the <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu">Public Utilities Article, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Copy of Rates.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Upon acceptance by the Commission of the proposed rates and charges required to be filed with the application by <cite path="20.73.02.07">COMAR 20.73.02.07</cite>, all known potential or current customers or users shall be provided with a written copy of the accepted rates and charges by the applicant.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Temporary Rates.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If any proposed rate or charge is accepted by the Commission on a temporary, provisional basis, that rate or charge shall be subject to any condition and requirement ordered or directed by the Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Any subsequent revisions to the accepted temporary, provisional rates and charges shall be filed with the Commission pursuant to the provisions of <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|4-203">Public Utilities Article, §4-203, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>All current and known potential customers or users of the services provided by the system shall be provided with a copy of any revised or final rates and charges as approved by the Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>As-Built Plans.</heading>
    <text>Upon receiving Commission authority to construct, each applicant shall prepare and permanently retain a complete set of "as-built" plans for the system.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Actual Costs of Plant.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The applicant shall record the actual cost of any subsequent plant construction and the date when the construction was placed into service in accordance with the Uniform System of Accounts, and shall retain bills, invoices, and any other document showing actual costs.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The applicant may consult with the Commission's Rate Research and Economics Division as to suggested methods in using this cost of plant construction information to determine annual depreciation methods and rates.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Public Utilities Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|2-121">2-121</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|5-204">5-204</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1982-10-11">Effective date: October 11, 1982 (9:20 Md. R. 1982)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
