<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Baltimore City — Transit Services for Public School Students</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>This chapter governs the distribution of fare products to any eligible Baltimore City Public School System (BCPS) student and youth worker in the Baltimore City YouthWorks program.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meaning indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Administration” means Maryland Transit Administration of the Department of Transportation. established pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|7-201">Transportation Article, §7-201, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“BCPS” means Baltimore City Public School System.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Eligible individual” means an individual enrolled and actively attending as a student in BCPS or enrolled and actively attending as a youth worker in the Mayor’s Office of Employment Development YouthWorks program, and who qualifies for student fares under this chapter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“YouthWorks” means the YouthWorks summer job program managed by the Baltimore City Mayor’s Office of Employment Development.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Baltimore City Public Schools.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>YouthWorks shall submit to the Administration a Complimentary Pass Application Form provided by the Administration, which shall include the following information:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Organization name, organization requestor, telephone number, primary email address, and contact individual; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Program start and ending dates, school calendar, and eligibility list, along with type of pass and total quantity requested.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>BCPS shall maintain an accurate, timely, and complete listing of all eligible individuals receiving the Administration pass products</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall provide Complimentary Passes for BCPS students for use between the hours of 5 a.m. and 8 p.m. on days when school is in session, and for school-related or educational extracurricular activities on and off campus.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>BCPS shall make every effort to notify the Administration when a student has ceased enrollment with BCPS, or to report a lost or stolen pass in a timely manner, so appropriate administrative action can be taken to deactivate the pass.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>BCPS shall submit an eligibility list to the Administration for verification of students utilizing the fare products by October 31 and April 30 each year.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>YouthWorks Summer Job Program.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>After obtaining approval as required by <cite path="|11|06|05|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>, an opioid treatment center shall submit an agreement signed by an authorized individual of the opioid treatment center on the form required by the Administration, agreeing to the obligations listed in this regulation and other obligations required by the Administration.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Organization name, organization requestor, telephone number, primary email address, and contact individual; and.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Program start and ending date, along with type of pass and total quantity requested.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>YouthWorks shall maintain accurate, timely, and complete listing of all eligible individuals receiving the Administration pass products.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Administration shall provide Complimentary Passes for YouthWorks workers during the YouthWorks summer job period and for purposes of engaging in YouthWorks-related activities.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If a YouthWorks worker ceases enrollment or attendance, the Mayor’s Office of Employment Development shall notify the Administration within 3 business days so appropriate administrative action can be taken to deactivate the pass.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>The Administration or its designee may conduct periodic verifications of YouthWorks’ enrollment information as it pertains to distribution of fare products with 30 days notice.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Payment.</heading>
    <text>The Administration may not collect any fees or reimbursement from BCPS or YouthWorks for passes or services provided.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|7-710">Transportation Article, §7-710, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2023-06-26">Effective date: June 26, 2023 (50:12 Md. R. 476)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
