<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Approved Training</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope.</heading>
    <text>These regulations describe the continuing education requirements for licensees.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>General.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In order to renew a license, the licensee shall submit to the Board satisfactory proof of the completion during the license renewal period of at least 20 clock or credit hours of approved training. Ten of the 20 credit hours of approved training shall be directly related to the category of the license that the individual holds. Each licensee holding two or more licenses issued by the Board may fulfill the continuing education requirements for renewal of all licenses by obtaining a total of 20 hours of approved training.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Exemptions. The requirements of §A, of this regulation, may be waived for any of the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A licensee was issued an initial license during the last 9 months of the license renewal period;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A licensee holds an apprentice license; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Other just cause shown.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Approval of Training.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Board-approved training shall be designed to improve, advance, or extend the licensee's professional skill and knowledge relating to the practice of well drilling. Accreditation of continuing education programs by the Board is based solely upon the content of the programs.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Board-approved training in the practice of well drilling may consist of participation in any of the following, provided there is satisfactory proof of completion acceptable to the Board:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>College-level or postgraduate course work given by an accredited college or university;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Courses, seminars, workshops, or lectures;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Extension studies and correspondence courses;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>In-service training;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Papers published in professional journals and requiring peer review;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Instruction of approved training courses; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Lectures and scheduled courses at national or regional meetings of the National Water Well Association.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Assignment of Credit.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For courses for which continuing education units (C.E.U.'s) have been assigned, one C.E.U. is equivalent to 10 clock or credit hours of approved training.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Credits shall be approved in not less than 1/2 hour increments.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Credits shall be approved on an hour-for-hour basis for attendance at an approved training program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Credits are approved on a 2-for-1 hour basis for the instructor of an approved training program.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>One credit hour is approved for each day of attendance at the Annual National Water Well Association Convention.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>One credit hour is approved for each day of attendance at a regional convention sponsored by the National Water Well Association.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>One-half credit hour is approved for attendance at a State association meeting, seminar, or convention.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Credits are approved on a credit hour-for-credit hour basis for a course, seminar, or workshop approved by the National Water Well Association for continuing education.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Procedure for Approval of Courses.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Courses submitted for Board approval shall be on a form provided by the Board and shall include the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Description of subject matter;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Length of course or courses, in hours;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Name of instructor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Date;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Time; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Location.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A change in subject matter, length, or instructor requires resubmittal and approval of the Board.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Courses conducted by water well-drilling contractors shall have the prior approval of the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Recording Credits.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Approved training obtained within the appropriate license renewal period shall be credited as provided in §C, of this regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Licensees shall submit a record of attendance for each course on forms provided by the Board.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Board may designate an alternative method for recording credits, when appropriate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Board shall maintain a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Cumulative record of continuing education credits for each licensee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Current list, called the Approved Training Log, of all training approved by the Board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Board shall notify each licensee of accumulated continuing education credits not later than 45 days before the license expiration date. Failure of the Board to provide notification does not relieve the licensee of the obligation to comply with the requirements for license renewal.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Proof of Training.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The licensee is responsible for the submission of proof of all approved training to the Board. Inability to substantiate credit hours submitted is grounds for disallowance of the credits in question.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Proof of training consists of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Official transcripts from the educational institution;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A certificate or other documentation signed by the instructor or sponsor of the training, attesting to the satisfactory completion of the training; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Other documentation determined by the Board to be adequate, in light of the nature of the training, to establish that training was actually received by the applicant.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gen|13-101">Environment Article, §13-101 </cite>et seq., Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1990-12-24">Effective date: December 24, 1990 (17:25 Md. R. 2910)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
