<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>07</num>
  <heading>Gifted and Talented Education</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>Gifted and talented students are found in all Maryland schools and in all cultural, ethnic, and economic groups. The intent of this chapter is to provide local school systems with direction for identifying students and developing and implementing the gifted and talented education programs and services needed to develop these students’ full potential. These regulations establish the minimum standards for student identification, programs and services, professional learning, and reporting requirements.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Identification of Gifted and Talented Students.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each local school system shall establish an equitable process for identifying gifted and talented students as they are defined in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-201">Education Article, §8-201, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The identification pool for gifted and talented students shall encompass all students.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The identification process shall use universal screening and multiple indicators of potential, ability, and achievement from an annually reviewed Maryland State Department of Education approved list of assessments and checklists.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>A universal screening process shall be used to identify a significant number of students in every school and at least 10 percent in each local school system, as early as possible, but no later than Grade 3. Additional identification shall occur at the 3—5 and 6—9 grade bands for participation in the programs and services described in <cite path="|13A|04|07|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Each school system shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Document early evidence of advanced learning behaviors, PreK—2;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Develop equitable policies for identification and a process for appeals that are clearly stated in writing, made public, and consistently implemented systemwide;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Review the effectiveness of its identification process; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Provide ongoing professional learning for teachers, administrators, and other personnel in the identification procedures, characteristics, academic, and social-emotional needs of gifted and talented students.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>The Department shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Review and approve each school system’s identification process to ensure compliance with this regulation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide a Maryland’s Model of Gifted and Talented Education: Maryland Gifted and Talented Student Identification Requirements document that includes available State-mandated achievement assessments for gifted and talented screening for adoption by school systems without an approved identification process.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Programs and Services.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each school system shall provide different services beyond those normally provided by the regular school program from an annually reviewed Maryland State Department of Education approved list of programs and services in order to develop the gifted and talented student’s potential. Appropriately differentiated, evidenced-based programs and services shall accelerate, extend, or enrich instructional content, strategies, and products to demonstrate and apply learning.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Each school system shall review the effectiveness of its programs and services.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Each school system shall implement programs and services for gifted and talented students that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provide a continuum of appropriately differentiated curriculum and evidence-based academic programs and services in grades PreK—12 during the regular school day for identified gifted and talented students.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide programs and services to support the social and emotional growth of gifted and talented students.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Provide programs and services to inform and involve parents/guardians of gifted and talented students.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Professional Learning.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Teachers and other personnel assigned specifically to work with students who have been identified as gifted and talented shall engage in professional learning aligned with the competencies specified by the Gifted and Talented Education Specialist certification in COMAR 13A.12.03.12.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Teachers who wish to pursue leadership roles in gifted and talented education shall be encouraged to obtain Gifted and Talented Education Specialist certification as defined in COMAR 13A.12.03.12.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>State Advisory Council.</heading>
    <text>The State Superintendent of Schools shall maintain an Advisory Council for Gifted and Talented Education that shall advise the Superintendent on issues and best practices relevant to the education of gifted and talented students in Maryland.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Monitoring and Reporting Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Local school system superintendents may exempt specific schools from the requirement to identify a significant number of gifted and talented students.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Beginning September 1, 2019, local school systems shall report in their consolidated local Every Student Succeeds Act (ESSA) plan:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The process for identifying gifted and talented students;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The number of gifted and talented students identified in each school;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The percentage of gifted and talented students identified in the local school system;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The schools that have been exempted from identification of a significant number of gifted and talented students and the rationale;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The continuum of programs and services; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Data-informed goals, targets, strategies, and timelines.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Beginning September 1, 2019, the Maryland State Department of Education shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Facilitate a peer-review of local school systems’ gifted and talented identification, programs, and services every 3 years; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Submit an annual report on the status and progress of gifted and talented students in Maryland to the State Board of Education.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|2-205">2-205</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|5-401">5-401</cite>(d), and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-201">8-201</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|8-204">8-204</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-04-02">Effective date: April 2, 2012 (39:6 Md. R. 409)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-07-15"><cite path="|13A|04|07|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective July 15, 2019 (46:14 Md. R. 622)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-07-15"><cite path="|13A|04|07|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective July 15, 2019 (46:14 Md. R. 622)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-07-15"><cite path="|13A|04|07|.03|A.">Regulation .03A</cite>, C amended effective July 15, 2019 (46:14 Md. R. 622)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-07-15"><cite path="|13A|04|07|.04">Regulation .04</cite> amended effective July 15, 2019 (46:14 Md. R. 622)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-07-15"><cite path="|13A|04|07|.06">Regulation .06</cite> amended effective July 15, 2019 (46:14 Md. R. 622)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
