<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>08</num>
  <heading>Program in Social Studies</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Requirements for Social Studies Instructional Programs for Grades Prekindergarten — 12.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each local school system shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provide in public schools an instructional program in social studies each year for all students in grades prekindergarten—8; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Offer in public schools a social studies program in grades 9—12 which enables students to meet graduation requirements and to select social studies electives.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Maryland Social Studies Program. The comprehensive instructional program shall provide for the diversity of student needs, abilities, and interests at the early, middle, and high school learning years, and shall include the content standards set forth in the College, Career, and Civic Life (C3) Framework for Social Studies State Standards under §§C—H of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Social Studies Processes and Skills. Students shall inquire about civics, geography, economics, history, and people and nations of the world using disciplinary literacy skills and processes to critically evaluate content through a variety of source materials across disciplines and use reading, writing, and other forms of communication to develop, defend, and critique arguments in order to take informed action.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Civics. Students shall inquire about the historical development of the fundamental concepts and processes of authority, power, and influence with particular emphasis on civic reasoning in order to become informed, responsible citizens, engage in the political process, and contribute to society.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Peoples of the Nation and the World. Students shall inquire about the people of the United States and the world using a historically grounded, multidisciplinary approach in order to recognize multiple narratives and acknowledge the diversity and commonality of the human experience.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Geography. Students shall inquire about the role of culture, technology, and the environment in the location, distribution, and impact of human activities using geographic tools and spatial thinking in order to demonstrate a significance of place.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Economics. Students shall  inquire about decisions made by individuals and groups using economic reasoning in order to understand the historical development and current status of economic principles, institutions, and processes needed to be effective citizens, consumers, and workers participating in local communities, the nation, and the world.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>History. Students shall inquire about significant events, ideas, beliefs, and themes to identify patterns and trends and to analyze how individuals and societies have changed over time to make connections to the present in their communities, Maryland, the United States, and the world.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Curriculum Documents. Consistent with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|4-111">Education Article, §4-111, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, each local system shall provide social studies curriculum documents for the elementary and secondary schools under its jurisdiction that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Include the content standards set forth in §§C—H of this regulation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Are aligned with the State Curriculum, as developed by the Maryland State Department of Education in collaboration with local school systems.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Student Participation. Each student shall participate in the comprehensive social studies program required by this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Certification Procedures.</heading>
    <text>By September 1, 2005 and each 5 years after that, each local superintendent of schools shall certify to the State Superintendent of Schools that the instructional programming within grades prekindergarten—12 meets, at a minimum, the requirements set forth in <cite path="|13A|04|08|.01">Regulation .01 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|2-205">Education Article, §2-205(c) </cite>and (h), Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1982-03-01">Effective date: March 1, 1982 (9:4 Md. R. 332)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-01-15">Chapter revised effective January 15, 1989 (15:27 Md. R. 3133)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-07-19" discontinuity="true">Regulations .01 and .02 repealed and new Regulations .01 and .02 adopted effective July 19, 2004 (31:14 Md. R. 1079)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-08-24"><cite path="|13A|04|08|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective February 16, 2015 (42:3 Md. R. 317); August 24, 2020 (47:17 Md. R. 797)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-01-14"><cite path="|13A|04|08|.01|I.">Regulation .01I</cite> amended effective January 14, 2010 (37:1 Md. R. 15)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
