<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>09</num>
  <heading>Program in Science</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Science Instructional Programs for Grades Prekindergarten — 12.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each local school system shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provide in public schools an instructional program in science each year for all students in grades prekindergarten—8; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Offer in public schools a science program in grades 9—12 which enables students to meet graduation requirements and to select science electives.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Maryland Science Program. The comprehensive instructional program shall provide for the diversity of student needs, abilities, and interests at the early, middle, and high school learning years, and shall include all the Maryland College- and Career-Ready Next Generation Science Standards (NGSS) for all students as set forth in §§C—H of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Science and Engineering Practices. Students shall demonstrate an understanding by engaging in scientific investigation that requires not only skill but also knowledge that is specific to each practice.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Crosscutting Concepts. Students shall demonstrate an understanding of the concepts that unify the study of science through their common application across fields in the major disciplines of natural science.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Earth/Space Science. Students shall demonstrate an understanding of the processes that operate on Earth and address its place in the solar system and galaxy.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Life Science. Students shall demonstrate an understanding of the key concepts that make sense of the life sciences which focus on patterns, processes, and relationships of living organisms.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Physical Science. Students shall demonstrate an understanding that there are mechanisms of cause and effect in all systems and processes that can be understood through a common set of physical and chemical principles.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Engineering, Technology, and Applications of Science. Students shall demonstrate an understanding by engaging in solving complex problems that include issues of social and global significance with an emphasis on identifying the best solution to a problem, which often involves researching how others have solved it before in complex problems.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Curriculum Documents. Consistent with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|4-111">Education Article, §4-111, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, each local system shall provide science curriculum documents for the elementary and secondary schools under its jurisdiction that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Include the Maryland College- and Career-Ready Next Generation Science Standards (NGSS) set forth in §§C—H of this regulation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Are aligned with the Maryland College- and Career-Ready Next Generation Science Standards (NGSS), as developed by the Maryland State Department of Education in collaboration with local school systems.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Student Participation. Each student shall participate in the comprehensive science program required by this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Certification Procedures.</heading>
    <text>By September 2005 and each 5 years after that, each local superintendent of schools shall certify to the State Superintendent of Schools that the instructional programming within grades prekindergarten—12 meets, at a minimum, the requirements set forth in <cite path="|13A|04|09|.01">Regulation .01 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|2-205">Education Article, §2-205(h), </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1983-06-07">Effective date: June 7, 1983 (10:11 Md. R. 976)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-01-15">Chapter revised effective January 15, 1989 (15:27 Md. R. 3133)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-07-19" discontinuity="true">Regulations .01 and .02 repealed and new Regulations .01 and .02 adopted effective July 19, 2004 (31:14 Md. R. 1079)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2021-06-14"><cite path="|13A|04|09|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective January 19, 2015 (42:1 Md. R. 18); June 14, 2021 (48:12 Md. R. 474)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-01-14"><cite path="|13A|04|09|.01|I.">Regulation .01I</cite> amended effective January 14, 2010 (37:1 Md. R. 15)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
