<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>12</num>
  <heading>Program in Mathematics</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Mathematics Instructional Programs for Grades Prekindergarten — 12.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each local school system shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provide in public schools an instructional program in mathematics each year for all students in grades prekindergarten—8;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Offer in public schools a mathematics program in grades 9—12. Beginning with students entering grade 9 in the 2014—2015 school year, each student shall enroll in a mathematics course in each year of high school that the student attends, up to a maximum of 4 years of attendance, unless in the 5th or 6th year a mathematics course is needed to meet a graduation requirement and to select mathematics and mathematics-related courses that shall include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Mathematics Transition Course;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Algebra II;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Pre-Calculus;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Discrete Mathematics,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Linear Algebra;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Probability and Statistics;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>AP<sup>©</sup> Computer Science;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>AP<sup>©</sup> Calculus (A/B);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>AP<sup>©</sup> Calculus (B/C);or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>A Computer Science course that is not AP<sup>©</sup> Computer Science if the local school system determines the course meets the mathematics standards required by this regulation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Maryland Mathematics Program. The comprehensive instructional program shall provide for the diversity of student needs, abilities, and interests at the early, middle, and high school learning years. Each local school system shall include the content standards in §§C—F of this regulation in its curriculum.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>For prekindergarten through grade 5, students shall demonstrate knowledge of the domains: Number, Counting and Cardinality, Number Operations and the Problems They Solve, Numbers in Base Ten, Number – Fractions, Measurement and Data Analysis, and Geometry.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>For grades 6—8, students shall demonstrate knowledge of the domains:  Ratios and Proportional Reasoning, The Number System, Expressions and Equations, Functions, Geometry, and Statistics and Probability.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>For high school students, students should demonstrate knowledge of the conceptual categories: Number and Quantity, Algebra, Functions, Geometry, and Statistics and Probability.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Standards for Mathematical Practice.  Students in prekindergarten through high school shall demonstrate knowledge of the processes and proficiencies of mathematics: make sense of problems and persevere in solving them, reason abstractly and quantitatively, construct viable arguments and critique the reasoning of others, model with mathematics, use appropriate tools strategically, attend to precision, look for and make use of structure, and look for and express regularity in repeated reasoning.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Curriculum Documents. Consistent with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|4-110">Education Article, §4-110, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, each local school system shall provide mathematics curriculum documents for the elementary and secondary schools under its jurisdiction that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Include the content standards described in §§C—F of this regulation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Are aligned with the Maryland College- and Career-Ready Standards as developed by the Maryland State Department of Education in collaboration with local school systems.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Student Participation. Each student shall have the opportunity to participate in the comprehensive mathematics program required by this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Certification Procedures.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>By September 1, 2020 and thereafter, upon adoption of new State standards, local school system curricula, or curriculum support materials, each local superintendent of schools or chief executive officer shall certify to the State Superintendent of Schools that the instructional programming for mathematics courses aligned to the Maryland College and Career Ready Standards meets, at a minimum, the requirements set forth in <cite path="|13A|04|12|.01">Regulation .01 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The superintendent or chief executive officer shall provide evidence of meeting the requirements. Acceptable forms of evidence include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A Maryland State Department of Education Curriculum Vetting Report demonstrating that the reviewed curriculum has earned an acceptable rating as determined by the agency on all sections for mathematics for the identified grade level(s) or course(s);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A curriculum vetting report produced by a nationally recognized external party that demonstrates alignment to Maryland College and Career Ready Standards for the identified grade level(s) or course(s); or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Documentation of national ratings to demonstrate an alignment to Maryland College and Career Ready Standards and strong (level 1) or moderate (level 2) evidence, as defined under §8101(21)(A)(i)(I) and §8101(21)(A)(i)(II) of the Every Student Succeeds Act, for all third-party curricula and curriculum support materials in use.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|2-205">2-205</cite>(c) and (h) and 7-205.1, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-12-01">Effective date: December 1, 1986 (13:24 Md. R. 2560)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-01-15">Chapter revised effective January 15, 1989 (15:27 Md. R. 3134)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-07-19" discontinuity="true">Regulations .01 and .02 repealed and new Regulations .01 and .02 adopted effective July 19, 2004 (31:14 Md. R. 1079)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-02-11"><cite path="|13A|04|12|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended as an emergency provision effective February 11, 2014 (41:5 Md. R. 339); emergency status expired</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-09-29"><cite path="|13A|04|12|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective September 29, 2014 (41:19 Md. R. 1081)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-01-14"><cite path="|13A|04|12|.01|J.">Regulation .01J</cite> amended effective January 14, 2010 (37:1 Md. R. 15)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-10-07"><cite path="|13A|04|12|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective October 7, 2019 (46:20 Md. R. 845)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
