<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>14</num>
  <heading>Program in English Language Arts/Literacy</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>English Language Arts/Literacy Instructional Programs for Grades Prekindergarten — 12.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each local school system shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provide in public schools an instructional program in English language arts/literacy each year for all students in grades prekindergarten—5;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide in public schools an instructional program in English language arts/literacy each year for all students in grades 6—8; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Offer an English language arts/literacy program in grades 9—12 which enables students to meet graduation requirements and to select English language arts electives including English Language Arts/Literacy Transition Courses.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Maryland English Language Arts/Literacy Program shall provide for the diversity of student needs, abilities, and interests at the early, middle, and high school years, and shall include content standards set forth in §§C—I of this regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Foundational Skills Pre-K—5. Students shall develop and apply the foundational skills of reading (including print concepts, phonological awareness, phonics and word recognition, and fluency) necessary to proficiently read a range of grade level appropriate texts with purpose and understanding.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Comprehension of Literary Text. Students shall read, comprehend and analyze a wide range of grade appropriate literary texts that meet the grade level text complexity guidelines of the Maryland College- and Career-Ready Standards for English Language Arts/Literacy.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Comprehension of Informational Text.  Students shall read, comprehend, and analyze a wide range of grade appropriate informational texts that meet the grade level text complexity guidelines of the Maryland College- and Career-Ready Standards for English Language Arts/Literacy.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>Writing. Students shall use writing as a way of offering and supporting opinions/claims, demonstrating understanding of the subjects they are studying, and conveying real and imagined experiences proficiently.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>Speaking and Listening.  Students shall command the skills needed to effectively communicate in a variety of contexts (including face to face and digital contexts) by presenting, listening and responding appropriately.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>H.</num>
      <text>Language.  Students will control the conventions of standard English grammar, usage, and mechanics as well as learn other ways to use language to convey meaning effectively through its structure and precise vocabulary.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>I.</num>
      <text>Literacy. Students shall read complex informational texts with confidence and independence and write what they know about a subject effectively when engaged in the study of history, social studies, science and technical subjects.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>J.</num>
      <text>Curriculum Documents. Consistent with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|4-111">Education Article, §4-111, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, each local school system shall provide English language arts/literacy curriculum documents for the elementary and secondary schools under its jurisdiction that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Include the content standards described in §§C—I of this regulation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Are aligned with the Maryland College- and Career-Ready Standards for English Language Arts/Literacy as developed by the Maryland State Department of Education in collaboration with local school systems.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>K.</num>
      <text>Student Participation. Each student shall have the opportunity to participate in the comprehensive Reading and English language arts program required by this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Certification Procedures.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>By September 1, 2020 and thereafter, upon adoption of new State standards, local school system curricula, or curriculum support materials, each local superintendent of schools or chief executive officer shall certify to the State Superintendent of Schools that the instructional programming for English language arts meets, at a minimum, the requirements set forth in <cite path="|13A|04|14|.01">Regulation .01 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The superintendent or chief executive officer shall provide evidence of meeting requirements. Acceptable forms of evidence include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Maryland State Department of Education Curriculum Vetting Report demonstrating that the reviewed curriculum has earned an acceptable rating as determined by the agency on all sections for English language arts for the identified grade level(s) or course(s);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A curriculum vetting report produced by a nationally recognized external party that demonstrates alignment to Maryland College and Career Ready Standards for the identified grade level(s) or course(s); or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Documentation of national ratings to demonstrate an alignment to Maryland College and Career Ready Standards and strong (level 1) or moderate (level 2) evidence, as defined under §8101(21)(A)(i)(I) and §8101(21)(A)(i)(II) of the Every Student Succeeds Act, for all third-party curricula and curriculum support materials in use.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Education Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|2-205">2-205</cite>(c) and (h), 7-202, and 7-205.1, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1986-12-01">Effective date: December 1, 1986 (13:24 Md. R. 2560)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1989-01-15">Chapter revised effective January 15, 1989 (15:27 Md. R. 3134)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2004-07-19" discontinuity="true">Regulations .01 and .02 repealed and new Regulations .01 and .02 adopted effective July 19, 2004 (31:14 Md. R. 1082)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2014-09-29"><cite path="|13A|04|14|.01">Regulation .01</cite> amended effective September 29, 2014 (41:19 Md. R. 1082)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-01-14"><cite path="|13A|04|14|.01|J.">Regulation .01J</cite> amended effective January 14, 2010 (37:1 Md. R. 15)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-10-07"><cite path="|13A|04|14|.02">Regulation .02</cite> amended effective October 7, 2019 (46:20 Md. R. 846)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
