<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>16</num>
  <heading>Programs in Fine Arts</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="13A|04|16|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Requirements for Fine Arts (Dance, Media Arts, Music, Theatre, Visual Art) Instructional Programs for Grades Prekindergarten—12.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Each local school system shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Provide an instructional program in fine arts each year for all students in grades prekindergarten—8 as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Within the prekindergarten—5 grade span, students shall have experiences in the fine art forms of dance, media arts, music, theatre, and visual art; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Within grades 6—8, students may specialize in one or more of the fine art forms of dance, media arts, music, theatre, and visual art; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Provide an instructional program that enables all students in grades 9—12 to meet graduation requirements, and to select from among fine arts elective courses of dance, media arts, music, theatre, and visual art that will prepare them for post-secondary education and careers.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Maryland Fine Arts Program. The school system must allot dedicated time in the instructional program aligned to the content standards set forth in <cite path="13A|04|16|.01|C.">§C of this regulation</cite> and must adhere to the Universal Design for Learning (UDL) principles to maximize learning opportunities for all diverse learners, including students with disabilities, students who are English learners, and students who are gifted and talented.  UDL shall guide local school systems in the development of curriculum, instructional planning, instructional delivery, material selection, and assessment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Content Standards. Students shall demonstrate the ability to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Generate and conceptualize artistic ideas and work;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Organize and develop artistic ideas and work;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Refine and complete artistic work;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Analyze, interpret, and select artistic work for presentation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Develop and refine artistic work for presentation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Convey meaning through the presentation of artistic work;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Perceive and analyze artistic work;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Interpret intent and meaning in artistic work;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Apply criteria to evaluate artistic work;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Synthesize and relate knowledge and personal experiences to make art; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Relate artistic ideas and works with societal, cultural, and historical context to deepen understanding.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Curriculum Guides. Consistent with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|4-111">Education Article, §4-111, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>, each local school system shall use fine arts curriculum documents in each of the fine arts disciplines for the elementary and secondary schools under its jurisdiction that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Include the content standards described in <cite path="13A|04|16|.01|C.">§C of this regulation</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Align with the Maryland State Standards for the Fine Arts for grades prekindergarten—12 as developed by the Maryland State Department of Education in collaboration with local school systems and in alignment with the National Core Arts Standards.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Student Participation. Each student shall participate in the fine arts instructional programs required by this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Fine Arts Education Advisory Panel.</heading>
    <text>The State Superintendent of Schools shall maintain a Fine Arts Education Advisory Panel that shall advise the Superintendent on issues and best practices relevant to fine arts education for students in Maryland.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Certification Procedures.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Beginning September 1, 2019, and each 5 years after that, each local superintendent of schools shall certify to the State Superintendent of Schools that the instructional programming within grades prekindergarten—12 meets, at a minimum, the requirements set forth in <cite path="|13A|04|16|.01">Regulation .01 of this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Each local school system shall report annually their goals, objectives, and strategies regarding the implementation of fine arts instructional programming and methods for measuring progress.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="ged|2-205">Education Article, §2-205, </cite>Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1988-07-01">Effective date: July 1, 1988 (15:9 Md. R. 1110)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1994-08-15"><cite path="|13A|04|16|.01|B.">Regulation .01B</cite> amended effective August 15, 1994 (21:16 Md. R. 1388)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2017-11-23" discontinuity="true">Regulations .01 and .02 repealed and new Regulations <cite path="|13A|04|16|.01">.01</cite>—<cite path="|13A|04|16|.03">.03</cite> adopted effective November 23, 2017 (44:23 Md. R. 1079)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
