<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>05</num>
  <heading>Reinstatement</heading>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|02|05|.01">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Eligibility for Reinstatement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Employees eligible for reinstatement include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Department employees on an approved leave of absence applying before the expiration of the leave of absence;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Transportation Service employees who are laid off and return within a 5-year period from the time of the employee's layoff;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Transportation Service employees who have separated in good standing applying within a 5-year period following the employee's resignation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Department employees who have not converted into the Transportation Service, and who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Are laid off and return within a 2-year period from the time of the employee's layoff, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Have separated in good standing applying within a 2-year period following the employee's resignation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An employee who is eligible and requests reinstatement shall be placed on the list of eligibles for the employee's former job classification and considered for future job openings. If selected, the employee is entitled to a salary equivalent to the employee's former grade and salary step, and shall receive reinstatement credits as specified in <cite path="11|02|05|.01|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An employee eligible for reinstatement who is hired into a classification other than the employee's former classification shall receive reinstatement credits as specified in <cite path="11|02|05|.01|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Reinstatement Leave Credits. An employee who is reinstated is entitled to restoration of leave earning rates based on years of former service, and an employee who is reinstated within 2 years is entitled to restoration of unused sick leave balances. In addition, an employee returning from a military leave of absence shall receive credit for the leave of absence.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Reinstatement from Active Military Service. An employee who requests to return to a Department position after serving a period of active military service shall be reinstated in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsp">State Personnel and Pensions Article, Title 11, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|2-102">2-102</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|2-103">2-103</cite>.4, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-01-18">Effective date: January 18, 1993 (20:1 Md. R. 27)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-08-30"><cite path="|11|02|05|.01|A.">Regulation .01A</cite> and B amended effective August 30, 1993 (20:17 Md. R. 1346)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
