<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>10</num>
  <heading>Employee Performance Appraisal</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Standards.</heading>
    <text>The Secretary shall establish standards for the evaluation of attendance, work quantity, work quality, and any other pertinent factors of employee performance, and may amend these standards as may be necessary from time to time.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Appraisals.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The appointing authority or the appointing authority's designee shall ensure that written appraisals of the performance of all Career Service, Commission Plan, and Executive Service employees working under the jurisdiction of the appointing authority or the appointing authority's designee be made at least once each year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The performance appraisal shall be made by the employee's immediate supervisor, whenever practicable, and shall be reviewed and approved by the next level of supervision.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The performance appraisal may be reviewed by the appointing authority or the appointing authority's designee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The employee's immediate supervisor shall discuss the performance appraisal with the employee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Less-than-standard appraisals shall be reported to the appointing authority or the appointing authority's designee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>An employee may appeal a performance appraisal or denial of salary increase in accordance with <cite path="|11.02.09">COMAR 11.02.09</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>G.</num>
      <text>An employee with a written performance appraisal rating equivalent to overall "meets standards" or higher may only grieve the evaluation up to Step Two of the grievance procedure outlined in <cite path="|11.02.09">COMAR 11.02.09</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Transportation Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|2-102">2-102</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|2-103">2-103</cite>.4, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1993-01-18">Effective date: January 18, 1993 (20:1 Md. R. 27)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2010-07-12"><cite path="|11|02|10|.02|G.">Regulation .02G</cite> amended effective July 12, 2010 (37:14 Md. R. 938)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
