<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>06</num>
  <heading>Procedures for Resolving Disputes</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>General.</heading>
    <text>This chapter establishes procedures for the review and resolution of disputes that arise in connection with exercise by the Maryland Heritage Areas Authority of its authority under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfi">Financial Institutions Article, Title 13, Subtitle 11, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Act” means Financial Institutions Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfi|13-1101">13-1101</cite>—<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfi|13-1124">13-1124</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Administrator” means the Administrator of the Authority.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Authority” means the Maryland Heritage Areas Authority established by the Act.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Certified heritage area” means a recognized heritage area that has been designated a certified heritage area in accordance with the Act and <cite path="|14.29.02">COMAR 14.29.02</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Decision of the Authority.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>“Decision of the Authority” means a decision, action, or exercise of statutory authority by the Authority and includes an exercise of authority by the Authority that is permitted, required, or contemplated under the Act.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>“Decision of the Authority” does not include a determination by the Authority:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Under the Act or <cite path="|14.29.01">COMAR 14.29.01</cite> regarding designation or an application for designation of a heritage area as a recognized heritage area;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Under the Act or <cite path="|14.29.02">COMAR 14.29.02</cite> regarding review and approval of a management plan or designation or an application for designation of a recognized heritage area as a certified heritage area;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Under the Act or <cite path="|14.29.03">COMAR 14.29.03</cite> related to review and approval of grant applications;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Under the Act or <cite path="|14.29.04">COMAR 14.29.04</cite> related to review and approval of loan applications; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Related to enforcement of the terms of a grant, loan, or other financing.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Petition” means a petition filed under <cite path="|14|29|06|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite> concerning a decision of the Authority.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Petitioner” means a person or entity that files a petition under <cite path="|14|29|06|.03">Regulation .03 of this chapter</cite> concerning a decision of the Authority.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Petition for Dispute Resolution.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A person or entity that disputes a decision of the Authority and is aggrieved by the decision may file a petition with the Authority that seeks to have the Authority resolve the dispute.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A petition submitted under this regulation shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Be in writing;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Be submitted to the Administrator;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Identify the decision of the Authority that the petitioner disputes;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Explain how the petitioner is aggrieved by the decision; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Identify any law, rule, or regulation that the petitioner contends is or was violated by the decision of the Authority.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="14|29|06|.04">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Review of Petitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Upon receiving a petition, the Administrator shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Review the petition;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Review the decision of the Authority that the petitioner disputes; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Refer to the Authority for its consideration the petition and the results of the Administrator’s review.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Within 90 days of receipt by the Administrator of a petition, the Authority shall consider the petition at meeting of the Authority during which the Authority shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Review the petition;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Consider the results of the Administrator’s review of the petition;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Provide the petitioner an opportunity to address the Authority and present to the Authority any additional information or evidence that is relevant to the petition; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Make a determination to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Alter, amend, or rescind the decision of the Authority; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Deny the petition by affirming the decision of the Authority.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Administrator shall promptly send written notice to the petitioner of the Authority’s determination under <cite path="14|29|06|.04|B.|(4)">§B(4) of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Authority’s minutes for a meeting during which it considers a petition shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A summary of all oral statements and discussions concerning the petition;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A copy of all documents submitted to, received by, or considered by the Authority on the petition; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Authority’s determination on the petition.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Appeal.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A determination made by the Authority under <cite path="|14|29|06|.04|B.">Regulation .04B of this chapter</cite> may be appealed by the petitioner to the Office of Administrative Hearings in accordance with <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg">State Government Article, Title 10, Subtitle 2, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>On appeal, a determination made by the Authority under <cite path="|14|29|06|.04|B.">Regulation .04B of this chapter</cite> may not be reversed or modified unless the petitioner establishes by a preponderance of the evidence that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The determination was arbitrary, capricious, or contrary to law, rule, or regulation; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Authority failed to follow its own procedures or this chapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The decision of the Office of Administrative Hearings on an appeal is the final administrative decision.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Financial Institutions Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfi|13-1107">13-1107</cite>(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfi|6">6</cite>), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfi|13-1108">13-1108</cite>(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfi|4">4</cite>)(ii), and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gfi|13-1124">13-1124</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2019-11-04">Effective date: November 4, 2019 (46:22 Md. R. 978)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
