<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>01</num>
  <heading>Leased or Rented Residences Benefiting from Weatherization Assistance</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>The purpose of this chapter is to provide requirements relating to leased or rented residences benefitting from weatherization assistance performed by the Department of Housing and Community Development pursuant to <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-224">Public Utilities Article, §7-224(e), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annotation app="2025-09-01" doc="Maryland Register, Volume 52, Issue 17" eff="2025-09-01" path="regulations|final|25-070-F" type="History" display="false"/>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Building owner” means an owner of a low-income residential property, including the owner’s agents and assignees.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Department” means the Department of Housing and Community Development, a principal department of the State.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Lease” means any oral or written agreement, express or implied, creating a landlord and tenant relationship, including any “sublease.”</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Low-income program” means a program of the Department that provides funds or services to provide energy efficiency and energy conservation measures, including weatherization assistance, to buildings occupied by income-eligible households, causing those buildings to become more energy efficient or to increase energy conservation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Low-income residential property” means a unit, building, or community of buildings, with residents who qualify for the low-income programs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Tenant” means a person lawfully occupying a low-income residential property pursuant to a lease.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Weatherization assistance” means the installation of materials to protect the interior of a building from outside elements.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation app="2025-09-01" doc="Maryland Register, Volume 52, Issue 17" eff="2025-09-01" path="regulations|final|25-070-F" type="History" display="false"/>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Applicability.</heading>
    <text>The regulations in this chapter apply to building owners who lease low-income residential properties to tenants and who obtain weatherization assistance through the low-income programs for those properties.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annotation app="2025-09-01" doc="Maryland Register, Volume 52, Issue 17" eff="2025-09-01" path="regulations|final|25-070-F" type="History" display="false"/>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Requirements Applicable to Building Owners.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>When a building owner obtains weatherization assistance for a low-income residential property, the benefits thereof, including utility bill reduction and preservation of affordable housing stock, must accrue primarily to tenants.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>After a building owner obtains weatherization assistance for a unit of a low-income residential property, a building owner may not:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Increase rent for the unit as a result of the weatherization assistance; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Terminate a lease or evict any tenant as a result of the weatherization assistance.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Violation of any part of this section by the building owner may result in the building owner being required to repay the Department for the low-income program’s share of the cost of the weatherization assistance<em>.</em></text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation app="2025-09-01" doc="Maryland Register, Volume 52, Issue 17" eff="2025-09-01" path="regulations|final|25-070-F" type="History" display="false"/>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">
      <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gpu|7-224">Public Utilities Article, §7-224(e), Annotated Code of </cite>
    </annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2025-09-01">Effective date: September 1, 2025 (52:17 Md. R. 874)</annotation>
  </annotations>
  <annotation app="2025-09-01" doc="Maryland Register, Volume 52, Issue 17" eff="2025-09-01" path="regulations|final|25-070-F" type="History" display="false"/>
</container>
