<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Petition for the Adoption of Regulations</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Who May File.</heading>
    <text>Any interested person may file a petition with the appropriate promulgating authority requesting the promulgation, amendment, or repeal of any regulation.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="11|01|02|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Form.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A petition requesting the promulgation of a regulation shall be in writing and shall contain a brief statement of the regulation sought, as well as a statement of the reasons in support of the request. The petition shall be signed by the petitioner and shall contain his home and business address and his telephone number.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A petition requesting the amendment or repeal of an existing regulation shall be in writing and shall fully set forth the regulation as to which the petition has been filed. If the petition is for the amendment of a regulation, the changes desired shall be completely described, and a brief statement of the reasons for the changes requested shall be given. If the petition is for the repeal of a regulation, it shall contain a brief statement of the reasons for which repeal is sought.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Any petition which is filed on behalf of other than an individual petitioner, in addition to the petitioner identification requirements of <cite path="11|01|02|.02|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, shall give the name, home and business addresses, and telephone number of the individual or individuals who have drawn the petition and caused it to be filed on behalf of the named petitioner.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Submission, Consideration, and Disposition.</heading>
    <text>The petition shall be filed with the appropriate promulgating authority, which shall give the petition its full consideration. Within 60 days after submission of a petition, the promulgating authority shall either deny the petition in writing, stating the reasons for its denial, or initiate appropriate promulgating procedures in accordance with its decision. If a new regulation is adopted, or if an existing regulation is amended or repealed by a promulgating authority other than the Secretary, in response to the filing of a petition, it shall be submitted to the Secretary for review and approval.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container"><cite doc="Md. Code" path="gtr|2-103">Transportation Article, §2-103(b)</cite>; State Government Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-122">10-122</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gsg|10-123">10-123</cite>; Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1973-01-15">Effective date: January 15, 1973</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1995-08-28"><cite path="|11|01|02|.03">Regulation .03</cite> amended effective January 26, 1979 (6:2 Md. R. 75); August 28, 1995 (22:17 Md. R. 1318)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
