<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>02</num>
  <heading>Qualifications</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>In this chapter, the following terms have the meanings indicated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Terms Defined.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Board" means the Elevator Safety Review Board.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Safety Code” has the meaning set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|12-801">Public Safety Article, §12-801(p), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Third-party qualified elevator inspector” has the meaning set forth in <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|12-801">Public Safety Article, §12-801(r), Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Qualifications for an Elevator Renovator Mechanic’s License.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant who applies for an elevator renovator mechanic’s license on or before January 1, 2013, shall demonstrate to the Board a minimum of 3 years of relevant work experience in elevator renovation that is acceptable to the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An applicant who applies for an elevator renovator mechanic’s license after January 1, 2013, shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Demonstrate to the Board an acceptable combination of relevant work experience and education; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Pass an exam approved by the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|35|02|.03">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.03</num>
    <heading>Qualifications for an Elevator Renovator Contractor’s License.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant who applies for an elevator renovator contractor’s license on or before January 1, 2013, shall demonstrate to the Board a minimum of 3 years of relevant work experience in elevator renovation that is acceptable to the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>An applicant who applies for an elevator renovator contractor’s license pursuant to <cite path="09|35|02|.03|A.">§A of this regulation</cite>, shall have until January 1, 2013, to have at least one of its employees or responsible management personnel pass an exam approved by the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>An applicant who applies for an elevator renovator contractor’s license after January 1, 2013, shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Demonstrate to the Board an acceptable combination of relevant work experience and education; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Pass an exam approved by the Board.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.04</num>
    <heading>Application for a Temporary Elevator Mechanic License.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A temporary elevator mechanic license may be issued by the Board upon receipt of the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An application on a form provided by the Board from a licensed elevator contractor that includes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A statement from a licensed elevator contractor that a licensed elevator mechanic is not available to perform construction, maintenance, or service and repair of elevators due to a labor shortage; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A certification by the licensed elevator contractor that the individual to receive the temporary license possesses sufficient documented education and experience to perform as an elevator mechanic without direct and immediate supervision;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An application on a form provided by the Board from an applicant seeking a temporary mechanic license; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A nonrefundable temporary mechanic license fee as established under <cite path="09.35.01.01">COMAR 09.35.01.01</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>A temporary elevator mechanic license is valid for 30 days from the date of issuance.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Board may deny a request from a licensed elevator contractor who does not hold a license in good standing or who is the subject of an active or pending complaint.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.05</num>
    <heading>Qualifications for a Temporary Elevator Mechanic License.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The following individuals may be considered for a temporary elevator mechanic license:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An individual who has a minimum of 3 years of acceptable work experience in the elevator industry performing construction, maintenance, service, or repair of elevators and is a second year apprentice enrolled in an approved apprenticeship and training program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An individual who has a minimum of 5 years of acceptable work experience in the elevator industry performing construction, maintenance, service, or repair of elevators under a licensed elevator mechanic; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An individual who has a minimum of 3 years of acceptable work experience in the elevator industry performing construction, maintenance, service, or repair of elevators and holds a license in good standing with no violations in any other state.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>All qualifying education and experience shall be documented by the licensed elevator contractor on an application provided by the Board.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Out-of-State individuals shall submit a letter of good standing from the state of licensure in addition to the required application.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.06</num>
    <heading>Renewal of Temporary Elevator Mechanic License.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Board may renew a temporary elevator mechanic license for additional 30 day periods as long as a licensed elevator mechanic is unavailable and the holder of the temporary license remains an employee of the certifying licensed elevator contractor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>To renew the temporary elevator mechanic license, the licensed elevator contractor shall submit the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A written notification to the Board that a shortage of license elevator mechanics continues;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A completed renewal application on a form the Board provides; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A nonrefundable renewal fee pursuant to <cite path="09.35.01.01">COMAR 09.35.01.01</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>The Board may refuse to renew the temporary license of a temporary licensee if the Board determines that the individual has had an adequate opportunity to obtain licensure under <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|12-827">Public Safety Article, §12-827, Annotated Code of Maryland</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Public Safety Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|12-823">12-823</cite>(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|4">4</cite>), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|12-826">12-826</cite>, <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|12-827">12-827</cite>(c), and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|12-834">12-834</cite>, Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-07-09">Effective date: July 9, 2012 (39:13 Md. R. 785)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-01-13"><cite path="|09|35|02|.04">Regulation .04</cite> adopted effective January 13, 2020 (47:1 Md. R. 12)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-01-13"><cite path="|09|35|02|.05">Regulation .05</cite> adopted effective January 13, 2020 (47:1 Md. R. 12)</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2020-01-13"><cite path="|09|35|02|.06">Regulation .06</cite> adopted effective January 13, 2020 (47:1 Md. R. 12)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
