<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>03</num>
  <heading>Scope of Practice</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Scope of Practice for Elevator Renovator Mechanics.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An elevator renovator mechanic may not engage in any work that affects the moving or mechanical parts of an elevator.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>All elevator renovations shall be compliant with the Safety Code.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If an elevator renovator mechanic performs any work that affects the weight, cab size, or fire ratings of an elevator, the work shall be performed in compliance with any applicable requirements of the Safety Code and, to the extent required, be done in consultation with a licensed elevator contractor or mechanic.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>If the renovation “alters” the elevator, as defined by the Safety Code, then a final inspection shall be performed by the Maryland Department of Labor's Division of Labor and Industry.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="09|35|03|.02">
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Scope of Practice for Elevator Renovator Contractors.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An elevator renovator contractor may not engage in any work that affects the moving or mechanical parts of an elevator.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>If an elevator renovator contractor performs any work that affects the weight, cab size, or fire ratings of an elevator, the work shall be performed in compliance with any applicable requirements of the Safety Code and, to the extent required, be done in consultation with a licensed elevator contractor or mechanic.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>If the renovation “alters” the elevator as defined by the Safety Code, then a final inspection shall be performed by the Maryland Department of Labor's Division of Labor and Industry.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Thirty days prior to the anticipated completion date of any elevator alteration, an elevator renovator contractor shall request a final acceptance inspection in accordance with <cite path="09.12.81.04">COMAR 09.12.81.04</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>E.</num>
      <text>Prior to putting the elevator back in service, the elevator renovator contractor shall ensure that an inspection is performed by an authorized third-party qualified elevator inspector to determine compliance with applicable law, regulations, and the Safety Code. If the authorized third-party qualified elevator inspector determines that the renovation “alters” the elevator, as defined in the Safety Code, then a final acceptance inspection is required as described in <cite path="09|35|03|.02|D.">§D of this regulation</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>F.</num>
      <text>A copy of the inspection report resulting from the final acceptance inspection required by <cite path="09.12.81.04">COMAR 09.12.81.04</cite> shall be provided to the owner of the elevator.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Public Safety Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|12-823">12-823</cite>(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|4">4</cite>), <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|12-826">12-826</cite>, and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gps|12-827">12-827</cite>(c), Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="2012-07-09">Effective date: July 9, 2012 (39:13 Md. R. 785)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
