<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>09</num>
  <heading>Speech-Impaired Applicants</heading>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.01</num>
    <heading>Speech-Impaired Applicants.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An applicant who claims a speech impairment shall fulfill all requirements for application and shall submit to the Board the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Documentation of the applicant's impairment from an otolaryngologist, who has current certification from the American Board of Otolaryngology; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Documentation of the applicant's impairment from a speech-language pathologist who has current certification from the American Speech-Language Hearing Association.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board shall require the speech-impaired applicant to prove ability to communicate adequately with patients and other health care professionals. The proof of ability to communicate shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Three letters from supervising physical therapists or instructors in a physical therapy program, attesting to the applicant's ability to communicate in a professionally competent manner; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A meeting before the Board where the applicant shall be required to demonstrate the manner in which communication with patients will occur.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A speech-language pathologist or otolaryngologist may be asked to attend the meeting in an advisory capacity to the Board to aid in assessing the applicant's ability to communicate.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>Regulation</prefix>
    <num>.02</num>
    <heading>Other Requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>A foreign-trained speech-impaired applicant shall notify the Board before taking a Board-approved standardized test of oral competency.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>The Board shall attempt to locate a speech-language pathologist fluent in the applicant's native language to assess the impairment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>A foreign-trained applicant who is in need of foreign accent reduction, but has competency in his or her native language, may obtain assistance from a bilingual speech-language pathologist before attempting to pass the test of spoken English.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation managed="false" type="Authority" dest="container">Health Occupations Article, §§<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|13-206">13-206</cite> and <cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|13-302">13-302</cite>(e)(<cite doc="Md. Code" path="gho|3">3</cite>), Annotated Code of Maryland</annotation>
    <annotation managed="false" type="History" subtype="Administrative History" dest="container" effective="1992-12-07">Effective date: December 7, 1992 (19:24 Md. R. 2126)</annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
